<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng"    type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.isosch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"     type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq" xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Stylometric Consistency Patterns in Translation
                    of Spoken Chinese to Written English: A Corpus Analysis of the CoVoST
                    Dataset</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Vincent
                        Chieh-Ying<dhq:family>Chang</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5013-4758</idno>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Tamkang University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>159738@o365.tku.edu.tw</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <!-- This information should be added when the file is created -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000854</idno>


                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="volume">020</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2025-03-01">1 March 2025</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
                    <!-- If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default): <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>     
                  CC-BY:  <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"/>
                  CC0: <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"/>
-->
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml"
                            >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref
                            target="https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml"
                            >https://dhq.digitalhumanities.org/projects.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/wiki/DHQ-Topic-Keywords; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->

                    <!-- Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new <term> element for each -->
                    <term corresp="#stylistics"/>
                    <term corresp="#corpora"/>
                    <term corresp="#translation"/>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <term>speech-to-text translation</term>
                    <term>stylometry</term>
                    <term>CoVoST</term>
                    <term>corpus-based analysis</term>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
            <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref type="gitHist"
                    target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/000854/000854.xml"
                    >GitHub</ref>.</change>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change>DHQ</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This study examines stylometric consistency patterns in professional human
                    translations of spoken Chinese to written English, using the CoVoST corpus.
                    Moving beyond traditional translation quality assessment, the investigation
                    studies how human translators navigate the speech-to-text modality shift and
                    whether this process produces domain-invariant stylistic regularities. Through a
                    framework combining stylometric analysis, machine learning, and digital
                    humanities critique, I identify a ‘consistency bias’ — manifested as
                    standardized lexical diversity, flattened syntactic structures, and repetitive
                    discourse patterns — that reveals how professional constraints and cognitive
                    processing shape translation output. My analysis of 16,899 human-translated
                    English sentences, with detailed statistical comparison of 300 sentences against
                    contemporary spoken English baselines, demonstrates that speech-to-text
                    translation exhibits significantly reduced lexical diversity (Cohen's <hi
                        rend="italic">d</hi>=0.34, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>&lt;0.001), shallower
                    syntactic structures (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>=0.33, <hi rend="italic"
                    >p</hi>&lt;0.001), and narrower modal verb usage (<hi rend="italic">d</hi>=0.43,
                        <hi rend="italic">p</hi>&lt;0.001) compared to original spoken English.
                    These findings illuminate the cognitive and professional constraints shaping
                    human translation practice; future research might consider how such patterns
                    subsequently inform machine translation systems trained on human-translated
                    corpora.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>PLACEHOLDER</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Professional human translation of spoken language into written text represents a
                    complex cognitive and linguistic process that remains understudied in
                    translation studies. While extensive research has examined text-to-text
                    translation <ptr target="#baker_1993"/> <ptr target="#laviosa_1998"/>, the distinct challenges of
                    translating oral discourse — with its disfluencies, incomplete structures, and
                    context-dependent meanings — into polished written prose have received limited
                    scholarly attention. This study addresses this gap by examining stylometric
                    patterns in professional human translations of spoken Chinese to written
                    English, using the CoVoST corpus <ptr target="#wang_2020"/> as the primary data source. Rather
                    than evaluating these translations against quality metrics — a common approach
                    that reinforces normative assumptions — I instead interrogate the internal
                    stylistic consistency of the translated output itself, seeking to understand
                    whether human translators apply standardized stylometric templates across
                    diverse content domains.</p>
                <p>The concept of translationese — the distinctive linguistic features that mark
                    translated text as different from originally authored content — has a rich
                    history in Translation Studies <ptr target="#gellerstam_1986"/> <ptr target="#baker_1993"/>. Digital
                    humanities scholars have since demonstrated how computational analysis of
                    textual patterns reveals deeper questions about authorship, style, and cultural
                    representation. <ptr target="#piper_2018"/> <ptr target="#underwood_2019"/>. My study extends this framework
                    to speech-to-text translation, examining whether the cognitive and professional
                    constraints of rendering oral discourse into written form produce distinctive
                    stylometric patterns that I term <term>consistency bias</term>. I
                    approach human translation not simply as a technical artifact but as a cultural
                    text that embodies specific human values and aesthetic choices during
                    translation processes.</p>
                <p>My study addresses a critical gap at the intersection of translation studies and
                    digital humanities by applying an integrated framework of stylometric analysis,
                    machine learning techniques, and humanistic critique to identify and
                    characterize consistency patterns in the CoVoST English corpus. I focus on four
                    key stylometric dimensions: lexical diversity (measured through Mean Type-Token
                    Ratio), syntactic complexity (parse tree depth), modal verb usage, and discourse
                    marker distribution. These features are selected based on their established
                    relevance in translation studies literature <ptr target="#laviosa_1998"/> <ptr target="#baker_1993"/>. By
                    employing unsupervised clustering and supervised classification enhanced with
                    SHAP (SHapley Additive exPlanations) values, I identify latent stylistic
                    patterns and quantify the importance of different linguistic features in
                    characterizing the corpus. I additionally incorporate Quantitative Content
                    Analysis (QCA) to examine semantic and discourse-level patterns, thereby
                    capturing how consistency manifests beyond formal linguistic features. This
                    methodological design draws on Ramsay's (2011) “algorithmic criticism,” wherein
                    computational methods serve not merely as measurement instruments but as
                    catalysts for humanistic interpretation.</p>
                <p>The significance of this research extends beyond technical assessment. Drucker
                    (2012) reminds us that digital humanists bear a responsibility to interrogate
                    the epistemological assumptions embedded in computational processes.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Literature Review</head>
                <div>
                    <head>2.1 Translationese in Human Speech-to-Text Translation</head>
                    <p>The concept of translationese — distinctive linguistic features that mark
                        translated text as different from originally authored content — has been a
                        central focus in Translation Studies for decades. Martin Gellerstam (1986)
                        first coined the term to describe the “fingerprints” that source languages
                        leave on target texts, identifying lexical and syntactic patterns that
                        distinguish Swedish translations from original Swedish texts. This
                        pioneering work established that translations constitute a distinct textual
                        category with identifiable linguistic characteristics. Mona Baker (1993)
                        expanded this concept by proposing translation universals — features that
                        appear in translated texts regardless of language pairs involved. These
                        include simplification (reduced lexical diversity), explicitation (adding
                        clarifying information), normalization (conforming to target language
                        conventions), and leveling out (convergence toward the middle of the
                        continuum of any linguistic feature). Baker's framework has been
                        instrumental in shifting translation research toward corpus-based
                        methodologies that can empirically identify these patterns.</p>
                    <p>Subsequent advances in both statistical and neural machine translation have
                        added new dimensions to translationese research. Antonio Toral and Andrew
                        Way (2018) showed that machine translations exhibit their own distinctive
                        patterns of translationese, often amplifying certain features found in human
                        translations. Their analysis of WMT (Workshop on Machine Translation)
                        evaluation campaigns revealed that machine translation processes tend to
                        produce outputs with lower lexical variety and higher source language
                        interference than human translations. Recent work by Riley et al. (2020)
                        reframes translationese as a distinct “language” within multilingual NMT
                        models. Their research demonstrates that biasing models to produce
                        translationese outputs inflates BLEU scores while decreasing human-rated
                        quality — a finding that underlines the divergence between automated metrics
                        and genuine translation quality. This reconceptualization of translationese
                        as a computational property rather than merely a linguistic artifact
                        represents an important theoretical advancement.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.2 Digital Humanities Approaches to Style, Authorship, and Text</head>
                    <p>While translation studies have developed robust frameworks for analyzing
                        translationese, digital humanities scholars have approached questions of
                        style, authorship, and translated text from complementary but distinct
                        theoretical perspectives. Franco Moretti's (2013) concept of “distant
                        reading” provides a foundational framework for understanding how
                        computational analysis of large textual corpora can reveal patterns
                        invisible to close reading. His framework has proven especially generative
                        for stylometric studies seeking to isolate the distinctive markers of
                        authorial voice across expansive textual archives. <ptr target="#piper_2018"/> extends
                        this work by examining how computational methods can reveal the “topological
                        imagination” of texts — the ways in which textual patterns encode specific
                        cultural and cognitive frameworks. Matthew Jockers (2013), in a
                        complementary vein, demonstrates how macroanalysis can isolate the “signal”
                        of authorial style from the “noise” of generic conventions. (underwood,
                        2019) further develops these approaches by examining how machine learning
                        models can identify patterns of literary change over time, thereby
                        defamiliarizing received literary-historical periodizations and revealing
                        gradual stylistic evolutions imperceptible to unaided reading.</p>
                    <p>The question of algorithmic text production has been addressed most directly
                        by <ptr target="#ramsay_2011"/>, whose concept of “algorithmic criticism” proposes that
                        computational methods should be used not simply to measure textual phenomena
                        but to generate new interpretive possibilities. For Ramsay, the most
                        productive digital humanities methods are those that “deform” texts in ways
                        that provoke fresh critical insight — a stance consonant with my treatment
                        of speech-to-text translations as cultural artifacts meriting humanistic
                        scrutiny. <ptr target="#drucker_2012"/> provides a crucial theoretical framework for
                        understanding the epistemological implications of computational text
                        analysis, emphasizing the need to recognize how computational visualizations
                        and metrics encode specific cultural assumptions. This perspective bears
                        directly on my analysis, since human translators, too, encode assumptions
                        about linguistic equivalence and textual fidelity in their professional
                        practice. Wendy Hui Kyong Chun (2011) further develops this critical
                        perspective by examining how computational systems participate in what she
                        terms the “programmability of vision” — the ways in which algorithms
                        “shape,” a concept that, transposed to translation, illuminates how
                        professional practices may delimit not only what is translated but what
                        remains translatable across linguistic and cultural divides.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.3 Stylometric Profiling in Translation</head>
                    <p>Stylometric analysis — the quantitative study of linguistic style — has
                        emerged as a powerful methodology for examining translationese. Sara Laviosa
                        (1998) pioneered corpus-based stylometric approaches in Translation Studies,
                        establishing metrics for measuring simplification through type-token ratios,
                        lexical density, and core vocabulary coverage. Mario Bisiada (2017) applied
                        stylometric techniques to examine editorial intervention in translation,
                        demonstrating how syntactic structures are modified during the translation
                        process — a methodology I adapt for my examination of speech translation
                        outputs.</p>
                    <p>In computational linguistics, stylometric features have proven effective for
                        translation detection and authorship attribution. <ptr target="#kurokawa_2009"/>
                        demonstrated that machine learning classifiers could distinguish translated
                        from original text with high accuracy using relatively simple stylometric
                        features, and <ptr target="#lembersky_2012"/> extended this work by showing how language
                        models could be adapted to account for translationese effects. In a more
                        recent application, <ptr target="#graham_2019"/> used stylometric features to analyze the
                        effect of analysis sample composition on MT evaluation, arguing that
                        target-original test data should be excluded from evaluation campaigns due
                        to the distinctive properties of translationese source text.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.4 Speech-to-Text Translation</head>
                    <p>Speech-to-text translation introduces additional complexities beyond
                        text-to-text translation. As Alex Waibel and Christian Fugen (2008) note,
                        translators working from speech input must handle disfluencies, incomplete
                        sentences, and other characteristics of spontaneous speech that rarely
                        appear in written text. These challenges can amplify certain aspects of
                        translationese or introduce new patterns specific to speech-based
                        translation.</p>
                    <p>The development of speech-to-text translation has accelerated with datasets
                        like CoVoST <ptr target="#wang_2020"/> and MuST-C <ptr target="#di-gangi_2019"/>. These resources enable
                        direct training of speech-to-text translation systems without intermediate
                        transcription steps. Sperber and Paulik (2020) caution, however, that
                        end-to-end systems may develop distinctive output patterns diverging from
                        both text-based MT and conventional human translation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.5 Research Gap and Contribution</head>
                    <p>While extensive research exists on translationese in both human and machine
                        translation, and digital humanities scholars have developed sophisticated
                        frameworks for analyzing translated text, a significant gap remains at the
                        intersection of these fields. Most existing studies compare machine
                        translations against human references or examine differences between
                        original and translated text and have primarily focused on text-to-text
                        translation with limited attention to speech input. My work addresses this
                        gap by identifying internal consistency patterns within human translations
                        of speech input — specifically through the CoVoST corpus — without relying
                        on human reference translations, thereby revealing how speech-specific
                        factors influence translationese patterns and contribute to a distinctive
                        translation voice. Methodologically, I integrate stylometric analysis with
                        machine learning and humanistic critique, applying unsupervised clustering
                        and SHAP-enhanced classification to identify latent stylistic patterns while
                        engaging with critical theories of translation consistency and textuality.
                        In bridging translation studies and digital humanities, this approach
                        demonstrates that computational methods can simultaneously expose technical
                        regularities and generate fresh avenues for cultural interpretation.
                        Finally, my research contributes to ongoing digital humanities discussions
                        about the politics of text production by examining how human translators
                        encode specific assumptions about linguistic equivalence, cultural
                        representation, and the nature of voice itself, offering both empirical and
                        theoretical insights into how professional translation practices shape
                        cross-cultural communication in the digital age.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Data and Corpus Description</head>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1 The CoVoST Corpus as Digital Cultural Artifact</head>
                    <p>The Common Voice Speech Translation (CoVoST) corpus represents not merely a
                        dataset but a digital cultural artifact that embodies specific
                        speech-to-text translation values and assumptions about cross-linguistic
                        communication. Developed by <ptr target="#wang_2020"/>, CoVoST derives from Mozilla's
                        Common Voice speech recognition dataset and includes translations across
                        multiple language pairs. For this study, I focus specifically on the Chinese
                        (zh-CN) to English translation component, comprising 16,899 English
                        sentences translated from Chinese spoken input.</p>
                    <p>CoVoST's architecture is particularly valuable because it preserves authentic
                        professional human translations of spoken input. As <ptr target="#wang_2020"/> document,
                        the English translations were produced by professional translators working
                        from Chinese audio recordings, not by automated systems. This human
                        translation of speech input provides rare access to how professional
                        translators handle the modality shift from oral discourse to written text —
                        a process that involves not merely linguistic transfer but also discourse
                        reformulation, register adjustment, and the resolution of speech-specific
                        features (disfluencies, false starts, incomplete utterances) into coherent
                        written prose. Each entry includes the original audio file path, the
                        professional English translation, and a data split designation
                        (train/test/validation). For my analysis, I focus exclusively on the test
                        set (n=4,232 sentences) to ensure my sample represents held-out data not
                        used in any potential downstream model training.</p>
                    <p>Heeding Drucker's (2012) insistence that data be understood as <term>capta</term> — taken rather than given — I approach the
                        CoVoST corpus not as a neutral resource but as a constructed artifact that
                        encodes specific assumptions about linguistic equivalence and cross-cultural
                        communication. The corpus covers diverse topics, and this topical diversity
                        allows us to examine whether any patterns manifest differently across
                        domains or remain constant regardless of subject matter.</p>
                    <p>My analysis revealed a distribution across domains with general content
                        comprising the majority (79.0%), followed by historical (10.7%), cultural
                        (5.7%), political (4.0%), and smaller proportions of technical and medical
                        content (0.3% each). This distribution constitutes a form of cultural
                        curation, one that shapes which varieties of cross-linguistic communication
                        receive analytical priority — a concern Liu (2012) has raised regarding the
                        latent biases of digital tools.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.2 Data Processing as Interpretive Act</head>
                    <p>My data processing pipeline involved several stages. In keeping with Ramsay's
                        (2011) notion of algorithmic criticism, I treat this processing not as a
                        neutral technical procedure but as an interpretive act that shapes what
                        patterns become visible for analysis.</p>
                    <p>First, I extracted the English translations from the corpus, preserving the
                        original sentence boundaries. I then performed sentence tokenization using
                        NLTK's <term>punkt</term> tokenizer, which is specifically trained
                        to handle the punctuation patterns of English text.</p>
                    <p>For syntactic analysis, I processed each sentence using the spaCy natural
                        language processing library (version 3.8.0) with the <hi rend="italic"
                            >en_core_web_sm</hi> model. This provided part-of-speech tagging,
                        dependency parsing, and syntactic tree structures necessary for calculating
                        parse tree depth and identifying syntactic patterns. The spaCy pipeline was
                        selected for its balance of accuracy and processing efficiency, though I
                        acknowledge, with Underwood (2019), that any computational tool embeds
                        linguistic assumptions whose cross-cultural applicability cannot be taken
                        for granted.</p>
                    <p>Word tokenization was performed using NLTK's <term
                            >word_tokenize</term> function, which accounts for English-specific
                        tokenization challenges such as contractions and punctuation. These tokens
                        served as the basis for calculating lexical diversity metrics and
                        identifying modal verbs and discourse markers.</p>
                    <p>To ensure the reliability of my analysis, I implemented extensive data
                        validation checks, including handling of empty sentences, removal of
                        non-linguistic symbols, and normalization of whitespace. The processed
                        corpus was then converted to a structured format suitable for statistical
                        analysis and machine learning applications. Throughout, I remained mindful
                        of what N. Katherine Hayles (2012) terms the materiality of digital text —
                        the manner in which computational processing inevitably inflects textual
                        meaning.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.3 Sampling Strategy and Epistemological Considerations</head>
                    <p>3.3.1 Validation Sample Analysis</p>
                    <p>While the complete CoVoST corpus contains 16,899 English translations, my
                        in-depth stylometric analysis was conducted on a representative sample of
                        300 sentences drawn exclusively from the test split (n=4,232 test sentences,
                        25.0% of corpus). This sampling strategy ensures my analysis is independent
                        of any potential training data and avoids circularity issues. I employed
                        stratified random sampling with a fixed random seed (seed=42) to ensure
                        reproducibility. Sentences were sampled proportionally across domain
                        categories (general, historical, cultural, political, technical, medical) to
                        maintain the domain distribution of the full test set. The resulting sample
                        comprises:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>General: 237 sentences (79.0%)</item>
                        <item>Historical: 32 sentences (10.7%)</item>
                        <item>Cultural: 17 sentences (5.7%)</item>
                        <item>Political: 12 sentences (4.0%)</item>
                        <item>Technical: 1 sentence (0.3%)</item>
                        <item>Medical: 1 sentence (0.3%)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>This distribution closely matches the full test set distribution (χ²=0.87,
                        df=5, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>=0.972), confirming representativeness. The
                        sampling code and exact sentence IDs are provided in my GitHub repository to
                        enable exact replication.</p>
                    <p>This sampling strategy negotiates what <ptr target="#moretti_2013"/> characterizes as the
                        productive tension between close and distant reading — balancing granular
                        textual scrutiny with the broader patterns discernible only at scale. For
                        specific analyses requiring greater computational resources, such as parse
                        tree depth calculation and discourse marker identification, this sampling
                        approach proved essential. However, basic statistical measures were
                        calculated on the entire corpus to provide a comprehensive overview of the
                        dataset's characteristics.</p>
                    <p>Drucker's (2012) critique of visual epistemology reminds us that sampling
                        decisions inevitably shape which patterns surface and which remain occluded.
                        The choice to focus on a representative sample rather than the full corpus
                        reflects specific epistemological assumptions about what constitutes valid
                        evidence and how patterns can be meaningfully identified across texts. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Methodology</head>
                <div>
                    <head>4.1 Stylometric Features as Cultural Indicators</head>
                    <p>My analysis focuses on four key stylometric dimensions that function not
                        merely as technical metrics but as cultural indicators that reveal how human
                        speech-to-text translation practices shape linguistic expression. These
                        features were selected based on their established relevance in translation
                        studies literature and their capacity to reveal the consistency patterns
                        that emerge when translators render spoken discourse into written form.4.1.1
                        Mean Type-Token Ratio (MTTR) and Lexical Diversity</p>
                    <p>Lexical diversity, measured through Mean Type-Token Ratio (MTTR), provides
                        insight into vocabulary richness and potential lexical flattening in
                        translated text. Unlike simple Type-Token Ratio (TTR), which is sensitive to
                        text length, MTTR calculates the average of multiple TTR values using a
                        sliding window approach. This method, advocated by <ptr target="#baker_1995"/> and
                        <ptr target="#laviosa_1998"/>, produces a more reliable measure of lexical diversity that
                        can be compared across texts of different lengths. Drawing on Piper's (2018)
                        treatment of lexical analysis as cultural critique, I regard MTTR not merely
                        as a technical metric but as a window onto how translation processes may
                        standardize linguistic expression. For each sentence in my corpus, I
                        calculated MTTR using a window size adjusted based on sentence length. For
                        sentences shorter than the standard window size, I calculated a single TTR
                        value. </p>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.1.2 Parse Tree Depth and Syntactic Complexity</head>
                        <p>Syntactic complexity, measured through parse tree depth, reveals
                            potential syntactic flattening or simplification in translated text.
                            Using spaCy's dependency parser, I calculated the maximum depth of the
                            syntactic tree for each sentence, where depth is defined as the longest
                            path from the root node to any leaf node. This metric, employed in
                            previous studies by <ptr target="#bisiada_2017"/> and <ptr target="#toral-way_2018"/>, provides
                            insight into how human translators handle complex syntactic structures
                            when translating from spoken Chinese to written English. Underwood's
                            (2019) computational approach to literary style informs my understanding
                            of parse tree depth as an indicator not only of syntactic complexity but
                            of how translation processes may reconfigure the cognitive texture of
                            linguistic expression.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.1.3 Modal Verb Frequency and Epistemic Stance</head>
                        <p>Modal verbs (<term>can</term>, <term>could</term>, <term>may</term>, <term>might</term>, <term>shall</term>, <term>should</term>,
                                <term>will</term>, <term>would</term>, <term>must</term>) play a crucial role in expressing certainty,
                            possibility, permission, and obligation. Their distribution in
                            translated text can reveal subtle shifts in modality and stance compared
                            to original writing. I calculated both the absolute frequency of each
                            modal verb and the ratio of modal verbs to total tokens in each
                            sentence. Liu's (2012) attention to the cultural dimensions of digital
                            text informs my treatment of modal verb usage as a barometer of how
                            translation processes may recalibrate epistemic stance.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.1.4 Comparative Baseline: Santa Barbara Corpus of Spoken American
                            English</head>
                        <p>To provide appropriate comparative context for my stylometric analysis, I
                            incorporated the Santa Barbara Corpus of Spoken American English
                            (SBCSAE) (dubois, 2000–2005) as a baseline. The SBCSAE contains
                            approximately 249,000 words of transcribed spontaneous conversations
                            recorded between 2000 and 2005, representing diverse speakers, settings,
                            and topics. This corpus provides a more suitable baseline than written
                            corpora (e.g., Brown Corpus) for several reasons:</p>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>Modality match: Both SBCSAE and CoVoST are speech-derived
                                texts.</item>
                            <item>Temporal proximity: SBCSAE (2000–2005) is temporally closer to
                                CoVoST's recording period (2019–2020).</item>
                            <item>Genre similarity: Both contain conversational, informal
                                discourse.</item>
                            <item>Register comparability: Both represent spoken language converted
                                to written form.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>I randomly sampled 300 utterances from SBCSAE, matching the sample size
                            of my CoVoST analysis, and calculated identical stylometric features
                            (MTTR, parse tree depth, modal verb frequency, discourse marker usage)
                            using the same computational pipeline (spaCy 3.8.0, NLTK). This parallel
                            processing ensures methodological consistency and enables direct
                            statistical comparison.</p>
                        <p>Discourse markers (e.g., <term>however</term>, <term>therefore</term>, <term>thus</term>,
                                <term>nevertheless</term>) signal logical relationships between clauses and
                            sentences. Their distribution can reveal how human translators handle
                            cohesion and textual organization. I identified 20 common English
                            discourse markers and calculated both their absolute frequency and the
                            ratio of discourse markers to total tokens in each sentence.</p>
                        <p>This feature, examined in previous work by <ptr target="#blum-kulka_1986"/> and
                            <ptr target="#zufferey-cartoni_2014"/>, provides insight into explicitation tendencies
                            in human translation of speech. Within Ramsay's (2011) framework of
                            algorithmic criticism, discourse marker usage functions as an indicator
                            of how translation processes may reconfigure the rhetorical architecture
                            of the source text.</p>
                        <p>In terms of limitations of baseline comparison, it has to be acknowledged
                            that comparing translated speech (CoVoST) with transcribed original
                            speech (SBCSAE) still conflates translation effects with potential
                            transcription/translation process differences. Transcription aims to
                            preserve original speech features, while translation involves linguistic
                            transfer and may introduce target-language norms. The comparative
                            analyses presented here should accordingly be read as exploratory rather
                            than causally definitive.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.2 Machine Learning as Interpretive Framework</head>
                    <p>To identify latent patterns in the stylometric features and quantify their
                        relative importance, I employed both unsupervised and supervised machine
                        learning techniques. Adopting Piper's (2018) view of computational analysis
                        as a mode of cultural critique, I treat these techniques as interpretive
                        lenses that foreground certain patterns while inevitably occluding
                        others.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.2.1 Unsupervised Clustering and Stylistic Regimes</head>
                        <p>I applied K-means clustering to identify natural groupings within the
                            corpus based on stylometric features. After testing different values of
                                <hi rend="italic">k</hi> using silhouette scores, I determined that
                                <hi rend="italic">k</hi>=2 provided the most coherent clusters. </p>
                        <p>The clustering was performed using scikit-learn's KMeans implementation
                            with 20 numeric features, including all stylometric measures described
                            above. This unsupervised approach allowed us to identify natural
                            stylistic patterns without imposing predetermined categories. Moretti's
                            (2013) distant-reading paradigm informs my interpretation of these
                            clusters: they may signal how professional translation practices
                            compress the rich continuum of human expression into a narrower set of
                            stylistic templates.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.2.2 Supervised Classification with SHAP and Feature
                            Importance</head>
                        <p>To understand the relationship between stylometric features and content
                            domains, I trained a Random Forest classifier to predict the domain
                            category (general, historical, cultural, political, technical, medical)
                            based on stylometric features. </p>
                        <p>I employed SHAP (SHapley Additive exPlanations) values to quantify the
                            contribution of each feature to the classification decisions. Liu's
                            (2012) emphasis on the cultural dimensions of digital methods guides my
                            reading of feature importance: The dominance of structural over
                            content-specific features may reflect what <ptr target="#drucker_2012"/> identifies as
                            a systemic privileging of formal pattern over contextual nuance.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.3 Quantitative Content Analysis (QCA) as Cultural Critique</head>
                        <p>To complement the stylometric analysis and provide insight into semantic
                            and discourse-level patterns, I implemented a form of Quantitative
                            Content Analysis (QCA) that functions not simply as a methodological
                            tool but as a framework for cultural critique. This approach allowed us
                            to examine how consistency patterns manifest not only in formal
                            linguistic features but also in content representation.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.3.1 Sentence Function Classification and Speech Act Analysis</head>
                        <p>I classified each sentence according to its primary discourse function:
                            factual description, question, opinion, or directive. This
                            classification was based on syntactic features (e.g., question marks for
                            questions), lexical cues (e.g., opinion verbs like think or “believe”),
                            and modal verbs associated with directives (e.g., “must,” “should”).
                            Hayles' (2012) concept of digital materiality informs my understanding
                            of these functional categories as indicators of how translation
                            processes may reshape the performative dimensions of language. </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>4.3.2 Domain Classification and Cultural Categorization</head>
                        <p>I implemented a keyword-based approach to classify sentences into broad
                            topical domains: medical, technical, political, historical, cultural, or
                            general. This classification was based on the presence of
                            domain-specific keywords and was later validated against the machine
                            learning classification results. Liu's (2012) critique of cultural
                            categorization in digital humanities cautions that domain
                            classifications are never neutral; they are interpretive frameworks that
                            shape how cultural knowledge is organized and accessed.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>4.4 Integrated Framework and Epistemological Considerations</head>
                    <p>My methodological approach represents an integrated framework that combines
                        computational analysis with humanistic interpretation. Ramsay's (2011)
                        algorithmic criticism frames my methods as interpretive acts that open new
                        possibilities for understanding the cultural dimensions of human translation
                        practice.</p>
                    <p>I recognize, with <ptr target="#drucker_2012"/>, that the choice of features, clustering
                        algorithms, and classification approaches shapes which patterns become
                        visible. By triangulating stylometric analysis, machine learning, and
                        quantitative content analysis, I seek a more comprehensive understanding of
                        how translation processes reshape linguistic expression across multiple
                        dimensions of textual structure and meaning.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Results</head>
                <div>
                    <head>5.1 Stylometric Consistency Patterns</head>
                    <p>My analysis of the CoVoST corpus revealed distinctive stylometric patterns
                        that suggest not merely technical limitations, but what <ptr target="#hayles_2012"/> might
                        term an emergent form of textual identity — a consistency pattern that
                        prioritizes uniformity over expressive diversity. The quantitative results
                        across my four key stylometric dimensions provide empirical evidence for
                        this phenomenon while opening new avenues for humanistic interpretation.</p>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.1.1 Lexical Standardization and the Flattening of Vocabulary</head>
                        <p>My analysis revealed an average MTTR of 0.9228 (SD=0.087) across the
                            CoVoST sample. Statistical comparison with the SBCSAE baseline
                            (M=0.9547, SD=0.104) demonstrates that CoVoST translations exhibit
                            significantly lower lexical diversity than original spoken English (<hi
                                rend="italic">t</hi>(598)=4.21, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>&lt;0.001,
                            Cohen's <hi rend="italic">d</hi>=0.34, 95% CI of difference: [0.017,
                            0.049]). This represents a small-to-medium effect size, indicating that
                            the translation process is associated with measurable lexical
                            standardization. Critically, CoVoST also shows significantly reduced
                            variance in MTTR (Levene's test: <hi rend="italic">F</hi>=8.73, <hi
                                rend="italic">p</hi>=0.003), with an interquartile range of 0.089
                            compared to SBCSAE's 0.142. This reduced variance indicates that
                            translations cluster more tightly around a consistent lexical diversity
                            level, regardless of content domain or sentence complexity — a pattern I
                            term <hi rend="italic">lexical consistency bias</hi>.</p>
                        <p>Distribution analysis (Figure 1) reveals that while SBCSAE shows a
                            relatively normal distribution of MTTR values spanning 0.65–1.00, CoVoST
                            shows a more concentrated distribution with fewer extreme values.
                            Kolmogorov-Smirnov test confirms these distributions differ
                            significantly (<hi rend="italic">D</hi>=0.187, <hi rend="italic"
                            >p</hi>&lt;0.001). These statistical patterns support the interpretation
                            that human translation of speech involves standardization of lexical
                            diversity, potentially reflecting cognitive efficiency strategies or
                            professional translation norms. <figure>
                                <head>Distribution of Mean Type-Token Ratio (MTTR) in CoVoST
                                    translations (n=300, blue) and SBCSAE original speech (n=300,
                                    orange). Violin plots show full distribution; box plots indicate
                                    median and quartiles. CoVoST exhibits significantly lower mean
                                    MTTR and reduced variance, indicating lexical consistency in
                                    translation. Statistical comparison: t(598)=4.21, p&lt;0.001,
                                    Cohen's d=0.34.</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
                                <figDesc>PLACEHOLDER</figDesc>
                            </figure> This standardization resonates with Liu's (2012) observation
                            that computational processes tend to favour predictable patterns over
                            the heterogeneous diversity characteristic of human expression.</p>
                        <table>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>Stylometric Feature</cell>
                                <cell>CoVoST (n=300)</cell>
                                <cell>SBCSAE (n=300)</cell>
                                <cell>t-statistic</cell>
                                <cell>p-value</cell>
                                <cell>Cohen's d</cell>
                                <cell>95% CI of Difference</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell/>
                                <cell>M (SD)</cell>
                                <cell>M (SD)</cell>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                                <cell/>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>MTTR (lexical diversity)</cell>
                                <cell>0.9228 (0.087)</cell>
                                <cell>0.9547 (0.104)</cell>
                                <cell>t(598)=-4.15</cell>
                                <cell>&lt;0.001***</cell>
                                <cell>-0.34</cell>
                                <cell>[-0.047, -0.017]</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>Parse tree depth (syntactic complexity)</cell>
                                <cell>5.65 (1.82)</cell>
                                <cell>6.34 (2.41)</cell>
                                <cell>t(598)=4.15</cell>
                                <cell>&lt;0.001***</cell>
                                <cell>0.33</cell>
                                <cell>[0.36, 1.02]</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>Modal verb ratio (epistemic stance)</cell>
                                <cell>0.0039 (0.0084)</cell>
                                <cell>0.0052 (0.0118)</cell>
                                <cell>t(598)=1.67</cell>
                                <cell>0.096</cell>
                                <cell>0.13</cell>
                                <cell>[-0.0002, 0.0028]</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>Modal diversity (Shannon entropy)</cell>
                                <cell>1.68 (0.52)</cell>
                                <cell>2.14 (0.61)</cell>
                                <cell>t(598)=5.32</cell>
                                <cell>&lt;0.001***</cell>
                                <cell>0.43</cell>
                                <cell>[0.29, 0.63]</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>Discourse marker ratio</cell>
                                <cell>0.0156 (0.0089)</cell>
                                <cell>0.0183 (0.0112)</cell>
                                <cell>t(598)=2.89</cell>
                                <cell>0.004**</cell>
                                <cell>0.27</cell>
                                <cell>[0.0009, 0.0045]</cell>
                            </row>
                            <row role="data">
                                <cell>Sentence length (words)</cell>
                                <cell>12.4 (5.8)</cell>
                                <cell>11.8 (6.3)</cell>
                                <cell>t(598)=-1.23</cell>
                                <cell>0.219</cell>
                                <cell>-0.10</cell>
                                <cell>[-1.58, 0.36]</cell>
                            </row>
                        </table>
                        <p>Table 1. Comparative Stylometric Features: CoVoST vs. SBCSAE. Note: MTTR
                            = Mean Type-Token Ratio. All tests are independent samples t-tests
                            (two-tailed, α=0.05). Effect size interpretation follows Cohen (1988):
                            small (d=0.2), medium (d=0.5), large (d=0.8). ***p&lt;0.001,
                            **p&lt;0.01, *p&lt;0.05.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.1.2 Syntactic Templating and the Binary Logic of Translation
                            Processing</head>
                        <p>Parse tree depth analysis revealed an average depth of 5.65 (SD=1.82)
                            across the sample<note> Note: I acknowledge that comparing translated
                                speech (CoVoST) with transcribed original speech (SBCSAE) conflates
                                translation effects with potential transcription/translation process
                                differences. The syntactic flattening I observe may reflect: (1)
                                translator strategies for managing speech-to-text conversion, (2)
                                target language (English) preferences, (3) source language (Chinese)
                                syntactic patterns, or (4) professional translation norms.
                                Disentangling these factors requires additional comparative
                                data.</note>. Statistical comparison with SBCSAE (M=6.34, SD=2.41)
                            reveals significantly shallower syntactic structures in CoVoST (<hi
                                rend="italic">t</hi>(598)=4.15, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>&lt;0.001,
                            Cohen's <hi rend="italic">d</hi>=0.33). The distribution (Figure 2)
                            shows two distinct peaks: one centred around depth 4–5 (simpler
                            structures) and another around depth 7–8 (more complex structures). This
                            bimodal distribution aligns with my unsupervised clustering results,
                            which identified two dominant style regimes in the corpus. <figure>
                                <head>Distribution of parse tree depth in CoVoST translations
                                    (n=300, blue) and SBCSAE original speech (n=300, orange). CoVoST
                                    exhibits bimodal distribution with peaks at depths 4–5 and 7–8,
                                    suggesting binary syntactic templating. SBCSAE shows more
                                    continuous distribution spanning wider range (2–18 vs. 2–12).
                                    Distributions differ significantly (Kolmogorov-Smirnov D=0.187,
                                    p&lt;0.001).</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image2.png"/>
                            </figure> The maximum parse depth also differs markedly: CoVoST max=12
                            vs. SBCSAE max=18. This “complexity ceiling” suggests that translators
                            avoid deeply nested syntactic structures even when source content might
                            warrant them. The syntactic flattening may reflect translator strategies
                            for managing the speech-to-text modality shift — converting oral
                            disfluencies and complex embedded structures into more linear written
                            syntax.</p>
                        <p>This binary pattern evokes what <ptr target="#galloway_2012"/> terms “interface
                            effects” — the manner in which mediating processes compress human
                            expression into discrete categories. Notably, the relationship between
                            sentence length and parse tree depth was less variable than would be
                            expected in original English writing. Even as sentence length increased,
                            parse tree depth tended to plateau, suggesting a “syntactic flattening”
                            effect where the translator defaults to familiar syntactic templates
                            rather than constructing more deeply nested structures.</p>
                        <p>The emergence of two dominant syntactic regimes rather than a continuous
                            spectrum invites reflection on what <ptr target="#underwood_2019"/> identifies as a
                            systemic preference for recognizable patterns — a preference whose
                            consequences for the transmission of complex ideas across linguistic
                            boundaries warrant sustained critical attention.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.1.3 Modal Verb Distribution and the Politics of Certainty</head>
                        <p>The analysis of modal verb frequency revealed an average modal ratio of
                            0.0039 (SD=0.0084). Comparison with SBCSAE (M=0.0052, SD=0.0118) shows
                            no significant difference in overall modal frequency (<hi rend="italic"
                                >t</hi>(598)=1.67, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>=0.096, Cohen's <hi
                                rend="italic">d</hi>=0.13). However, modal distribution patterns
                            differ significantly (χ²=47.3, df=8, <hi rend="italic">p</hi>&lt;0.001),
                            with “will” and “can” together accounting for 73% of modal usage in
                            CoVoST compared to 52% in SBCSAE (Figure 3). <figure>
                                <head>Frequency Distribution of Modal Verbs in CoVoST Human
                                    Translation Output.</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
                                <figDesc>PLACEHOLDER</figDesc>
                            </figure> Statistical analysis of modal diversity (measured as Shannon
                            entropy of modal distribution) confirms this pattern: CoVoST <hi
                                rend="italic">H</hi>=1.68 vs. SBCSAE <hi rend="italic">H</hi>=2.14
                                (<hi rend="italic">t</hi>(598)=5.32, <hi rend="italic"
                            >p</hi>&lt;0.001, Cohen's <hi rend="italic">d</hi>=0.43). This medium
                            effect size indicates that translation is associated with measurable
                            reduction in modal diversity. The preference for “will” and “can” over
                            semantically similar but less frequent alternatives may reflect
                            translator cognitive efficiency strategies — defaulting to
                            high-frequency, semantically transparent modals rather than nuanced
                            alternatives. However, this pattern could also reflect source language
                            (Chinese) modal system differences, as Chinese modal particles do not
                            map one-to-one onto English modal verbs.</p>
                        <p>The limited use of modals expressing uncertainty (“might,” “may,”
                            “could”) points to a flattened epistemic profile in translation, one
                            that privileges definiteness over the nuanced ambiguity characteristic
                            of spontaneous speech. Concurrently, the dominance of these two modals
                            over those expressing obligation or permission raises questions about
                            how cultural differences in epistemic stance may be compressed during
                            the speech-to-text translation process.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.1.4 Discourse Marker Patterns and the Mechanics of Coherence</head>
                        <p>Discourse marker analysis showed an average marker ratio of 0.0031, with
                            “therefore” and “however” being the most commonly used markers. The
                            distribution of discourse markers (Figure 4) revealed a preference for
                            additive and contrastive markers over causal or temporal ones,
                            suggesting a tendency toward simplified logical cohesion in translation. <figure>
                                <head>Distribution of Discourse Marker Types in Speech
                                    Translations.</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image4.png"/>
                                <figDesc>PLACEHOLDER</figDesc>
                            </figure> The relatively low overall frequency of discourse markers
                            compared to original English writing suggests a possible
                            underrepresentation of explicit cohesive devices. The preference for
                            additive and contrastive markers over causal and temporal ones may
                            reflect how translators prioritize local coherence at the expense of the
                            more varied rhetorical architecture found in spontaneous speech.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5.2 Machine Learning Insights</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.2.1 Binary Stylistic Regimes</head>
                        <p>K-means clustering with <hi rend="italic">k</hi>=2 revealed two distinct
                            stylistic clusters within the corpus (Figure 5):</p>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>PLACEHOLDERCluster 0 (73% of samples): Characterized by shorter
                                sentences (average token count: 9.43), simpler syntactic structures
                                (lower parse tree depth), and lower lexical diversity.</item>
                            <item>Cluster 1 (27% of samples): Characterized by longer sentences
                                (average token count: 21.58), more complex syntactic structures, and
                                higher lexical diversity.</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>
                            <figure>
                                <head>K-Means Clustering of Stylometric Profiles in Human
                                    Translation Output (k=2).</head>
                                <graphic url="resources/images/image5.png"/>
                                <figDesc>PLACEHOLDDER</figDesc>
                            </figure>The emergence of two primary “style modes” rather than a
                            continuous spectrum suggests that translators may default to one of two
                            stylistic templates, a pattern <ptr target="#steyerl_2014"/> might characterize as a
                            form of reductive standardization — one that compresses the nuanced
                            variation present in source speech into binary categories.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.2.2 Feature Importance and the Politics of Algorithmic
                            Attention</head>
                        <p>SHAP analysis of my Random Forest classifier revealed that four features
                            accounted for over 87% of the model's predictive power in domain
                            classification:</p>
                        <list type="unordered">
                            <item>MTTR (lexical diversity): 27.7%</item>
                            <item>Parse tree depth (syntactic complexity): 21.6%</item>
                            <item>Token count (sentence length): 19.5%</item>
                            <item>Average sentence length: 18.9%</item>
                        </list>
                        <p>The dominance of these structural features over content-specific ones
                            (such as particular modal verbs or discourse markers) indicates a
                            systemic privileging of form over content <ptr target="#liu_2012"/>. This finding
                            supports my hypothesis that consistency patterns manifest primarily
                            through standardized structural patterns rather than content-sensitive
                            stylistic adaptation.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5.3 Content Analysis and the Cultural Politics of Translation</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.3.1 Sentence Function Distribution</head>
                        <p>My QCA classification of sentence functions revealed a strong
                            predominance of factual statements (approximately 80% of sentences),
                            with questions, opinions, and directives appearing at much lower
                            frequencies. This predominance may reflect what <ptr target="#hayles_2012"/>
                            identifies as a preference for informational content over interactive or
                            evaluative functions, with implications for how voice and agency are
                            represented in translated speech.</p>
                        <p>The relationship between sentence function and stylometric features was
                            also revealing: Factual statements showed the most consistent
                            stylometric patterns, while opinions and directives exhibited greater
                            stylistic variation. This variation suggests that different speech acts
                            exhibit differential resistance to stylistic standardization:
                            straightforward informational content appears most susceptible to
                            consistency bias, while more complex communicative functions retain
                            greater stylistic latitude.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>5.3.2 Domain Distribution</head>
                        <p>The domain classification revealed that general content dominated the
                            corpus (79.0%), followed by historical (10.7%), cultural (5.7%),
                            political (4.0%), and smaller proportions of technical and medical
                            content (0.3% each). Cross-referencing domains with stylometric features
                            revealed limited domain-specific stylistic adaptation. While some
                            variation was observed (e.g., historical content showed slightly higher
                            parse tree depth on average), the differences were less pronounced than
                            would be expected in original English writing across these domains.</p>
                        <p>This limited domain-specific adaptation further corroborates the
                            consistency bias hypothesis: Human translators appear to apply
                            relatively standardized stylistic patterns regardless of content domain,
                            rather than calibrating their output to domain-specific conventions. The
                            tension between professional efficiency and cultural specificity becomes
                            particularly salient when translation mediates between distinct
                            linguistic and cultural contexts.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5.4 Classification Performance</head>
                    <p>My Random Forest classifier achieved an accuracy of 61.11% in predicting
                        content domains based solely on stylometric features. This performance,
                        significantly above the baseline for this multi-class classification task,
                        indicates that despite the consistency patterns, some domain-specific
                        stylistic signals remain detectable in the speech-to-text output.</p>
                    <p>However, the classification report revealed uneven performance across
                        domains. The model performed best on the “general” category (precision:
                        0.71, recall: 0.84) but struggled with more specialized domains like
                        “cultural” (precision: 0.00, recall: 0.00) and “political” (precision: 0.00,
                        recall: 0.00). This uneven performance suggests that certain cultural
                        domains resist stylometric categorization more than others, a finding
                        consistent with the broader consistency bias observed across the corpus.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>5.5 Validation Sample Analysis</head>
                    <p>To verify the robustness of my findings, I conducted validation analysis on
                        an independent sample of 200 sentences drawn from the remaining CoVoST test
                        set (n=3,932) using a different random seed (seed=2024). Results confirmed
                        the consistency of my primary findings:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>MTTR: Primary sample M=0.9228, Validation M=0.9241 (SD=0.091),
                            t(498)=0.16, p=0.872</item>
                        <item>Parse tree depth: Primary M=5.65, Validation M=5.71 (SD=1.89),
                            t(498)=0.35, p=0.729</item>
                        <item>K-means clustering: Validation sample shows same 73%/27% binary
                            cluster distribution (χ²=0.21, p=0.647)</item>
                        <item>Random Forest accuracy: Validation sample 59.5% vs. primary sample
                            61.11% (McNemar's test p=0.412)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>These non-significant differences confirm that my findings are not artifacts
                        of specific sample selection but represent generalizable patterns in the
                        CoVoST test set.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>6. Discussion</head>
                <div>
                    <head>6.1 Translation Consistency Patterns and Professional Practice</head>
                    <p>The results of my stylometric analysis reveal a distinctive pattern I term
                        stylometric consistency bias in professional human translations of spoken
                        Chinese to written English. This phenomenon manifests not merely as a
                        technical limitation but as a distinctive translational aesthetic that
                        emerges from the interaction between spoken source material and professional
                        translation practice. The bimodal distribution observed in my clustering
                        analysis — revealing two dominant “style regimes” rather than a continuous
                        spectrum of stylistic variation — suggests that speech-to-text translations
                        operate with a limited stylistic repertoire that prioritizes professional
                        efficiency over expressive diversity. This “algorithmic habitus” in human
                        translation practice suggests that professional and cognitive constraints
                        produce standardized output — not because humans are becoming machine-like,
                        but because both human and machine translation operate under efficiency
                        pressures that favour consistency over contextual variation.</p>
                    <p>This binary stylistic templating aligns with what <ptr target="#galloway_2012"/> describes
                        as “interface effects.” The interface between spoken Chinese and written
                        English appears to enforce a standardized aesthetic that compresses the rich
                        variation of human expression. This standardization raises important
                        questions about what is lost when translation crosses not only linguistic
                        but also modal boundaries (from speech to text). Additionally, the dominance
                        of structural features (MTTR, parse tree depth, sentence length) in
                        predicting content domains further supports this interpretation: The
                        translator's output is characterized more by formal linguistic properties
                        than by domain-appropriate stylistic choices, reflecting a tendency to
                        prioritize structural regularity over contextual sensitivity.</p>
                    <p>The observed lexical consistency patterns — where MTTR values cluster around
                        a standardized level regardless of content type — point to a systematic
                        flattening of linguistic diversity. Unlike the simplification universals
                        described in previous translationese research <ptr target="#baker_1993"/>, this is not
                        necessarily a reduction in lexical diversity <hi rend="italic">per se</hi>,
                        but rather a standardization of lexical diversity across different content
                        types. This distinction is important, as it suggests that consistency bias
                        manifests not as universal simplification but as the imposition of a uniform
                        stylistic register that serves professional efficiency rather than
                        expressive fidelity.</p>
                    <p>In addition, my comparative analysis using SBCSAE as a baseline represents a
                        significant methodological improvement over comparisons with written
                        corpora, but important limitations remain. The comparison conflates three
                        distinct factors:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Translation vs. transcription: CoVoST involves cross-linguistic
                            transfer and target-language normalization, while SBCSAE involves
                            within-language transcription that aims to preserve original speech
                            features.</item>
                        <item>Source language influence: CoVoST translations may reflect Chinese
                            source language patterns (syntax, discourse organization) that differ
                            from English original speech in SBCSAE. Disentangling translation
                            effects from source language transfer would require parallel analysis of
                            source Chinese audio, which is beyond my current scope.</item>
                        <item>Professional vs. naturalistic speech: CoVoST translations are produced
                            by professional translators under specific task constraints, while
                            SBCSAE represents spontaneous conversation. The consistency patterns I
                            observe may reflect professional translation practices rather than
                            inherent properties of translated speech.</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>These confounds mean my findings should be interpreted as exploratory
                        patterns that identify potentially translation-related stylometric features,
                        rather than definitive evidence of translation effects. Future research
                        incorporating parallel original/translated speech corpora, multiple language
                        pairs with shared target language, and experimental manipulation of
                        translation vs. transcription tasks would provide stronger causal inference
                        about the sources of stylometric consistency in speech-to-text
                        translation.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.2 Cultural Implications of Standardization in Translation
                        Practice</head>
                    <p>The standardization observed in my analysis raises critical questions about
                        cultural loss in translation. <ptr target="#piper_2018"/> argues that stylistic patterns
                        encode specific cultural and cognitive frameworks; their flattening through
                        translation may therefore represent a form of cultural attenuation. The
                        underrepresentation of modals expressing uncertainty and the predominance of
                        factual statements suggest a “certainty bias” — a preference for
                        definiteness that may reflect professional norms of clarity over the nuanced
                        ambiguity characteristic of spontaneous speech.</p>
                    <p>This tendency resonates with Steyerl's (2014) analysis of the politics of
                        readability — the manner in which standardized systems prioritize
                        processability over cultural specificity. In the context of
                        Chinese-to-English translation, this raises particular concerns about how
                        non-Western linguistic patterns and cultural expressions might be
                        systematically reshaped to conform to target-language norms developed
                        primarily in Western professional contexts.</p>
                    <p>The relatively low frequency of discourse markers compared to benchmark
                        values from original English writing indicates a possible
                        underrepresentation of explicit cohesive devices. This finding contrasts
                        with the “explicitation hypothesis”in human translation <ptr target="#blum-kulka_1986"/>,
                        which suggests that translations tend to be more explicit than original
                        texts. My results suggest that human translators of speech may not follow
                        this pattern, instead producing less explicitly cohesive text than would be
                        expected in original spoken discourse. This pattern may reflect the
                        cognitive demands of simultaneous modality shift and linguistic transfer,
                        which leave fewer resources for explicit cohesion marking.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.3 Toward a Critical Theory of Translation Standardization
                        Patterns</head>
                    <p>My findings suggest the need for a critical theory of translation
                        standardization patterns that accounts for the specific aesthetic and
                        political dimensions of human speech-to-text translations. Traditional
                        notions of translationese have focused on the differences between translated
                        and original text <ptr target="#gellerstam_1986"/> or between human and machine
                        translation <ptr target="#toral-way_2018"/>. My research points to a third dimension: the
                        emergence of a distinctive translational voice that reflects the specific
                        constraints and biases of the speech-to-text modality shift.</p>
                    <p>I propose the term <term>speech-to-text translation
                            characteristics</term> to describe this phenomenon — a set of stylistic
                        features characterized by:</p>
                    <list type="unordered">
                        <item>Binary stylistic templating (alternating between two dominant style
                            regimes)</item>
                        <item>Lexical consistency patterns (standardized lexical diversity
                            regardless of content)</item>
                        <item>Syntactic flattening (limited variation in parse tree depth relative
                            to sentence complexity)</item>
                        <item>Reduced modal and discourse marker diversity (limited expression of
                            uncertainty and logical relationships)</item>
                        <item>Domain-invariant stylistic patterns (limited adaptation to
                            domain-specific conventions)</item>
                    </list>
                    <p>This conceptualization moves beyond simple human-vs-machine binaries to
                        recognize the specific stylistic fingerprint of human speech-to-text
                        translation as a cultural text worthy of critical interpretation. It
                        acknowledges that human translators produce output with distinctive
                        aesthetic characteristics that reflect not just technical limitations but
                        specific professional values, cognitive constraints, and translational
                        priorities.</p>
                    <p>Ramsay's (2011) algorithmic criticism invites us to treat these patterns not
                        as mere technical artifacts but as sites for critical engagement with the
                        politics of translation. The standardization of linguistic output according
                        to professional efficiency rather than cultural sensitivity raises pressing
                        questions about whose communicative needs are served — and whose are
                        attenuated — by prevailing translation practices.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.4 Ethical Dimensions of Voice Representation</head>
                    <p>The consistency patterns identified in my analysis raise important ethical
                        questions about voice representation in speech-to-text translation contexts.
                        As speech-to-text translation becomes increasingly prevalent in
                        cross-cultural communication, education, and media consumption, the
                        flattening of stylistic diversity may have far-reaching consequences for how
                        individual and cultural voices are represented and perceived.</p>
                    <p>Chun's (2011) work on the programmability of vision provides a useful
                        framework for understanding how translation practices reshape not just
                        individual translations but our broader understanding of cross-linguistic
                        communication. Just as image-processing algorithms shape what we can see,
                        translation practices shape what we can hear and understand across
                        linguistic boundaries. The standardization of output according to
                        professional norms may therefore constitute a form of discursive power that
                        privileges certain modes of expression over others.</p>
                    <p>These patterns raise important questions about consent and agency in
                        speech-to-text translation. When a speaker's voice is processed through a
                        translation process that systematically reshapes their linguistic expression
                        according to professional norms, to what extent is their voice still their
                        own? This question becomes particularly urgent in contexts where translation
                        mediates communication between individuals with different levels of power
                        and privilege — for instance, in immigration proceedings, international
                        business negotiations, or cross-cultural educational settings.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.5 Implications for Translation Practice and Future Research</head>
                    <p>My findings carry several implications for translation practice and pedagogy.
                        First, they suggest that current evaluation metrics, which focus primarily
                        on accuracy and fluency, may not adequately capture the stylistic dimensions
                        of translation quality. Incorporating stylometric measures into evaluation
                        frameworks could provide a more comprehensive assessment of speech-to-text
                        translation that accounts for the preservation of stylistic diversity and
                        cultural specificity.</p>
                    <p>Second, the identified consistency patterns suggest potential areas for
                        improvement in translator training. Pedagogical approaches that explicitly
                        cultivate stylistic variation could help address the binary templating
                        tendency I observed. Similarly, domain-specific training might enhance
                        translators' ability to produce domain-appropriate stylistic features that
                        better reflect the rich variation of human expression.</p>
                    <p>Third, my results highlight the importance of diverse source data that
                        includes varied speech styles and registers. The dominance of factual
                        statements in my corpus suggests a potential bias in the source data toward
                        informational content, which may limit translators' exposure to other speech
                        functions effectively. Expanding source data to include a wider range of
                        speech acts and cultural contexts could help address this limitation.</p>
                    <p>Finally, my analysis suggests the need for more interdisciplinary approaches
                        to translation studies that integrate insights from linguistics, cognitive
                        science, and digital humanities. Future research might consider how the
                        consistency patterns identified here inform the assessment of AI translation
                        systems, given that such systems are often trained on human-translated
                        corpora like CoVoST. These observations would prove useful in evaluating
                        whether machine translation amplifies or attenuates the consistency bias
                        already present in human translation practice.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>6.6 Limitations and Future Research</head>
                    <p>Several limitations of my study should be acknowledged. First, my analysis
                        focused on a single language pair (Chinese to English) and a specific
                        translation context (the CoVoST corpus). Future research should examine
                        whether similar patterns emerge across different language pairs and
                        speech-to-text translation contexts, particularly those involving
                        non-Western languages and diverse cultural contexts. </p>
                    <p>Second, while my sample size (300 sentences) was sufficient for detailed
                        stylometric analysis, a larger-scale study could provide more robust
                        statistical evidence and potentially reveal more subtle patterns. </p>
                    <p>Third, my study did not have access to the original Chinese speech
                        recordings, which limited my ability to analyze how specific features of the
                        source speech influenced the translated output. Future research
                        incorporating parallel analysis of source speech and translated text could
                        provide valuable insights into this relationship.</p>
                    <p>Finally, my machine learning approach, while revealing important patterns,
                        represents just one possible analytical framework. Alternative approaches,
                        such as deep learning-based stylistic analysis or more sophisticated natural
                        language processing techniques, could uncover additional dimensions of
                        consistency bias not captured in my current analysis.</p>
                    <p>Future research should proceed along five convergent lines. First, a
                        systematic comparative analysis of speech-to-text versus text-to-text
                        translation would help isolate modality-specific effects. Second, human
                        perception studies are needed to examine how consistency bias shapes user
                        experience and comprehension across culturally diverse audiences. Third, a
                        longitudinal programme tracking translation practices across successive
                        versions would reveal whether consistency bias intensifies or diversifies
                        over time. Fourth, cross-linguistic replication using language pairs beyond
                        Chinese–English would test the generalizability of the consistency bias
                        construct. Fifth, experimental studies comparing translator output under
                        different task constraints (e.g., time pressure, domain expertise) could
                        help disentangle cognitive from professional sources of standardization.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>7. Conclusion</head>
                <p>This study has demonstrated that professional human translations of spoken
                    Chinese to written English exhibit distinctive stylometric consistency patterns
                    that manifest across multiple linguistic dimensions. Through an integrated
                    framework combining stylometric analysis, machine learning, and digital
                    humanities critique, I have identified a <term>consistency bias</term>
                    characterized by standardized lexical diversity, binary syntactic templating,
                    reduced modal diversity, and domain-invariant stylistic patterns.</p>
                <p>These findings contribute to translation studies by extending the concept of
                    translationese to speech-to-text translation and by identifying specific
                    stylometric features that characterize this modality shift. They contribute to
                    digital humanities by demonstrating how computational methods can reveal the
                    cultural dimensions of translation practice and by providing empirical evidence
                    for critical theories of standardized text production.</p>
                <p>This project exemplifies a digital humanities approach that uses computational
                    methods not only to measure stylistic effects but to interrogate how translation
                    practices recursively shape the aesthetics they purport to reproduce.</p>
                <p>Most fundamentally, my research raises critical questions about the nature of
                    voice in speech-to-text translation. The consistency patterns bias I have
                    identified suggests that professional translation does not simply transfer — it
                    reshapes linguistic expression according to professional norms that may not
                    align with the expressive intentions of original speakers. As speech-to-text
                    translation becomes increasingly central to global communication, understanding
                    and addressing these consistency patterns becomes not just a technical challenge
                    but an ethical imperative.</p>
                <p>The implications of this research extend to the development and evaluation of AI
                    translation systems, which are frequently trained on human-translated corpora
                    such as CoVoST. Future research might consider whether machine translation
                    systems amplify or attenuate the consistency bias already present in human
                    translation practice — a question with profound consequences for the fidelity of
                    cross-cultural communication in the digital age.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baker_1993" label="Baker 1993">Baker, M. (1993) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Corpus linguistics and translation studies: implications and
                        applications</title>, in Baker, M., Francis, G. and Tognini-Bonelli, E.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">Text and Technology: In Honour of John
                        Sinclair</title>. Amsterdam: John Benjamins, pp. 233–250.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bisiada_2018" label="Bisiada 2018">Bisiada, M. (2018) <title
                        rend="quotes">Translation and editing: A study of editorial treatment of
                        nominalisations in draft translations</title>, <title rend="italic"
                        >Perspectives: Studies in Translation Theory and Practice</title>, 26(1),
                    pp. 24–38 <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/0907676X.2017.1290121"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1080/0907676X.2017.1290121</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blum-kulka_1986" label="Blum-Kulka 1986">Blum-Kulka, S. (1986) <title
                        rend="quotes">Shifts of cohesion and coherence in translation</title>, in
                    House, J. and Blum-Kulka, S. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Interlingual and
                        Intercultural Communication: Discourse and Cognition in Translation and
                        Second Language Acquisition Studies</title>. Tübingen: Gunter Narr, pp.
                    17–35.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chun_2011" label="Chun 2011">Chun, W.H.K. (2011) <title rend="italic"
                        >Programmed visions: Software and memory</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="di-gangi_2019" label="Di Gangi et al. 2019" sortKey="Digangi">Di
                    Gangi, M.A., Cattoni, R., Bentivogli, L., Negri, M. and Turchi, M. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes">MuST-C: A multilingual speech translation corpus</title>, in
                        <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2019 Conference of the North
                        American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human
                        Language Technologies, Volume 1 (Long and Short Papers)</title>.
                    Minneapolis, MN: Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 2012–2017. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/N19-1202"
                        >https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/N19-1202</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker_2012" label="Drucker 2012">Drucker, J. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Humanistic theory
                        and digital scholarship</title>, in Gold, M.K. (ed.) <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis, MN: University of
                    Minnesota Press, pp. 85–95.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="du-bois_2005" label="Du Bois et al. 2000-2005" sortKey="Dubois">Du Bois, J.W., Chafe, W.L., Meyer, C., Thompson, S.A.,
                    Englebretson, R. and Martey, N. (2000–2005) <title rend="italic">Santa Barbara
                        Corpus of Spoken American English, Parts 1–4</title> [corpus]. Philadelphia,
                    PA: Linguistic Data Consortium.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="galloway_2012" label="galloway_2012">Galloway, A.R. (2012) <title rend="italic">The interface
                        effect</title>. Cambridge: Polity Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gellerstam_1986" label="gellertstam_1986">Gellerstam, M. (1986) <title rend="quotes">Translationese
                        in Swedish novels translated from English</title>, in Wollin, L. and
                    Lindquist, H. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Translation Studies in
                        Scandinavia</title>. Lund: CWK Gleerup, pp. 88–95. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="graham_2019" label="Graham, Haddow, and Koehn 2019">Graham, Y., Haddow, B. and Koehn, P. (2019) <title
                        rend="quotes">Translationese in machine translation evaluation</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">arXiv</title> [cs.CL]. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1906.09833"
                        >https://doi.org/10.48550/arXiv.1906.09833</ref>
                </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hayles_2012" label="Hayles 2012">Hayles, N.K. (2012) <title rend="italic">How we think:
                        Digital media and contemporary technogenesis</title>. Chicago, IL:
                    University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="jockers_2013" label="Jockers 2013">Jockers, M.L. (2013) <title rend="italic">Macroanalysis:
                        Digital methods and literary history</title>. Urbana, IL: University of
                    Illinois Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kurokawa_2009" label="Kurokawa, Goutte, and Isabell 2009">Kurokawa, D., Goutte, C. and Isabelle, P. (2009) <title
                        rend="quotes">Automatic detection of translated text and its impact on
                        machine translation</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Machine
                        Translation Summit XII: Papers</title>. Ottawa, Canada, pp. 81–88.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="laviosa_1998" label="Laviosa 1998">Laviosa, S. (1998) <title rend="quotes">Core patterns of
                        lexical use in a comparable corpus of English narrative prose</title>,
                        <title rend="italic">Meta: Translators’ Journal</title>, 43(4), pp. 557–570.
                        <ref target="https://doi.org/10.7202/003425ar"
                        >https://doi.org/10.7202/003425ar</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lembersky_2012" label="Lembersky, Ordan, and Wintner 2012">Lembersky, G., Ordan, N. and Wintner, S. (2012) <title
                        rend="quotes">Language models for machine translation: Original vs.
                        translated texts</title>, <title rend="italic">Computational
                        Linguistics</title>, 38(4), pp. 799–825. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1162/COLI_a_00111"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1162/COLI_a_00111</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="liu_2012" label="Liu 2012">Liu, A. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Where Is cultural
                        criticism in the digital humanities?</title>, in Gold, M.K. (ed.) <title
                        rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Minneapolis, MN:
                    University of Minnesota Press, pp. 490–509.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti_2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, F. (2013) <title rend="italic">Distant
                        reading</title>. London: Verso.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piper_2018" label="Piper 2018">Piper, A. (2018) <title rend="italic">Enumerations: Data
                        and literary study</title>. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="radford_2022" label="Radford et al. 2022">Radford, A., Kim, J.W., Xu, T., Brockman, G., McLeavey, C.
                    and Sutskever, I. (2022) <title rend="quotes">Robust speech recognition via
                        large-scale weak supervision</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        Machine Learning Research</title>, 23(219), pp. 1–39.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ramsay_2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, S. (2011) <title rend="italic">Reading Machines:
                        Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>. Urbana, IL: University of Illinois
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="riley_2020" label="Riley et al. 2020">Riley, P., Caswell, I., Freitag, M. and Grangier, D. (2020)
                    <title rend="quotes">Translationese as a Language in <soCalled>multilingual</soCalled> NMT</title>, in <title rend="italic"
                        >Proceedings of the 58th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational
                        Linguistics</title>. Online: Association for Computational Linguistics, pp.
                    7737–7746. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.691"
                        >https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.691</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sperber_2020" label="Sperber and Paulik 2020">Sperber, M. and Paulik, M. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                        >Speech translation and the end-to-end promise: Taking stock of where we
                        are</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 58th Annual Meeting
                        of the Association for Computational Linguistics</title>. Online:
                    Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 7409–7421. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.661"
                        >https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2020.acl-main.661</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="steyerl_2014" label="Steyerl 2014">Steyerl, H. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Proxy politics:
                        Signal and noise</title>, <title rend="italic">e-flux Journal</title>, 60,
                    pp. 1–10. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://www.e-flux.com/journal/60/61045/proxy-politics-signal-and-noise"
                        >https://www.e-flux.com/journal/60/61045/proxy-politics-signal-and-noise</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tan_2025" label="Tan et al. 2025">Tan, H., Faradishi Widiaputri, R., Meyer Saragih, J., Ko,
                    Y., Sudoh, K., Nakamura, S. and Sakti, S. (2025) <title rend="quotes">NAIST
                        simultaneous speech translation system for IWSLT 2025</title>, in <title
                        rend="italic">Proceedings of the 22nd International Conference on Spoken
                        Language Translation (IWSLT 2025)</title>. Vienna, Austria (in-person and
                    online): Association for Computational Linguistics, pp. 369–378. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2025.iwslt-1.39"
                        >https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/2025.iwslt-1.39</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="toral-way_2018" label="Toral and Way 2018">Toral, A. and Way, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">What
                        Level of quality can neural machine translation attain on literary
                        text?</title>, in Moorkens, J., Castilho, S., Gaspari, F. and Doherty, S.
                    (eds.) <title rend="italic">Translation Quality Assessment: From Principles to
                        Practice</title>. Cham: Springer, pp. 263–287. <ref
                        target="https://www.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-91241-7_12"
                        >https://www.doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-91241-7_12</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="underwood_2019" label="Underwood 2019">Underwood, T. (2019) <title rend="italic">Distant Horizons:
                        Digital evidence and literary change</title>. Chicago, IL: University of
                    Chicago Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="waibel-fugen_2008" label="Waibel and Fügen 2008">Waibel, A. and Fügen, C. (2008) <title rend="quotes">Spoken
                        language translation</title>, <title rend="italic">IEEE Signal Processing
                        Magazine</title>, 25(3), pp. 70–79. <ref
                        target="https://doi.org/10.1109/MSP.2008.918415"
                        >https://doi.org/10.1109/MSP.2008.918415</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wang_2020" label="Wang et al. 2020">Wang, C., Pino, J., Wu, A. and Gu, J. (2020) <title
                        rend="quotes">CoVoST: A diverse multilingual speech-to-text translation
                        corpus</title>, in <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Twelfth Language
                        Resources and Evaluation Conference</title>. Marseille: European Language
                    Resources Association, pp. 4197–4203. Available at: <ref
                        target="https://aclanthology.org/2020.lrec-1.517/"
                        >https://aclanthology.org/2020.lrec-1.517/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zufferey-cartoni_2014" label="Zufferey and Cartoni 2014">PLACEHOLDER</bibl>

            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
