<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">The Ancient World in Nineteenth-Century Fiction; or,
                    Correlating Theme, Geography, and Sentiment in the Nineteenth Century Literary
                    Imagination</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Matthew L. <dhq:family>Jockers</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Nebraska</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mjockers@unl.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Associate Professor of English</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000250</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2016-06-07">7 June 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Natural Language Processing</item>
                        <item>Sentiment Analysis</item>
                        <item>Topic Modeling</item>
                        <item>Literature</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change who="EH" when="2016-04-06">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p><title rend="quotes">The Ancient World in 19th-Century Fiction</title> is a
                    lightly revised version of a lecture delivered at the first meeting of the
                    Digital Classicists Association. The intent of the lecture, in accordance with
                    the invitation to deliver it, was to introduce literary <q>macroanalysis</q> in
                    the context of the ancient world and offer some exploration of how the ancient
                    world is represented in the 19th-century literary imagination.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Macroanalysis of literary geography</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>My primary objective in this paper is to introduce some methods that fall under the
                umbrella of what I call <q>macroanalysis.</q> Despite my title, I’m not going to be
                drawing any grand conclusions about the ancient world. My hope is that by sharing
                these approaches I will stimulate some thought and give classicists a comfortable
                and familiar footing onto which I can introduce some foreign methodologies</p>
            <p> A couple of years ago, a small group of us in the Stanford Literary Lab became
                interested in literary geography, and we began work on a research project to map the
                places that appear in a corpus of 3500 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century
                    novels.<note> Initial results were presented as a co-authored paper at the 37<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> Annual Meeting of the Social Science History
                    Association: Allen, Ben, Cameron Blevins, Ryan Heuser and Matthew L. Jockers.
                        <title rend="quotes">A Geography of Nineteenth-Century English and American
                        Literature.</title> Social Science History Association, 37<hi
                        rend="superscript">th</hi> Annual Meeting, Vancouver, British Columbia,
                    November 2, 2012. </note> Obviously this work cannot be done by hand, or, more
                accurately, it cannot be done quickly and easily by hand. It turns out that this is
                not a simple problem to solve computationally either. We faced two primary problems. </p>
            <p>First was the problem of <emph>identification</emph>. How could we use computers to
                accurately identify place-names in novels? The obvious approach of using gazetteers
                proved problematic. In one gazetteer we consulted, <title rend="italic"
                    >Providence</title> was a place and so was <title rend="italic">Hope</title>:
                These may be places, yes, but they are also something else. Simply running a search
                for all places in the gazetteer that also appeared in the fiction would have yielded
                far too many false positives.</p>
            <p>Second was the problem of <title rend="italic">ambiguity</title>; place names are
                ambiguous. <title rend="italic">Charlotte</title>, for example, is used only as a
                first name in our corpus and never as a city. <title rend="italic">Florence</title>
                is almost always a character but occasionally a city in Italy. <title rend="italic"
                    >Charlton</title>, <title rend="italic">Denver</title>, <title rend="italic"
                    >Albany</title>, <title rend="italic">Hastings</title>, <title rend="italic"
                    >Belmont</title>, <title rend="italic">Gresham</title>, <title rend="italic"
                    >Wilmington</title>, and <title rend="italic">Woodstock</title> are all in our
                corpus, and all more commonly used as last names than as cities. A second problem of
                ambiguity is that place names are often reused in different locations: <title
                    rend="italic">Richmond</title> is both a town in southwest London and a city in
                Virginia. <title rend="italic">Dartmouth</title> is a city in England, the U.S.,
                Canada, and Australia. <title rend="italic">Georgia</title> is both a U.S. state and
                a country in Eastern Europe. </p>
            <p>To tackle the first problem of identification, we scrapped the gazetteer in favor of
                Named Entity Recognition (NER). NER is a Natural Language Processing (NLP) tool that
                identifies places using a trained statistical model that is sensitive to semantic
                and syntactic information in the text. NER is not perfect; it sometimes thinks that
                Florence the character is Florence the city, but we devised a way of muting that
                problem of place ambiguity using a technique called topic modeling.</p>
            <p>Topic modeling is a complex process that cannot be explained in detail here. I have
                written a useful explanation on my blog.<note> See <ref
                        target="http://www.matthewjockers.net/2011/09/29/the-lda-buffet-is-now-open-or-latent-dirichlet-allocation-for-english-majors/"
                        >http://www.matthewjockers.net/2011/09/29/the-lda-buffet-is-now-open-or-latent-dirichlet-allocation-for-english-majors/</ref></note>
                For now, you can think of books like plates that you fill up at a buffet full of
                topics, and in this case the topics are places. Imagine that Jane Austen and Herman
                Melville wandered into an imaginary buffet, but instead of choosing to fill their
                plates with peas and fish they chose the settings for their novels: so, Melville
                might choose a helping of New England and a bit of South Pacific, Austen a ladle of
                London and a smidgen of the English Midlands. The topic modeling process has a way
                of identifying and measuring these textual features as they exist within their
                individual plates and within the <q>buffet</q> as a whole. </p>
            <p> In other work I had done for my book, I had applied this technique as a way to
                identify 500 themes in a corpus of 3500 novels <ptr target="#jockers2013"/>. Figures
                1 and 2 offer example themes that the machine returned.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The first of these is a cluster of words that might be <emph>labeled</emph> or
                    <emph>described</emph> as <emph>wilderness and frontier</emph>. <note> These
                    word clouds are generated based on the weighted probabilistic data that the
                    topic modeling process returns. Larger words are more central to the overall
                    topic.</note> The second we might call <emph>ancient gods and
                    goddesses</emph>.<note> You can find all 500 themes on my web site: <ref
                        target="http://www.matthewjockers.net/macroanalysisbook/macro-themes/"
                        >http://www.matthewjockers.net/macroanalysisbook/macro-themes/</ref></note></p>
            <p>It turns out that a similar approach can be used to effectively identify and
                disambiguate the place names in the corpus. This topic modeling method works because
                when a writer sets a book in a particular place that writer tends to mention other
                places that are geographically related. An author writing about Ireland, for
                example, might mention Dublin, Galway, and Belfast. Another author writing about
                Belfast, Maine, is not likely to also mention Dublin and Galway and so the machine
                learns that Belfast, Ireland is different from Belfast, Maine.</p>
            <p>Figures 3 through 6 present four <q>place clusters</q> taken from 100 that I
                harvested in this research. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure06">
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>These clusters show that topic modeling can be used as an effective way to identify
                collocated place names and thereby aid in place-name disambiguation by giving us a
                general sense of the regions being talked about in the corpus. I found during this
                research that my conception of place needed to be a bit less geographic in nature
                and a bit less specific than what we had first imagined. That is to say, a bit less
                about Giza and more about Egypt, less about Crete and more about Greece. In
                retrospect this all seems very appropriate. In writing <title rend="italic"
                    >Ulysses</title> James Joyce was not, after all, trying to write an atlas of
                Dublin. Joyce wanted to capture the essence of the city.<note> This, despite that
                    fact that Joyce once jokingly bragged that if Dublin were destroyed <q>it would
                        be possible to rebuild the entire city, brick by brick, using <hi
                            rend="italic">Ulysses</hi>.</q> (For details see <ref
                        target="http://www.irishleftreview.org/2010/06/18/dublin-psychogeographical-society-bloomsday-special-3/"
                        >http://www.irishleftreview.org/2010/06/18/dublin-psychogeographical-society-bloomsday-special-3/</ref>)</note>
                And so, as it happens, the places this method identified did not necessarily have to
                be places you could find on a map: heaven and hell were both represented in the
                corpus, as were Mars, Venus and Earth. More important than these outliers, the
                technique provided a tractable means of disambiguating different places with the
                same names: <title rend="italic">Georgia</title>, for example, could appear inside a
                topic about the American South, as well as in a topic of countries in Eastern Europe
                (see figures 7 and 8).</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure07">
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Given the way the model works, we can be confident that instances of Georgia labeled
                by the topic model as occurring in the American South cluster are in fact mentions
                of the state, and those in the other topic are mentions of the country in Europe. </p>
            <p>Occasionally character names slip into the geographic clusters. Note, for example,
                the occurrence of the name <title rend="italic">Baltimore</title> in the Egypt
                cluster (<ref target="#figure06">Figure 6</ref>) or <title rend="italic"
                    >Logan</title> in the Greece cluster (<ref target="#figure07">Figure 7</ref>).
                But in general these errors are not frequent enough across the entire corpus to
                corrupt the general sense of place conveyed in the cluster. In Figure 9, you will
                notice that <title rend="italic">Illinois</title> shows up just below the <q>n</q>
                in <q>Ireland.</q>
                <title rend="italic">Illinois</title> appears in this cluster because our text
                collection contains several hundred books that were originally digitized by the
                University of Illinois. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>These books contain bits of boilerplate metadata that we had not yet effectively
                extracted when I prepared these images. We have subsequently improved on this
                problem, but here again, the error is trivial in the larger context.<note> To
                    improve the process, we took two approaches to this problem. First, we removed
                    from our consideration all places whose ambiguity we identified as especially
                    pernicious. Second, we ranked the places that the tagger had identified from
                    most to least frequent. We skimmed off the top 1000 places, which accounted for
                    more than 85% of all mentions of all places that the NER tool had detected. We
                    then divided these into four groups of 250 places and each of us, that is
                    myself, Ben Allen, Cameron Blevins, Ryan Heuser, identified and read a random
                    sample of 25 sentences in which each place occurred (we wrote a simple query
                    script for this). If a given place occurred more than 12 times as a last name or
                    other noun, or if the word changed the place to which it referred more than 12
                    times, we marked down the place in a blacklist. We were left with about 650
                    places we could trust.</note> Which is to say that even with these obvious
                aberrations, the tool successfully identifies a cluster of words that captures the
                essence of the <emph>place</emph> that we know as Ireland. Irish cities and regions
                — Dublin, Munster, Cork, Tipperary, Ulster, and so on, all surround the headword,
                    <q>Ireland.</q> Alongside these are smaller but obviously Irish localities:
                Galway Bay, Wicklow, etc. It is an imperfect method for identifying pure distinct
                places, but it is not at all ineffectual or unproductive in the identification of
                    <emph>place</emph> as defined more broadly and thought of in terms of
                    <emph>literary representation of place</emph> rather than pure geography. In
                that sense it is a very bad method for geographers and a very good method for
                literary scholars.</p>
            <p>Not only does the topic model data help to give us a sense of the dominant places in
                the corpus as a whole, the model also provides us with a book-by-book measure of the
                proportion, or percentage, of each place or theme in each text. As we might expect,
                the model returned proportional data that showed that the Irish authors in the
                corpus were far more likely to write about Ireland than their English or American
                peers. This kind of data can be used to plot literary attention to place over time;
                figure 10 presents a picture of attention to Ireland over time broken out by author
                nationality. </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>The y-axis in Figure 10 is a measure of the yearly mean proportion of the Ireland
                cluster. Which is to say that in 1839, to pick a random year, about 14% of the
                places mentioned in Irish-authored books were Ireland. </p>
            <p>To get the full sense of how Ireland is being portrayed within these particular books
                would seem to require closer inspection, and, at the scale of a few books, we could
                achieve this by close reading. As a method for gaining a fuller sense of how a place
                is represented across the entire corpus, however, close reading is just not
                plausible. </p>
            <p>The method I'm describing here is effective if we really wish to study the
                representation of place on a broad scale. The question becomes not, <emph>How is
                    Ireland depicted by the Irish author Maria Edgeworth?</emph>, but <emph>How is
                    Ireland depicted in the 19<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century Irish
                    novel?</emph> Or, to use another example, when authors are writing about
                    <emph>slavery</emph> in the <emph>American South</emph>, what words do they
                employ that express perspective, attitude, or sentiment; and even more importantly
                for literary history, how, if at all, do these representations change over time,
                across author genders, and across author nationalities (see Figure 11).</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Figure 11 introduces a third element of analysis: so far I have talked about place
                and theme, and here I introduce <emph>affect</emph> or what is more commonly
                referred to as <emph>sentiment</emph>. Using techniques similar to those described
                above, I generated a set of 25 sentiment clusters. You can see one of them in Figure
                11 (emphasized in red). For this work, I drew on research in the fields of sentiment
                analysis and opinion mining in order to develop a method of scoring the topical
                clusters. In my system, each cluster is scored on a scale from -1 to +1 where -1 is
                a very negative perspective (colored in red) and +1 is positive sentiment that is
                colored green; 0 is neutral and yellow. The scoring here is based in large part upon
                a list of 6800 positive and negative opinion/sentiment words for English collected
                by Bing Liu of the University of Illinois at Chicago in his <emph>opinion
                    lexicon</emph>
                <ptr target="#minqing2004"/>. <note> Also see <ref
                        target="http://www.cs.uic.edu/~liub/FBS/sentiment-analysis.html"
                        >http://www.cs.uic.edu/~liub/FBS/sentiment-analysis.html</ref></note> Space
                does not permit going into the details of the methodology here; I provide instead
                five more examples from the total of 25. Figure 11 shows a negative sentiment
                characterized by the large headwords of <emph>guilt</emph> and <emph>cruelty</emph>.
                Figure 12 shows five more clusters conveying (from top to bottom and then middle)
                that which is <emph>beautiful,</emph> that which is <emph>amiable</emph>, that which
                is <emph>wretched,</emph> that which is <emph>dead</emph>, and that which is
                    <emph>temperate</emph>.</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>Just like the thematic and geographic clusters previously discussd, the presence of
                these sentiments is measured across the corpus and across every book in the corpus.
                So, for example, the data suggest that the book in my collection with the most
                sustained expressions of <emph>guilt</emph> and <emph>cruelty</emph> is an
                Irish-authored novel appropriately titled <title rend="italic">The Victims of
                    Society</title>.</p>
            <p>By simultaneously analyzing data about sentiment alongside the data for place and
                theme, we can begin to explore and identify areas of the corpus and specific books
                in the corpus where certain places are statistically correlated with particular
                themes and/or particular emotions. Unsurprisingly, the theme most closely associated
                with Ireland, is a theme I have labeled <emph>Tenants and Landlords</emph> (Figure
                13). </p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>I say <q>unsurprising</q> because the history of Ireland in the 19<hi
                    rend="superscript">th</hi> century is largely a history of tensions between the
                landed and tenant classes. What was interesting about these correlations was that
                they varied dramatically depending on author nationality. So, for example, in novels
                written by Irish authors, the tenant landlord theme was correlated with
                representations of Ireland. When only English authors were examined, the statistical
                correlation dropped to a level indicating no correlation whatsoever. What this
                suggests, then, is that it is the Irish authors and not the English authors who are
                fixating on the tenant landlord situation within a specifically Irish context. Put
                into plain terms: English authors, when talking about Ireland, tend to avoid mention
                of the Tenant and Landlord situation.</p>
            <p>Other themes that correlated closely with Ireland included those in Table 1. I was
                rather disheartened to see <emph>drinking</emph> topping the list since it seems to
                confirm so many of the stereotypes we have about the Irish, but when I parsed the
                data, I discovered something surprising and unexpected.</p>
            <table>
                <row>
                    <cell>Drinking: Liquor and Beer</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Livestock and Produce</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Peasant Dwellings</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Family, Friends, and Neighbors</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Villains and Traitors</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Government and Rebellion</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Police and Magistrates</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>America</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Revenge and Vengeance</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Personal Character</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Crowds and Mobs</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Habits and Customs</cell>
                </row>
                <row>
                    <cell>Hatred and Jealousy</cell>
                </row>
            </table>
            <p>At the scale of the entire corpus, <emph>Ireland</emph> and <emph>drinking</emph>
                were highly correlated. When I examined the data for Irish authors alone, however, I
                discovered that there was not such a high correlation. The Irish wrote about Ireland
                and the Irish wrote about drinking, but the two things were not generally written
                about simultaneously. Seeing this, I naturally expected to find that it was the
                English authors who were tending to write about the two things simultaneously. I was
                wrong. How then could <emph>drinking</emph> have been correlated with
                    <emph>Ireland</emph> at the level of the whole corpus? It turns out we have the
                temperate Puritans to blame. It is the American authors who most closely associate
                    <emph>Ireland</emph> with <emph>drinking</emph>. Indeed, in American books where
                    <emph>drinking</emph> is a dominant theme, <emph>Ireland</emph> is the place
                most frequently mentioned. Also closely associated is the theme of <emph>Sin and
                    Repentance</emph>! So, at least in terms of this corpus, it would seem that a
                good deal of the blame for the stereotype of the hard drinking Irish sits squarely
                on American shoulders. </p>
            <p>I now return to the four place clusters and terrain that will be more familiar to
                classicists (seen together in Figure 14).</p>
            <figure>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>I have culled these four out of the larger set of 100 because these four seem to be
                most closely associated with the ancient world; or at least to literary
                representations of the ancient world as it existed in the 19<hi rend="superscript"
                    >th</hi>-century literary imagination. For each of these four place clusters, it
                is possible to track literary attention over time, by author sex and by author
                nationality. Figures 15-17 graph a few of these dimensions for illustration.</p>
            <figure>
                <head><title rend="italic">Egypt</title> when explored in terms of
                        <emph>time</emph> and <emph>author gender</emph></head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
                
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <head><title rend="italic">Egypt</title> when explored in terms of
                        <emph>time</emph> and <emph>author nation</emph></head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
                
            </figure>
            <figure>
                <head><title rend="italic">Mediterranean</title> in terms of
                        <emph>time</emph> and author <emph> nation</emph></head>
                <graphic url="resources/images/figure17.png"/>
                
            </figure>
            <p>In addition to graphing, or tracking, literary attention to these places over time, I
                can also examine how the appearance of certain locales is correlated with certain
                themes and sentiments, just as in the previous example of <title rend="italic"
                    >Ireland</title>. </p>
            <p>When representations of <title rend="italic">Egypt</title> are strong, the most
                highly correlated themes include <title rend="italic">Persian slavery, Gods and
                    Goddesses, Deserts, Art and Beauty, Earth and the Universe</title>. The most
                significant sentiments include that which is <emph>Magnificent and Splendid,</emph>
                that which is <emph>Holy and Sacred,</emph> that which is <emph>Beautiful,
                    and</emph> that which is <emph>Moral.</emph></p>
            <p>When representation of <title rend="italic">Greece</title> are strong, the most
                highly correlated themes include <emph>Gods and Goddesses, Philosophy and Wisdom,
                    Spirit and Soul, Art and Beauty, and Poetry</emph>. The most significant
                sentiments include that which is <emph>Magnificent and Splendid,</emph> that which
                is <emph>Holy and Sacred,</emph> that which is <emph>Beautiful,</emph> and that
                which is <emph>Moral.</emph><note> Note that these sentiments are identical to those
                    for Egypt</note></p>
            <p>When representation of <title rend="italic">Jerusalem</title> are strong, the most
                highly correlated themes include <emph>Jews, Land, Art and Beauty, Deserts,
                    Processions and Spectacles, Sin and Salvation, Victory in War,</emph> and
                    <emph>Heaven and the Soul</emph>. The most significant sentiments include that
                which is <emph>Holy and Sacred,</emph> and that which is <emph>Magnificent and
                    Splendid.</emph></p>
            <p>When representation of the <title rend="italic">Mediterranean</title> are strong, the
                most highly correlated themes include <emph>Ships and their Crews, Outlaws and
                    Robbers, Natural Beauty, Ruins, Female Heroines, Sea Voyages, Men with
                    Guns,</emph> and <emph>Servants.</emph> This is a very different thematic
                profile, and the most significant sentiments include that which is <emph>Fair and
                    Mild,</emph> that which is <emph>Magnificent and Splendid,</emph> and that which
                is <emph>Unhappy and Wretched.</emph></p>
            <p>It is tempting to move from these macroscale observations and correlations to deeper
                interpretations about the specific books in the corpus or the specific writers, and
                this movement between scales is precisely what I am advocating in my book, <title
                    rend="italic">Macroanalysis</title>. Instead of rehearsing those arguments here,
                I want to conclude with an observation of a more general nature. First a warning
                about the very sort of research I am engaged in: we need to keep in mind that this
                type of macroanalysis only reveals the larger, general tendencies in the corpus. The
                most we can say at this scale is that certain things tend to occur more often, or
                less often, than others; what we capture here are the general tendencies within the
                corpus. Having said that, I would also note that it is equally problematic to speak
                only of particulars. In other words, it is just as dangerous to move from distant
                readings to specific conclusions as it to move from close reading to general
                theories of literary history. Just as we would not expect an economist to generate a
                sound theory about the economy based on the behavior of few workers in his or her
                neighborhood, I don’t think we can generate sound theories of literary history by
                reading only a few books.</p>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="Jockers 2013" xml:id="jockers2013">Jockers, Matthew. <title
                        rend="italic">Macroanalysis: Digital Methods and Literary History</title>.
                    University of Illinois Press, 2013. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Minqing and Liu 2004" xml:id="minqing2004">Minqing Hu and Bing Liu.
                        <title rend="quotes">Mining Opinion Features in Customer Reviews.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Proceedings of Nineteenth National Conference on Artificial
                        Intelligence</title> (AAAI-2004), San Jose, USA, July 2004.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
