<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Excavating Infrastructure in the Analog Humanities’
               Lab: An Analysis of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Aleksandra <dhq:family>Kil</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Wrocław (Poland)</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>aleksandra.kil-matlak@uwr.edu.pl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Aleksandra Kil is a PhD candidate in Cultural Studies and a member of the
                     Laboratory of Contemporary Humanities at the University of Wrocław (Poland).
                     Her research areas include media theory and philosophy of the humanities. In
                     her current work she studies index cards as an apparatus of making knowledge in
                     the analog humanities.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000468</idno>
            <idno type="volume">014</idno>
            <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2020-09-25">25 September 2020</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2020-05-22" who="jmurel">Finished encoding</change>
         <change when="2020-05-08" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>In this paper I present Claude Lévi-Strauss’s <title rend="italic">Laboratoire
                  d’anthropologie sociale</title> (LAS), established in 1960, as a case study of the
               archaeology of the humanities infrastructure. Building on media archaeology and
               critical infrastructure studies, I stress the significance of the research
               infrastructure in the analog humanities and I show how the LAS was organized around
               the Human Relations Area Files (HRAF), a vast ethnographical pre-electronic
               repository produced at Yale. The paper looks into how the <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> were mobilized to secure funding and space for Lévi-Strauss’s lab
               and gain infrastructural advantage (boosted by the <title rend="italic"
               >Files</title>’ paper-ness), helping it then to establish its position as <q>richly
                  endowed.</q> As I suggest, it might be due to these pragmatic considerations – not
               recognized as epistemically valid – that the Laboratory has not had any important
               place in the readings of Lévi-Strauss’s work. The paper also highlights <q>care
                  work</q> – taking care of resources and relocations – undertaken by Lévi-Strauss
               and his collaborators. Finally, examining the rationale and history of the HRAF and
               looking at its use at the LAS, I demonstrate how the tool was refitted to serve the
               particular needs and ambitions of the Parisian lab. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
         	<p>The author looks into the Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale's Human Relations Area Files 
         	and how their production helped secure funding and space for the lab.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Revisiting a certain chapter in the history of structuralism from the point of view
               of contemporary digital research in the humanities sounds in no way provocative or
               controversial. Claude Lévi-Strauss’s structuralism, with its systemic, large-scale
               view, has already been referred to in the context of digital humanities, as in Alan
               Liu’s article discussing the backdrop for the DH-fuelled debates on meaning <ptr
                  target="#liu2013"/>. Moreover, there has been some evident interest in structural
               anthropology’s liaisons with computers (for instance: <ptr target="#seaver2014"/>)
               and its linkage with cybernetics <ptr target="#geohegan2011"/>. As I will show in
               this paper, it is also by dint of its specific institutional and infrastructural
               making that the structuralist movement continues to prove compelling for today’s
               research agenda in the digital humanities. With <title rend="italic">Laboratoire
                  d’anthropologie sociale</title> as its main hothouse, Lévi-Straussian anthropology
               appears to have been an early-adopter of the now increasingly popular idea of the
               humanities lab.</p>
            <p>This paper uses a case study of Claude Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratory of Social
               Anthropology, or simply the LAS, officially established at the Collège de France in
               1960 and still a part of its structure, to gain insights into the significance of
               infrastructure in the analog humanities laboratory. In order to cast some light on
               the physical situatedness of the LAS and the pragmatic, entrepreneurial side of its
               workings, I will discuss how this lab was initially organized around its prominent
               research apparatus – namely, the Human Relations Area Files, commonly referred to as
               the <title rend="italic">Files</title> or HRAF – and how this instrument was
               mobilized by Lévi-Strauss to secure funding and space and fulfill the goals as well
               as scientific ambitions of structural anthropology. </p>
            <p>What exactly were the <title rend="italic">Files</title>? In hindsight, they appear
               to be a vast pre-electronic ethnographical database. Their creators described this
               instrument as <quote rend="inline">a collection of primary source materials</quote>
               as well as a <quote rend="inline">major data retrieval system</quote>
               <ptr target="#lagacé1974" loc="ix"/>. HRAF, produced at Yale, served as a repository
               of selected ethnographic literature, mainly already-published articles and books
               written in or translated into English, with the aim being to cover all known cultures
               (or at least a representative sample of them).</p>
            <p>Each paragraph of a text was annotated and indexed by HRAF analysts using two sets of
               categories. The first (known as <title rend="italic">Outline of World
                  Cultures</title>) was geographical, with each world region, ethnic and cultural
               group ascribed an individual numeric code. The second (<title rend="italic">Outline
                  of Cultural Materials</title>) involved indexing the materials according to
               subject matter, which ultimately strives to cover all aspects of human existence
               (from religion, magic, kinship, law and political systems to technology, cuisine and
               sexual practices, etc.). In each file on a particular culture, the source texts were
               reproduced both in full, maintaining the original page order, as well as in processed
               form, thus bearing significant amounts of metadata (on multiple levels), with the
               pages relating to a particular subject grouped together. Each page of a document also
               contained a header featuring standard bibliographical information as well as the
               codes (or notations) signaling, for example, the level of education attained by the
               author or an assessment of the quality of the source. Also attached was the <title
                  rend="italic">File Guide</title> that included information on which other sources
               relating to a particular culture had also been consulted but not included among the
                  <title rend="italic">Files</title>. The name of the HRAF analyst who created the
               particular text was also given. Examples of sample file pages could be found in <ptr
                  target="#lagacé1974"/> and on the HRAF website.<note><ref
                     target="https://hraf.yale.edu/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/HRAF_Paper_Microfiche_Files.pdf"
                     >https://hraf.yale.edu/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/HRAF_Paper_Microfiche_Files.pdf</ref>.</note>
               A glimpse of these multilayered metadata and indexing methods is still offered to
               some extent by today’s eHRAF online database – here are examples of the HRAF files of
               Claude Lévi-Strauss’s ethnographic texts on the Nambicuara and Bororo.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>HRAF metadata to Lévi-Strauss’s “The Social use of kinship terms among
                  Brazilian Indians. eHRAF World Cultures. Screenshot by the author</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <head>Lévi-Strauss’s paper “Contribution to the study of the social organization of
                  the Bororo Indians” (page 13) annotated on the paragraph level in the eHRAF
                  database. eHRAF World Cultures. Screenshot by the author</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Analog humanities lab</head>
            <p>My interest in the LAS and its practicalities developed while conducting research
               within the collaborative project “The humanities laboratory as a mode of knowing.
               From archaeology to a project”, designed with Jacek Małczyński and Dorota Wolska and
               reflecting upon the forms a laboratory-type approach to scholarship could take in the
                  humanities.<note>The Laboratory of Social Anthropology is one of the case studies
                  we chose to investigate in the project (alongside, for instance, Aby Warburg’s
                  Kulturwissenschaftliche Bibliothek, Paul Otlet’s Mundaneum and Jerzy Grotowski’s
                  Laboratory Theatre). Furthermore, we inquire into alchemy cabinets and the
                  cabinets of curiosities as possible pre-figurations of the humanities lab. We
                  presented preliminary findings of this study in a joint paper <title rend="quotes"
                     >From the Archaeology of the Humanities Lab: A Tricky Case of Claude
                     Lévi-Strauss’s <title rend="italic">Laboratoire d’anthropologie
                     sociale</title></title> at the conference <title rend="italic">Making of the
                     Humanities VII</title> (15-18 November 2018, University of Amsterdam).
                  Expanding on that research, this paper goes into further detail about the
                  significance of infrastructure in the LAS.</note> Starting from the basic premise
               that the humanities laboratory is a distinct mode of knowing and that it is not to
               serve as a mere imitation of the scientific lab (despite its obvious adjacency to
               that domain), we assume the following determinants in helping to grasp specificity of
               this modus: (1) experimenting, (2) collaboration, (3) the significance of the
               research infrastructure, (4) openness (personal, discipline-wise, and institutional),
               (5) the labile position of the researcher (fluidity of the boundaries between the
               inside and the outside of the laboratory, and the resulting problem of the humanist’s
               involvement). In an attempt to revise the image of the laboratory as an institution
               of strictly natural sciences and to search for deeper discursive layers of this
               particular knowledge-making setting, we have taken up the <hi rend="italic"
                  >archaeology of the humanities laboratory</hi>.<note>A growing interest in the
                  humanities labs (their early forms as well as their infrastructural side) has been
                  shared by several scholars – e.g. Lori Emerson, Jussi Parikka and Darren Wershler
                  in their forthcoming publication <title rend="italic">The Lab Book: Situated
                     Practices in Media Studies</title> (the project website: <ref
                     target="https://manifold.umn.edu/projects/the-lab-book"
                     >https://manifold.umn.edu/projects/the-lab-book</ref>) and Steven E. Jones in
                  his recent work on reconstructing Roberto Busa’s lab (see: <ref
                     target="#jones2018">Jones 2018</ref> and the collaborative project website:
                     <ref target="http://www.recaal.org/">http://www.recaal.org/</ref>). The
                  arguments historicizing the current <term>lab fever</term>, which are similar to
                  our assumptions, have also been made by Grant Wythoff <ref target="#wythoff2018"
                     >(2018)</ref>. Other recent works pertaining to the history of the laboratory
                  in the humanities concentrate on the nineteenth century German philological
                  seminars (see: <ref target="#spoerhase2019">Spoerhase 2019</ref>) and the interwar
                  laboratory operating at the intersection of applied linguistics and acoustics
                  (see: <ref target="#tkaczyk2019">Tkaczyk 2019</ref>). While the focus of many
                  existing works covering this subject is mostly technical and/or design
                  laboratories of various kinds (media labs, digital humanities labs, fablabs,
                  hacklabs, etc.), our project looks into the cases which would not fall into these
                  categories or may not have been otherwise entangled with media studies or other
                  kindred fields. Thus, the proposed framework of the project, aiming to address the
                  question of the laboratory in the humanistic scholarship conceived more broadly,
                  is complementary to the already mentioned studies. Such a general (and perhaps
                  inescapably vague) conceptualization of the humanities would mean that we have a
                  predilection for an interpretive, qualitative approach, straddling various
                  theoretical and methodological orientations, and we tend to emphasize the
                  humanities’ specificity in regard to the natural and social sciences. However,
                  when looking for the historical instances of the lab we are interested in
                  different disciplines, methods and styles of inquiry – vide this paper discussing
                  the laboratory of structural anthropology which – due to its analytical,
                  anti-historical orientation – could be sometimes contrasted with what is
                  traditionally recognized as humanistic knowledge, especially when one takes into
                  consideration the used nomenclature and national conventions – e.g. distinguishing
                  between the <term>human sciences</term> and the <term>humanities</term>.
               </note></p>
            <p>For at least a decade the humanities have seen a conspicuous proliferation of new
               initiatives labelled as laboratories. Little is known, however, about their
               historical forms. Analysis of them, in a somewhat Foucauldian manner, steers clear of
               seeking the unequivocal origins of the humanities lab and creating a <q>linear</q>
               history – instead it foregrounds recursion and the element of chance in the process
               of constituting the humanistic laboratory. Exploring the LAS as one of the
               prefigurations of the contemporary humanities labs<note>It could be rightfully argued
                  that searching for precursors does not fit a style of analyses inspired by Michel
                  Foucault’s archaeology of knowledge with its disregard for genesis, continuity and
                  totalization. Therefore, we should be cautious when conceptualizing the status of
                  the LAS and choosing terminology. As stated in the dictionaries, <q>precursor</q>
                  and <q>forerunner</q> are by and large used as synonyms, although <q>precursor</q>
                  connotes not only something happening or existing before another thing, but also a
                  person or thing paving the way for the other’s future accomplishments. Together
                  with Małczyński and Wolska I opted for <q>prefiguration</q>, assuming that – being
                  less common and slightly less burdened with teleological thinking – it would be a
                  safer choice.</note> and focusing on its <q>infrastructural advantage</q>, which
               will be explicated later on, is intended here as a deliberate media-archaeological
               move, undermining claims that the observed <q>laboratorization</q> of the field is
               merely a recent and fleeting trend. </p>
            <p>In this archaeological vein, I situate Lévi-Strauss’s lab in the <term>analog
                  humanities</term>. I adopt a notion of the analog humanities, aiming to use it in
               a more rigorous, theory-laden sense rather than simply in a non-methodical,
               metaphorical way, sometimes signaled by the quotation marks around the term. What I
               propose is to instill a kind of reflexivity or a retrospective, pre-posterous logic
               in it (a notion of <term>pre-posterous</term>, pertaining to history and meaning
               intentional anachronisms, is borrowed from the Dutch art historian Mieke Bal). As
               Jonathan Sterne argues: <cit source="#sterne2015"><quote rend="block">the
                        <term>analog humanities</term> refers to a nexus of methodological,
                     technological, and institutional conditions across the humanities that have
                     only come into clear focus in retrospect. They refer to the cultural and
                     material infrastructures on which humanists depended and still depend.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#sterne2015" loc="19"/></cit></p>
            <p>In this sense the term serves as a heuristic, <quote rend="inline"><emph>a rhetorical
                     before, </emph> to accompany the digital,</quote> despite being somewhat <quote
                  rend="inline">monolithic</quote>
               <ptr target="#sterne2015" loc="19"/>. One could say that this idea of the analog
               humanities perfectly embodies the pre-posterous thinking (where <q>pre-</q> and
                  <q>post-</q> are being playfully reconfigured) since it evolved and actually made
               sense <emph>after</emph> the digital turn in the humanities had drawn our attention
               to the technological modes of inquiry and to epistemic implications of the academic
               infrastructures. However, the term is not intended here merely as a negative; a
               blurry category denoting everything being pre-digital or not-digital. Elsewhere, in
               his entry on the analog in the <title rend="italic">Digital Keywords</title>, Sterne
               claims that <quote rend="inline">we should return some specificity to <term>the
                     analog</term> as a particular technocultural sphere</quote>
               <ptr target="#sterne2016" loc="41"/> — it is not to denote any natural
               (pre-technical) state of the world, but rather a certain technology of inscription
               (or representation). With a background in sound studies and the history of sound
               recording, Sterne conceives of the analog era as a period dominated by analog
               technologies reproducing print, sound, video and images, but not erasing any earlier
                  media.<note>The author is not explicit about any dates. We could gather that this
                  period spans across the second half of the nineteenth century and the twentieth
                  century. It would be better, though, not to determine when it definitely ends, as
                  if it gave up to the digital era. Sterne is careful not to draw a line here,
                  stressing that the digital devices operate on the layers of the analog
                  technologies or have analog components. Although we are inclined to contrast the
                  analog with the digital, we could also shift the focus to their points of contact.
                  To further complicate the matter, one shall bear in mind a semantic vagueness of
                  these terms. As evidence by numerous lexicon entries and articles, there are
                  various ways of defining the analog and the digital – some definitions foreground
                  technical conditions (continuity vs discontinuity of the signal), while the others
                  focus more on their cultural and affective attributes (analog being closer to
                  nature and human senses, triggering nostalgia, etc.) or even on a deeper
                  philosophical sense (see: <ref target="#buckley2014">Buckley 2014</ref>, <ref
                     target="#cramer2015">Cramer 2015</ref>, <ref target="#galloway2014">Galloway
                     2014</ref>, <ref target="#schrey2014">Schrey 2014</ref>, <ref
                     target="#robinson2008">Robinson 2008</ref>).</note> Being rather
               chronologically specific (although not in a strict way), the notion of analog
               humanities thus irresistibly seems a periodization concept (which could be deemed
                  problematic).<note>My grappling with the idea of the analog humanities seen as a
                  periodization tool is in line with the critique of using media as temporal markers
                  presented by Cox <ref target="#cox2015">(2015)</ref> and Gitelman <ref
                     target="#gitelman2010">(2010)</ref>.</note> Even if we cannot entirely avoid
               this logic, I would argue that the analog humanities serve here as a term identifying
               a particular techno-cultural state of scholarship; that is, the role of the word
                  <q>analog</q> in this expression is primarily to emphasize mediality of knowledge
               production in the humanities and not so much to carve out a certain era.<note>It is
                  worth mentioning that in the literature we can find other terms intended to
                  capture earlier technological conditions of the scholarship, for example
                     <term>print-based humanities</term> (see: <ref target="#hayles2012">Hayles
                     2012</ref> and <ref target="#hayles2013">Hayles and Pressman 2013</ref>) and
                     <term>print humanities</term> (see: <ref target="#mandell2015">Mandell
                     2015</ref>). The scope of the analog humanities would be more limited, but the
                  print remains essential also in this media environment (and so does paper).</note>
               In this way perhaps the <term>analog humanities</term> could still make sense in
               light of the debates on the post-digital, which, as David M. Berry argues, currently
               defines our times. Berry and Fagerjord notes that Sterne’s definition of the analog
               humanities is useful in exploring the links between media and epistemology in the
               humanities, although <quote rend="inline">it might overstate the disjuncture between
                     <q>analog</q> and <q>digital</q></quote>
               <ptr target="#berry2017"/>.<note>The analog, the digital and the post-digital would
                  describe specific historical worlds of experiencing media. As Berry and Dieter
                  state, the post-digital signifies the most recent moment, characterized by <quote
                     rend="inline">immersive, disorientating experiences of computational
                     infrastructures as they scale up and intensify</quote>
                  <ptr target="#berry2015"/>. On the other hand, regarding the present time (and the
                  near future), the authors discourage us from delineating the digital and the
                  non-digital, arguing that such distinctions become nonsensical (as the digital is
                  being seamlessly interwoven in our daily lives).</note></p>
            <p>Therefore, in my paper I follow Sterne – I understand the analog humanities as a
               concept retrospectively facilitated by the digital humanities, intended to
               characterize a techno-cultural condition of the earlier scholarship. At the same
               time, I see the analog humanities not as everything that preceded the digital and
               post-digital age, but rather as a media ecology of print, index cards, typewriters,
               sound recordings, transparencies, overhead projectors, copiers and microfiches, etc.,
               used by the scholars, especially in the second half of the twentieth century, to
               which my case study points to. If we were to find a vivid and detailed illustration
               of this, a description of the LAS’s first interior, written by Emmanuelle Loyer, a
               biographer of Lévi-Strauss, comes to mind: <cit source="#loyer2018"><quote
                     rend="block">Desks, closets, metal filing cabinets, slide and microfilm
                     cabinets, a ladder, a coat rack, two secretary desks, ten armchairs, as well as
                     data processing and scientific machines: a stencil duplicator, two photocopy
                     machines (Arcor and Polymicro), a projector for still images, two microfilm
                     readers, an electric calculator, a stereophonic record-player, a camera, three
                     tape recorders, electric typewriters (Olivetti, <quote rend="inline">extended
                        carriage</quote> Everest, Olympia, Royal, etc.), and a celestial
                     globe.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="385"/></cit><note>The last component of this verbal
                     snapshot is perhaps less surprising if one recalls a figure of speech, which
                     Lévi-Strauss seemed to be fond of, positioning anthropology as the astronomy of
                     the social sciences.</note> By the <quote rend="inline">analog humanities
                  lab</quote> I understand the laboratory of the analog humanities or, to make it
               more pleonastic, the humanities laboratory which emerged from the analog humanities
               (of which the LAS happens to be an instantiation). The humanities laboratory is seen
               as a mode of knowing, but certainly in the case of the LAS it also materializes as a
               research institution under the very label of the lab (and with the physical
               premises). Lévi-Strauss’s laboratory constitutes a good case to be investigated
               within the framework I adopt in this paper, but naturally it is not the only example
               of the analog humanities.<note>Another example I have been studying is the use of
                  scholarly index cards, especially in the context of cultural studies in Poland –
                  the first department of cultural studies was formally founded in 1972 by Stanisław
                  Pietraszko, whose collection of cards I have been analyzing in my dissertation.
                  See: <ref target="#kil2017">Kil 2017</ref>.</note></p>
            <p>The framework of this study is the archaeology of the humanities infrastructure,
               built upon media archaeology<note>My discussion of the analog humanities lab
                  presented above is in fact framed in a media archaeological perspective, in which
                  insights of past and often obsolete technologies inform our understanding of the
                  contemporary media age and vice versa. Media archaeology foregrounds the
                  materiality of scholarly work, revisiting old and purportedly discarded
                  technologies of intellectual labour (such as the HRAF in both paper and
                  microfiches form) and avoids viewing technological change in terms of imminent
                  progress. The proposed archaeology of the humanities infrastructure also alludes
                  to a Foucauldian sense of <term>archaeology</term>, repurposed by media scholars
                  (e.g. F. Kittler), and seen here as an analysis of the (techno-cultural)
                  conditions of knowledge. Media archaeology does not form a unified field or
                  discipline, being perhaps rather a style or aesthetics of the historical
                  reflection on media and cultural techniques (for a synthesizing account see: <ref
                     target="#parikka2012">Parikka 2012</ref>). The most stimulating for my thinking
                  have been works and ideas by Lori Emerson, Errki Huhtamo, Markus Krajewski, Jussi
                  Parikka, and Siegfried Zielinski.</note> and informed by the critical
               infrastructure studies.<note>The body of research within the purview of critical
                  infrastructure studies have been growing, as evidenced by an extensive
                  bibliography curated by Alan Liu, which can be found online: <ref
                     target="https://cistudies.org/critical-infrastructures-bibliography/"
                     >https://cistudies.org/critical-infrastructures-bibliography/</ref>. Critical
                  infrastructure studies encompass many different approaches to infrastructure
                  (informed by the science and technology studies, ethnography, media studies,
                  digital humanities, art and design, etc.). They also seem to include a narrower
                  field of studies dealing with research infrastructure or – even more precisely,
                  humanities infrastructure, seen as a more domain-specific type of infrastructure,
                  devoted specifically to enable research and used within the scholarly communities.
                  Different, yet overlapping, terms exist in the literature – namely: research
                  infrastructure (see: <ref target="#anderson2013">Anderson 2013</ref>), knowledge
                  infrastructure (see: <ref target="#bowker2017">Bowker 2017</ref>), scholarly
                  (information) infrastructure (see: <ref target="#borgman2007">Borgman 2007</ref>),
                  academic infrastructure (preferred by Svensson as the one carrying fewer
                  connotations with science – see: <ref target="#svensson2016">Svensson 2016</ref>).
                  I find it fruitful not to reduce the complexity evidenced by this rich terminology
                  and mesh together the insights coming from these different approaches. As far as
                  the humanities are concerned, although it could be useful to grasp specificity of
                  specialized facilities, tools, resources, institutions and standards supporting
                  research in the humanities, in some cases we may as well resort to a more generic
                  understanding of infrastructure (bearing in mind that research infrastructures
                  tend to be layered upon or entangled with other kinds of substrates). Svensson
                  also argues for a rather broad understanding: <quote rend="inline">With an
                     inclusive definition of research infrastructure, almost anything needed to
                     carry out research in the humanities could be included: ranging from paper,
                     pens, books, furniture and people to database structures, grid computing
                     facilities, visualization centers and libraries</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2011"/>. Additionally, it will be discussed further in the
                  paper that the HRAF is in fact illustrative of the porous boundaries between the
                  concept of research infrastructure associated with science and engineering (and
                  often understood as infrastructure tout court) and the humanities
                  infrastructure.</note> The work being done in this vibrant subfield of the
               humanistic theory encourages us to examine infrastructure as unavoidably
                  relational<note>A relational character of infrastructure (put forward in a
                  canonical work by Star and Ruhleder <ref target="#star1996">(1996)</ref> and
                  eagerly adopted by others) is understood as an emphasis on <emph>when</emph>, not
                     <emph>what</emph> is infrastructure. For Star and Ruhleder that means
                  infrastructure is always embedded in organized practice. Interestingly,
                  relationality entrenched in the concept could also be seen in the origins of the
                  word – according to <ref target="#carse2017" loc="29">Carse (2017, 29)</ref>, in
                  the language of the late nineteenth century’s French engineering, infrastructure
                  primarily referred to construction work done prior to laying road tracks and also
                  the very road beds beneath the tracks. Thus rails, trains and train stations –
                  which we commonly imagine as emblematic <emph>infra</emph>structure – actually
                  used to serve as <emph>super</emph>structure in relation to what was done to make
                  these projects happen.</note> and heterogenous, comprising material equipment and
               installations as well as their human builders and operators, underlying protocols,
               ideas, or standards. In other words, it highlights both ‘the hard and soft
               scaffolding’ of research, as named by Shannon Mattern (2016). Furthermore,
               infrastructure critics and theorists helpfully remind us to study media <quote
                  rend="inline">with an infrastructural disposition, that is, with questions of
                  resources and distribution in mind</quote>
               <ptr target="#parks2015" loc="357"/>, performing an <quote rend="inline"
                  >infrastructural inversion – foregrounding the truly backstage elements of work
                  practice</quote>
               <ptr target="#star1999" loc="380"/> and to <quote rend="inline">engage with
                  infrastructure on the level of packaging</quote>
               <ptr target="#svensson2015" loc="345"/>. In the case of Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratory,
               the latter could be understood quite literally – as ways of handling tons of packages
               filled with paper files and sent regularly from New Haven, Connecticut to Paris since
               the beginning of the 1960s. It is this concrete piece of infrastructure that mostly
               preoccupies me in this paper and I dwell on the reasons for it in the sections that
               follow.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The HRAF as humanities infrastructure</head>
            <p>Before turning directly to the nitty-gritty of the LAS, it ought to be mentioned that
               there has in fact been very little exploration and discussion of the significance of
               the laboratory in relation to Lévi-Strauss’s oeuvre.<note>A notable exception could
                  be a recently translated biography by Loyer <ref target="#loyer2018">(2018)</ref>,
                  whose meticulous archival and ethnographic work provides valuable insights into
                  the LAS’s history and allows for the behind-the-scenes view (presented in the
                  chapter <title rend="quotes">The Manufacture of Science</title>). To her work I
                  owe my deepened knowledge of the LAS’s functioning. Other relevant sources include
                  mainly interviews with Lévi-Strauss, his own writings as well as memoirs and
                  occasional materials published by the LAS.</note> What could possibly account for
               such a surprising marginalization or lack of interest? Together with Małczyński and
               Wolska I posited that the laboratory idea could either have been forgotten (as a
               relatively minor element of the structuralist program) or overlooked because of the
               dominance of anti-laboratory ways of thinking fostered by the interpretive
               anthropology after the peak of structuralism had passed.<note>What I mean here is
                  that the idea of laboratory could have lost traction in the anthropological
                  meta-discourse due to a growing impact of phenomenology and hermeneutics and after
                  the interpretive turn. The latter is exemplified by Clifford Geertz. In his
                  influential <title rend="quotes">Thick description</title> (in <title
                     rend="italic">The Interpretation of Cultures</title>) published in 1973, Geertz
                  remained antagonistic to such a mode of scholarship in which anthropologists
                  construct models, study cultures as if they were <q>natural experiments</q> and
                  adopt a concept of the <q>natural laboratory</q>; <quote rend="inline">what kind
                     of a laboratory is it where <emph>none</emph> of the parameters are
                     manipulable?</quote> – asked Geertz provocatively <ptr target="#geertz1973"
                     loc="319"/>, polemically alluding to the structuralist anthropology. For a
                  further discussion on the competing visions of anthropological research (the one
                  aligning itself with social science and the other oriented towards the humanistic
                  interpretation) and the resulting perception of the HRAF see: <ref
                     target="#tobin1990">Tobin 1990</ref>.</note> Perhaps it might also be the case
               that the laboratory has neither been forgotten nor overlooked, but has instead been
               passed over in silence in light of the pragmatic reasons behind its founding. These
               very reasons will be revealed as my <q>infrastructural inversion</q> unfolds, making
               a case for the <emph>significance</emph> of infrastructure (as one of the
               hypothetical determinants of the humanities laboratory listed above), understood in a
               twofold way – as evidenced by the dictionaries, significance could mean both
               importance, the quality of being worthy of attention and the ability to convey
               meaning. The latter could be further interpreted within the media studies
               perspective, asserting that conveying is hardly epistemically neutral and that to
               convey meaning would be at the same time to shape it. We can rephrase it into a
               question of how research tools, spatial arrangements and management of resources
               affect the process of humanistic knowing. </p>
            <p> As already stated, infrastructure is of vital importance to my description of the
               LAS. Not only does it result from a chosen approach (according to which the HRAF
               prefigures research infrastructure as we know it today – for example a digital
               repository), but it is also grounded in primary source material – Lévi-Strauss’s own
               statements show that the <title rend="italic">Files</title>, acquired with no little
               difficulty, were at the heart of the Laboratory’s work. Lévi-Strauss admitted that
               the HRAF formed the center around which he built the institution and that the role of
               this research instrument was <quote rend="inline">comparable to that of the telescope
                  or electron microscope in the natural sciences</quote> (cited in: <ref
                  target="#abélès2008" loc="66">Abélès 2008, 66</ref>). What this comparison clearly
               shows is that while grasping infrastructure in the humanities, one is likely to be
               challenged by its juxtaposition with science.</p>
            <p>Therefore, to stress the situatedness of the apparatuses and avoid modelling
               humanistic infrastructure on the sciences, Patrik Svensson puts forward the idea of
               the humanistiscope, which <quote rend="inline">is much less laden than the
                  aforementioned devices, although it borrows from a scientific infrastructural
                  logic and the Greek for <q>to look/examine</q> (which also points to the
                  commonplace privileging of the visual in the infrastructure turn)</quote>
               <ptr target="#svensson2015" loc="339"/>. In his paper, Svensson examines which
               assumptions and expectations are deeply entrenched in the very concept of
               infrastructure, relating it to science and engineering. Interestingly, the HRAF –
               although it is <q>just</q> a paper-based collection of indexed ethnographic reports –
               falls exactly into this category by being (1) expensive,<note>HRAF is a
                  membership-based research agency, based at Yale but financially independent and
                  not-for-profit. According to a report from 2000, member dues were considered to be
                  too high for many academic institutions to be willing to join it (see: <ref
                     target="#ember2000">Ember and Human Relations Area Files 2000</ref>).</note>
               (2) <quote rend="inline">used beyond single research groups,</quote><note>Starting as
                  a single project based at the Yale Institute of Human Relations, in 1949 the HRAF,
                  Inc. became an interuniversity research consortium with five founding members. Now
                  there are over 400 institutions (such as universities, libraries, museums, etc.)
                  with access to the <title rend="italic">Files</title>.</note> (3) having <quote
                  rend="inline">considerable longevity</quote> and (4) <quote rend="inline">a sense
                  of discreteness and unity,</quote> being <quote rend="inline">described by a name
                  or a phrase</quote>
               <ptr target="#svensson2015" loc="345"/>, or, we could add, in this case also by an
               acronym. The HRAF thus constitutes a perfect instantiation of infrastructure tout
               court. Likewise, it meets the basic criteria of infrastructure proposed by <ref
                  target="#star1999" loc="381-2">Susan Leigh Star (1999, 381-382)</ref>, such as
               embeddedness in other structures or layers, transparency (unless it breaks) and
               taken-for-grantedness, significant reach, modularity, the ability to embody standards
               and protocols and a nature that is learnt and practiced through community-driven
               conventions.</p>
            <p>It seems particularly relevant to consider a lab of the analog humanities in terms of
               its infrastructure. The humanities have always had infrastructure even if it was
               rather unlikely to be recognized as readily as in the case of the contemporary
               cyberinfrastructure and the digital labs. Commenting on a common (and erroneous)
               notion that the humanities in general do not actually have (or have had)
               infrastructure, Svensson writes: <cit source="#svensson2015"><quote rend="block">the
                     view of basic humanities as having little or no significant infrastructure not
                     only assumes a science- and technology-based idea of what makes up
                     infrastructure but also imposes a pen-and-paper construction of the humanities.
                     Pen and paper, while inherently communicative and collaborative, is also linked
                     to the assumption that humanities scholarship is to a large extent a solitary
                     endeavor.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#svensson2015" loc="147"/></cit> The <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> serve here as a puzzling example eluding straightforward typologies
               – they fulfill a pen-and-paper model only partially: as paper files comprising
               photocopies of articles and monographs which had earlier been annotated by hand by
               the analysts and as a collectively authored tool designed to aid an individual
               researcher’s work as well as to diversify pedagogy at both pre-university and college
               level. In addition, despite being made from paper, the HRAF Files have always seemed
               to be heading into the digital age, being more than suitable for informatization.
               Today the HRAF exists as online databases (eHRAF World Cultures and eHRAF
                  Archaeology).<note>They can be accessed here: <ref
                     target="http://hraf.yale.edu/products/">http://hraf.yale.edu/products/</ref>
                  (free trials of both databases are also being offered).</note></p>
            <p>To unpack the HRAF as foundational infrastructure in the LAS I am posing the
               following questions: how and when did the <title rend="italic">Files</title> find
               their way to Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratory? How did they operate? What did they bring
               along – in terms of any in-built theory, methods, scientific rationale as well as
               reputation, possible connotations and network of allies and foes? How was the HRAF
               put to use (or repurposed) in the particular setting of the LAS and in Lévi-Strauss’s
               own work? What was its position then and what status does it enjoy today? </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Infrastructural advantage and the persistence of paper</head>
            <p>Moving on to describe in greater detail the inner workings of the LAS and its use of
               the HRAF, one should actually start from the beginning. But when exactly was that? It
               is difficult to pinpoint when Lévi-Strauss first learnt about the <title
                  rend="italic">Files</title>. Having spent several years in the US meeting the most
               prominent American anthropologists, he availed himself of cutting-edge trends and
               methods and must have heard of the widely advertised initiative started at Yale
               University by the anthropologist George Peter Murdock.<note>The first mention of
                  Murdock and his <title rend="italic">Cross-Cultural Survey</title> (which later
                  became the HRAF) I found in a paper delivered by Lévi-Strauss as early as in 1952
                  and later published in his <title rend="italic">Structural anthropology </title>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1968" loc="306"/>.</note> As reported in a volume
               published for the occasion of the LAS’s fiftieth anniversary <ptr
                  target="#zonabend2010" loc="4"/>, Lévi-Strauss managed to acquire the files as
               early as 1958, two years before the Laboratory was formally established. He might
               have benefitted from his role as secretary general of the International Social
               Science Council, founded under the auspices of UNESCO (of which he happened to say
               that it was an organization <quote rend="inline">without goal or function,</quote>
               but in disposition of <quote rend="inline">some means</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="60–61"/>. With UNESCO funding and thanks to the
               efforts of Gaston Berger from the French Ministry of National Education, Claude
               Lévi-Strauss’s Laboratory (as a part of the École pratique des hautes études) came
               into possession of the only complete paper copy of the HRAF card index in Europe. As
               Lévi-Strauss noted, he succeeded in this mission <quote rend="inline">after many
                  tribulations;</quote> moreover, the funding conditions meant that his center was
               obliged to make the HRAF available to any interested party <ptr
                  target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="63"/>. </p>
            <p>If we were to apply the categories used in describing competition over natural
               resources, we could say that it was because of the files that LAS acquired
                  <term>infrastructural advantage</term>, having access to something otherwise
               unavailable outside North America and Japan. In order to emphasize its
                  <q>ownership</q> of the imported papers or to <q>domesticate</q> them – for HRAF
               members did not technically own the files, they only enjoyed the privilege of keeping
               and using them – the Laboratory gave its own name to the collection – <title
                  rend="italic">Centre documentaire d'ethnologie comparée</title>.<note>We could
                  ponder on the possible ramifications of this <q>imported</q> nature of the <title
                     rend="italic">Files</title>, produced (selected and annotated) in the United
                  States and used at a French academic institution. For instance, could it be an
                  issue that all texts collected in the HRAF index – aiming at representing <q>the
                     world cultures</q> – were in English (some being translated from other
                  languages, also from French, but reportedly original versions were also filed)?
                  Could the Anglo-American pedigree of the tool have invited criticism (if we bear
                  in mind the situation of the social sciences in post-war France described by Loyer
                  – they are said to have been underfunded, supported by UNESCO and frowned upon by
                  the Marxist left, who <quote rend="inline">looked very unfavorably on these
                        <q>American</q> sciences of capitalist social engineering</quote>
                  <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="380"/>)? Or perhaps contrariwise, could it have been
                  seen as a positive sign of international academic cooperation or even a welcome
                     <q>gift</q> from a scientific community of the country which sheltered numerous
                  French exiles, Lévi-Strauss included, during the war?</note> The infrastructural
               advantage of the LAS was of course closely related to prestige and the sense of
               exclusivity which was in turn – perhaps surprisingly – amplified by a paper
               technology. It should be said that in 1958 the <title rend="italic">Files</title>
               were introduced in a microfiche format which proved quite efficient – cheaper to
               ship, more durable and taking up far less space. Still, the paper versions continued
               to be produced until 1984. Why did Lévi-Strauss’ Laboratory opt for the paper
               version, given its constant problems with obtaining adequate space (a more detailed
               account of these difficulties will follow)? After all, subscribing to the paper HRAF
               was burdensome, involving endless boxes of 5 x 8 inches loose paper slips which had
               to be carefully filed and properly stored.<note>As Geoffrey Rockwell <ref
                     target="#rockwell2010">(2010)</ref> observes, one of the inherent problems of
                  infrastructure is that it has to be maintained.</note> Loyer notes that in its
               second year in the LAS the HRAF already consisted of <quote rend="inline">about two
                  million index cards, organized in 380 double metal filing cabinets, weighing 7.5
                  tons and taking up 18 cubic meters of space</quote>
               <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="383"/>.</p>
            <p>There are a few possible explanations of this seemingly strange preference of the
               LAS’s administrators (namely, Claude Lévi-Strauss and his deputy and right-hand, Isac
               Chiva). First is that a robust HRAF collection could have acted as a pretext
               concocted by Lévi-Strauss in his efforts to receive a more comfortable location. What
               is more, one of the researchers currently working in the LAS drew my attention to the
               fact that due to the singular rules of succession at the Collége de France, it is
               more likely for the chair to justify its continued existence when it possesses some
               expensive specialist equipment (which usually pertained to the natural sciences
               chairs, but also to the extraordinary resources used by humanists, like for instance
               particularly rich and valuable libraries or collections of artifacts).<note>For this
                  clue I am thankful to Professor Wiktor Stoczkowski who shared his insights into
                  the history of the LAS with my colleagues and me during his visit at the
                  University of Wrocław (personal communication, May 2018).</note></p>
            <p>On the other hand, the persistence of paper <title rend="italic">Files</title> in the
               LAS could have more to do with joining an international prestigious club than with
               locally situated institutional equilibristics. <ref target="#lemov2015" loc="137"
                  >Rebecca Lemov (2015, 137)</ref> notes that the Laboratory was among the handful
               of first-tier subscribers (i.e. sponsor members), alongside for example Harvard, who
               received full-sized paper copies. Everyone else (the so called microfiles members)
               received miniaturized photographic reproductions.</p>
            <p>However, there is yet another explanation that should be considered: the limited
               number of twenty five paper sets of the HRAF ever produced (one set located in the
               headquarters at Yale and twenty-four copies entrusted to the sponsor members) was
               part of the arrangements made by the HRAF corporation with the publishers holding the
               copyrights to the ethnographic sources reprinted in the <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> — they agreed on releasing twenty five copies in total (see: <ref
                  target="#roe2007" loc="64">Roe 2007, 64</ref>). Expanding the number of
               subscribers was thus only feasible by changing the medium of publication – apparently
               microfiches were acceptable as derivative version of paper <q>originals</q>, which
               were ultimately xeroxed copies. As evidenced by a 1970 report by the HRAF president
                  <ref target="#ford1970" loc="39">Clellan Ford (1970,39)</ref>, in that period
               there were already eight microfiche collection of the <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> in Europe (for instance in Germany, Holland, Sweden and
               Switzerland). The Laboratory of Social Anthropology in Paris was thus in charge of a
               truly unique resource but only for several years after its purchase or as long as we
               conceive this exclusivity as bound to a concrete technology of reproduction.</p>
            <p>Roe remarks that paper versions of HRAF indeed held some prestige – in fact, they
               were highly valued, kept in specially arranged and locked places and not available to
               students or members of the public without some precautions (such as prior training)
                  <ptr target="#roe2007" loc="64"/>. However, what can be inferred from the updated
               lists of subscribers published throughout the years in occasional reports is that not
               every sponsor member that acquired a paper-based collection decided to keep it –
               hence the paper <title rend="italic">Files</title> travelled to new campuses. Perhaps
               the membership was too costly to maintain for many years or it just seemed more
               practical and modern to switch to microfiches. Alternatively, apart from all the
               practical issues, being a part of an exclusive paper-aficionados club did not in the
               end turn out to be sufficiently prestigious.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Resources and relocations: highlighting <q>care work</q></head>
            <p>Fresh batches of files reached the Laboratory each year thanks to its subscription.
               Cataloging and storing the materials demanded ever more effort and space.
               Lévi-Strauss explained that this was the reason behind the Laboratory’s multiple
               changes of location. The Laboratory’s location for the first five years of its
               existence was in an annex to the Musée Guimet on Avenue d’Iéna (formerly the private
               residence of Emile Guimet, it was not necessarily fit to house a research
               organization). It comprised two rooms, with the largest being almost completely
               filled by the files, while a smaller one (a reconfigured bathroom with the stumps of
               pipes protruding from the floor) was shared by several researchers: Lévi-Strauss,
               Isac Chiva, his collaborator Françoise Flis (Zonabend) and Jean Pouillon, the editor
               of <title rend="italic">L’Homme</title>.<note>When located on Avenue d’Iéna, Isac
                  Chiva mentioned that the laboratory’s secretarial staff (typewriters,
                  receptionists, <quote rend="inline">people in charge of accounting, mail, library
                     resources and archiving</quote>) used to work together in another office (cited
                  in: <ref target="#loyer2018" loc="386">Loyer 2018, 386</ref>). They could have
                  been all located in the second larger room (where the HRAF was stored).</note>
               This did not stop Susan Sontag from claiming in her review article <title
                  rend="quotes">A Hero of our Time</title>
               <ref target="#sontag1963">(1963)</ref> that Lévi-Strauss <quote rend="inline">heads a
                  large and richly endowed research institute</quote>, much to the bewilderment of
               Chiva. The reputation enjoyed by the Laboratory and its founder certainly encouraged
               one to imagine its physical location as something much grander than it was in
               reality. </p>
            <p>Its second home, this time located in the Latin Quarter (Place Marcelin-Berthelot)
               and installed in the Collége buildings (which, as revealed in the interview with
               Didier Eribon, appeared crucial to <ref target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="75"
                  >Lévi-Strauss (1991, 75)</ref>), was more grandiose but even it became too cramped
               over time. The burgeoning HRAF files were too heavy for the eighteenth-century
               building’s ceilings to bear. There was also a growing team of over thirty technical
               and research staff. Space was in short supply. The sound of talking and the noise
               generated by typewriters made working conditions in the common room difficult, if not
               impossible. Rooms were thus divided to create individual compartments. There seems to
               be a case here of the HRAF exerting proxemic dominance. The ability to store the
                  <title rend="italic">Files</title> even took precedence over guaranteeing
               individual and spacious offices for researchers. The Latourian non-human actor
               dominated the Laboratory’s space. Accommodating the HRAF collection was an issue that
               made Lévi-Strauss and Chiva boldly apply for greater floorspace, customarily rather
               unthinkable for the human sciences facilities. Loyer points out that Lévi-Strauss
               requested 2,000 square meters, while the standard was 150-200, envisioning a perfect
               location as having <quote rend="inline">an adjoining reading room, two offices for
                  archivists, a photographic workshop, fifteen offices for researchers and a reading
                  and conference room</quote>
               <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="390–391"/>. The Laboratory moved to its third and
               current location in 1985, doubling its space.</p>
            <p>Presenting his Laboratory in the journal <title rend="italic" xml:lang="fr">Reveu de
                  L’enseignement supérieur</title>, Lévi-Strauss indicates four main areas it should
               develop in, namely: teaching, documentation, research and publication <ref
                  target="#lévistrauss1965a">(1965)</ref>. He spoke at length about how the training
               in anthropology should be organized in his text <title rend="quotes">The Place of
                  Anthropology in the Social Sciences and Problems Raised in Teaching It</title>
               (see: <ref target="#lévistrauss1968">Lévi-Strauss 1968</ref>). On several occasions
               Lévi-Strauss voiced his views on how neglected were problems of tools and resources
               in the human sciences, beginning his response to a UNESCO survey in 1964 with these
               words: <cit source="#lévistrauss1983"><quote rend="block">how much more efficient it
                     would have been if, at the national level, there were the granting of a place
                     of work to scattered researchers, who are most often demoralized by the lack of
                     a chair, a table, and the few square yards indispensable for the decent
                     exercise of their work; by the nonexistence or insufficiency of libraries, and
                     the lack of funds</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1983" loc="289"/></cit>.</p>
            <p>Earlier on, in <title rend="italic">The Structural Study of Myth</title>, where he
               imagines analyzing myths by disassembling them into smaller units written down on
               index cards, pigeon-holed and reconfigured with the help of enormous wooden boards
               (two meters long and one and one-half meters high), later to be replaced by
               perforated cards and IBM equipment, Lévi-Strauss complains about the limited means
               for such research in France. What he has in mind speaking of such means is <quote
                  rend="inline">a spacious workshop</quote>, <quote rend="inline">special
                  devices</quote> and a team comprising both researchers and technicians. He adds:
                  <quote rend="inline">it is much desired that some American group, better equipped
                  than we are here in Paris, will be induced by this paper to start a project of its
                  own in structural mythology</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1955" loc="443"/>.<note>This reference to a potentially
                  better equipped American research team appears only in the version of <title
                     rend="italic">The Structural Study of Myth</title> published in 1955 in <title
                     rend="italic">The Journal of American Folklore</title> – its later version
                  published in French as a chapter of <title rend="italic">Anthropologie
                     structurale</title> lacks such a statement.</note> As evidenced by this quote,
               Lévi-Strauss envisaged his research as inherently collective. However, one can argue
               that this idea of collaboration is principally of a pragmatic (or instrumental)
               nature; Lévi-Strauss was aware that such a study would only be feasible (in a
               reasonable time) when taken up by a group.</p>
            <p>Lévi-Strauss actively sought to secure funds and spaces, since, as he noted, they
               were inadequate at the outset. He was able to seize the chance of establishing a
               prospering human sciences lab, recognizing in the 1960s that, thanks to the French
               state's Fifth Plan, new funding opportunities for collective research had
                  arrived.<note>Reporting on how new higher education policies – oriented toward
                     <q>modernization</q> and triggering influx of money for social sciences – in
                  Gaullist France had shaped the research agenda of the LAS, Loyer touches on
                  several state-sponsored projects in the 1960s and 1970s joined by members of the
                  Laboratory. One example is the interdisciplinary, collective and multiyear study
                  on Plozévet, a French village in Brittany, where the LAS researchers conducted
                  anthropology of the contemporary rural communities. Loyer points out that
                  Lévi-Strauss was not personally too keen on such research (mostly for
                  methodological reasons), nonetheless he grasped these fieldwork missions as
                  strategically important means of bringing in funds, creating new posts as well as
                  gaining recognition for the consolidating discipline. See: <ref
                     target="#loyer2018" loc="380–383">Loyer 2018, 380–383</ref>.</note> Moreover,
               cognizant of the perks of the status of <q>laboratory chair</q> (which entitled the
               holder to greater office space), Lévi-Strauss had the faculty assembly vote to grant
               them such a status, although at that time only 14 out of 52 chairs in the Collége had
               a laboratory (see: <ref target="#loyer2018" loc="391">Loyer 2018, 391</ref>). He was
               skilled in garnering attention, using the experience gained in the US and contacts
               with the charities like Rockefeller or Ford Foundation and the Wenner-Gren
                  Foundation.<note>He might have learnt this from Roman Jakobson, a friend and
                  mentor during his American years, who was also knowledgeable when it comes to
                  obtaining funds and promoting his research to collaborators in the US, especially
                  when structuralism went hand in hand with and flourished because of cybernetics.
                  More on this topic – see: <ref target="#geohegan2011">Geoghegan 2011</ref>.</note>
               Loyer describes the LAS not as <quote rend="inline">a theoretical engine room</quote>
               of structuralism, but rather a place where scholars <quote rend="inline">would
                  receive resources they needed to pursue their work</quote>
               <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="399"/> – inter alia, the HRAF files. <note>The <title
                     rend="italic">Files</title> act here as both sources (they were advertised as a
                  collection of primary source materials) and – from an infrastructural perspective
                  – resources, understood as a <quote rend="inline">reserve on which one can draw
                     when necessary</quote> – Christine L. Borgman suggests these terms tend to be
                  conflated, but in this case both seem applicable, underlining different aspects of
                  the HRAF <ptr target="#borgman2007" loc="121–122"/>.</note> For instance, Philippe
               Descola (later the director of the LAS) remembers that as a young researcher not yet
               fully engaged in the Laboratory, he benefitted from it, occasionally making
               photocopies (however trivial and mundane this privilege might seem for us today) <ptr
                  target="#zonabend2010" loc="46"/>.</p>
            <p>In light of the above brief reconstruction of the Lévi-Straussian knack for academic
               entrepreneurship, we could say that the <quote rend="inline">infrastructural
                  disposition</quote>, advised by Lisa Parks, foregrounding questions of resources
               and distribution, is actually something that characterizes Lévi-Strauss. Apart from
               his great intellectual renown, he epitomizes the canny organizer and facilitator.</p>
            <p>To use a notion proposed by Antonijević, Dormans and Wyatt in their study on
               collaboration in virtual knowledge <ref target="#antonijević2013">(2013)</ref>,
               looking after coworkers, space, resources and budget allocations could be seen as
               expressions of <term>care work</term> – a sort of immaterial, affective labor in
               academia. Many of this informal aspects of being <q>caring</q> as well as <q>careful </q>
               <ptr target="#antonijević2013" loc="66"/> tend to remain invisible in research
               outputs, difficult to discern against a backdrop of administrative documents and
               traditional academic genres. In posthumous overviews and summaries of the scientific
               legacy one is more likely to find a list of an academic’s achievements, projects,
               awards and publications than an appreciation like this one stating that <quote
                  rend="inline">Lévi-Strauss was to devote a significant part of his life to
                  channeling young (and not so young) energies and to organizing collective
                  work</quote>
               <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="375"/>.</p>
            <p>However, a discussion of care work in the LAS is not to depict it as an idealized,
               team-spirited site of academic work; free of conflicts and forming the proclaimed
                  <q>direct democracy</q> (while Lévi-Strauss explicitly spoke of this prevailing
               modus operandi, supposedly <quote rend="inline">down to and including the cleaning
                  woman</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="79"/>, his biographer suggests it was rather an
                  <quote rend="inline">enlightened monarchy</quote>
               <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="404"/>.<note>As Antonijević, Dormans and Wyatt note,
                  one should not overlook various instances of academic carelessness (mistreating
                  colleagues, data, texts and sources) <ptr target="#antonijević2013" loc="66"/>.
                  Along with the memoirs of former members of the LAS (later Lévi-Strauss’s
                  successors in the role of director) such as Descola and Nathan Wachtel, who recall
                  a friendly, hardly doctrinaire atmosphere and a collective spirit <ptr
                     target="#zonabend2010" loc="11–13"/>, one should also consider any signs of
                  friction or even animosity (not to be found in the occasional official
                  publications of the Laboratory) – e.g. Lévi-Strauss mentioned the split with
                  Robert Jaulin who had left the LAS as a result of personal differences (<quote
                     rend="inline">we quickly separated because we were incompatible</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="154"/>) and he commented on disputes related
                  to the events of May 1968, speaking of the LAS’ feminist-oriented researchers who
                     <quote rend="inline">got stirred up and were asked to leave the
                     laboratory</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="79"/>.</note> Nor should it be suggested that
               Lévi-Strauss was a lone <q>hero</q> (to echo Sontag’s essay title) – in fact, a great
               deal of care work in the LAS must have been done cooperatively, engaging other
               academics and staff. This also involved taking care of the HRAF – someone had to
               unpack, arrange, catalog and maintain the files pouring into the LAS’ library in
               order to make them available. Throughout the years there have been several people
               managing the library (Marion Abélès, among others) and additional specialists in
               charge of the HRAF (Nicole Belmont, Tina Jolas, Roberto Miguelez, Solange Pinton – to
               name just a few) <ptr target="#zonabend2010" loc="44–45"/></p>
            <p>Being used to doing administrative work alongside his scientific activities,
               Lévi-Strauss stated that <quote rend="inline">directing the laboratory was a
                  load</quote> he <quote rend="inline">carried most willingly</quote>, though not
               without <quote rend="inline">some secretarial help</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="64"/>.<note>He could have not disposed of this
                     <q>secretarial help</q> after he had retired as the LAS’ director – his
                  secretarial work was taken care of by Eva Kempinski, who – as stated by Strauss
                  and Eribon in the Prologue to the interview – <quote rend="inline">in addition to
                     typing the manuscript, did so much to organize a transcription laden with
                     additions, deletions, and corrections</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="viii"/>.</note> Also, he relied heavily on the
               LAS’ assistant director and his long-time closest collaborator, Isac Chiva. In a
               private letter to Chiva dated back to 1976, he admitted: <quote rend="inline">I have
                  not said that the laboratory helped me directly in my own work, but that I could
                  never have managed to do it if you had not so greatly relieved me of the task of
                  managing that institution,</quote> repeating this praise much later (in 2003) in
               another letter: <quote rend="inline">For I would never have embarked on the adventure
                  of the laboratory if I had not known that you were ready to come along with
                  me</quote> (cited in: <ref target="#loyer2018" loc="387–388">Loyer 2018,
                  387-388</ref>). What might be true of any academic center, the LAS could not have
               flourished if it had not been for a significant load of immaterial work performed by
               its permanent, apprentice and visiting researchers, by technicians, journal editors,
               research coordinators, archivists, librarians, and the secretarial personnel. Strauss
               could have been a central figure crucial for functioning of the lab (often attributed
               to him as <q>his</q> laboratory), but he also thrived on the endeavors undertaken by
               others. Even if, as his biographer points out, Lévi-Strauss never stopped working on
               his own, nourishing his <q>soloist</q> nature and spending half a day in the
               Laboratory and the rest in his office, it could be claimed that the LAS, the plan for
               which Lévi-Strauss had had in his mind for a long time,<note>As we read in Loyer’s
                  biography, an initial (but already fully-fledged) idea of the Laboratoire
                  d’anthropologie sociale was born in 1949, when Lévi-Strauss first applied (with no
                  success, though) to the Collége de France. According to Loyer, he had known that
                  the Collége was <quote rend="inline">a golden prison</quote> and its professors
                  had no research teams and doctoral students to supervise. That is why he wanted to
                  create a research center connected to his chair and a journal of international
                  reach (<title rend="italic">L’Homme</title>, managed by Jean Pouillon, his close
                  collaborator and a key figure in the LAS). <quote rend="inline">The research
                     center and journal were the long arms of the new position,</quote> writes Loyer
                     <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="354"/>.</note> constituted for him a vital
               knowledge environment, additionally luring many academics from around the world. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Background of the HRAF </head>
            <p>Let us now turn again to the Human Relations Area Files in order to investigate the
               conceptual and practical baggage that the HRAF might have carried along – its
               theoretical and methodological pedigree, inherent assumptions, and any links –
               institutional or personal – clinging to this instrument.</p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Files</title> are in a way a co-authored publication – a
               product of the teamwork of the HRAF analysts<note>The people behind the HRAF
                  production did not form a unified group. It is worth mentioning Lemov’s account of
                  this process: <quote rend="inline">They hired two strata of data <q>processors</q>
                     - a team of graduate students and their wives to go through texts and mark the
                     targeted information and an auxiliary team of typists and office workers to do
                     the clerical work of typing and filing</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lemov2012" loc="133"/>. Cf. Jones <ref target="#jones2018"
                     >(2018)</ref> pointing out the gendered and hierarchical data processing at the
                  Busa’s lab.</note> and the authors of the ethnographic texts. It is not only the
               research team associated with Yale who were behind their production and distribution,
               but also a consortium officially founded in 1949 that initially involved other US
               universities: Harvard and the Universities of Pennsylvania, Oklahoma and
               Washington.</p>
            <p>Tracing the history of HRAF, the anthropologist George Peter Murdock emerges as the
               driving force behind the whole enterprise. As Rebecca Lemov has noted in her book
                  <title rend="italic">World as Laboratory</title>
               <ref target="#lemov2006">(2006)</ref>, Murdock was a Yale professor famous for his
               encyclopedic knowledge. In 1928, he started constructing a bibliography on the
               subject of various cultures around the world. After several years working alone, his
               project transformed into the collective endeavor that became the <title rend="italic"
                  >Cross-Cultural Survey</title>. From 1935, Murdock’s team operated under the aegis
               of the Yale Institute of Human Relations, which saw it as suitable for their
               experimental and comparative social science research. It is particularly notable —
               and has already been discussed at length (see: <ref target="#price2012">Price
                  2012</ref>, <ref target="#price2016">2016</ref>) — that the <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> experienced their most intensive period of development during the
               Second World War. It was then that the project acquired the financial support of the
               military and US intelligence. It was a valuable operational instrument during the War
               and also later in Cold War imperialist policy, offering a rich source of systematic
               data that could easily be misused as intelligence information. Lévi-Strauss was
               almost certainly aware (at least to some extent) of the rather inglorious backstage
               of the HRAF development. He noted in interviews that it was created <quote
                  rend="inline">on behalf of the United States government</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="63"/>.</p>
            <p>According to the handbook <title rend="italic">Nature and Use of the HRAF
                  Files</title>
               <ptr target="#lagacé1974"/>, the files were initially intended as a tool for testing
               hypotheses (constructed on the basis of causal relations between variables) and hence
               would lead to the generation of a <quote rend="inline">valid theory in the social and
                  behavioral sciences.</quote> Exemplary questions posed by cross-cultural
               researchers could be: <q>Is there an association between most important subsistence
                  activity and level of political complexity?</q> or <q>Why do some societies
                  practice matrilocal residence and others patrilocal residence?</q>
               <ptr target="#ember1998" loc="6"/>. Lagacé claims a certain <q>a-theoretical</q>
               nature of this apparatus, stating that the <title rend="italic">Files</title>
               <quote rend="inline">constitute an organized collection of data, and they should be
                  used to retrieve data, not theory</quote>
               <ptr target="#lagacé1974" loc="15"/>.</p>
            <p>Looking for theoretical underpinnings of the HRAF, Rebecca Lemov inquired into
               Murdock’s education and any intellectual influences he might have been affected by –
               rejected by Franz Boas, he did his Ph.D. at Yale, studying under A. G. Keller in the
               tradition of W. G. Sumner (both associated with the evolutionism to which Boas was
               rather hostile). However, Lemov concludes that <quote rend="inline">the files were
                  now neither Kellerian nor Boasian, but, increasingly, Murdockian</quote>
               <ptr target="#lemov2012" loc="136"/>. This, on the one hand, could mean that he
               started to realize his own vision of anthropology as a part of the empirical
               behavioral sciences and connect the <title rend="italic">Files</title> with a
               discourse of laboratory trials, calling the HRAF <quote rend="inline">a sort of
                  social science laboratory</quote>
               <ptr target="#murdock1950" loc="718"/>. On the other hand, he tended to present the
               HRAF as a merely auxiliary tool, reducing the time and effort needed to complete
               research by taking out <quote rend="inline">the leg work</quote>, <quote
                  rend="inline">all the routine unproductive labor</quote> and freeing the
               researcher’s creativity <ptr target="#murdock1950" loc="719"/>.</p>
            <p>The HRAF-ers were well aware of the critical responses to that idea – Ford noted that
               it was seen as unnecessary <q>pampering</q> of scholars by, for instance, Alfred
               Kroeber <ptr target="#ford1970" loc="9"/>. This could seem not only needless, but,
               more importantly, undesirable for epistemic reasons. In their review of the HRAF,
               Clarke and Henige discuss reducing the chores like bibliographical survey and
               translation of sources: <quote rend="inline">we can ask, if only rhetorically here,
                  whether the serious scholar should allow him or herself this particular luxury.
                  That is, both the HRAF and electronic databases may well take too many decisions
                  (as well as some work) away from the individual scholar, and it is indeed
                  debatable whether this is, on balance, desirable</quote>
               <ptr target="#clarke1985" loc="50"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The <title rend="italic">Files</title> and the LAS: refitting</head>
            <p>In this section I examine on what levels the <title rend="italic">Files</title> were
               compatible with the LAS’s research and what was its connection to Lévi-Strauss’s
               work. Did the HRAF afford structuralist studies? How was it put to use in Paris?
               Bruno Latour offered a fairly radical take on it, stating that <quote rend="inline"
                  >Lévi-Strauss’s theories of savages are an artifact of card indexing at the
                  Collége de France</quote>
               <ptr target="#latour2011" loc="20"/>. Putting aside Latour’s rhetorical emphasis, is
               the connection indeed so undeniable? </p>
            <p>Like Murdock and his team at Yale, Lévi-Strauss appreciated the speed with which
               information could be searched for in the HRAF catalog. Based on his own empirical
               testing, i.e. using his own experience, Murdock claimed that using the files meant a
               text could be written in a little more than 24 hours rather than the 24 days that a
               standard search through a library would entail <ptr target="#murdock1950" loc="720"
               />. Perhaps this is what Margaret Mead also had in mind when she criticized the Human
               Relations Area Files for being <quote rend="inline">instant anthropology, like
                  instant coffee.</quote><note>Mead’s opinion was cited by Isac Chiva in his text
                     <title rend="quotes">Une communauté de solitaires: le Laboratoire
                     d’anthropologie sociale</title>
                  <ptr target="#chiva2004"/>, but with no direct source attribution.</note> It was
               both the unusual speed and reliance on second-hand, republished sources (which the
               HRAF-ers called simply <q>data</q>, as though it were stripped of context) that is
               targeted here. There is no hiding the fact that using the HRAF might provoke
               associations with an already at that time outdated <q>armchair anthropology</q>.
               Interestingly, a tool which was said to elevate a regular library to the next level
               in terms of its scope and ease could have interested Lévi-Strauss, who described
               himself as a <q>library man</q>, not necessarily too keen on prolonged fieldwork
               (see: <ref target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="44">Lévi-Strauss and Eribon 1991,
               44</ref>).</p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Files</title>, conceived as a kind of laboratory by Murdock
               and called the <q>laboratory without walls</q> by librarians, as Clarke and Henige
               acknowledge <ptr target="#clarke1985" loc="47"/>, embodied a narrative and aura of
               experimentation, tailored for the needs of the Laboratory of Social Anthropology.
               After all, the laboratory label was chosen by the LAS founder on purpose, and he was
               aware of the obvious connotations it carried.<note>Given Lévi-Strauss’ scientistic
                  ambitions, one could argue that it is possible to consider LAS an imitation of a
                  scientific laboratory and not a fully-fledged human sciences (let alone
                     <q>humanities</q>) institution. Of course, any clear-cut answers would depend
                  both on the definition of the humanities applied and the academic tradition
                  (which, for example, deploy different names, such as the <q>human sciences</q> and
                     <q>humanities</q>) used to contextualize the argument. If we consider that the
                  LAS is an example of the <q>scientification</q> of the humanities, we should be
                  cognizant of the conditions of this process which may be not be symmetrical to
                  what is happening in today’s scholarship. On the contemporary
                     <q>scientification</q> of the humanities in relation to the laboratory see:
                     <ptr target="#pawlicka2017"/>.</note> His views on the relations between the
               natural, social and human sciences and the position of the latter are in fact quite
               compelling and by all means would deserve a more detailed investigation. Risking an
               oversimplification, one could say that Lévi-Strauss’s mindset was close to a nuanced
               form of scientism. While speaking about choosing a name for his center, he resorts to
               etymology, as if he tried to revisit the history of the lab as a strictly science
               domain, as well as nodding to the <q>hard</q> sciences, which he understands as
                  <q>more advanced</q>: <cit source="#belmont2008"><quote rend="block">Some people
                     were surprised that the term <term>laboratory</term> could be applied to a
                     center for the human sciences. In adopting it, however, we did not follow a
                     fashion nor were misled by appearances. According to the etymology, a
                     laboratory is first of all a place where one works. And it suffices to enter
                     ours to see that the methods of ethnological research today adopt a style that
                     brings them closer to those of more advanced sectors.</quote> (cited in: <ref
                     target="#belmont2008" loc="62">Belmont 2008, 62</ref>)</cit> Elsewhere, he
               said: <quote rend="inline">We consider ourselves, rather, as artisans, laboriously
                  bending over phenomena which are too small to excite human passions, but whose
                  value comes from the fact they can, when grasped at this level, become the object
                  of a rigorous knowledge</quote> (cited in: <ref target="#pace1983" loc="5">Pace
                  1983, 5</ref>). </p>
            <p>It is interesting to look into this metaphorical language of the lab (microscopes and
               lab benches that researchers bend over are only hinted at in the scene imagined in
               the latter quote) that Strauss drew on, constructing a conceptual image of his
                  center.<note>It is not only language making up a picturesque image of the lab.
                  This metaphor could also materialize in a physical form – consider Lévi-Strauss’s
                  awe and fascination with a former geology lab, in which buildings he installed the
                  LAS (Place Marcelin-Berthelot). He marveled at its mahogany cabinets storing
                  mineral collections, elegant, sturdy furniture and aura of the mid-nineteenth
                  century laboratory. He said affectionately: <quote rend="inline">Nowhere else, I
                     thought, would I rather spend my days than in these spacious, silent, and
                     secret rooms</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="76"/>. I would argue that we could think of
                  these spaces as <term>epistemic surroundings</term>, which Mario Wimmer describes
                  as places where one could think with what is at hand and these spatial
                  arrangements shape the very process of thinking. He writes on the <q>material
                     concepts</q> and is interested in how they contribute to knowing on a more
                  unconscious level: <quote rend="inline">My basic assumption is that this surplus
                     of meaning is an effect of both the excess of the materiality of language, as
                     well as the experience that emerges in the process of research but which cannot
                     be translated into scholarly discourse and thus enters, in its
                     symbolic-material form, the epistemic surroundings where it acquires a latent
                     existence</quote>
                  <ptr target="#wimmer2017" loc="251"/>. Was the laboratory a material concept in
                  Lévi-Strauss’ thinking?</note> Besides, the LAS – the first social science lab in
               the Collége – was not an only initiative so denominated. There was also the
               Laboratory of Graphics at the École des hautes études en sciences sociales (founded
               by Jacques Bertin, who created diagrams for <title rend="italic">The Raw and the
                  Cooked</title>).<note>As for the laboratorial Zeitgeist and the origins of the
                  idea for the LAS, it is rather unclear whether Lévi-Strauss’s lab was inspired by
                  the American cybernetics centers like MIT’s CENIS and Research Laboratory of
                  Electronics which Strauss was familiar with and even engaged in some cooperation.
                  As documented in his letters to Jakobson, in the early 1950s Lévi-Strauss sought
                  funding in the US to open in France a center for structuralist analysis
                  undergirded by cybernetics. As discussed by Geoghegan and Loyer, it is not
                  probable that the LAS was a direct realization of these plans.</note></p>
            <p>Like a telescope or microscope, the HRAF perfectly fit Lévi-Strauss’s famous formula
               of conducting anthropology <q>from afar.</q> According to Lévi-Strauss, <quote
                  rend="inline">the anthropologist is the astronomer of the social sciences: his
                  task is to discover a meaning for configurations which, owing to their size and
                  remoteness, are very different from those within the observer’s immediate
                  purview</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1968" loc="378"/>. Indeed, locating hundreds of files on a
               single table or a collection of two million pages on the subject of three hundred
               cultures from around the world in metal drawers in one room offered a perfect example
               of zooming out in producing knowledge.</p>
            <p>Melvin Ember, who served as the HRAF president in 1987, promoted the <title
                  rend="italic"> Files</title> by quoting a passage on laboratorial anthropology
               treating societies as <q>ready-made</q> experiments. The author of these words was
               none other than Claude Lévi-Strauss <ptr target="#ember1988"/>. In a text presenting
               the LAS, Lévi-Strauss used exactly the same terminology as the creators of HRAF:
               variables, positive and negative correlations, and the verification of hypotheses
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1965a" loc="90"/>. However, elsewhere he mostly referred
               to it as <quote rend="inline">an enormous documentary tool</quote> or <quote
                  rend="inline">a bibliographical treasure</quote> and he stressed: <quote
                  rend="inline">the card index to the <title rend="italic">Files</title>, which some
                  people have unwisely denigrated, is above all a library</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="63, 77"/>. This actually proves that Lévi-Strauss
               treated this tool in a fairly traditional way.</p>
            <p>What puzzles me is the fact that despite all the praise, Lévi-Strauss hardly spoke of
               the <title rend="italic">Files</title> as useful in his writing. Even while
               describing his work on the well-documented and abundant volumes of <title
                  rend="italic">Mythologies</title>, when he had to <q>comb through</q> all relevant
               ethnographic literature to distill myths, he never made use of the HRAF collection
                  explicit.<note>Jason Pribilsky interpreted a famous cartoon by Maurice Henry
                  depicting the great French intellectuals – Foucault, Derrida, Barthes and
                  Lévi-Strauss, with his nose in papers – asking a question (of a rather rhetorical
                  nature) if Strauss was actually <quote rend="inline">lost in the pages of Human
                     Relations Area Files</quote>
                  <ptr target="#pribilsky2016" loc="11"/>. My tentative answer to such a question
                  would be that he probably wasn’t or at least he would not have seen it as reading
                  the HRAF, but instead the ethnographic reports deposited there.</note> It is
               possible, of course, that he had used it like a standard library and decided to cite
               only primary sources he retrieved, without acknowledging the tool itself (which seems
               also to be the case in the usage of today’s online repositories).</p>
            <p>Was HRAF widely used in the Parisian Laboratory? I was not able to determine it, but,
               according to Lévi-Strauss himself, some key figures like Raymond Aron, Gabriel Le
               Bras, Jacques Lacan and Pierre Bourdieu expressed interest in it (cited in: <ref
                  target="#loyer2018" loc="385">Loyer 2018, 385</ref>). Also, Simone de Beauvoir was
               said to consult the HRAF (see: <ref target="#salerno2004" loc="137">Salerno 2004,
                  137</ref>). Regarding collaboration fostered by the HRAF, it appears that sharing
               infrastructure did not necessarily lead to working together.<note>The ideas of
                  sharing and collaboration are entwined in the definitions of infrastructure
                  promoted by e-Science programs (and imported to the humanities as well) – see:
                     <ref target="#anderson2012" loc="153">Anderson and Blanke 2012,
                  153</ref>.</note> The collection was rather used individually by scholars.
               Referring to an already mentioned account of the spatial constraints imposed on the
               LAS’s members by the growing HRAF, we can observe that expansion of the <title
                  rend="italic">Files</title> led to shrinkage of office space and eventually
               resulted in adding partition walls, <quote rend="inline">especially under the Mansard
                  roof, to create individual cubicles</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="77"/>. The sheer size of the HRAF was perhaps
               more likely to affect work habits and forms of sociality in the Laboratory
               (solidifying a perceived need for a solo studio, or a cubicle) rather than transform
               modes of doing research. Regarding affordances of the <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> coming from their content and organization, they could have lent
               themselves to analyses undertaken by the LAS’s researchers. Lévi-Strauss talks about
               collaborating with his colleagues (Lucien Sebag and Jean-Claude Gardin) on the
               mythology of Pueblos – preparing an inventory, <quote rend="inline">laying a myth on
                  the table and analyzing it together</quote>
               <ptr target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="127"/> – maybe the <title rend="italic"
                  >Files</title> could have been used for such purposes.<note>But such collaboration
                  did not result in co-authored publications. Speaking of collective work,
                  Lévi-Strauss pointed to his seminar: <quote rend="inline">our weekly seminar can
                     become the meeting place for a team whose members, already united by other
                     ties, can thus keep each other informed of their individual work. It goes
                     without saying that this collaboration supposes a certain unity of views,
                     without, however, excluding a doctrinal independence. The unity results from
                     the fact that whether to get inspiration or to combat them, the participants
                     readily take as terms of reference the ideas that we, ourselves, continue to
                     develop in both our lectures at the Collège and the discussions - often very
                     lively - which occupy the last part of each seminar</quote>
                  <ptr target="#lévistrauss1983" loc="63"/>.</note></p>
            <p>Moreover, being a database-like tool, consisting of chunks of ethnographic texts as
               discrete units mapping different cultures and enabling manipulation and
               reconfiguration by the scholar, the HRAF could afford and at the same time epitomize
                  <quote rend="inline">structuralist activity</quote> defined by Roland Barthes as
               the <quote rend="inline">fabrication</quote> of the world, which <quote rend="inline"
                  >involves two typical operations: dissection and articulation</quote>
               <ptr target="#barthes1972" loc="216"/>. Barthes explains: <quote rend="inline"
                  >Structural man takes the real, decomposes it, then recomposes it; this appears to
                  be little enough (which makes some say that the structuralist enterprise is
                     <q>meaningless,</q>
                  <q>uninteresting,</q>
                  <q>useless,</q> etc.)</quote>
               <ptr target="#barthes1972" loc="215"/>. Interestingly, the very accusations were also
               made with regard to the <title rend="italic">Files</title> (reportedly, Margaret Mead
               spoke of their <quote rend="inline">artlessness</quote> – see <ref
                  target="#tobin1990" loc="477">Tobin 1990, 477</ref>).</p>
            <p>It should be noted here that the critique of the Human Relations Area Files – not
               uncommon then<note>Actually, reconstructing the critical arguments against the <title
                     rend="italic">Files</title> and analyzing how they changed throughout the years
                  would be of value. I would just like to point to Joseph Tobin’s interesting piece
                     <title rend="quotes">The HRAF as Radical Text?</title> (1990), which is a truly
                  tongue-in-cheek interpretation of the <title rend="italic">Files</title> as
                  reactionary in a political and also epistemological sense, but stylistically
                  radical. Tobin shows that in the course of the interpretive turn in anthropology
                  (after <title rend="italic">Writing Culture</title>), HRAF was dismissed as
                  uncool, dull and falsely scientific. But even before there were considerable
                  objections to it voiced by British anthropologists. Tobin argues it shows a
                  transatlantic rift between visions of how anthropological theory should be built.
                  What was artless <quote rend="inline">tabulated nonsense</quote> for Edmund Leach
                  (Cambridge), remains a valid behavioral sciences theory created by analyzing
                  causal relationships between variables for his American colleagues using
                  Cross-Cultural Survey and disapproving British anthropology for being <quote
                     rend="inline">overwhelmingly humanistic</quote>, descriptive and intuitive
                  (cited in: <ref target="#tobin1990" loc="478">Tobin 1990, 478</ref>).</note> – was
               expressed inside the LAS, too. Furthermore, it came from the chief expert on
               informatization, appreciated by Lévi-Strauss, Jean-Claude Gardin (who ran <title
                  rend="italic">Section d’Automatique documentaire</title> in CNRS). Gardin is
               recognized as a pioneer of archaeological computing. As early as in 1960 he published
               an article reviewing the HRAF in which he points out two main problems of this tool –
               on a practical level it is too expensive and cumbersome and on a theoretical level it
               imposes a rigid classification scheme and its categories are too broad to
               operationalize and lack cross-referencing (see: <ref target="#gardin1960">Gardin
                  1960</ref>). He also suggests that the HRAF could be opposed because of its
               aspirations to universality, or the <q>totalitarianism</q> of a general system. After
               a few critical remarks on the HRAF, Gardin elaborates on a different project in the
               making, undertaken in order to search through vast ethnographic literature by
               employing mechanical methods. The ethnographer in charge of this task had been
               Françoise Izard (later known as Héritier), who became Lévi-Strauss’s successor.</p>
            <p>Yet another interesting critique that should be addressed here pertains to Murdock
               and his methods and dates back to 1952. The critic is Lévi-Strauss himself. While
               acknowledging Murdock’s contribution to the study of social structure by
                  <q>rejuvenating statistical methods</q> and <q>painstaking effort</q> in creating
               Cross-Cultural Survey (a.k.a. HRAF), he points out that the number of 250 cultures
               selected by Murdock as a sample for cross-cultural analyses is an <q>overindulgent
                  estimate</q>, data is abstracted and the categories used in the scheme mirrored
               the traditional evolutionary anthropological theory rather than do justice to terms
               derived from the source material. It is also to be noted – Lévi-Strauss continues –
               that the method proves efficient mostly in a negative way (when used to scrutinize
               whether any alleged correlations are plausible). Finally, he states: <quote
                  rend="inline">the reader here may easily verify that I take the greatest care to
                  dissociate my conceptions from those of Radcliffe-Brown and Murdock</quote>,
               adding that he never used statistical methods <ptr target="#lévistrauss1968"
                  loc="306–324"/>. This is all rather serious methodological and theoretical
               critique, suggesting unambiguously that Lévi-Strauss was not willing to use the HRAF
               in the ways intended by Murdock. Perhaps that is why he <q>reduced</q> it to a rich
               bibliographical treasury, intending to repurpose it for his newly opened center as a
               well-equipped library of literature (in English, so probably less widely available in
               France). After all, having conducted research in the New York Public Library, he knew
               how useful it was since he touted this place as the bedrock of his expanded
               anthropological erudition.</p>
            <p>It would be interesting to examine what has become these days of the paper HRAF in
               the LAS. The paper version of HRAF today serves as something of a curiosity. It takes
               up a lot of space, although nobody uses it for research purposes, but a lot of people
               do like to take photos in front of it. It is reminiscent of the categories coined by
               Anke te Heesen writing about a type of furniture – the cabinet or cupboard – and its
               role in making academic knowledge. The author distinguished several subcategories,
               one of them being <term>Ordungsmöbel</term>, enabling storing and sorting and the
               other one <term>Representationmöbel</term>, which is for example a decorative old
               cabinet, usually emptied and put in the rector’s office as a nostalgic representative
               of the great many years of tradition <ptr target="#heesen2007"/>. Although HRAF
               drawers are not empty and materials still can be consulted (by appointment), the
               paper files do not really serve as a go-to library resource, but rather an index of
               the fascinating origins and adventures of the Laboratory. It is worth asking whether
               structural anthropology might have shared the fate of the HRAF: has it become to some
               degree a museum piece?</p>
            <p>Traversing through the reception of structuralism and the legacy of the Laboratory in
               today’s anthropology is beyond the scope of this paper. Notwithstanding, I would like
               to mention Paul Rabinow’s critique of the LAS. As he has noted, despite its
               significant achievements in fostering a collective mode of research, LAS has not
               stood the test of time, failing to adapt its methods to changing realities and
               solidifying a hierarchical structure perpetuated by Lévi-Strauss’ personal charisma
                  <ptr target="#rabinow2006"/>. Rabinow, Collier and Lakoff are also critical of the
                  <title rend="italic">Files</title> and their claims to universality <ptr
                  target="#collier2006"/>. What is worth noting, though, is that Rabinow and his
               colleagues have advocated for anthropological laboratories and have founded one
               themselves. In their blueprint for the lab, infrastructure is recognized as
               meaningful, no mimicry of the natural science is intended and the most important role
               is occupied by <q>rigorous</q> concept work (based on collective
                  agreement).<note>Rabinow et al. founded the Laboratory for the Anthropology of the
                  Contemporary (LAC). A striking resemblance to the LAS is most certainly
                  unintentional here, but the idea provokes us to think of the similarities and
                  dissimilarities between the two endeavors. What is worth mentioning, Rabinow’s
                  drive to the <q>laboratory of the interpretive human sciences</q> comes from
                  dissatisfaction with the individual project as the dominant mode of knowledge
                  production. </note></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusions</head>
            <p>This study is a contribution to the archaeology of the humanities laboratory
               approached from an infrastructure and media angle. My goal was to shed more light on
               the significance of infrastructure in the analog humanities’ lab by focusing on the
               case of the <title rend="italic">Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title> founded
               in 1960 and directed (till 1982) by Claude Lévi-Strauss. Drawing on the literature
               from the field of humanities infrastructure and research infrastructure as well as
               other seminal works in critical infrastructure studies, I have shown how the
               Laboratory was organized around the Human Relations Area Files. They played an
               important role in seeking funds and space and – considered as valuable and rare
               resources – were used to gain infrastructural advantage (based on their paper-ness)
               and helped to position the LAS as <q>richly endowed</q>. I suggest that it may be
               partly due to these pragmatic reasons – recognized as not epistemically related or
               valid – that the Laboratory has not had any important place in the readings of
               Lévi-Strauss’s work.</p>
            <p>Moreover, the LAS has not been (yet) rediscovered by the movement towards the
               humanities labs which we are observing in the present day. We could be tempted to see
               Lévi-Strauss as a proto-digital humanist (or the humanities’ computing fellow), given
               his interest in applying computers and new means of documentation to anthropological
               research. In fact, he rather adhered to more old-fashioned, <q>makeshift</q> methods
               (as admitted in: <ref target="#lévistrauss1991" loc="138">Lévi-Strauss and Eribon
                  1991, 138</ref>). Meanwhile, he observed – not without great interest – how others
               in his Laboratory were figuring out how to benefit from computing in the anthropology
               of kinship.<note>More on these early attempts at computerizing anthropology in the
                  LAS can be found in: <ref target="#zonabend2010" loc="36–37">Zonabend et al. 2010,
                     36-37</ref> and <ref target="#lévistrauss1965b">Lévi-Strauss 1965b</ref>. Also,
                  Loyer writes that since 1967 the LAS could share an SDS 9300 computer with a
                  nuclear physics laboratory at the Collége (she also claims that the LAS was marked
                  by a rather naïve enthusiasm for computers) <ptr target="#loyer2018" loc="401"/>.
                  This allows us to say that the computer in Lévi-Straussian thinking was not just
                  imagined, as Seaver claims <ptr target="#seaver2014"/>, but actually quite
                  real.</note></p>
            <p>What this paper also highlights, is a significant load of immaterial academic <q>care
                  work</q>, which means here taking care of (re)sources and (re)locations.
               Lévi-Strauss appears to be a skillful administrator, fundraiser, facilitator of
               teaching and publishing platforms and a vocal advocate for the human sciences
               (despite the scientism he may have subscribed to). He was able to coordinate the
               LAS’s activities with French state-driven research programs, taking advantage of new
               higher education policies in the 1960s and 1970s. Caring for the LAS’ material
               conditions (i. e., maintaining its costly and burdensome HRAF collection) was,
               though, a team effort. Refocusing my history of this lab on the <q>hidden figures</q>
               (who contributed greatly to the actual quotidian work of the research institution,
               failing to be fully acknowledged) seems worthy of exploration and would entail
               seeking additional source materials.</p>
            <p>Lastly, I also examined the place of the <title rend="italic">Files</title> in the
               Laboratory of Social Anthropology in terms of their mutual or contradictory research
               goals and methods and theoretical underpinnings. Considering how the HRAF contributed
               to the situatedness of the lab, I elucidated its <q>imported</q> character and
               possible implications thereof. I argued that although maintaining this enormous
               collection influenced the organization of the physical premises of the LAS, it
               apparently did not alter in a significant way the modes of study (neither did it
               start intensive research collaborations within the lab, which is sometimes believed
               to result from sharing infrastructure). It could be said that the HRAF used by
               Strauss and his Laboratory took on various functions, ranging from boosting the sense
               of excellence and exclusivity, through being a rhetorical tool in discourse on
               modernization of the human sciences and experimental anthropology, to even being a
               bargaining chip in negotiation for a bigger locale. In several respects the <title
                  rend="italic">Files</title> were compatible with research agenda in the Laboratory
               of Social Anthropology and with its founder’s own proclivities, constituting a
               repository of <quote rend="inline">ready-made experiments</quote> and lending
               themselves to structuralist <q>dissection and articulation</q>. However, it is more
               likely that <title rend="italic">Files</title> in the LAS were actually tailored for
               its specific (infrastructural) needs and used more traditionally than was intended by
               their creators – not as a machine for drawing statistical correlations, but rather an
               efficient library catalog. Through the <q>infrastructural inversion</q> it all comes
               into focus, proving how seemingly prosaic arrangements tend to be epistemically
               laden. </p>
            <p>Continuing this study will need to pick up some loose threads and engage with the
               materiality of knowledge production in the LAS. Further research could usefully
               explore topics such as Lévi-Strauss’s strong inclination to experiments performed
               with the help of models and mobiles (made from paper and wires and hanging from the
               ceiling in the Laboratory) and all the <q>handiwork</q> invested in modelling, which
               he conceived – contrary to common belief – as the work of an engineer rather than
               a bricoleur. </p>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix" xml:id="acknowledgements">
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This research is a part of the collaborative grant <hi rend="italic">Laboratorium
                  humanistyczne jako modus poznania. Od archeologii do projektu [The humanities
                  laboratory as a mode of knowing. From archaeology to a project]</hi>, NCN OPUS 13,
               no. UMO-2017/25/B/HS2/00593, 2018-2021, based at the Department of Cultural Studies,
               University of Wrocław, and funded by the National Science Centre in Poland.</p>
            <p>I wish to specially thank Dorota Wolska and Jacek Małczyński, with whom I have been
               working closely on this project, for their invaluable advice, patience and support. I
               would also like to acknowledge other members of the project team for providing
               feedback on my study and willingness to discuss their own work on the humanities
               laboratory (in alphabetical order): Maciej Bączyk, Joanna Bednarek, Karolina
               Charewicz-Jakubowska, Mirosław Kocur, Krzysztof Łukasiewicz, Rafał Nahirny, Adam
               Pisarek, Joanna Sieracka.</p>
            <p>I benefitted greatly from the thoughtful and inspiring comments by the DHQ special
               issue editors and two anonymous reviewers. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="abélès2008" label="Abélès 2008">Abélès, M. <title rend="quotes">Le fichier
                  des Human Relations Area Files</title>. <title rend="italic">La Lettre du Collége
                  de France</title>, (2008): 66–67.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson2013" label="Anderson2013">Anderson, S. <title rend="quotes">What
                  are Research Infrastructures?</title>
               <title rend="italic">IJHAC</title> 7 (2013): 4–23.
               doi:10.3366/ijhac.2013.0078.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="antonijević2013" label="Antonijević et al. 2013">Antonijević, S., Dormans,
               S., and Wyatt, S. <title rend="quotes">Working in Virtual Knowledge. Affective labor
                  in scholarly collaboration</title>, in <title rend="italic">Virtual Knowledge:
                  Experimenting in the Humanities and the Social Sciences</title>, The MIT Press,
               Cambridge, MA (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="barthes1972" label="Barthes 1972">Barthes, R. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Structuralist Activity</title>, In <title rend="italic">Critical Essays</title>,
               Northwestern University Press, Evanston, 213–220, (1972).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="belmont2008" label="Belmont 2008">Belmont, N. <title rend="quotes">Le
                  Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title>. <title rend="italic">La lettre du
                  Collège de France</title>, 62–65, (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berry2015" label="Berry and Dieter 2015">Berry, D. M., and Dieter, M.
                  <title rend="quotes">Thinking Postdigital Aesthetics: Art, Computation and
                  Design</title>. In D. M. Berry, M. Dieter (eds) <title rend="italic">Postdigital
                  Aesthetics. Art, Computation and Design</title>, Palgrave Macmillan, Houndmills,
               Basingstoke, Hampshire; New York, NY, 1–11, (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berry2017" label="Berry and Fagerjord 2017">Berry, D. M., and Fagerjord,
               A. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities: Knowledge and Critique in a Digital
                  Age</title>. Polity Press, Cambridge, (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="borgman2007" label="Borgman 2007">Borgman, C. L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Scholarship in the Digital Age: Information, Infrastructure, and the
                  Internet</title>. The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA (2007).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowker2017" label="Bowker 2017">Bowker, G. C. <title rend="quotes">How
                  knowledge infrastructures learn</title>. In P. Harvey, C. B. Jensen, and A. Morita
               (eds), <title rend="italic">Infrastructures and social complexity: a
                  companion</title>, Routledge, London; New York, 391–403 (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="buckley2014" label="Buckley 2014">Buckley, J. <title rend="quotes">Analog
                  versus Digital</title>. In M.-L. Ryan, L. Emerson, and B. Robertson (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">The Johns Hopkins Guide to Digital Media</title>, John Hopkins
               University Press, Baltimore, (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carse2017" label="Carse 2017">Carse, A. <title rend="quotes">Keyword:
                  Infrastructure – How a Humble French Engineering Term Shaped the Modern
                  World</title>. In P. Harvey, C. B. Jensen, and A. Morita (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Infrastructures and social complexity: a companion</title>,
               Routledge, London; New York, 27–39, (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chiva2004" label="Chiva 2004">Chiva, I. <title rend="quotes">Une
                  communauté de solitaires: le Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title>. In
                  <title rend="italic">Claude Lévi-Strauss</title>, Éditions l’Herne, Paris, 68–75,
               (2004).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clarke1985" label="Clarke and Henige 1985">Clarke, J. A., and Henige, D.
                  <title rend="quotes">The Human Relations Area Files</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Behavioral &amp; Social Sciences Librarian</title> 3 (1985), 45–52.
               doi:10.1300/J103v03n04_05.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="collier2006" label="Collier et al. 2006">Collier, S., Lakoff, A., and
               Rabinow, P. <title rend="quotes">What is a Laboratory in the Human Sciences?</title>
               <title rend="italic">ARC Working Papers</title> (2006). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://anthropos-lab.net/wp/publications/2007/08/workingpaperno1.pdf"
                  >http://anthropos-lab.net/wp/publications/2007/08/workingpaperno1.pdf</ref>
               [Accessed January 30, 2019] </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cox2015" label="Cox 2015">Cox, G. <title rend="quotes">Postscript on the
                  Post-digital and the Problem of Temporality</title>. In D. M. Berry, M. Dieter
               (eds), <title rend="italic">Postdigital Aesthetics. Art, Computation and
                  Design</title>, Palgrave Macmillan, Houndmills, Basingstoke, Hampshire; New York,
               NY, 151–162 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cramer2015" label="Cramer 2015">Cramer, F. <title rend="quotes">What Is
                     <q>Post-digital</q>?</title> In D. M. Berry, M. Dieter (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">Postdigital Aesthetics. Art, Computation and Design</title>,
               Palgrave Macmillan, Houndmills, Basingstoke, Hampshire; New York, NY, 12–26
               (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ember1998" label="Ember et al. 1998">Ember, C. R., Ember, M., and Human
               Relations Area Files, Inc. <title rend="italic">A basic guide to cross-cultural
                  research using the HRAF collections</title>. Human Relations Area Files, New
               Haven, Conn. (1998).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ember1988" label="Ember 1988">Ember, M. <title rend="quotes">The Human
                  Relations Area Files: Past and Future</title>. <title rend="italic">Behavior
                  Science Research</title> 22 (1988), 97–104.
               doi:10.1177/106939718802200109,.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ember2000" label="Ember and Human Relations Area Files 20004">Ember, M.,
               and Human Relations Area Files, Inc. <title rend="italic">HRAF in the 21st century:
                  blueprint for the future after 50 years</title>. Human Relations Area Files, Inc.,
               New Haven, Conn. (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ford1970" label="Ford 1970">Ford, C. S. <title rend="quotes">Human
                  Relations Area Files: 1949-1969 A Twenty-Year Report</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Behavior Science Notes</title> (1970). doi:10.1177/106939717000500101.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="galloway2014" label="Galloway 2014">Galloway, A. R. <title rend="italic"
                  >Laruelle: Against the Digital</title>. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
               (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gardin1960" label="Gardin 1960">Gardin, J.-C. <title rend="quotes">Les
                  Human Relations Area Files et la Mécanographie dans la documentation
                  ethnographique</title>. <title rend="italic">Cahiers d’Études africaines</title> 1
               (1960), 150–152. doi:10.3406/cea.1960.2954.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="geertz1973" label="Geertz 1973">Geertz, C. <title rend="quotes">Thick
                  Description: Towards an Interpretive Theory of Culture</title>. In <title
                  rend="italic">The Interpretation of Cultures</title>. Basic Books, New York
               (1973). Available at: https://philarchive.org/archive/GEETTD [Accessed January 30,
               2020].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="geohegan2011" label="Geohegan 2011">Geoghegan, B. D. <title rend="quotes"
                  >From Information Theory to French Theory: Jakobson, Lévi-Strauss, and the
                  Cybernetic Apparatus</title>. <title rend="italic">Critical Inquiry</title> 38
               (2011), 96–126. doi:10.1086/661645.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gitelman2010" label="Gitelman 2010">Gitelman, L. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Ages, Epochs, Media</title>. In V. Jackson (ed), <title rend="italic">On
                  periodization: selected essays from the English Institute</title>, English
               Institute in collaboration with the American Council of Learned Societies, Cambridge,
               MA. Available at: <ref target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.90047.0001.001"
                  >http://hdl.handle.net/2027/heb.90047.0001.001</ref> [Accessed April 18,
               2019].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2012" label="Hayles 2012">Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic">How We
                  Think: Digital Media and Contemporary Technogenesis</title>. The University of
               Chicago Press, Chicago; London (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2013" label="Hayles and Pressman 2013">Hayles, N. K., and Pressman,
               J. (eds), <title rend="italic">Comparative Textual Media: Transforming the Humanities
                  in the Postprint Era</title>. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
               (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="heesen2007" label="Heesen 2007">[Heesen 2007] Heesen, A. T. (ed), <title
                  rend="italic">Auf / Zu. Der Schrank in den Wissenschaften: Der Schrank in den
                  Wissenschaften</title>. Akademie Verlag, Berlin (2007).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jones2018" label="Jones 2018">[Jones 2018] Jones, S. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Reverse Engineering the First Humanities Computing Center</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly, </title>2 (2018). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/2/000380/000380.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/12/2/000380/000380.html</ref> [Accessed
               January 30, 2020].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kil2017" label="Kil 2017">Kil, A. <title rend="quotes">Archive/Apparatus
                  of the Scholar. On the Index Cards of Stanisław Pietraszko</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Czas Kultury</title>, 2 (2017), 86–101. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://czaskultury.pl/en/archiveapparatus-of-the-scholar-on-the-index-cards-of-stanislaw-pietraszko/"
                  >http://czaskultury.pl/en/archiveapparatus-of-the-scholar-on-the-index-cards-of-stanislaw-pietraszko/</ref>
               [Accessed April 18, 2019]</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lagacé1974" label="Lagacé 1974">Lagacé, R. O. <title rend="italic">Nature
                  and Use of the Hraf Files: A Research and Teaching Guide.</title> HRAF MANUALS.
               Human Relations Area Files, Inc., New Haven, Conn. (1974).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="latour2011" label="Latour 2011">Latour, B. <title rend="quotes">Drawing
                  Things Together</title>. In M. Dodge, R. Kitchin, C. Perkins (eds), <title
                  rend="italic">The Map Reader: Theories of Mapping Practice and Cartographic
                  Representation</title>, John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, 65–72.
               doi:10.1002/9780470979587.ch9. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lemov2006" label="Lemov 2006">Lemov, R. <title rend="italic">World as
                  Laboratory: Experiments with Mice, Mazes, and Men</title>. Hill and Wang. A
               division of Farrar, Straus and Giroux, New York (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lemov2012" label="Lemov 2012">Lemov, R. <title rend="quotes">Filing the
                  Total Human: Anthropological Data Banks at Mid-Twentieth Century</title>. In
                  <title rend="italic">Social Knowledge in the Making</title>. The University of
               Chicago Press, Chicago, 119–150 (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lemov2015" label="Lemov 2015">Lemov, R. <title rend="italic">Database of
                  Dreams: The Lost Quest to Catalog Humanity</title>. Yale University Press, New
               Haven and London (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lévistrauss1955" label="Lévi-Strauss 1955">Lévi-Strauss, C. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Structural Study of Myth</title>. <title rend="italic">The
                  Journal of American Folklore</title> 68 (1955), 428-444. doi:10.2307/536768. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lévistrauss1965a" label="Lévi-Strauss 1965a">Lévi-Strauss, C. <title
                  rend="quotes">Présentation d’un Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Reveu de L’enseignement supérieur</title>, (1965) 87–92. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lévistrauss1965b" label="Lévi-Strauss 1965b">Lévi-Strauss, C. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Future of Kinship Studies</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and
                  Ireland</title>, 13 (1965). doi:10.2307/3031752.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lévistrauss1968" label="Lévi-Strauss 1968">Lévi-Strauss, C. <title
                  rend="italic">Structural anthropology Vol. 1</title>. Penguin Press, London
               (1968).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lévistrauss1983" label="Lévi-Strauss 1983">Lévi-Strauss, C. <title
                  rend="italic">Structural Anthropology. Vol. 2</title>. University of Chicago
               Press, Chicago (1983).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lévistrauss1991" label="Lévi-Strauss and Eribon 1991">Lévi-Strauss, C.,
               and Eribon, D. <title rend="italic">Conversations with Claude Lévi-Strauss</title>.
               University of Chicago Press, Chicago (1991).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2013" label="Liu 2013">Liu, A. <title rend="quotes">The Meaning of the
                  Digital Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">PMLA</title> 128 (2013), 409–423.
               doi:10.1632/pmla.2013.128.2.409. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="loyer2018" label="Loyer 2018">Loyer, E. <title rend="italic">Lévi-Strauss:
                  a biography. </title>Polity Press, London (2018). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mandell2015" label="Mandell 2015">Mandell, L. <title rend="italic"
                  >Breaking the Book: Print Humanities in the Digital Age</title>. Wiley Blackwell,
               Chichester, W. Sussex (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mattern2016" label="Mattern 2016">Mattern, S. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Scaffolding, Hard and Soft – Infrastructures as Critical and Generative
                  Structures</title>. <title rend="italic">Spheres</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="http://spheres-journal.org/scaffolding-hard-and-soft-infrastructures-as-critical-and-generative-structures/"
                  >http://spheres-journal.org/scaffolding-hard-and-soft-infrastructures-as-critical-and-generative-structures/</ref>
               [Accessed January 30, 2019].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murdock1950" label="Murdock 1950">Murdock, G. P. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Feasibility and Implementation of Comparative Community Research: With Special
                  Reference to the Human Relations Area Files</title>. <title rend="italic">American
                  Sociological Review</title> 15 (1950), 713–720. doi:10.2307/2086603. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pace1983" label="Pace 1983">Pace, D. <title rend="italic">Claude
                  Lévi-Strauss.</title> Routledge &amp; Paul, Boston (1983).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="parikka2012" label="Parikka 2012">Parikka, J. <title rend="italic">What is
                  media archaeology?</title>. Polity Press, Cambridge, UK; Malden, MA (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="parks2015" label="Parks 2015">Parks, L. <title rend="quotes"><q>Stuff You
                     Can Kick</q>: Toward a Theory of Media Infrastructures</title>. In P. Svensson
               and D. T. Goldberg (eds), <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and the
                  Digital</title>, The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 355–373 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pawlicka2017" label="Pawlicka 2017">Pawlicka, U. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Data, Collaboration, Laboratory: Bringing Concepts from Science into Humanities
                  Practice</title>. <title rend="italic">English Studies</title> 98 (2017), 526–541.
               doi:10.1080/0013838X.2017.1332022.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pribilsky2016" label="Pribilsky 2016">Pribilsky, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Will to Enclose: Foucault’s Archive in the Era of Cold War Big Data</title>.
                  <title rend="italic">Le foucaldien</title> 2 (2016), 1. doi:10.16995/lefou.11. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="price2012" label="Price 2012">Price, D. H. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Counterinsurgency and the M-VICO System: Human Relations Area Files and
                  anthropology’s dual-use legacy</title>. <title rend="italic">Anthropology
                  Today</title> 28 (2012), 16–20. doi:10.1111/j.1467-8322.2012.00850.x.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="price2016" label="Price 2016">Price, D. H. <title rend="italic">Cold War
                  Anthropology: The CIA, the Pentagon, and the Growth of Dual Use
                  Anthropology</title>. Duke University Press, Durham and London (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rabinow2006" label="Rabinow 2006">Rabinow, P. <title rend="quotes">Steps
                  toward an anthropological laboratory</title>. <title rend="italic">ARC Working
                  Papers</title>, 19 (2006). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://www.ram-wan.net/restrepo/teorias-antrop-contem/Rabinow_Laboratory.pdf"
                  >http://www.ram-wan.net/restrepo/teorias-antrop-contem/Rabinow_Laboratory.pdf</ref>
               [Accessed 18 April, 2019].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="robinson2008" label="Robinson 2008">Robinson, D. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Analog</title>. In M. Fuller (ed) <title rend="italic">Software Studies: A
                  Lexicon</title>, The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 21–31 (2008).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rockwell2010" label="Rockwell 2010">Rockwell, G. <title rend="quotes">As
                  Transparent as Infrastructure: On the research of cyberinfrastructure in the
                  humanities</title>. In <title rend="italic">Online Humanities Scholarship: The
                  Shape of Things to Come - OpenStax CNX</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://cnx.org/contents/PVdH0-lD@1.3:_USvuzFn@2/As-Transparent-as-Infrastructure-On-the-research-of-cyberinfrastructure-in-the-humanities"
                  >https://cnx.org/contents/PVdH0-lD@1.3:_USvuzFn@2/As-Transparent-as-Infrastructure-On-the-research-of-cyberinfrastructure-in-the-humanities</ref>
               [Accessed January 30, 2019]. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roe2007" label="Roe 2007">Roe, S. K. <title rend="quotes">A Brief History
                  of an Ethnographic Database</title>. <title rend="italic">Behavioral &amp; Social
                  Sciences Librarian</title> 25 (2007), 47–77. doi:10.1300/J103v25n02_03. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salerno2004" label="Salerno 2004">Salerno, R. A. <title rend="italic"
                  >Beyond the Enlightenment: Lives and Thoughts of Social Theorists</title>. Praeger
               Publishers, Westport, Conn. (2004).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schrey2014" label="Schrey 2014">Schrey, D. <title rend="quotes">Analogue
                  Nostalgia and the Aesthetics of Digital Remediation</title>. In K. Niemeyer (ed)
                  <title rend="italic">Media and Nostalgia: Yearning for the Past, Present and
                  Future</title>, Palgrave McMillan, Basingstoke (2014).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="seaver2014" label="Seaver 2014">Seaver, N. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Structuralism: Thinking with Computers</title>. <title rend="italic">Savage
                  Minds. Notes and Queries in Anthropology</title>. Available at:
               /2014/05/21/structuralism-thinking-with-computers/ [Accessed February 4, 2019]. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sontag1963" label="Sontag 1963">Sontag, S. <title rend="quotes">A Hero of
                  our Time</title>. <title rend="italic">New York Review of Books. </title>
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.nybooks.com/articles/1963/11/28/a-hero-of-our-time/"
                  >https://www.nybooks.com/articles/1963/11/28/a-hero-of-our-time/</ref> [Accessed
               January 30, 2019]. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="spoerhase2019" label="Spoerhase 2019">Spoerhase, C. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Seminar Libraries as Laboratories of Philology: The Modern Seminar Model in
                  Nineteenth-Century German Philology</title>. <title rend="italic">History of
                  Humanities</title> 4 (2019), 103–123. doi:10.1086/701988.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="star1999" label="Star 1999">Star, S. L. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Ethnography of Infrastructure</title>. <title rend="italic">American Behavioral
                  Scientist</title> 43 (1999), 377–391. doi:10.1177/00027649921955326. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="star1996" label="Star and Ruhleder 1996">Star, S. L., and Ruhleder, K.
                  <title rend="quotes">Steps Toward an Ecology of Infrastructure: Design and Access
                  for Large Information Spaces</title>. <title rend="italic">Information Systems
                  Research</title> 7 (1996), 111–134. doi:10.1287/isre.7.1.111.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sterne2015" label="Sterne 2015">Sterne, J. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Example: Some Historical Considerations</title>.  In P. Svensson and D. T.
               Goldberg (eds), <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and the Digital</title>, The
               MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 17–33 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sterne2016" label="Sterne 2016">Sterne, J. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Analog</title>. In B. Peters (ed), <title rend="italic">Digital Keywords: A
                  Vocabulary of Information Society and Culture</title>, Princeton University Press,
               Princeton, 31–44 (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2011" label="Svensson 2011">Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes">From
                  Optical Fiber To Conceptual Cyberinfrastructure</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5 (2011). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000090/000090.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/5/1/000090/000090.html</ref>. [Accessed
               April 18, 2019].</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2015" label="Svensson 2015">Svensson, P. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Humanistiscope - Exploring the Situatedness of Humanities Infrastructure</title>.
               In P. Svensson and D. T. Goldberg (eds), <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and
                  the Digital</title>, The MIT Press, Cambridge, MA, 337–353 (2015).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="svensson2016" label="Svensson 2016">Svensson, P. <title rend="italic">Big
                  Digital Humanities: Imagining a Meeting Place for the Humanities and the
                  Digital</title>. University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor.
               doi:10.3998/dh.13607060.0001.001. (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tkaczyk2019" label="Tkaczyk 2019">Tkaczyk, V. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Archival Traces of Applied Research: Language Planning and Psychotechnics in
                  Interwar Germany</title>. <title rend="italic">Technology and Culture</title> 60,
               (2019), 64–95. doi:10.1353/tech.2019.0064</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tobin1990" label="Tobin 1990">Tobin, J. <title rend="quotes">The HRAF as
                  Radical Text?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Cultural Anthropology</title> 5 (1990), 473–487.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wimmer2017" label="Wimmer 2017">Wimmer, M. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Afterlives of Scholarship: Warburg and Cassirer</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >History of Humanities</title> 2 (2017), 245–270. doi:10.1086/690581. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wythoff2018" label="Wythoff 2018">Wythoff, G. <title rend="quotes">On
                  Method in the Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Configurations</title>, 2,
               (2018). 10.1353/con.2018.0024</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zonabend2010" label="Zonabend et al. 2010">Zonabend, F., Neveux, F., and
               Descola, P. <title rend="italic">Le Laboratoire d’anthropologie sociale: 50 ans
                  d’histoire, 1960-2010</title>. Collège de France, Paris (2010).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
