<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->The Lives of Mistresses and Maids: Editing Victorian Correspondence with Genealogy,
               Prosopography, and the TEI</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Kailey <dhq:family>Fukushima</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of British Columbia</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>ksfukush@uvic.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Karen <dhq:family>Bourrier</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Calgary</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>karen.bourrier@ucalgary.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Janice <dhq:family>Parker</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Calgary Public Library</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>parkerjr@ucalgary.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>N/A</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000595</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->1</idno>
            <date when="2022-03-11">11 March 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-02" who="BRG">updated ptr tags</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>In this paper, we explore the material conditions of scholarship and digital editorial work that make uncovering nineteenth-century women’s lives possible in the twenty-first century. Taking our project, <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, a TEI-edition of the letters of the bestselling Victorian author, as a case study, we discuss research methods that combine digital scholarly editing with genealogy and prosopography. We argue that by combining research tools aimed at scholars, such as the Text Encoding Initiative (TEI), and the <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>, with research tools aimed at a more general audience, such as <title rend="italic"><title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title></title> and the <title rend="italic">British Newspaper Archive</title>, we can develop more creative and inclusive research methods and in turn, gain a fuller picture of women’s and working-class lives.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>In this paper, we explore the material conditions of scholarship and digital editorial work that make uncovering nineteenth-century women’s lives possible in the twenty-first century.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
        <div>
           <head></head>
        <epigraph><quote rend="block"> <p>
             <emph>It is much to be regretted that no lives of maids… are to be found in
               the Dictionary of National Biography.</emph>
         </p>
         <p>– Virginia Woolf, <title rend="italic">Three Guineas </title> (1938)</p></quote></epigraph>
         
         
         <p>Prosopography, a form of collective life writing that documents the characteristics of a
            group, has a long and gendered history. Developed as a historical research method in the
            second half of the nineteenth century and early twentieth century, by scholars studying
            populations including Ancient Rome and seventeenth-century English Puritans <ptr target="#verboven2007" loc="42"/>, much early prosopographical research focused on the lives of men. In the
            twenty-first century, we have inherited the legacy of this research; 85% of the entries
            in the <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography </title>(<title rend="italic"
               >ODNB</title>), a Victorian project begun by Sir Leslie Stephen, are of notable
               men.<note> As of March 2019, using the advanced search function available in the
               online edition, we find 6,974 notable women to the 54,011 notable men. If we limit
               our search to the long nineteenth century (1789 to 1914), women fare marginally
               better, making up 14% (rather than 13%) of notable people (4,698 women and 30,135
               men). Other scholars have noticed this issue and the <title rend="italic">ODNB</title> is
               working to rectify the situation. See Alison Booth, <title rend="quotes">Fighting for Lives in the <title
                  rend="italic">ODNB</title>,</title> for an overview of the problem of the lack of
               representation of women and the working classes at the time of the launch of the
               online <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title> in 2004. Mari
               Takayanagi’s introduction to the August 2018 update to the <title rend="italic"
                  >ODNB</title>, includes a focus on women and parliament after 1918.</note> Yet, in
            the same historical period, prosopography has been a congenial form for documenting
            women’s lives. As Alison Booth reminds us, in volume form, the collected lives of women
            have thrived since at least the second half of the nineteenth century, when the
            publication of volumes aimed at a general audience of (female) readers tripled and then
            quadrupled every decade, remaining a popular form to the present day <ptr target="#booth2004" loc="29"/>. Booth
            identifies <title rend="italic">Collective Biographies of Women</title> from as far back as the Middle Ages and notes
            that <quote rend="inline">Catalogs of notable women have flourished in plain view for centuries, while
               generation after generation laments the absence of women from the past</quote> <ptr target="#booth2004" loc="2–3"/>. On
            the one hand, then, women have been given short shrift in scholarly prosopographies such
            as the <title rend="italic">ODNB</title>. On the other hand, prosopography is one genre in which the lives of women
            and other marginalized groups have often flourished, in part because the collective form
            does not require believing that any individual woman is important enough to merit
            full-length biographical treatment, but rather that women’s history in general is
            important. </p>
         <p>In the late twentieth and early twenty-first centuries, the gendered history of
            prosopography has become intertwined with that of the digital humanities. Some of the
            most important early feminist digital humanities projects, including <title rend="italic">The Orlando Project</title>
            <ptr target="#brown2006a"/>, <title rend="italic">The Women Writers Project</title> <ptr target="#flanders1988"/>, and the
            <title rend="italic">Collective Biographies of Women</title> <ptr target="#booth2013"/>, analyze and generate prosopographies
            centered around women, in part because digitization offers the promise of more space to
            represent women’s writing and women’s lives freed from the constraints of the codex
            form. Of course, all projects remain bound by other constraints, including time and
            funding, and as Julia Flanders et al remind us in their work on encoding proper names,
            we must ask ourselves honestly about the feasibility and utility of this markup <ptr target="#flanders1998" loc="287"/>. There is a tension, then, in prosopography, between a necessary selectivity about
            which figures to include given the restraints imposed by the prosopographical format,
            whether it is a short chapter in a collective biography or a predetermined set of fields
            in a database, and a desire for greater inclusivity, especially in terms of representing
            marginalized lives. Yet, as we argue here, it is also possible for the restraints of the
            prosopographical format to be generative.</p>
         <p>In this paper, through a case study of a TEI edition of the letters of the popular
            Victorian novelist, Dinah Craik, we argue that the restraint imposed by the TEI template
            can lead us to a more inclusive prosopography, both in terms of the people included, and
            in the information-seeking methods we use to collect data on historical figures. Our
            project encodes and gives biographical detail not only for every person named in the
            letters, but also every person referenced but not necessarily named, many of whom are
            women referenced only as sisters, wives, and servants. TEI templates such as the one we
            use in <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title> may seem constraining; however, as as Jacqueline Wernimont argues in her writing on <title rend="italic">The Orlando Project</title>, technologies such as <title rend="italic">The Orlando Project</title>s’s XML Document Type Definition (DTD)
            can be read as <q>generative</q> and <quote rend="inline">productive of a model of the text, but not the sole or
            	authoritative model</quote> <ptr target="#wernimont2013" loc="¶13"/>. We follow Wernimont in arguing for the generative
            possibilities of mark up; in our case, the establishment of a TEI prosopographical
            template creates an imperative to fill every element and attribute, a departure from
            more selective standard editorial practice for nineteenth-century letters. We extend
            recent work in digital prosopography that explores the complex process of modelling
            people as data <ptr target="#crompton2016"/> <ptr target="#hedley2018"/> by demonstrating
            how we have combined scholarly tools such as the TEI with para-scholarly genealogical
            databases and recently digitized nineteenth-century newspapers and books to give the
            fullest account of each <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry possible. This approach is labor-intensive,
            and our project has relied heavily on the expertise and labor of student research
            assistants and librarians, as well as on external funding from the Social Sciences and
            Humanities Research Council of Canada (SSHRC). </p>
         <p>Given the work-intensive nature of our approach, a second goal of this paper is to
            highlight the affective labor of data collection, and the ingenuity involved in toggling
            back and forth between multiple sources to uncover data about nineteenth-century women
            who have left little trace. This type of research does not often receive the credit that
            other forms of scholarship do. Susan Brown argues that <quote rend="inline">activities of practical benefit
            to others</quote> in the digital humanities, including <quote rend="inline">structuring, manipulating,
            transforming, or remediating data</quote> can be defined as service labor in the digital
            humanities; this type of service labor, which often takes place in the library or is
            closely associated with librarianship, is feminized and less prestigious than other
            forms of scholarship <ptr target="#brown2018" loc="¶9"/>. In writing about our method of data collection in
            detail, we respond to recent calls in feminist digital humanities to recognize the labor
            and material conditions involved in data collection. Elizabeth Losh and Wernimont use
            the acronym MEALS to signal their feminist emphasis on how the <quote rend="inline">material, embodied,
            affective, labor-intensive, and situated character of engagements with computation can
            operate experientially for users in shared spaces.</quote> <ptr target="#losh2018" loc="17"/>. Catherine D'Ignazio and
            Lauren F. Klein point out that when data products are released to the public, the
            workers who collected the data and processed them for use are rarely credited. D’Ignazio
            and Klein make a feminist argument for showing the work involved in the entire life
            cycle of the project <ptr target="#dignazio2020" loc="ch. 7"/>.<note> D’Ignazio and Klein focus on the
               exploitation of a <q>global underclass,</q> often of BIPOC women, involved in data
               collection across the globe <ptr target="#dignazio2020"/>. While we are
               mindful that student research assistants at a North American university are
               comparatively privileged, within the hierarchy of the university we aspire to
               highlight their labor.</note> Midway through our project, we aim to document our data
            collection as a feminist practice. </p>
         <p>The <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title> project has been ongoing at the University of Calgary in
            Alberta, Canada, since January 2015 and now includes more than 400 letters published
            with Northeastern University’s TEI Archive Publishing and Access Service (TAPAS), and an
            accompanying prosopography that offers an inclusive and standardized set of information
            on every person mentioned by name or by reference in Craik’s letters. These encoded
            letters constitute the first phase of our project, in which we have focused on letters
            written by Craik and addressed to her publishers and other acquaintances in artistic and
            literary fields.<note> Archives across the United States and the United Kingdom hold
               over 1000 of Craik’s letters and 14 years of diaries: most importantly the Mulock
               Family Papers at the University of California at Los Angeles, the Dinah Maria Mulock
               Craik collection in the Harry Ransom Center at the University of Texas at Austin, and
               the Morris L. Parrish Collection of Victorian novelists at Princeton University.
               These collections include previously unpublished correspondence to Victorian
               luminaries including Elizabeth Barrett Browning and Oscar Wilde, as well as personal
               correspondence to her brother in the Crimea and her father in the Staffordshire
               Insane Asylum.</note> Craik’s letters are important not only because they shed light
            on the career of an important and well-connected author, but because of what they can
            tell us about the venues and types of publications and networks of connection that could
            sustain a nineteenth-century woman writer’s career for upwards of forty years. Craik’s
            career is remarkable not only for its success and length but for the literary
            sociability that sustained it, as she maintained relationships with writers, publishers
            and artists from her adolescent years to her death. Writing about digital editions of
            early modern correspondence, Camille Desenclos argues that one of the main aims of
            editing correspondence is <quote rend="inline">the (re)-constitution of networks</quote>; through <quote rend="inline">links created
            first between the sender and the addressee and then between the different people
            mentioned within the letters, a social, commercial and even cultural network can be
            reconstructed</quote> <ptr target="#desenclos2016" loc="188"/>. Craik’s letters are a testament to the power of social
            networks in a woman writer’s career, especially those centered around the home like that
            of Anna Maria and Samuel Carter Hall’s literary salon. Ultimately, we plan to use our
            encoded letters and prosopography to analyze Craik’s networks, but in this paper we
            focus on the methods we have developed to build an inclusive prosopography that helps
            our users glean meaning from component parts of the digital edition. </p>
         <p>Our work builds on scholarship in feminist and queer digital prosopography which focuses
            on the complex processes of modeling people as data, rather than on a final statistical
            analysis of a completed prosopographical dataset.<note> Recent work on the concepts of
               mark up and race further underscores the point that data is never neutral. For
               example, Jessica Marie Johnson offers black digital practice as a positive
               alternative to the digitization of eighteenth and nineteenth century records of
               slavery which threaten to replicate the violence of the slave ship register <ptr target="#johnson2018" loc="57"/>.
               Working at the intersection of Black studies and the digital humanities, Kim
               Gallon has argued that technology, including mark-up can expose the social
               construction of race <ptr target="#gallon2016" loc="42"/>. In <title rend="italic">Numbered Lives</title>, Jacqueline
               Wernimont reminds us that quantum media, which she defines as media that <quote rend="inline">count,
                  quantify, or enumerate,</quote> are not neutral or universal, but have historically been formulated with white, Christian men in mind <ptr target="#wernimont2019" loc="1, 31"/>.</note> In their prosopography for
            the <title rend="italic">Yellow Nineties</title> project, Alison Hedley and Lorraine Janzen Kooistra explore what it
            means to build a prosopography, a form that tends to work by <quote rend="inline">flattening out differences and
            anomalies to create a typical subject,</quote> based on an understanding that identity is
         	intersectional, <quote rend="inline">fluid and contingent</quote> <ptr target="#hedley2018" loc="¶3"/>. As Hedley and Kooistra note, the
            constraints of the TEI can guide prosopographical research while also affording
            flexibility in describing individual lives. They find that it is possible to <quote rend="inline">tailor the
            extensible markup language (XML)</quote> of the TEI using elements such as <code>&lt;addName&gt;</code> to
            account for nineteenth-century figures such as William Sharp, who not only wrote under the pseudonym Fiona Macleod but also created a <quote rend="inline">social, legal, and textual network</quote> as Macleod that allowed Sharp to live a second life with <quote rend="inline">a feminine literary persona</quote> <ptr target="#hedley2018" loc="162"/>.<note> Since the publication of this article, the
                  <title rend="italic">Yellow Nineties Personography</title> has moved from the TEI to
               linked open data. See <ptr target="#hedley2017"/>, <title rend="quotes">From TEI to Linked Open Data: Crossing the Stile.</title> The
               TEI has also recently added the element <code>&lt;persona&gt;</code>, for use when an individual
               such as Macleod / Sharp has multiple identities.</note> Similarly, in the Lesbian and
            Gay Liberation in Canada Project, Michelle Schwartz and Constance Crompton create a TEI
            prosopography that seeks to document the complexity of gay and lesbian lives in Canada
            rather than to <quote rend="inline">reduce liberationists to a few statistical averages</quote> <ptr target="#crompton2016" loc="¶1"/>.
            Following these scholars, we argue for a more expansive and inclusive form of digital
            prosopography, both in terms of which historical figures merit inclusion in a
            prosopography, and in terms of our information-seeking methods for prosopographical
            research. In making this twofold argument for inclusive prosopography, we demonstrate a
            method of research that makes full use of digitized records and information retrieval
            sources now available to us, regardless of their perceived scholarly value.</p>
         <p>While our focus in this paper is on developing an inclusive method for generating a TEI
            prosopography, much of the research on prosopography has focused on how scholars might
            make the best use of a completed prosopographical dataset, whether it is to support
            research questions about a historical group of people or to integrate a prosopography
            created using one technology with another one (for example, transforming a TEI
            prosopography to Linked Open Data). In collecting standardized biographical data on a
            large number of people, prosopography enables researchers to aggregate individual lives
            and make data-driven claims, for example, about the average life of a Roman slave or the
            relationship between Puritanism and a positive attitude toward science <ptr target="#verboven2007" loc="41–42"/>. Prosopography also has a long relationship with genealogy, which has been
            used to uncover individuals' ancestors and lineage, allowing scholars to make claims,
            for example, about the number of Roman officials from the same small network of families
            <ptr target="#verboven2007" loc="38–40"/>. The standardized, statistical nature of prosopography
            makes it a natural fit for computational research. Addressing concerns that
            prosopographical templates can decontextualize information about a person, presenting it
            as a straightforward fact, beginning in the 1990s scholars including John Bradley and
            Harold Short developed a factoid-based approach to prosopography, which uses relational
            technology to link person records to information about people in primary sources
            <ptr target="#bradley2005"/> <ptr target="#bradley2015"/>. This approach positions prosopography
            as a collection of situated <q>factoids</q> with potential tensions or contradictions, rather
            than as a standalone <quote rend="inline">‘scholarly overview’ of a person</quote> <ptr target="#bradley2005" loc="8"/>.
            Recent work has focused on how to make prosopographical data more widely discoverable
            online. The question of how to integrate prosopography with the semantic web has spurred
            scholars to explore ontologies such as CIDOC-CRM, FOAF, and SKOS <ptr target="#bradley2015"/> <ptr target="#brown2013"/>
            <ptr target="#brown2019"/>, and to work with TEI and MARC authority
            records with the goal of making prosopographical data interoperable with library
            catalogues <ptr target="#crompton2016"/>. </p>
         <p>Our contribution to digital prosopography begins at the opposite end of the research
            process, with developing an inclusive research method for collecting prosopographical
            data that leverages a combination of scholarly tools and databases aimed at family
            historians. This method grows out of our project’s user orientation, which has led us to
            prioritize actions that increase the availability of users’ information interactions
            within our digital edition. Our use of genealogical databases does not focus on
            uncovering family networks, which are not currently part of our TEI tagset, but rather
            on researching obscure people, particularly women and the working classes, who would
            otherwise be lost to history. Prosopography is notoriously labor-intensive; a problem
            with prosopographical research has been that the sources needed to complete research on
            a group of people, for example, the social background of a group of
            geographically-diverse Oxford students in the 1950s, has been scattered across the United Kingdom
            <ptr target="#verboven2007" loc="52"/>. Discovery services developed over the last thirty years and
            aimed at family historians, such as <title rend="italic">Ancestry</title> or <title rend="italic">FindMyPast</title>, offer a solution to this
            problem by aggregating not only previously scattered parish baptismal, birth, death and
            census records, but also, more recently, data including asylum records, military
            records, and even dog registration records.<note> Dog registration records can prove
               unexpectedly useful. Census records were not taken in Ireland until 1900, fifty years
               after they began in the UK. However, we were able to track the residences of Craik’s
               daughter Dorothy through dog licenses, which began in 1865 and have been digitized on
               <title rend="italic">Ancestry</title>.</note>
         </p>
         <p>Leveraging family history databases would seem to be a straightforward solution to some
            of the difficulties of prosopographical research, but scholars tend to be suspicious of
            resources aimed at family historians.<note> Print sources continue to carry more
               cultural prestige than their digital surrogates or born-digital sources, which may
               increase scholars’ reluctance to acknowledge their use. As Blaney and Siefring write,
               <quote rend="inline">many scholars still prefer to cite the print version of a work, even when they have
               only seen a digital surrogate</quote> in part because of the <q>perceived prestige</q> of print
            	sources over digital <ptr target="#blaney2017"  loc="¶1"/>.</note> Tanya Evans writes
            that genealogists <quote rend="inline">have been dismissed by professional and academic historians... as
            ‘misty-eyed and syrupy’ and their findings and practices deemed irrelevant to the wider
            historical community</quote> <ptr target="#evans2011" loc="49–51"/>. This suspicion operates at an institutional level;
            public libraries are much more likely to offer subscriptions to genealogical databases
            than university libraries. Marianne Van Remoortel notes that because these databases
            <quote rend="inline">primarily target amateur genealogists and do not count many universities among their
               subscribers, their potential remains largely untapped</quote> <ptr target="#vanremoortel2016" loc="134"/>. This concern is part
            of a long tradition of suspicion in the academy toward those who do research without the
            training and credentials valued in the university. N. Katherine Hayles writes that <quote rend="inline">most
            professional fields in the humanities have their shadow fields,</quote> and that scholars
            <quote rend="inline">often regard such activity as a nuisance because it is not concerned with the questions
               the scholar regards as important or significant</quote> <ptr target="#hayles2012" loc="36"/>. Following Hayles, we
            demonstrate that scholars would do well to incorporate the expertise and digital tools
            developed by and for those outside the academy.</p>
         <p>Prosopography is a central component of editing correspondence, but often historical
            persons mentioned in letters are researched with varying levels of detail depending upon
            their perceived historical significance. <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title> offers a case study that
            shows what a TEI prosopography might look like when a project’s research practices
            disallow such selective value judgments. Three digital editions of nineteenth-century
            letters — <title rend="italic">The Letters of Charlotte Mary Yonge</title> <ptr target="#mitchell"/>, <title rend="italic">The Olive Schreiner Letters Online</title>
             <ptr target="#stanley2007"/>, and the TEI edition of the <title rend="italic">Vincent
            Van Gogh Letters</title> <ptr target="#jansen1994"/> — differ in the level of granularity with
            which they encode the correspondents and people mentioned in the letters. The <title rend="italic">Vincent
            Van Gogh Letters</title> give full name dates of birth and death and occupation for all persons
            mentioned and typically no more (though there are separate written essays detailing Van
            Gogh’s family). <title rend="italic">The Charlotte Yonge Letters</title> give a full name, date of birth and death, a
            description including either occupation or relationship to Yonge, and a short
            biographical sentence for those named in the letters. <title rend="italic">The Olive Schreiner Letters</title> write
            their prosopographical data in paragraphs, with differing levels of detail. For example,
            a Miss Battie is described as <quote rend="inline">a typist who Schreiner approached to type some of her
               manuscripts</quote> about whom no further information is known <ptr target="#stanley2012a"/>, while the
            actor Wilson Barrett is described in a full paragraph with suggestions for further
            reading <ptr target="#stanley2012b"/>. </p>
         <p>Our research practice takes our prosopography in a different direction than these editions
            of correspondence, in that we aim to fill out a template for historical people in the
            letters whether Craik mentions them by name or by reference. In the following section,
            we offer three case studies of the research methods used to uncover information about
            the lives of nineteenth-century women. We demonstrate how we disambiguated two of
            Craik’s servants, referred to as <q>Mary</q> and <q>Little Mary</q> in the letters, uncovered a
            woman referred to only as Henry Blackett’s sister, and connected a woman author referred
            to as Miss Blyth to her pseudonym, May Beverley. We enter into this level of detail with
            the dual goal of providing an example of how we have combined scholarly and
            para-scholarly information resources to gather the most detail possible for every
            <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry, and the feminist aim of making the labor of the student research
            assistants who gathered this data visible.</p></div>
         <div>
            <head>Encoding Nineteenth-Century Women: Harriet Blackett, Mary Popham Blyth, Mary
               Bonnar, and Mary Chandler</head>
            <p>Prosopography has an important role to play in our assessment of women’s careers,
               since the networks of writers, artists, editors and publishers that supported a
               career like Craik’s did not have the same public visibility as those of her male
               contemporaries. While many early digital humanities projects cast a wide net,
               considering the texts and lives of hundreds of women writers, focusing on one
               individual woman writers’ connections has the potential to reveal a detailed,
               historically situated network of literary sociability. As Elisa Beshero-Bondar and
               Elizabeth Raisanen argue, while many digital humanities projects tend to consider
               women writers collectively, doing so may elide the historical specificity and
               idiosyncrasies of particular women writers; we can seek to redress this problem in
               part by launching projects devoted to single women writers, like Mary Russell
               Mitford, the subject of Beshero-Bondar and Raisanen’s work <ptr target="#besherobondar2017" loc="741"/>. As we will
               show, these egocentric networks have the potential to uncover detailed, situated, and
               inclusive historical networks in addition to building a prosopographical database
               that <quote rend="inline">alters one’s attention to individuals, blurring historical or textual
                  specificity</quote> <ptr target="#booth2015" loc="103"/>. Although Craik remains the thread that connects all
               the people in our prosopography, the very work of building a prosopographical TEI
               file distributes our attention across communities.</p>
            <p>The initial TEI structure for our prosopography, a separate file with a
               <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> template for every person named or mentioned in Craik’s letters, was
               modelled after <title rend="italic">Digital Mitford</title>, which takes on a similar level of
               granularity in prosopographical encoding <ptr target="#besherobondar2013"/>. Each
               <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry is assigned an <code>@xml:id</code> (we use <q>LastnameFirstname</q>) then, we
               endeavour to also include a full <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> (<code>&lt;surname&gt;</code> and
               <code>&lt;forename&gt;</code>), assigned <code>@sex</code>, date of <code>&lt;birth&gt;</code>, and date of <code>&lt;death&gt;</code>, as well as
               a short biographical <code>&lt;note&gt;</code>. Our project includes further sections for the
               census categories <code>&lt;occupation&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;nationality&gt;</code>. As an example, see the
               <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry for Craik’s close friend, Minna Lovell (see Figure 1). At the
               time of writing, our personography contains 989 person entries focusing on historical
               people mentioned in the letters, with further entries for pets and fictional people.
               Digitized civil records such as historical census and probates have become essential
               to our practice of inclusive digital prosopography; we have also found that the
               genealogical databases through which we access these records can afford new areas of
               inquiry into our project’s dataset. </p>
            
            <figure>
               <head> Minna Lovell’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the <q>Historical People</q> <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>
                  of the <q>Craik Site Index</q></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure1.png"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of xml interface</figDesc>
            </figure>
           
            <p>Our adoption of a strict set of prosopographical tags has led us to diversify our
               data and develop more inclusive approaches to information seeking. Every time that a
               name is mentioned in a transcribed letter, we tag it with a <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> and use
               a <code>@ref</code> attribute to point the element to <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry with an <code>@xml:id</code> in our
               prosopography. We do the same with a <code>&lt;rs&gt;</code> or <q>referencing string</q> when people
               who are mentioned but not named (e.g. <q>his wife</q>). Then, no matter how minor the
               reference, we try to complete each element in our template. In order to research
               people like Craik’s fellow lodger, whose forename may have been either May or Marian
               and whose surname may have been either James or Anderson, we turn to genealogical
               sources such as <title rend="quotes">FamilySearch.com</title> and <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, which digitize census data, birth
               and death certificates, marriage certificates, and probates, among other records.
               These primary sources can help us to provide the full names, life ranges,
               nationalities, occupations, and often the residences for many of the unknown people
               from Craik’s letters. Usually, knowing the few facts provided in a census report such
               as full name, occupation, and nationality, helps us to reformulate our previous
               searches. Having more robust search terms helps us to find more information about
               otherwise unknown lives in newspaper databases such as the <title rend="italic">British Newspaper Archive</title>
               and in optical character recognition (OCR) generated transcripts of nineteenth-century <title rend="italic">Google Books</title>.</p>
            <p>The structure of our TEI prosopography protocols discourages and even disallows our
               instinctive value judgments about who counts in a collective biography. For example,
               Craik’s two servants, whom she calls <q>Mary</q> and <q>Little Mary</q> exemplify the
               working-class women’s lives that, as Virginia Woolf notes, were excluded from the
               original <title rend="quotes">DNB</title>, yet both merit <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entries in our project’s prosopography.
               Because we knew relatively little about the two Marys, and because Craik omits both
               women’s surnames in her letters, we used the names that Craik used to refer to them
               as their @xml:id values. Then, we turned to genealogical databases seeking
               information that would help us to populate the elements in our TEI tagset. Internal
               evidence from Craik’s letters assured us that we could disambiguate between the two
               Marys by tracing the residents of Craik’s household through mid-century census
               records. Craik writes about both servants in a letter to her brother in 1860, in
               which she details a <q>domestic revolution</q> in her home:</p>
            <p><quote rend="block">On Wednesday night or rather Thursday morng [morning] came the grand domestic crash –
               found out unfortunate Mary in drinking – stealing – lying. – I had taken the baby, –
               &amp; nearly clothed her &amp; it too – these 4 months – got her nursed thro’ her bad
               illness – &amp;c. &amp;c. – All no good – she is thoroughly depraved. Your instinct
               was right &amp; my pity wrong. – I got her out of the house as soon as I could. &amp;
               little Mary came up at an hour’s notice. A great blessing. <ptr target="#craik1860a"/></quote></p>
            <p>In the census of 1861 — one year after this dramatic story of alcoholism and unwed
               pregnancy — the Craik household at Wildwood in Hampstead lists two servants: Mary
               Chandler, age 23, and Mary Bonnar, age 13 <ptr target="#census1861b"/>. We verified our assumption
               that the younger Mary was <q>Little Mary</q> by looking into Craik’s servants beyond the
               year 1861. Mary Bonnar stayed with Craik for the next decade and is listed as a
               servant at Dinah and George Craik’s residence, the Corner House, in 1871 <ptr target="#census1871"/>.
               We filled in the rest of Mary Chandler’s and Mary Bonnar’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code>
               entries using the records available to us through genealogical databases. Craik was
               known in her career for writing about the relationships between gentlewomen and their
               female servants, in her novel, <title rend="italic">Mistress and Maid</title> <ptr target="#craik1863"/> and essays <title rend="italic">A Woman’s
               Thoughts about Women</title> <ptr target="#craik1858"/>. Her letters, and accompanying prosopography, give
               us a glimpse into the sometimes dramatic lives of the servants with whom Craik was on
               such intimate terms.</p>
            <p> Our practice of encoding unnamed people in Craik’s letters with a referencing
               string, a <code>@type</code> attribute with the value <q>person,</q> and a <code>@ref</code> attribute propels our
               research team to seek out all the obscure, singular mentions of people that one might
               choose to leave out of a codex edition or even another digital edition. Moreover, our
               use of this tag has revealed new information needs, as it populates our prosopography
               with marginal figures and has catalyzed our move toward para-scholarly information
               resources. Overall, we have found that the <code>&lt;rs&gt;</code> tag prompts us to politicise
               our prosopographical research as we create space in our prosopography for the
               frequently unnamed wives, daughters, and sisters whose private labor supported
               public-oriented men. For example, in the letter cited above, Craik writes that Thomas
               Hughes — author of <title rend="italic">Tom Brown’s School Days</title> (1857) — and his wife would be joining her
               for early tea <ptr target="#craik1860a"/>. At the mention of <q>his wife,</q> we created an <code>@xml:id</code> with
               a placeholder value <q>MrsHughes.</q> Recently digitized birth certificates, death
               certificates, and census material helped us to create a full prosopographical entry
               for Anne Frances Hughes, including an updated <code>xml:id</code>, and one which occupies equal
               space to the account of her husband’s life.</p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Anne Frances Hughes’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the <q>Historical People</q>
                  <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> of the <q>Craik Site Index</q></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/921-Other-6729-1-4-20190415.png"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of xml interface</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
           
            <p>Our workflow for the <code>&lt;rs&gt;</code> tag often leads to complex prosopographical research
               requiring a greater diversity of genealogical and other information resources. In
               October 1860, Craik wrote to her brother Benjamin Mulock that her friend and
               publisher Henry Blackett was in the midst of familial troubles.</p>
            <p><quote rend="block">Mr. Blackett was here last night – &amp; told me his woes. His sister has fallen into
               <q>a low way</q> – &amp; he fears he must put her in an Asylum – but means to take her to
               live with him first, &amp; try what he can do. – He has terrible health himself, poor
               man – He is a worthy sort. I wouldn't leave him. <ptr target="#craik1860d"/></quote></p>
            <p>When encoding this passage, we used a <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> tag on the name Henry Blackett
               and pointed it toward a <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the Craik Site Index with the <code>@xml:id</code>
               value, <q>BlackettHenry.</q> We encoded the words <q>His sister</q> with a <code>&lt;rs&gt;</code>
               referencing string and a <code>@type</code> attribute with the value <q>person.</q> This tag pointed
               toward a draft <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry with the <code>@xml:id</code> value <q>MissBlackett.</q>
               Information about the lives of historical men, even those who made a major impact on
               the publishing industry, can also sometimes be scarce. Henry Blackett — one of the
               founding members of the London-based publishing firm Hurst and Blackett — does not
               have an entry in the <title rend="italic">ODNB</title>, but his status as one of the most well-established
               publishers in the era enabled us to piece together his biographical details from a
               combination of census records, writers’ biographies, and monographs on Victorian
                  publishing.<note> Blackett’s professional endeavors are documented in sources
                  including as John Sutherland’s <title rend="italic">Victorian Novelists and Their
                     Publishers </title> <ptr target="#sutherland1976"/> and <title rend="italic">The Longman Companion
                        to Victorian Fiction </title> <ptr target="#sutherland1988"/> and he often appears in biographies
                  of writers who worked with Hurst and Blackett. We pieced together his biographical
                  details from print and digital books on platforms such as <title rend="italic">Google
                     Books</title>, <title rend="italic">HaithiTrust</title>, and the <title rend="italic"
                     ><title rend="italic">Internet Archive</title></title>.</note>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <head>Henry Blackett’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the <q>Historical People</q>
                  <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> of the <q>Craik Site Index</q></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/921-Other-6730-1-4-20190415.png"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of xml interface</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            <p>Figure 3: Henry Blackett’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the <q>Historical People</q>
               <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> of the <q>Craik Site Index</q></p>
            <p>Scholarly sources offer scarce details about Henry Blackett’s family and personal
               life; as such, our research into his sister’s life depended upon the robust research
               affordances of para-scholarly information retrieval services. To begin filling out
               the <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry for his sister, we located Henry Blackett’s early census
               records on <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>. In this case, we used information from the Craik Site Index,
               but we find that low-barrier digital sources such as <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title> often provide enough
               information to begin an effective search on genealogical platforms. Using Henry
               Blackett’s birth and death dates and his place of birth, we searched British census
               records, focusing on the first two decades of his life, when he might have lived
               with his parents and siblings. The census for 1851 shows a 25-year-old Henry Blackett
               living at 16 Bedford Row, Islington, Middlesex with his widowed mother Martha, his
               three younger sisters, two visitors (his future wife and mother-in-law), and two
               servants. This step narrowed our search to one among three Blackett sisters: Martha
               (b. 23 August 1822), Harriet (b. 2 March 1829), or Catherine (b. 30 June 1831)
               (Census 1851). It also helped build a basic TEI template and stub entries for the
               Blacketts, which could help us to verify that all of our future searches pertained to
               the same Blackett family. Next, we searched for Henry Blackett’s household data
               around the time that Craik was writing about his sister’s declining mental health. In
               April 1861, less than six months after Craik composed her letter, Henry Blackett
               lived at Westside, Ealing, Middlesex with his wife Ellen, his five children, and his
               sister, Harriet <ptr target="#census1861a"/>. In this census report, Harriet was not listed as a
               visitor, but as a resident of Henry Blackett’s household. </p>
            <p>The governmental records aggregated by genealogical databases provided us with
               adequate information to build a prosopographical record for Harriet Blackett, an
               otherwise obscure figure in British literary history. However, we were ultimately
               unable to provide a precise date of death of Harriet Blackett. In March 1864, she
               married a man named Joseph James and adopted the much more common name <q>Harriet
               James.</q> Without a middle name on record, we have been unable to discern between the
               many Harriet Jameses in the Church of England Burial Records and the Civil
               Registration Death Indexes. Harriet James’s name does not appear in any digitized
               probates. A search into recently digitized Victorian asylum records did not yield
               results at the time of writing, but may in the future as more of these records are
               digitized as part of the <q>Lunacy Patient Admission Registers</q> on <title rend="italic">Ancestry</title> and other
               platforms. To accommodate this gap in our research, we included the attribute
               <code>@notBefore="1881-04-03"</code> to indicate that Harriet (Blackett) James was still alive at
               the time of the 1881 census.</p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot of Harriet Blackett’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the <q>Historical
                  People</q> <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> of the <q>Craik Site Index</q></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/921-Other-6731-1-4-20190415.png"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of xml interface</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            <p> Our prosopographical template affords a flexible way of encoding the multiple name
               changes that marked some nineteenth century women’s lives. A final example
               illustrates the complexities that enter prosopographical research when an author uses
               a variety of names — including a maiden name, married name, and pen name — throughout
               her lifetime. In four letters that Craik wrote to the publisher Alexander Macmillan
               in 1860, she makes passing reference to a young writer named Miss Blyth, who was
               attempting to publish one of her novels with Macmillan and Company. These four
               letters, housed in the Berg collection at the New York Public Library, were all
               composed when Craik was working as a publisher’s reader for Macmillan and Company. As
               such, Craik’s letters to Macmillan detail her opinions on the promise and
               publishability of the work under review. Craik’s opinion of the young writer was
               generally favourable. She writes:</p>
            <p><quote rend="block">There’s a wonderful deal in this Miss Blyth. – I don’t like strongly to advise for
               this tale – and yet I should be sorry for you to miss it. – I wonder if when done she
               will submit to a solid hard criticism &amp; condensation It might be made a very very
               nice book – if gone over again. I am sure. – <ptr target="#craik1860c"/></quote></p>
            <p>After revision, Craik declares the novel <q>satisfactory</q> and concludes that <quote rend="inline">the
               strong clear hand with which she has corrected and re-ended it – shows me more than
               ever how good a writer she will become. – </quote> <ptr target="#craik1860e"/>.</p>
            <p>Creating a prosopographical entry for Miss Blyth proved challenging: with nothing but
               a common British surname to begin our research, we had to amalgamate data from a mix
               of scholarly and para-scholarly information resources before we could initiate a
               query in genealogical databases. Because Craik mentions Miss Blyth with proper names
               throughout the Berg letters, we encoded all instances with the <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> tag
               and created an <code>@xml:id</code> for <q>MissBlyth</q> in our Craik Site Index. We added a <code>@ref</code>
               attribute to the original <code>&lt;persName&gt;</code> tags and pointed them to the <code>@xml:id</code>.
               Open-source digitization projects such as <title rend="italic">Google Books</title> and the <title rend="italic">Internet Archive</title> were
               essential for initiating a prosopographical record for Miss Blyth. Instead of working
               with the sparse biographical information and common surname that we had on hand, we
               started a search profile by uncovering the manuscript she was working on with
               Macmillan and Company in 1860. Craik’s letters reveal that Miss Blyth’s manuscript
               was entitled <title rend="italic">Aunt Jessie</title> <ptr target="#craik1860c"/> and included characters named Herbert, Mabel,
               Millicent, and Jackson <ptr target="#craik1860b"/>. Two characters named <q>M &amp; J</q> were engaged
               in courtship <ptr target="#craik1860b"/>. Craik’s reflections on Miss Blyth and her manuscript gave
               us further insight into the subject matter. On <title rend="italic">Aunt Jessie</title>, Craik writes that <quote rend="inline">the
               Crimea life is as fresh &amp; natural-like as if she had seen it – she must have got
               it from nature, secondhand: as I got from Ben – </quote> <ptr target="#craik1860c"/>. Furthermore, Craik’s
               first response to <title rend="italic">Aunt Jessie</title> was <quote rend="inline">it garred me greet</quote> <ptr target="#craik1860c"/> — a Scottish
               colloquialism which roughly means <quote rend="inline">compelled me greatly</quote> <ptr target="#gar" loc="vol 2"/>. The latter of
               these two details puzzled us: Macmillan was Scottish, and Craik might have been
               dipping into colloquialisms as a form of amicability, but, it was also possible that
               either the writer or the content of <title rend="italic">Aunt Jessie</title> was Scottish. With these details in
               mind, we began our search for titles similar to <title rend="italic">Aunt Jessie</title> that were published in
               the latter portion of 1860 — hoping, of course, that Macmillan heeded Craik’s advice
               to publish the tale.</p>
            <p> To create a prosopographical entry for an unknown writer like Miss Blyth, we had to
               adopt an inclusive and iterative research process, combining fragments from public
               and academic information resources including <title rend="italic">Google Books</title>, the <title rend="italic">Internet Archive</title>,
               newspaper, scholarly, and eventually, genealogical databases. Just as we expected,
               searches in <title rend="italic">The Orlando Project</title> and elsewhere retrieved many writers named Blyth,
               including Estelle Blyth, Myrna Blyth, E. H. Blyth, and Sophie Veitch, <q>a Scotswoman</q>
               and sensation novelist <quote rend="inline">who lived the early part of her life abroad,</quote> wrote travel
               books in the 1860s, and sometimes used the pseudonym <q>J. A. St John Blythe</q> <ptr target="#brown2006a"/>.
               Eventually, we found a novel on <title rend="italic">Google Books</title> called <title rend="italic">The Moor Cottage</title>,
               published by Macmillan and Company in 1861 <ptr target="#beverley1861"/>. By conducting free text
               searches in this novel, we found a main character named Aunt Jessie with secondary
               characters named Herbert, Mabel, Millicent, and Jackson. We verified that this novel
               featured the Crimean War, and found that the plot included a romance that confirmed
               Craik’s comments praising the <quote rend="inline">lovemaking between Millicent &amp; Jackson</quote> <ptr target="#craik1860c"/>.
               <title rend="italic">The Moor Cottage</title> was authored by a writer named May Beverley; yet, our
               prosopography entry in progress indicated that this person might have shared an
               identity with Miss Blyth. While researching May Beverley, we found that she published
               books for young readers between 1859 and 1871, including <title rend="italic">Little Estella and Other
               Fairy Tales</title> with Macmillan in 1859. We had trouble connecting this author with the
               name Blyth until we found an 1874 advertisement for May Beverley’s <title rend="italic">The City of the
               Plain, and other Tales</title> edited by Reverend E. H. Blyth, Hammersmith <ptr target="#hayes1874"/>.</p>
            <p>As our example of Miss Blyth demonstrates, an openness toward combining diverse
               scholarly and para-scholarly information resources can afford more inclusive
               representations of marginalized figures in prosopographical research. After learning
               the name of May Beverley’s one-time editor Reverend E. H. Blyth, we learned that
               Blyth had a sister who shared his literary inclinations. Mary Popham Blyth is listed
               in the personography of Troy J. Bassett’s <title rend="italic">At the Circulating Library: A Database of
               Victorian Fiction 1837–1901</title> <ptr target="#basset2018a"/>. She was born in Beverley, Yorkshire
               <ptr target="#basset2018b"/>. May Beverley, then, was a pseudonym that combined a diminutive of
               Mary Blyth’s forename with her place of birth. As we researched her career, we
               learned that Mary Popham Blyth wrote under both her given name, her initials M. P.
               B., and her pseudonym from the years 1859 to 1871. She was also an amateur artist
               whose works appeared in the India Office Library <ptr target="#archer1969" loc="133"/>. After connecting
               the pseudonym to the author mentioned in the letter, we were able to fill in the tags
               required by our TEI prosopography. The profile on Troy J. Bassett’s <title rend="italic">At the
               Circulating Library</title> catalyzed our <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry for the <code>xml:id</code> Miss Blyth, but
               we verified the information with sources such as <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, <title rend="italic">Familysearch.com</title>,
               <title rend="italic">Google Books</title>, and the <title rend="italic">Internet Archive</title>. Census records helped us correct her birth
               year from 1831 to 1841, while also adding key information such as <code>&lt;occupation&gt;</code>
               and <code>&lt;nationality&gt;</code>. Our <code>&lt;note&gt;</code> was populated with information from Craik’s
               letters and includes biographical information that centres around her relationship to
               Craik. </p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Screenshot of Mary Popham Blyth’s <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry in the <q>Historical
                  People</q> <code>&lt;div&gt;</code> of the <q>Craik Site Index</q></head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/921-Other-6732-1-4-20190415.png"/>
               <figDesc>screenshot of xml interface</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
            
            <p>Our research does not always yield such certainty over the identity of a person, and
               we find that it is important to be able to encode for levels of certainty in
               identifying prosopographical subjects. Publishing was
               often a family business in the nineteenth century, and in the case of Craik’s first
               publishers, Chapman and Hall, we are not always certain whether letters addressed to
               <q>Mr. Chapman</q> were meant to reach Edward Chapman, founder of the firm, or his cousin,
               Frederic Chapman, who took on major responsibilities at the firm following Hall’s
               death in 1847 <ptr target="#patten2004"/>. In these cases, we make use of the TEI’s certainty
               attribute (<code>@cert</code>) with a <q>low,</q> <q>medium</q> or <q>high</q> attribute value to qualify the
               degrees of certainty in interpretative encoding. For example, in a letter that Craik
               wrote between the 6th and 7th of December 1855, she recounts the contents of her
               recent mail to her brother, Ben. Craik writes that she received <quote rend="inline">a box of good things
               from an Aunt of the Pmalderites a nice old lady who promised me shortbread &amp; I
               don’t know what &amp; sent a box-full</quote> <ptr target="#craik1855"/>. Based on what we already know
               about Craik’s social networks, we inferred that <q>the Pmalderites</q> was a reference to
               the family of Craik’s friend Allan Park Paton — a Scottish writer and editor whom
               Craik often visited at his dwelling, Pmalder Cottage, in Greenock. However, the
               letter did not produce adequate leads to follow up on our suspicions. Like most
               genealogical research, our prosopographical research can be an endless back-and-forth
               process of consulting multiple digital platforms and analogue materials, and
               unfortunately, it does not always yield successful results. </p>
            <p>Our difficulties in identifying historic people are further compounded by working
               with unclear handwritten manuscript materials. Proper names can be challenging to
               work with; place and person names are among the most difficult words for a
               twenty-first century researcher to read accurately. Whereas the original recipient of
               the letter was embedded in the same social network as the letter writer, the
               twenty-first century reader must rely on a knowledge of the sender’s handwriting and
               its peculiarities as well as a general sense of common surnames in nineteenth-century
               England to make an educated guess as to what the proper name might be. There has been
               research into proper names using prosopography; omnastics has, for example, identified
               common slave names in ancient Rome <ptr target="#verboven2007" loc="37–38"/>. Our research problem
               again begins with developing the prosopography in the first place rather than
               analyzing a completed dataset, and with paleography rather than omnastics. Put
               simply, how should a researcher develop a <code>&lt;person&gt;</code> entry for a name they cannot
               read? Again, a wide search encompassing a range of sources can help. While it was not
               at first apparent to us whether a person who appeared to be Craik’s neighbor was
               named <q>Miss Wilkinson</q> or <q>Miss Wilkensen</q> or something else altogether; genealogical
               records reveal that a Sarah Wilkinson was a neighbor of Craik’s, and newspaper
               articles surrounding Craik’s adoption of a daughter and neighbor Miss Wilkinson’s
               involvement confirm the reading. As the example of Miss Wilkinson shows, addresses, a
               key component of correspondence, can clarify a person’s identity when all else fails. </p>
            <p>Recognizing the importance of mobility and propinquity in Craik’s career led us to
               change our initial template and adopt a <code>&lt;residence&gt;</code> tag in our TEI
               prosopography. The <code>&lt;residence&gt;</code> tag is useful in terms of clarifying both
               identity and temporal location: it can clarify both the identity of those referred to
               in a letter and the date of the letter. Because nineteenth-century census information
               was collected door-to-door, address information for historical subjects is also
               available in genealogical databases. In combination with datable w3c attributes <code>@from</code>
               and <code>@to</code> or <code>@notBefore</code> and <code>@notAfter</code>, we have begun to use the <code>&lt;residence&gt;</code> tag
               to track the addresses of Craik’s closest friends, colleagues, and collaborators.
               Developing a list of Craik’s residences and the timeframe that she lived there as
               part of her prosopographical entry helps us to narrow down dates for letters with no
               dateline; frequently, her letters will include an address so that the recipient would
               know where to write back, but a partial dateline that is missing the year or is
               absent altogether, since the recipient would have presumably known what year it was.
               We have also included residences for Craik’s close friends and associates, since it
               is not uncommon for her to write a letter from a friend’s residence, or to refer
               within a letter to a friend by residence or street name. When a letter is addressed
               from 1 Doune Terrace, we can infer that Craik was visiting the publisher Robert
               Chambers in Edinburgh when it was written. Sometimes, as in the case of the reference
               to the Pmalderites, Craik will refer to a family by their residence. For example, on
               Christmas Eve in 1886, Craik records in her diary <quote rend="inline">Went to Eden Cottage to see the
               family collection of babies — a very sweet sight — to the delight of grandparents —
               parents — uncles &amp; aunts.</quote> The residence tag in our prosopography allows us to
               quickly determine that the Miers family, close friends and neighbors of Craik’s with
               connections to Brazil, lived at Eden Cottage. The addition of the <code>&lt;residence&gt;</code>
               tag, which disambiguates dates and people, is thus especially useful for new members
               of the project as it creates an accessible internal reference. It has also provided
               the basis for further research into geolocating Victorian residences in order to
               explore the role of propinquity — frequent, unplanned interaction due to physical
               proximity — in women writers’s careers. </p>
            <p>Not all proper names have proven tractable to these research methods. Although the
               structure of our TEI prosopography drives us to completion, there are cases when we
               cannot complete an entry, and the TEI is flexible enough to allow for these
               instances. In some cases, entries remain incomplete because of our workflow: it may
               be practical to research an obscure person at a later date and instead focus on
               completing a transcription of a long letter. A lack of information may also prevent
               completion. Sometimes, searching a genealogical database with nothing but the fact
               that someone with the surname <q>Linos</q> helped Craik to organize a small glee club
               around the year 1862 is not enough to work with. In such cases, we create and use stub entries,
               which may be as simple as whichever part of a name is mentioned in a letter (first
               names in case of servants or intimate friends, last names in case of middle-class
               friends, acquaintances and professional connections), plus an <code>@xml:id</code> and gender
               attribute. If more information arises, these stub entries can be fleshed out at a
               later date. Nevertheless, the number of lives we have been able to uncover by using
               all sources available to us, regardless of their perceived scholarly value, has been
               illuminating. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion: Communities of Practice</head>
            <p>Current digital research methods are shifting the boundaries around whose labor,
               methods, expertise, and tools can be included in definitions of scholarship. In our
               work on <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, we embrace this shift as we develop an inclusive and
               situated practice of digital prosopography designed to aid the users of our digital
               edition in their engagements with Craik’s encoded correspondence. Combining the
               scholarly editorial practices set out by the TEI with genealogical databases and
               other para-scholarly resources has led us to a research methodology that takes full
               advantage of the digital resources that are available to us at this historical
               moment. Inclusivity is at the helm of our research practice; it drives our methods
               for populating the TEI prosopography with marginalized lives from Craik’s
               correspondence, and it propels us toward diverse research methods for completing our
               TEI tagsets. Our research team uses and acknowledges our debt to a range of scholarly
               and para-scholarly information resources for prosopography, many of which have been
               designed for researchers who work outside of the institutional structures of the
               university, and in the <q>shadow fields</q> of the academy <ptr target="#hayles2012" loc="36"/>. Genealogical
               databases such as <title rend="italic">Ancestry</title> and <title rend="italic">FamilySearch</title> and mass digitization projects like
               <title rend="italic">Google Books</title>, the <title rend="italic">Internet Archive</title>, and the <title rend="italic">British Newspaper Archive</title> have long
               served the information needs of public researchers, both hobbyists and professionals.
               Originally, these para-scholarly resources fulfilled our project’s needs where
               traditional scholarly databases have fallen short, and they have gradually become
               paramount to the success of our prosopographical method. In short, where in the past
               many of these lives would have been glossed over in edited letters, the combination
               of the TEI and genealogical resources allows us to pause and expand our understanding
               of Craik’s networks to include women like Harriet Blackett, Mary Popham Blyth, Mary
               Bonnar, and Mary Chandler. It is our hope that our prosopography, which traces the
               lives of everyone mentioned in one author’s correspondence, serves to shed some light
               on lives that often go unremarked.</p>
            <p> To conclude, we would also like to suggest that a more inclusive research process
               has the potential to build a wider community of practice. Our work on the <title rend="italic">Digital
               Dinah Craik</title> prosopography has led our project team to open our research communities
               as well as our research practices. Our approach, method, and practice of digital
               prosopography developed from sustained interactions among project members with a
               variety of community research experiences. Our project is situated in a traditional
               academic setting, with work taking place in the university library before the
               COVID-19 pandemic. It began as a collaboration among academic researchers (one
               professor with a small team of graduate and undergraduate students), and it has been
               shaped by lessons learned among genealogy collectives at the local public library.
               Over time, academic librarians, including Christie Hurrell and Ingrid Reiche, public
               library staff, especially Janice Parker, and local genealogists, including Alyson
               Bennett, have contributed to <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, often importing techniques and
               sources from their own communities of practice. Our use of genealogical databases in
               particular draws on the expertise of those with a background working in the public
               library system. We would suggest that one larger outcome of utilizing a diverse range
               of scholarly and para-scholarly sources is the ability to build a more diverse
               community of practice that incorporates knowledge and expertise from outside of the
               academy.</p></div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgments</head>
            <p>Thank you to the anonymous peer reviewers and the editorial board of <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> for their
               helpful feedback. We would like to acknowledge and thank the past and present members
               of the <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title> project: Hannah Anderson, Keila Aleman, Alyson Bennett,
               Will Best, Sidney Cunningham, Jaclyn Carter, Aaron Ellsworth, Kerry-Leigh Fox,
               Kylee-Anne Hingston, Christie Hurrell, Sonia Jarmula, Kelsey Jacobi, Sarah Kent,
               Elizabeth Ludlow, Janice Parker, Zainub Rahman, Ingrid Reiche, Pippa Ruddy, Lecia
               Givogue Stevenson, Lindsey Stewart, and Kiana Wong. </p>
           
            
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
           
            <bibl xml:id="ancestry" label="Ancestry 1997–2022"> Ancestry, 1997–2022, <ref target="www.Ancestry.com/">www.Ancestry.com/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="archer1969" label="Archer 1969"> Archer, M. <title rend="italic">British Drawings in the India Office Library: Amateur
               Artists.</title> Her Majesty’s Stationery Office, London (1969).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baignet2005" label="Baignet et al. 2005"> Baigent, E., Brewer C., and Larminie. V. <title rend="quotes">Women and the Archive:
               The Representation of Gender in the Dictionary of National Biography and the Oxford
               English Dictionary.</title><title rend="italic"> Archives: The Journal of the British Records Association</title>, 30
               (2005): 13–35.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="basset2018a" label="Basset 2018a"> Basset, T. <title rend="italic">At the Circulating Library: A Database of Victorian
               Fiction, 1837–1901.</title> Victorian Research Web, last updated 7 January 2022,
               <ref target="www.victorianresearch.org/atcl/">www.victorianresearch.org/atcl/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="basset2018b" label="Basset 2018b"> Basset, T. <title rend="quotes">At the Circulating Library Author Information: Mary Popham
               Blyth.</title> <title rend="italic">At the Circulating Library: A Database of Victorian Fiction, 1837–1901</title>.
               Victorian Research Web, last updated 7 January 2022,
               <ref target="www.victorianresearch.org/atcl/show_author.php?aid=2129">www.victorianresearch.org/atcl/show_author.php?aid=2129</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="besherobondar2013" label="Beshero-Bondar 2013–2022"> Beshero-Bondar, E., ed. <title rend="italic">Digital Mitford: The Mary Russell
               Mitford Archive</title>. University of Pittsburgh at Greensburg, 2013-2019, last modified 4 April
               2021, <ref target="digitalmitford.org/">digitalmitford.org/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="besherobondar2017" label="Beshero-Bondar and Raisanen 2017"> Beshero-Bondar, E. and Raisanen, E. 2017.
               <title rend="quotes">Recovering from Collective Memory Loss: the Digital Mitford's Feminist Project.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Women's History Review</title>, 5. 26 (2017): 738-50.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="beverley1861" label="Beverley 1861"> Beverley, M. <title rend="italic">The Moor Cottage: A Tale of Home Life</title>. Macmillan &amp;
               Co., London (1861).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="blaney2017" label="Blaney and Siefring 2017"> Blaney, J. and Siefring, J. <title rend="quotes">A Culture of non-citation:
               Assessing the Digital Impact of British History Online and the Early English Books
               Online Text Creation Partnership.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11. 1 (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="booth2004" label="Booth 2004"> Booth, A. <title rend="italic">How To Make it as a Woman: Collective Biographical History
               from Victoria to the Present</title>. University of Chicago Press, Chicago (2004).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="booth2005" label="Booth 2005"> Booth, A. <title rend="quotes">Fighting for Lives in the ODNB: or, Taking Prosopography
               Personally.</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Victorian Culture</title>, 10. 2 (2005): 267–79.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="booth2015" label="Booth 2015"> Booth, A. <title rend="quotes">Frances Trollope in a Victorian Network of Women’s
               Biographies.</title> In V. Alfano and A. Stauffer (eds), <title rend="italic">Virtual Victorians: Networks,
                  Connections, Technologies</title>. Palgrave Macmillan (2015), 83–106.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="booth2013" label="Booth 2013–2017"> Booth, A., ed. <title rend="italic">Collective Biographies of Women</title>. Scholars’ Lab,
               University of Virginia, 2013–2017, cbw.iath.virginia.edu/.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bourrier2019" label="Bourrier 2019"> Bourrier, K. <title rend="italic">Victorian Bestseller: The Life of Dinah Craik.</title> University of Michigan Press, Ann Arbor (2019).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bourrier2015" label="Bourrier 2015–2022"> Bourrier, K, ed. <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>. TEI Archive Publishing and Access Service (TAPAS). https://tapasproject.org/node/443. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bradley2005" label="Bradley and Short 2005">Bradley, J. and Short, Harold. <title rend="italic">Text into Databases: The Evolving Field of New-style Prosopography.</title> <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title>, 20, Issue Suppl., (2005): pp. 3–24. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqi022">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqi022</ref>.</bibl> 
            <bibl xml:id="bradley2015" label="Bradley and Short 2015">Bradley, J. and Paisen, Michele. <title rend="quotes">Factoid-based Prosopography and Computer Ontologies: An Integrated Approach.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</title>, 30.1 (2015): pp. 86–97. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt037">https://doi.org/10.1093/llc/fqt037</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="britishnewspaper" label="British Newspaper Archive"> British Newspaper Archive. Findmypast Newspaper Archive Limited, 2011-2019,
               <ref target="www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk/">www.britishnewspaperarchive.co.uk</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brown2006a" label="Brown et al 2006–2022a"> Brown, S., Clements, P., and Grundy, I., eds. <title rend="italic">Orlando:
               Women’s Writing in the British Isles from the Beginnings to the Present.</title> Cambridge
               University Press Online, 2006-2019, orlando.cambridge.org. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brown2006b" label="Brown et al 2006–2022b"> Brown, S., Clements, P., and Grundy, I., eds. <title rend="italic">Sophie Veitch
               entry: Writing screen within Orlando: Women's Writing in the British Isles from the
               Beginnings to the Present.</title> Cambridge University Press Online, 2006-2019,
               orlando.cambridge.org. Accessed 7 March 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brown2018" label="Brown 2018"> Brown, S., <title rend="quotes">Delivery Service: Gender and the Political Unconscious of
               Digital Humanities.</title> In Losh, E. and Wernimont, J., (eds), <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information:
               Intersectional Feminism and Digital Humanities</title>, Minnesota University Press
               (2018).</bibl>
           <bibl xml:id="brown2013" label="Brown and Simpson 2013"> Brown, S. and Simpson, J. <title rend="quotes">The Curious Identity of Michael Field and its Implications for Humanities Research with the Semantic Web.</title> <title rend="quotes">IEEE International Conference on Big Data</title> (6-9 October 2013). https://doi.org/10.1109/BigData.2013.6691674. </bibl>
             <bibl xml:id="brown2019" label="Brown et al. 2019"> Brown, S., Cummings, J., Drudge-Wilson, J., Lemak, A., Martin, K., Mo, A., and Stacey, D. <title rend="quotes">Linked Literary History, or An Ontology of One’s Own: The Canadian Writing Research Collaboratory Ontology.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Conference [DH2019]</title> (9-12 July 2019). https://doi.org/10.34894/IQH1PI.</bibl> 
            <bibl xml:id="cannadine2019" label="Cannadine 2019"> Cannadine, D., ed. <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>. Oxford
               University Press Online, 2019, www.oxforddnb.com.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="census1851" label="Census 1851"> Census Returns of England and Wales, 1851. The National Archives of the
               UK (TNA); Public Records Office (PRO), 1851; class: HO107; piece: 1499; folio: 120;
               p. 27, GSU roll: 87832. <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="census1861a" label="Census 1861a"> Census Returns of England and Wales, 1861. The National Archives of
               the UK (TNA); Public Records Office (PRO), 1861; class: RG 9; piece: 93; folio: 140;
               p. 19; GSU roll: 542572. <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="census1861b" label="Census 1861b"> Census Returns of England and Wales, 1861. The National Archives of
               the UK (TNA); Public Records Office (PRO), 1861; Class: RG 9; piece: 778; folio: 56;
               p. 17; GSU roll: 542699. <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="census1871" label="Census 1871"> Census Returns of England and Wales, 1871. The National Archives of the
               UK (TNA); Public Records Office (PRO), 1871; class: RG10; piece: 872; folio: 149; p.
               39; GSU roll: 827770. <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, 2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="churchofengland" label="Church of England Marriages and Banns"> Church of England Marriages and Banns, 1754-1932. Church of England Parish Records,
               London Metropolitan Archives; London, England; Reference Number: p80/ste/013.
               <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1855" label="Craik 1855"> Craik, D. <title rend="quotes">[Letter from Dinah Craik to Benjamin Mulock, 5–6 December].</title> Mulock Family Papers, Box 1, Folder 7, University of California at Los Angeles</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1886" label="Craik 1886"> Craik, D. <title rend="quotes">Diary, December 24, 1886,</title> Craik Collection, Harry Ransom Center,
               University of Texas at Austin.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1858" label="Craik 1858"> Craik, D. <title rend="italic">A Woman’s Thoughts About Women.</title> Hurst and Blackett,
               1858.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1860a" label="Craik 1860a"> Craik, D. <title rend="quotes">Letter from Dinah Craik to Ben Mulock, 17 March to 7
               April 1860.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, ed. K. Bourrier,
               tapasproject.org/node/2669.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1860b" label="Craik 1860b"> Craik, D. <title rend="quotes">Letter from Dinah Mulock Craik to Alexander Macmillan,
               May 1860.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, ed. K. Bourrier,
               <ref target="tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-alexander-macmillan-may-1860">tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-alexander-macmillan-may-1860</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1860c" label="Craik 1860c"> Craik, D. <title rend="quotes">Letter from Dinah Mulock Craik to Alexander Macmillan,
               between April and June 1860.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, ed. K. Bourrier,
               <ref target="https://tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-alexander-macmillan-between-april-and-june-1860">https://tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-alexander-macmillan-between-april-and-june-1860</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1860d" label="Craik 1860d"> Craik, D. <title rend="quotes">Letter from Dinah Mulock Craik to Ben Mulock, 14–23
               October 1860.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, ed. K. Bourrier,
               <ref target="tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-ben-mulock-14%E2%80%9323-october-1860">tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-ben-mulock-14%E2%80%9323-october-1860</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1860e" label="Craik 1860e"> Craik, D.<title rend="quotes">Letter from Dinah Mulock Craik to Alexander Macmillan, 6
               November 1860.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Dinah Craik</title>, ed. K. Bourrier,
               <ref target="tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-alexander-macmillan-6-november-1860">tapasproject.org/digitaldinahcraik/files/letter-dinah-mulock-craik-alexander-macmillan-6-november-1860</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="craik1863" label="Craik 1863"> Craik, D. <title rend="italic">Mistress and Maid.</title> Hurst and Blackett, 1863.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crompton2016" label="Schwartz and Crompton 2016"> Schwartz, M., &amp; Crompton, C. <title rend="quotes">Lesbian and Gay
               Liberation in Canada: Representing the Dyke Dynamo.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/le Champ
                  Numérique</title>, 5. 3 (2016). <ref target="http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.27">http://doi.org/10.16995/dscn.27</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="desenclos2016" label="Desenclos 2016"> Desenclos, C. <title rend="quotes">Early Modern Correspondence: A New Challenge for
               Digital Editions.</title> In Driscoll M. J. and Pierazzo, E., (eds) <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarly
               Editing: Theories and Practices</title>, Open Book Publishers (2016), 183–201.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dignazio2020" label="D’Ignazio and Klein 2020"> D’Ignazio, C. and Klein, L. <title rend="italic">Data Feminism</title>, The MIT Press, Cambridge
               (2020). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="evans2011" label="Evans 2011"> Evans, T. <title rend="quotes">Secrets and Lies: The Radical Potential of Family History.</title>
               <title rend="italic">History Workshop Journal</title>, 71 (Spring 2011): 49–73.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flanders1988" label="Flanders et al 1988–2022"> Flanders, J., Bauman, S., Clark, A., and Connell, S., (eds).
               <title rend="italic">Women Writers Project</title>. Northeastern University, 1988-2022,
               <ref target="www.wwp.northeastern.edu/">www.wwp.northeastern.edu/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flanders1998" label="Flanders et al 1998"> Flanders, J., Bauman, S. Canon, P, and Courane, M. <title rend="quotes">Names
               Proper and Improper: Applying the TEI to the Classification of Proper Nouns.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Computers and the Humanities</title>. 31 (1998): 285-300.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gar" label="Gar"> <title rend="quotes">Gar v. 2 ,</title><title rend="italic">Scottish National Dictionary (1700–), Dictionary of the Scots Language,</title>
               <ref target="www.dsl.ac.uk/entry/snd/gar_v2">www.dsl.ac.uk/entry/snd/gar_v2</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="garnett1894" label="Garnett 1894"> Garnett, R. <title rend="quotes">Mulock, Dinah Maria, afterwards Mrs. Craik (1826–1887).</title>
               <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>. Oxford University Press (2004). Date of
               access 10 Nov. 2021,
               <ref target="https://www-oxforddnb-com.ezproxy.lib.ucalgary.ca/view/10.1093/odnb/9780192683120.001.0001/odnb-9780192683120-e-19519">https://www-oxforddnb-com.ezproxy.lib.ucalgary.ca/view/10.1093/odnb/9780192683120.001.0001/odnb-9780192683120-e-19519</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016"> Gallon, Kim. <title rend="quotes">Making the Case for the Black Digital Humanities.</title> In
               Klein, L. and Gold, M. K., (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of
               Michigan Press (2016), 42-49, <ref target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2">dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayes1874" label="Hayes 1874"> <title rend="quotes">J. T. Hayes Advertisements.</title> In Heygate, W. E. <title rend="italic">The Eucharist: on its
               Types and Other Like Subjects</title>. J. T. Hayes (1874), 45,
               <ref target="books.google.ca/books?id=ce8CAAAAQAAJ&amp;dq">books.google.ca/books?id=ce8CAAAAQAAJ&amp;dq</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hayles2012" label="Hayles 2012"> Hayles, N. K. <title rend="italic">How We Think: Digital Media and Contemporary
               Technogenesis</title>. University of Chicago Press, 2012.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hedley2017" label="Hedley 2017"> Hedley, A. <title rend="quotes">From TEI to Linked Open Data: Crossing the Stile.</title> <title rend="italic">The
               Yellow Nineties Online</title>, eds. Denisoff D. and Janzen Kooistra, L., Ryerson University,
               2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hedley2018" label="Hedley and Kooistra 2018"> Hedley, A. and Janzen Kooistra, L. <title rend="quotes">Prototyping
               Personography in The <title rend="italic">Yellow Nineties Online</title>: Queering and Querying History in the
               Digital Age.</title> In Wernimont, J. and Losh, E., (eds), <title rend="italic">Bodies of Information:
               Intersectional Feminism and Digital Humanities</title>, Minnesota University Press
               (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jansen1994" label="Jansen et al 1994–2009"> Jansen, L., Luijten, H. and Bakker, N., eds. <title rend="italic">Vincent Van
               Gogh: The Letters</title>. Van Gogh Museum, 1994-2009, last updated 2009, <ref
                  target="http://vangoghletters.org/vg/">http://vangoghletters.org/vg/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018"> Johnson, J. M. <title rend="quotes">Markup Bodies: Black [Life] Studies and
               Slavery [Death] Studies at the Digital Crossroads.</title> <title rend="italic">Social Text</title> 1 December 2018; 36
               (4 (137)): 57–79. doi: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="keatsrohan2007" label="Keats-Rohan 2007"> Keats-Rohan, K. S. B. <title rend="quotes">Introduction. Chameleon or Chimera?
               Understanding Prosopography.</title> In Keats-Rohan, K. S. B. (ed), <title rend="italic">Prosopography Approaches
               and Applications: A Handbook, Prosopographica et Genealogica</title> (2007), 1–35. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="losh2016" label="Losh et al 2016"> Losh, E., Wernimont, J., Wexler, L., and Wu, H-A. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Putting
               the Human Back into the Digital Humanities: Feminism, Generosity, and Mess.</title> In
               Klein, L. and Gold, M. K., (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>, University of
               Michigan Press (2016), 92–103, <ref target="dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2">dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/debates/2</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="losh2018" label="Losh et al 2018"> Losh, E. and Wernimont, J., (eds), <title rend="quotes">Introduction.</title> <title rend="italic">Bodies of
               Information: Intersectional Feminism and Digital Humanities</title>, Minnesota University
               Press (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lunacypatients1846" label="Lunacy Patients Admission Registers, 1846-1912">Lunacy Patients Admission Registers, 1846-1912. The National Archives of the UK; Kew,
               Surrey, England; Class: MH 94, Piece: 23. <title rend="italic">Ancestry.com</title>, 2014.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell" label="Mitchell C. et al n. dat"> Mitchell, C., Jordan, E., and Schinske, H., eds. <title rend="italic">Letters
               of Charlotte Mary Yonge</title>. University College of London, accessed 14 April 2019,
               <ref target="c21ch.newcastle.edu.au/yonge/">c21ch.newcastle.edu.au/yonge/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell1983" label="Mitchell S. 1983"> Mitchell, S. <title rend="italic">Dinah Mulock Craik</title>. Twayne Publishing, 1983.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitchell2004" label="Mitchell 2004"> Mitchell, S. <title rend="quotes">Craik [née Mulock], Dinah Maria (1826–1887),
               writer.</title> <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</title>, September 23, 2004, Oxford
               University Press,
               <ref target="www.oxforddnb.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-19519">www.oxforddnb.com/view/10.1093/ref:odnb/9780198614128.001.0001/odnb-9780198614128-e-19519</ref>.
               Accessed 2 Apr. 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ancestryb" label="Ancestry 2013"> <title rend="quotes">Overview,</title> Ancestry.co.uk, Ancestry, 21 November 2013, <ref
               target="https://www.ancestry.co.uk/cs/legal/Overview"
               >https://www.ancestry.co.uk/cs/legal/Overview</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="patten2004" label="Patten 2004"> Patten, R. L. <title rend="quotes">Chapman, Frederic (1823–1895), publisher.</title> <title rend="italic">Oxford
               Dictionary of National Biography</title>. 23. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="showalter1975" label="Showalter 1975"> Showalter, E. <title rend="quotes">Dinah Mulock Craik and the Tactics of Sentiment: A
               Case Study in Victorian Female Authorship.</title> <title rend="italic">Feminist Studies</title> 2. 2.2 (1975):
               5–23.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stanley2007" label="Stanley et al 2007–2012"> Stanley, L., Dampier, H., and Shepherd, D., eds. <title rend="italic">Olive
               Schreiner Letters Online</title>. The Digital Humanities Institute, University of Sheffield,
               2008-2012, <ref target="http://www.oliveschreiner.org/"
                  >www.oliveschreiner.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stanley2012a" label="Stanley et al 2012a"> Stanley, L., Dampier, H., and Shepherd, D., eds. <title rend="quotes">Miss
               Battie,</title> <title rend="italic">Olive Schreiner Letters Online</title>, The Digital Humanities Institute, University
               of Sheffield, 2012, <ref
                  target="http://www.oliveschreiner.org/vre?view=personae&amp;entry=3"
                  >www.oliveschreiner.org/vre?view=personae&amp;entry=3</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stanley2012b" label="Stanley et al 2012b"> Stanley, L., Dampier, H., and Shepherd, D., eds. <title rend="quotes">Wilson
               Barrett,</title> <title rend="italic">Olive Schreiner Letters Online</title>. The Digital Humanities Institute,
               University of Sheffield, 2012, <ref
                  target="http://www.oliveschreiner.org/vre?view=personae&amp;entry=203"
                  >www.oliveschreiner.org/vre?view=personae&amp;entry=203</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sutherland1988" label="Sutherland 1988"> Sutherland, J. <title rend="italic">The Longman Companion to Victorian Fiction</title>. Pearson
               Longman, New York (1988).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sutherland1976" label="Sutherland 1976"> Sutherland, J. <title rend="italic">Victorian Novelists and Their Publishers</title>. Athlone
               Press, London (1976).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="takayanagi2018" label="Takayanagi 2018"> Takayanagi, M. <title rend="quotes">What’s New: August 2018.</title> <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of
               National Biography</title>, Oxford University Press Online, 2018,
               <ref target="www.oxforddnb.com/page/about">www.oxforddnb.com/page/about</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanremoortel2016" label="Van Remoortel 2016"> Van Remoortel, M. <title rend="quotes">Who Do You Think They Were? What Genealogical
               Databases Can Do for Victorian Deriodical Studies.</title> In King, A., Easley, A., and
               Morton, J., (eds), <title rend="italic">Researching the 19th c Periodical Press: Case Studies</title>, Routledge
               (2016), 131–44.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="verboven2007" label="Verboven et al 2007"> Verboven, K., Carlier, M., and Dumolyn, M. <title rend="quotes">A Short Manual to
               the Art of Prosopography.</title> In <title rend="italic">Prosopography Approaches and Applications: A Handbook</title>,
               Prosopographica et Genealogica (2007), 36-70.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wernimont2019" label="Wernimont 2019"> Wernimont, J. <title rend="italic">Numbered Lives: Life and Death in Quantum
               Media</title>. MIT Press, 2019.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wernimont2013" label="Wernimont 2013"> Wernimont, J. <title rend="quotes">Whence Feminism? Assessing Feminist Interventions in Digital Literary Archives.</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 7.1 (2013): <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/7/1/000156/000156.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="woolf1938" label="Woolf 1938"> Woolf, V. <title rend="italic">Three Guineas.</title> Harcourt Inc., New York (1938).</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
