<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Digital Collaborations: A Survey Analysis of
                    Digital Humanities Partnerships Between Librarians and Other Academics</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jessica Wagner
                        <dhq:family>Webster</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Baruch College, City University of New York</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>jessica.wagnerwebster@baruch.cuny.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jessica Wagner Webster is Digital Initiatives Librarian and Assistant
                            Professor at Baruch College, City University of New York. She holds an
                            MLS in archives and an MA in American History from the University of
                            Maryland. Her research focuses on material culture, trends in archival
                            practice, documentation of underdocumented populations, collection of
                            student life materials, and digital humanities work in an archival and
                            library context. Her work has been published in The American Archivist
                            and Archival Issues, and she has presented widely at archives, library,
                            and digital humanities conferences. Her practical responsibilities
                            include designing long-term archival preservation and access systems,
                            developing workflows for processing born-digital materials, and
                            selecting and digitizing print materials for access.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000441</idno>
                <idno type="volume">013</idno>
                <idno type="issue">4</idno>
                <date when="2019-12-14">14 December 2019</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2019-11-08" who="murelj">Created file and began encoding</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The present study will investigate the perceptions of information professionals
                    about their role in the work of digital humanities scholars, as well as the
                    perceptions of digital humanities scholars on the role of information
                    professionals in their research. While other scholarly literature has considered
                    collaborations between these groups via surveys or interviews with small project
                    teams, the present study will provide a large-scale analysis of collaborations
                    using survey responses from more than 500 scholars, librarians, and archivists.
                    Questions sought to determine the extent to which these groups collaborate with
                    one another on project teams; how these collaborations unfold and who initiates
                    them; whether IPs have begun to adjust and adapt their work to support specific
                    DH projects, or to make their content more appealing and easy for potential
                    future DH projects; and what administrative hurdles are faced during the
                    collaboration. The survey also address how information professionals and DH
                    scholars view the success of the collaboration after completing their work, and
                    whether they intend to collaborate in future. To conclude, the article will
                    consider what these responses tell us about how best to support all members of
                    these collaborations.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Examines perceptions of DH scholars' preceptions of information professionals, and vice-versa,
                and how to support both in collaborative research</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <p>As technological tools have developed over the last several decades, humanities
                scholars have explored the opportunities computing technology makes available for
                conducting and enhancing their research. Scholars have developed techniques such as
                using software to mine texts and creating data visualizations such as maps, charts,
                and graphics. Further, they have developed new software products to aid in their
                research. These techniques allow scholars to grapple new kinds of qualitative and
                quantitative research questions, as well as to work with data and text at scale.
                Similarly, archivists and librarians have developed an extensive literature and tool
                set to collect, accession, make accessible, and preserve a wide variety of digital
                content for their collections. Many of these skills and techniques overlap with
                those of DH practitioners; for example, digitizing a text document and performing
                optical character recognition to generate a searchable transcript could be a key
                step in both a DH scholar's research and an archivist's making a historic pamphlet
                accessible for researchers. Furthermore, texts and DH projects generated by the work
                of DH scholars might be worth accessioning and preserving as part of their
                collections; steps in the archival workflow might have to be adjusted to accommodate
                data sets, websites, applications, visualizations, and other products that result
                from DH scholars' work.</p>
            <p>The present study will investigate the perceptions of information professionals (IPs)
                about their role in the work of DH scholars, as well as the perceptions of DH
                scholars on the role of IPs in their research. While other scholarly literature has
                considered collaborations between these groups via surveys or interviews with small
                project teams (e.g., <ref target="#keener2015">Keener 2015</ref>, <ref
                    target="#poremski2017">Poremski 2017</ref>), the present study will provide a
                large-scale analysis of collaborations using survey responses from more than 500
                scholars, librarians, and archivists. The survey questions were based upon findings
                in a literature review focusing on DH labor, best practices, and case studies, and
                were designed to identify trends across both groups. I wanted to determine the
                extent to which these groups collaborate with one another on project teams.
                Questions sought to ascertain how these collaborations unfold and who initiates
                them; whether IPs have begun to adjust and adapt their work to support specific DH
                projects, or to make their content more appealing and easy for potential future DH
                projects; and what administrative hurdles are faced during the collaboration. After
                working together, how do IPs and DH scholars view the success of the collaboration,
                and do they intend to collaborate in future? What do these responses tell us about
                how best to support all members of these collaborations?</p>
            <div>
                <head>Literature Review</head>
                <p>Digital humanities collaborations between information professionals and subject
                    faculty/researchers/alt-academics have been written about extensively, primarily
                    by information professionals; indeed, I was unable to find any studies on these
                    collaborations authored by subject faculty. First, of course, collaborations
                    between information professionals and subject specialists have been common
                    occurrences since the advent of this kind of work. Further, sometimes a
                    researcher inhabits both roles: an information professional may also pursue
                    subject research and perform digital humanities work, and vice versa <ptr
                        target="#porter2014"/>. To place the present study into context, I will
                    focus on scholarship that focuses on the labor that goes into digital humanities
                    work, as well as scholarship that describes different types of collaborations in
                    the digital humanities.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Labor</head>
                    <p>Some scholars writing about library labor in the digital humanities have
                        focused on the question of whether information professionals should be seen
                        as acting in <q>service</q> to subject scholars, or whether they inhabit the
                        role of a professional peer.</p>
                    <p>Two prominent research organizations sought to frame the discussion around
                        ways librarians can support digital humanities scholars in their work, and
                        discussed difficulties encountered in developing and supporting these
                        collaborations. In 2011, the Association of Research Libraries released
                            <title rend="italic">SPEC Kit 326: Digital Humanities</title>, a report
                        based on a survey of membership about their experiences providing digital
                        humanities project support. Responses indicate that while most libraries
                        provide digital services, often this is done in an ad-hoc way, with chronic
                        understaffing and underfunding <ptr target="#bryson2011"/>. Similarly, for
                        their OCLC report <title rend="quotes">Does Every Research Library Need a
                            Digital Humanities Center?</title>, Jennifer Schaffner and Ricky Erway
                        consulted DH scholars and attended digital humanities conferences to
                        identify scholars’ research needs. Their final report provided library
                        administrators with recommendations for aiding digital humanities scholars
                        with their projects <ptr target="#schaffner2014"/>.</p>
                    <p>However, several scholars have provided critiques of this service approach,
                        focusing on power imbalances inherent in the academy between librarians and
                        scholars. Trevor Muñoz problematizes the idea that librarians should be seen
                        in a service role for scholars doing digital humanities research. He argues
                        that library administrators often defend library investment in DH projects
                        as a way to show the library’s value, justify its existence, and expand
                        funding for other essential library functions. However, he argues that
                            <quote rend="inline" source="#muñoz2016">digital humanities research
                            [is] core to the theory and practice of librarianship in its own
                            intellectual terms rather than as a useful lever in some temporary
                            tactical maneuver</quote> and should instead be a <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#muñoz2016">source of ideas</quote> for librarians on its own
                            <ptr target="#muñoz2016"/>. Dot Porter points out that librarians
                        themselves may be doing digital humanities work, and that setting up digital
                        humanities scholars in contrast to librarians may not be accurate or
                        fruitful <ptr target="#porter2014"/>. Bethany Nowviskie discusses the <quote
                            rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2013">strong service ethic</quote> that
                        remains a key part of library culture, but describes how it can place
                        librarian-practitioners and library resource allocation at a significant
                        disadvantage <ptr target="#nowviskie2013"/>. If a librarian’s goal is to
                        provide <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2013">self-effacing
                            service</quote> while <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2013">not
                            distracting the researcher for his or her work,</quote> this can
                        ultimately lead to a misleading <quote rend="inline" source="#nowviskie2013"
                            >smooth, professional veneer over increasingly decrepit and under-funded
                            infrastructure – effectively…hiding the messy innards of an organization
                            from one’s faculty,</quote> who might otherwise be <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#nowviskie2013">a library’s strongest allies</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nowviskie2013" loc="58"/>.</p>
                    <p>Miriam Posner agrees, outlining key ways library collaborations in the
                        digital humanities are undermined by the structure of academic libraries and
                        the frequent lack of resources and institutional support from library and
                        university administration. Posner argues that <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#posner2013">it can be very challenging for a librarian charged
                            with <q>supporting</q> a project to dissuade a faculty member from
                            barreling ahead with a half-baked idea,</quote> in part because of power
                        differentials built into academia between librarians and scholars <ptr
                            target="#posner2013" loc="46"/>. A recent study of librarians active in
                        DH by Molly Dahl Poremski shows that these issues continue to exist: <quote rend="inline" source="#poremski2017">The current landscape of
                            DH librarianship shows a profession that is not entirely prepared to
                            meet the needs of its users. [...] Given the nature of our profession,
                            we rise to meet this challenge with enthusiasm, even if our levels of
                            funding and support may not be as high as our hopes. DH librarians
                            appear to be making do with what they have available to them but require
                            additional aid, both institutionally and professionally</quote>
                        <ptr target="#poremski2017" loc="149"/>.</p>
                    <p>Another key line of criticism has focused on library work in the digital
                        humanities sphere as <term>emotional labor</term> or <term>feminized
                            labor</term>, in which the structures and hierarchies in place that mark
                        library work as service work disincline other scholars from seeing
                        librarians as peer collaborators <ptr target="#shirazi2014"/>. Building on
                        this, Logsdon, Mars, &amp; Tompkins explore ways that librarians, as
                        intermediaries between expert and novice researchers, and as people who have a
                        wide breadth of knowledge in research skills, tools, and disciplines, can be
                        a huge asset in DH collaborations. However, in spite of this occupation of
                        liminal space, and in fact because of it, librarians often must provide
                        emotional labor in the context of collaborating with digital humanities
                        researchers, by, for example, <quote rend="inline" source="#logsdon2017"
                            >appearing enthusiastic about projects that you suspect will be too
                            unwieldy to succeed given the time and human resources available and
                            knowing how to manage the proposer’s expectations without damaging their
                            enthusiasm for the digital project,</quote> or <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#logsdon2017">maintaining a professional demeanor even when your
                            expertise is marginalized in a given project</quote>
                        <ptr target="#logsdon2017" loc="164"/>.</p>
                    <p>Though these studies and analyses problematize the “service model” of
                        librarianship, they do not attempt to assess how digital humanities scholars
                        or information professionals interpret or navigate these power dynamics
                        within the context of their specific projects or institutions.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Best Practices, Case Studies, and Surveys</head>
                    <p>The bulk of literature around digital humanities collaborations focuses on
                        case studies and the development of best practice guidelines. For example,
                        scholars have described collaborations in pedagogy, instructing students on
                        the use of TEI <ptr target="#green2016"/>; in the development of scholarly
                        digital editions <ptr target="#clement2013"/>; or in managing a large-scale
                        digitization project <ptr target="#braunstein2015"/>. Many of these also
                        share best practices or lessons learned, while sharing any specific
                        roadblocks or difficulties noticed during the project <ptr
                            target="#lorang2015"/>
                        <ptr target="#vinopal2013"/>. <note>Several of these articles mention <quote
                                rend="inline">digital curation</quote> as a key role for information
                            professionals to play in these collaborations; Poole and Garwood
                            describe this role as being responsible for <quote rend="inline"
                                source="#poole2018">the active and ongoing management of data [...]
                                over its entire lifecycle to make it as highly-functional as
                                possible, especially for sharing and reuse.</quote>
                            <ptr target="#poole2018"/>.</note></p>
                    <p>Another prevalent theme in the literature pertains to the role of digital
                        humanities centers in fostering collaborations between librarians and
                        subject faculty. For example, Rosenblum and Dwyer outline their experiences
                        as a faculty member and librarian co-leading a digital humanities center at
                        the University of Kansas, and offer best practices for maximizing the
                        effectiveness of collaborating across disciplines in this way.
                        Interestingly, the university-wide task force that initially suggested a
                        dual-leadership model in this case had envisioned a very clear breakdown of
                        responsibilities: the leader drawn from humanities faculty would be
                        responsible for <quote rend="inline" source="#rosenblum2016">the scholarly
                            contribution of research projects and educational programs,</quote>
                        while the librarian would <quote rend="inline" source="#rosenblum2016">focus
                            on the digital realization of scholarship and the access, organization,
                            and preservation of sustainable digital research content working with
                            various campus partners</quote>
                        <ptr target="#rosenblum2016" loc="114"/>. As the authors assumed their
                        leadership roles, however, they did find that the division of labor was much
                        less clear and explicit as initially expected, and they collaborated on
                        many, if not all, tasks <ptr target="#rosenblum2016" loc="122"/>. This may
                        be an example, then, of a situation in which library and faculty
                        collaborators act more as peers.</p>
                    <p>Several researchers have conducted surveys or interviews with collaboration
                        partners to get a sense of the nature of collaborations and touch on key
                        issues that arose. Poole and Garwood interview participants in several
                        international-scale, grant-funded collaborative digital humanities projects.
                        They determin that while very few information professionals were explicitly
                        listed as members on project teams, in almost every case information
                        professionals performed essential functions on the project. They conclude,
                        among other things, that <quote rend="inline" source="#poole2018">librarians
                            [and] archivists' work remains largely invisible in these projects. It
                            must be made visible to exploit existing and to provide evidence for
                            additional resources</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#poole2018">infrastructure must be leveraged and policy
                            developed or clarified for optimal collaboration between librarians and
                            DH</quote>
                        <ptr target="#poole2018" loc="818"/>. </p>
                    <p>In a similar vein, Alix Keener interviewed pairs of subject faculty and
                        information professionals from several institutions from the Center for
                        Institutional Cooperation (CIC) collaborative. In this survey, faculty and
                        librarians were asked a series of questions to elicit their notion of the
                        role of librarians in digital humanities work. Key findings include the fact
                        that many faculty feel that support for digital humanities work is much more
                        mature and institutionalized in the library than in their home academic
                        departments; meanwhile, the librarians interviewed did not feel that digital
                        humanities were nearly as universally supported in their own library
                        departments. Keener speaks to the question of librarian-as-service-provider
                        versus librarian-as-peer, stating that librarians are perceived as peers and
                        colleagues by their faculty colleagues and report feeling like peers to
                        those colleagues themselves, though participants were generally aware of
                        tensions about the inclusion of librarians in DH work <ptr
                            target="#keener2015"/>. Interestingly, several respondents pointed out
                        that collaboration generally is viewed with skepticism in the humanities,
                        whether with librarians or other scholars; tensions felt may be less a
                        function of the fact that librarians are not subject faculty, but instead
                        the fact that collaborations are viewed with some disdain in the humanities
                        world, while they tend to be more supported generally within the digital
                        humanities community.</p>
                    <p>After consulting the literature, I determined that while collaborations
                        between digital humanities scholars and information professionals had been
                        studied within limited parameters (e.g., project teams at large institutions
                        with digital humanities infrastructure, as in Keener, or internationally, as
                        in Poole and Garwood), collaborations occurring within and across a wider
                        spectrum of institutions, particularly smaller institutions with limited
                        resources, required further study. In addition, the literature describing
                        perspectives on collaboration from digital humanities scholars is limited,
                        though some scholars have theorized about labor imbalances across the
                        academic institutions and about challenges stemming from administrative
                        support (e.g., <ref target="#posner2013">Posner 2013</ref> and <ref
                            target="#nowviskie2014">Nowviskie 2014</ref>). My research was informed
                        by my own positioning and background as a digital archivist in a small but
                        developing university digital library program. In my own career, I have
                        found that resources and institutional support often play a significant role
                        in the ability of librarians and archivists to initiate and participate in
                        digital humanities projects of any kind, and have primarily seen information
                        professionals function in an advisory or collaborative capacity when asked
                        to support projects initiated by research or subject faculty. My personal
                        experience, therefore, supports findings by Posner and Nowviskie as outlined
                        above, but I desired to test whether information professionals in a variety
                        of institutional settings had had similar experiences, and to determine what
                        circumstances breed successful collaborations. I therefore designed a
                        large-scale study to investigate how IPs and scholars perceive, develop, and
                        assess their DH collaborations and the degree to which the collaborations
                        are considered successful.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Survey Methodology</head>
                <p>To investigate digital humanities collaborations among a variety of
                    practitioners, a survey was developed with a total of 33 questions. The full
                    survey can be viewed in Appendix I. The survey contained some questions that
                    were presented to all respondents, as well as questions directed only to those
                    who identified as library/archives professionals or faculty/graduate
                    students/alt-academics in subject areas. Other respondents (such as
                    administrators and IT professionals) were presented with a subset of these
                    questions as well. The survey was distributed via online lists such as the
                    Society of American Archivists listserv, Code4Lib, the UVictoria's DHSI list,
                    and HASTAC, in order to achieve a wide array of participants in both the
                    library-affiliated and subject faculty worlds. The online survey methodology was
                    selected because of its ease of implementation and its ability to reach a very
                    wide cohort of practitioners <ptr target="#vehovar2017"/>. The survey was
                    available between August 24 and October 5, 2016, and 508 responses were
                    collected during that time. Of these, 242 surveys, or 47.64%, were completed in
                    full. As respondents were permitted to skip questions in the survey, I accepted
                    all submitted surveys, and analyzed each question based on the total number of
                    valid responses submitted for that question. I used Microsoft Excel to view and
                    analyze the data.</p>
                <p>Many of the survey questions were free-text; respondents could write in as much
                    or as little information as they wanted, rather than choose from a list of
                    responses. For these questions, I looked for recurring themes in the answers and
                    calculated how many respondents mentioned the most frequent themes in their
                    statements.</p>
                <p>During my analysis of the results, several errors were discovered in the
                    structure and internal logic of the survey. In some cases, respondents were
                    given the opportunity to answer questions for which they were not the intended
                    audience. For example, in one case, I intended to ask archives and library
                    professionals about their plans for long-term preservation of digital projects,
                    but the question was presented to all respondents. In these circumstances, I
                    separated out the answers provided by the intended audience and analyzed those;
                    if the answers provided by the erroneous recipients proved to be useful, I
                    analyzed them separately and reported it as such. Also, a number of respondents
                    (60) answered that they did not collaborate on the project they were describing;
                    I chose to remove those responses from my overall survey analysis, as the focus
                    of this project is on collaborative projects specifically.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Survey Results</head>
                <div>
                    <head>Participants</head>
                    <p>Of the 508 survey responses, nearly 48% identified themselves as an
                        archivist, librarian, or a graduate student in either of these areas. Nearly
                        34% identified themselves as a faculty member (20.35%) or graduate student
                        (13.31%) in a subject area outside of library or archives. Of the remaining
                        respondents, approximately 10% self-identified academic researchers,
                        administrators, or IT professionals. For the purposes of this article, I
                        will distinguish between two groups: information professionals (IPs), which
                        consist of librarians, archivists, and graduate students in those two
                        disciplines (48% of the total); and other digital humanities scholars (DHs),
                        which consist of subject faculty, students in subject disciplines,
                        alt-academic scholars, administrators, and others (52%).</p>
                    <p>Studying and comparing the responses of information professionals to those of
                        other types of digital humanities scholars does highlight, and perhaps
                        reify, a binary between those two groups. As the above literature review
                        demonstrates, information professionals conduct digital humanities research
                        alone and in collaboration with other scholars, and casting them as distinct
                        from other scholars poses the risk of painting them as less qualified
                        researchers, or erasing their work from discussions of digital humanities as
                        a field. However, as Posner argues and as the survey results will show,
                        information professionals face different workloads than other DH scholars
                        often do, especially those scholars for whom teaching and research is a
                        primary responsibility <ptr target="#posner2013"/>. Further, administrative
                        structures and funding requirements, as well as expectations of a <q>service
                            orientation</q>, work differently in library and archives departments
                        than in academic departments (or, indeed, in information technology
                        departments or digital humanities centers). Grouping and comparing responses
                        as I do below allows me to explore how these realities affect the experiences
                        of the collaborative partners.</p>
                    <p>I also inquired about the subject specialties of the faculty and graduate
                        students responding to the survey. 43.25% of respondents said that English,
                        literature, foreign language literature, writing, or affiliated disciplines
                        were their area of expertise. 17.85% indicated history, while an additional
                        3.78% specified Medieval history or studies. Remaining respondents mentioned
                        a variety of other disciplines, including anthropology, art and art history,
                        media studies, and, indeed, digital humanities. The majority of respondents
                        (77.24%) reported working in a college or university setting, with the next
                        largest group employed at museum or arts organizations (7.09%). 24.66% of
                        the graduate student respondents reported that they were enrolled in a
                        digital humanities track or major. In this survey, I did not ask respondents
                        whether their institution had a standalone Digital Humanities Center; this
                        would be an interesting avenue for further research.</p>
                    <p>The vast majority of respondents worked on at least one digital humanities
                        project: 18.45% had worked on one project, and 73.02% had worked on more
                        than one. I instructed respondents who had worked on multiple projects to
                        consider their most recent project when answering the survey questions.</p>
                    <p>One line of inquiry not included in this survey pertains to the employment
                        status of respondents: or whether they held a faculty, administrative or
                        staff role; if they were faculty, whether they were full-time or adjunct;
                        whether they were tenure-track or tenured; or if librarians or archivists,
                        whether they held faculty status or staff status. Further research on how
                        employment status affects collaborations, funding, and administrative
                        support could be very fruitful.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Nature of Digital Humanities Deliverables</head>
                    <p>I asked all respondents to describe the DH projects they had worked on,
                        asking them to mention deliverables and which members of the team
                        contributed to which aspects of the project. I chose not to provide a
                        definition for "digital humanities project" in order to allow respondents to
                        include anything that met with their own definition of the idea. Indeed, one
                        respondent wrote that they were not sure whether to include their project
                        because <quote rend="inline">[a]rguably, this isn't digital humanities, but
                            the phrase has been stretched so far that some people would include it
                            in their definition – [I]'m not sure what yours is.</quote></p>
                    <p>Many respondents described multiple projects in their response to this
                        free-text question, or included a number of digital humanities workflows or
                        outputs that dealt with a particular collection or theme. I collected 201
                        responses to this question. I analyzed the responses and flagged recurring
                        features that were listed, such as websites, digitization projects, and
                        application development; this analysis generated 546 features (for the
                        purposes of this article, I will refer to these features as <term>data
                            points</term>). For this particular question, I calculated percentages
                        based on the number of responses; because most responses mentioned projects
                        with several features, and some responses even mentioned multiple projects,
                        I wanted to show how many individual practitioners mentioned particular
                        features in their answers. The results of this question can be seen in <ref
                            target="#">Figure 1</ref>.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                        <figDesc>Participant descriptions of DH Projects</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p>For these respondents, then, a web component is key, either for delivering
                        the results of their analysis or as the deliverable itself. Approximately
                        60% of respondents mentioned a website, Omeka gallery, or web exhibit as an
                        outcome of their projects. Approximately 32% mentioned digitization of print
                        or analog materials. Approximately 28% mentioned programming, creation of
                        applications, use of Scalar, or other technical work. Approximately 25%
                        mentioned creation of a database, catalog, or searchable archive, and
                        approximately 24% of respondents mentioned metadata work. Interestingly,
                        some hallmarks of digital humanities projects, including maps, data
                        visualizations, and textual analysis, were mentioned by fewer than 15% of
                        respondents each.</p>
                    <p>Indeed, because the framing of the question focused primarily on
                        deliverables, few respondents went into depth discussing their research
                        methodology, subject selection, or critical approach. This is a blind spot
                        in the research design: perhaps because of my information-professional
                        approach, I focused on the research products rather than the lines of
                        scholarly inquiry advanced by these collaborations. In part, this serves to
                        hide the intellectual contributions of all respondents, particularly
                        information professionals, who may have fewer fora to showcase their
                        research output <ptr target="#posner2013"/>. Future research might inquire
                        and analyze the scholarly dialogue between collaborators in IP and DH
                        partnerships.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Initiating the project: Beginning the Collaboration</head>
                    <p>Next, I wanted to identify who initiated collaborative projects: did subject
                        specialists reach out to information professionals, or vice versa? How did
                        these collaborations begin? When I asked information professionals about
                        their collaborations with academic colleagues, 61.93% of the total responses
                        (197) mentioned collaboration with faculty or professional colleagues from
                        their own institution; 11.17% of responses mentioned that they worked with
                        graduate students from their own institution; 16.24% reported working with
                        faculty from other institutions; and 1.52% described working with graduate
                        students from another institution. 9.14% of respondents mentioned that they
                        worked on their project(s) alone.<note>I asked respondents throughout the
                            survey to answer questions based on their most recent collaboration or
                            project, but many respondents wrote about experiences with multiple
                            projects nonetheless. In those circumstances, I parsed the response and
                            tallied each part individually. For example, if a respondent wrote that
                            they worked with a subject faculty member on one project and with a
                            graduate student on another project, I logged one response for a faculty
                            collaboration and another response for a graduate student collaboration.
                            Totals and percentages reflect this approach throughout the
                            article.</note> Again, these respondents were removed from the remainder
                        of the survey at this juncture.</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 1. IP Collaborations</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Information professionals collaborated with…</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Percentage of Respondents</cell>
                            <cell role="label">n=</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Faculty/ Professional colleagues, same
                                institution</cell>
                            <cell role="data">66.03%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">103</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Faculty/ Professional colleagues from another
                                institution</cell>
                            <cell role="data">12.82%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">20</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Students from my institution</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10.90%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">17</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Alone</cell>
                            <cell role="data">9.62%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">15</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Students from another institution</cell>
                            <cell role="data">0.64%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">1</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Total</cell>
                            <cell role="data">100.00%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">156</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>When I asked academic colleagues about their work on projects with library
                        and archives professionals, their responses were as follows. Out of 231
                        respondents, 37.23% said they worked with both archivists and librarians.
                        20.35% reported that they worked with librarians; 11.26% reported that they
                        worked with archivists; and 7.36% said they worked with information
                        professionals but were not sure whether they were librarians or archivists.
                        23.81% reported that they worked on their projects alone. Of course, as this
                        survey was clearly described as being designed to study collaborative
                        projects, it is no surprise that those who took the survey had collaboration
                        experience. (Again, at this juncture of the survey I removed any additional
                        respondents who reported working alone on their projects.)</p>
                    <table>
                        <head>Table 2. DH Collaboations</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">DH Scholars collaborated with…</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Percentage of respondents</cell>
                            <cell role="label">n=</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Colleagues in both areas</cell>
                            <cell role="data">37.23%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">86</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Librarians</cell>
                            <cell role="data">20.35%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">47</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Alone</cell>
                            <cell role="data">23.81%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">55</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Archivists</cell>
                            <cell role="data">11.26%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">26</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Yes, but not sure which</cell>
                            <cell role="data">7.36%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">17</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Total</cell>
                            <cell role="data">100.01%</cell>
                            <cell role="data">231</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>Next, I asked the DH scholars and the information professionals whether they
                        initiated the project themselves, or were invited to join by a colleague.
                        The standout finding here is that almost 78% of the time, faculty
                        respondents said that the project was their idea, and they reached out to
                        their information professional colleagues to join them. For the archivists
                        and librarians who responded, over 50% of the responses indicated
                        that faculty colleagues initiated the project (51.56% of responses for
                        archivists and 53.70% for librarians). For the archivists and librarians,
                        responses ranged between 19 and 25% for initiating the project on their own
                        or for coming up with the project in tandem with their colleague. This
                        finding shows that for these respondents, academic researchers are
                        frequently initiating collaborations with information professionals for some
                        portion of their project. </p>
                    <p>This response is underscored by the next set of questions, displayed <ref
                            target="#table03">in Table 3</ref>. I asked anyone who responded that
                        the project had been initiated by a colleague how they came to be involved.
                        First, approximately 72% of the respondents to this question were
                        information professionals, which confirms the findings in the previous
                        question. I broke the responses down: for information
                        professionals, approximately 27% were simply asked to join by colleagues;
                        approximately 18% had a skill necessary to complete the project;
                        approximately 18% have jobs that explicitly include DH projects in their
                        scope; approximately 9% were part of a staff or team that were assigned the
                        project; approximately 9% applied to a job opening that included work on
                        that project; and approximately 7% invited themselves onto the
                        team/volunteered to participate. 13% had another response.</p>
                    <table xml:id="table03">
                        <head>Table 3. Ways Collaborators Joined Projects They Did Not
                            Initiate</head>
                        <row role="label">
                            <cell role="label">Method</cell>
                            <cell role="label">Information Professionals (n=44)</cell>
                            <cell role="label">DH Scholars (n=17)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Part of staff/team that was assigned specific
                                project</cell>
                            <cell role="data">8.9% (n=4)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">15.8% (n=3)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Had Necessary Skills/In a role that is required to be
                                looped in</cell>
                            <cell role="data">17.8% (n=8)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">21.1% (n=4)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Other</cell>
                            <cell role="data">13.3% (n=6)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10.5% (n=2)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Invited Myself</cell>
                            <cell role="data">6.7% (n=3)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">21.1% (n=4)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Was Asked</cell>
                            <cell role="data">26.7% (n=12)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">15.8% (n=3)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Applied for Job Opening/Internship</cell>
                            <cell role="data">8.9% (n=4)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">10.5% (n=2)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data">Job Explicitly Includes DH</cell>
                            <cell role="data">17.8% (n=8)</cell>
                            <cell role="data">5.3% (n-=1)</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row role="data">
                            <cell role="data"/>
                            <cell role="data"/>
                            <cell role="data"/>
                        </row>
                    </table>
                    <p>In contrast, when I broke down the responses for academic and professional
                        colleagues, the responses were as follows: approximately 16% were simply
                        asked to join by colleagues; approximately 21% had a skill necessary to
                        complete the project; approximately 5% have jobs that explicitly include DH
                        projects in their scope; approximately 16% were part of a staff or team that
                        were assigned the project; approximately 11% applied to a job opening that
                        included work on that project; and approximately 21% invited themselves onto
                        the team/volunteered to participate. 11% had another response.</p>
                    <p>Information professionals are still much more likely to be asked to join a
                        project than subject faculty and other academic colleagues. Academic
                        colleagues were much more likely to invite themselves to join a project of
                        interest to them. Both IPs and scholars were roughly equally likely to be
                        asked to join because of a skill they possessed. IPs were much more likely
                        to have a job that explicitly includes DH work, but academic colleagues were
                        much more likely to be part of a team assigned to a DH project. These
                        responses demonstrate that scholarly researchers outside of the library have
                        more opportunities and flexibility to take on DH projects if they are
                        interested in doing so. Information professionals may be more likely to be
                        constrained by their role, or limited by time and resources, as we will see
                        later in this study; this may prevent them from being the primary motivator
                        in establishing DH projects. However, another factor to consider is
                        cultural; the longstanding perception of librarians and archivists as
                        service-providers may be entrenched enough that scholars are more likely to
                        draw on IP’s expertise than the other way around. Further research could
                        examine constraints on when information professionals initiate projects.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Successes and failures</head>
                    <p>Both DH scholars and information professionals were asked to reflect upon
                        their interactions with colleagues, and asked to suggest what could be done
                        to improve similar (or future) collaborations. 57.89% of the DH scholars
                        responded that the collaboration was successful, with another 31.58%
                        responding that they had mixed results. Only 3 responses (2.63%) were a
                        clear <q>no</q> (the remainder were coded as N/A, other, or that the project
                        was still ongoing). Those scholars who felt they had a mixed experience most
                        commonly mentioned that they wished the library/archives staff had more time
                        or resources to share. Several also mentioned that they would have liked
                        more clarity about project planning and timelines; more training so they
                        could do more of the work on their own; or more of a mutual understanding
                        around key project terms like <term>metadata</term>,
                            <term>preservation</term>, and <term>sustainability</term>.</p>
                    <p>The information professionals’ assessment was a bit more complex. 82
                        information professionals answered this question. Of these, 28.05% said it
                        was a successful collaboration; 8.7% said it was not; 58.54% said it was a
                        mix; and 3.66% said N/A or other. I then broke the <q>mixed</q> responses
                        into categories, to further analyze their explanations; these responses were
                        parsed into 68 data points. 16.18% of the data points mentioned issues
                        around communication, responsiveness, and expectation-setting with their
                        faculty counterparts. 10.29% mentioned that the project would be more
                        successful with increased funding. 8.82% mentioned issues around leadership,
                        coordination, and decisionmaking; 8.82% mentioned the lack of familiarity on
                        the part of faculty with IT or librarianship/archival work and what would be
                        possible to accomplish; and another 8.82% mentioned the need for improved
                        institutional support (aside from funding). For example, one librarian
                        wrote, <quote rend="inline">Collaboration with my immediate colleagues
                            was/is successful, but the way our projects fit into the overall library
                            structure is still very tricky. [Our digital project has an] unfunded
                            mandate and this model is not sustainable, in terms of staff time
                            required. So, it's not that collaboration could be better but the
                            infrastructure around the collaboration needs to be better.</quote>
                        Another librarian wrote, <quote rend="inline">Collaboration with faculty was
                            good. Getting buy in from library admin is harder.</quote></p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure02">
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                        <figDesc>Participant responses to survey question</figDesc>
                    </figure>
                    <p>From these responses, information professionals seem to be frequently turned
                        to for support and labor, and they would like to be able to do these digital
                        humanities projects. However, they may not have the time, resources, or
                        support to do so. Further, many respondents mentioned that faculty
                        colleagues had different expectations than they did around what was possible
                        via their collaboration: how much time it would take, how responsive each
                        party would need to be, and what kind of IT or library work was feasible and
                        what was not. Further research could highlight the hurdles, especially
                        administratively, that prevent information professionals from working on
                        digital humanities projects.</p>
                    <p>Interestingly, 5.88% also mentioned that they felt some snobbery or
                        dismissiveness on the part of faculty against their information professional
                        counterparts. One archivist said, <quote rend="inline">It was hard for
                            academic colleagues to acknowledge the fact that I am myself also
                            faculty and also have research interests to pursue…. They didn't
                            understand why I was driving the project, and thought it needed to come
                            out of a pet question or topic under study by a <q>serious</q> scholar.
                            I was studying user response to data visualizations. And I got an
                            awesome digital humanities project out of it.</quote> It is important to
                        note, however, how few responses mentioned this kind of tension.</p>
                    <p>I also asked several questions pertaining to issues around resource
                        allocation, which provide a preliminary snapshot into the funding associated
                        with these respondents’ DH projects. First, all respondents were asked, in a
                        free-text question, <quote rend="inline">How was the project funded?</quote>
                        Each respondent could list as many responses as they desired; phrases were
                        coded and collected to yield 272 data points. Of these, 36.76% of responses
                        mentioned receiving no additional funding at all to complete the project;
                        the project was funded only out of regular salary or department funds. A
                        similar percentage, 37.78%, of responses included a mention of funding by
                        external or governmental grants (respondents who identified as DHers were
                        more likely to mention that they had external funding: 41.28% of DHers
                        mentioned external or governmental grants in their responses, whereas only
                        32% of IPs did). Additional funding for these projects came in the form of
                        internal (departmental or institutional) grants. Responses across these
                        categories were consistent between DH and IP respondents, aside from the
                        difference in those reporting external grant funding.</p>
                    <p>Next, I asked all respondents, <quote rend="inline">What extra resources (eg
                            staff, time, equipment), if any, did completion of the project
                            require?</quote> This, too, was a free-text question, and answers were
                        parsed and coded. Out of a total of 356 responses, the most frequent
                        responses were staff time (specifically existing staff time reallocated from
                        other projects and responsibilities) at 35.92%; acquisition of equipment or
                        software at 24.14%; and additional staff, volunteer or students hired, at
                        18.10%. Response rates for each of these categories were similar between DH
                        and IP respondents.</p>
                    <p>Lastly, due to my interest in institutional support for information
                        professionals participating in DH work, I asked only the IP respondents to
                            <quote rend="inline">Please describe any support, interest, or
                            roadblocks you faced from supervisors while taking on this
                            project.</quote> Out of 76 respondents, 57.89% reported that they
                        received support from their supervisor. Respondents were also permitted to
                        add a free-text explanation to this answer; the most popular issues they
                        reported supervisors mentioning were concerns around the time it would take
                        to complete the project (15.79%); IT support (9.21%); issues around funding
                        (9.21%); and issues around copyright (3.95%).</p>
                    <p>These results provide some preliminary context for the key issues
                        collaborative partners face in their work in DH. Many projects were
                        supported by external grant funding. A lot of the projects were completed
                        using existing staff and staff time, rather than via an injection of
                        additional resources or staff. Many projects were not awarded any additional
                        funding at all. A slim majority of information professionals reported
                        support from supervisors, but supervisors mentioned concerns about the
                        investment of time and resources required to participate in these DH
                        projects. As a practicing information professional, these results suggest to
                        me that while there is a lot of interest in this work among scholars,
                        information professionals, and supervisors, resources may be limited to
                        complete it, and for information professionals in particular, projects of
                        this type that may be added to more established workloads represent a
                        resource crunch rather than an inducement to build capacity. Further
                        research is necessary to understand the varied experiences of library
                        scholars and other researchers, as well as the responses and support
                        provided by their administrative and institutional contexts.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The role of IPs, according to DHers</head>
                    <p>Next, I wanted to explore the ways digital humanities scholars outside the
                        library perceived the role of information professionals in contributing to
                        their shared projects, and how that might have changed as a result of
                        working with an information professional. I targeted a series of questions
                        to the digital humanities scholars about their perceptions.</p>
                    <p>First, I asked, <quote rend="inline">Has your understanding of the work of
                            your archives/library colleagues changed in any way? Please
                            explain.</quote> There are 69 free text answers to this question. Most
                        people responded that they learned something new (60.87%), and the majority
                        of these new things can be characterized as positive. Examples include:
                            <quote rend="inline">I have more respect for their skills and
                            knowledge</quote>; <quote rend="inline">I have a better understanding of
                            the different roles of librarians/archivists</quote>; and <quote
                            rend="inline">I have more ideas about collaborating with them in the
                            future.</quote> Nearly 57% of the answers in the <term>lessons
                            learned</term> category pertain to the subject researchres learning more
                        about what goes into library work. For example, one respondent wrote: <quote
                            rend="inline">I wasn't aware before of the <q>mismatches</q> between
                            archival metadata (like EAD) versus the kinds of metadata other academic
                            researchers need for searching and retrieval.</quote> However, not all
                        the lessons learned were positive: some people (nearly 16%) learned lessons
                        they described in negative terms, such as that information professionals
                            <quote rend="inline">don't have good technical skills</quote> or that
                        they were not aware of how understaffed the libraries were. In addition,
                        some responded that they were already well aware of what information
                        professionals do from having worked with them extensively in the past. </p>
                    <p>Next, I asked DH scholars to explain whether they felt it was the role of
                        archivists and librarians to prepare analog materials for use in digital
                        humanities projects, such as by digitizing text or adding geodata to maps.
                        Many archivists and archival repositories are seeking ways to make their
                        collections more visible and usable by seeking to participate in such
                        digital projects; I was curious to see whether DH scholars expected this
                        work from IPs. The answers to this question were, again, a mix. 37.35% of
                        respondents said yes; 10.84% said no; and 38.12% said they were unsure, or
                        that it wasn’t necessarily in the purview of archivists and librarians.</p>
                    <p>Some respondents added comments or explanations to their response; I parsed
                        these into 136 data points for analysis. 8.82% of the responses mentioned
                        that this work should be done as a collaboration between information
                        professionals and scholars; and 4.41% mentioned that IPs, on their own,
                        would not know what should be digitized or prepared for DH projects, and
                        should rely on scholar-driven research to develop their projects. This kind
                        of answer points to some interesting contrasts in training and expectations
                        among IPs and DH scholars. Many information professionals are experienced
                        with selecting materials to highlight, and many are subject specialists
                        themselves. Further, library and archival training can help teach IPs to
                        identify materials that would be of interest to scholars. In fact, within
                        the last fifteen years, the archival community has focused resources on
                        processing and showcasing <q>hidden collections,</q> those materials that
                        might not have been yet made visible to users due to resource or time
                        constraints. From the perspective of IP training, digitizing collections and
                        making them accessible can be a way to draw the attention of scholars and
                        develop new projects around their holdings. However, resource constraints
                        often limit IPs’ ability to do this kind of work.</p>
                    <p>DH scholars, on the other hand, might have an area of particular interest to
                        their own scholarship. Their work is project-based and tied to specific
                        corpora that would support their own research. As one respondent put it, IPs
                        shouldn’t preemptively digitize materials because <quote rend="inline">often
                            they don't know what might be of interest to scholars.</quote> As
                        another put it, <quote rend="inline">I don't know how [to] help librarians
                            know which materials to prioritize, and it would be a shame to invest an
                            enormous effort into digitizing, collecting, or correlating data that
                            then never gets used.</quote> However, it
                        is an expected part of an information professional’s purview to perform
                        research and investigate what content is most suitable for digitization, if
                        resources permit.</p>
                    <p>Next, I asked scholars whether they felt that it was the role of information
                        professionals to <quote rend="inline">preserve and make accessible in the
                            long term digital humanities projects created by scholars like
                            yourself?</quote> I had 80 responses to this question; 61.25% said yes,
                        this is within the purview of IPs, 7.5% said no, and 31.25% said not sure or
                        not necessarily. A number of these respondents provided more detail in their
                        explanation; I parsed these into 28 data points, and the most popular
                        answers were as follows. 21.43% of the answers mentioned that IPs should
                        continue providing access to digital humanities projects like they have
                        always done with other resources, like books. 21.43% mentioned that
                        information professionals doing this sort of preservation work preserves the
                        relationship between a scholar, their work, and their institution; and
                        14.29% mentioned the idea that libraries have the resources or
                        infrastructure necessary to do this sort of preservation. 14.29% argued that
                        information professionals and digital humanities scholars should be having
                        conversations and what sorts of work should be preserved and why. Overall,
                        most scholars reported support for the notion that information professionals
                        should be involved in this work.</p>
                    <p>To conclude this section, I asked DH scholars, <quote rend="inline">How can
                            archivists or librarians help your work in future digital humanities
                            projects?</quote> Responses varied widely. I parsed the responses into
                        109 data points, and they break down as follows. Most respondents (24%)
                        requested help with technical and library skills. 13.76% mentioned an
                        interest in initiating or improving more collaborations. A number of
                        respondents asked IPs to <quote rend="inline">share,</quote>
                        <quote rend="inline">collaborate,</quote>
                        <quote rend="inline">connect,</quote> and <quote rend="inline"
                            >contribute</quote> (12.84%) to overall projects. 4.59% of the answers
                        highlighted help with metadata specifically. 4.59% mentioned that time and
                        funding hurdles can prevent DHers from capitalizing effectively on IPs'
                        expertise. Other noteworthy themes: some DH scholars noted that IPs are key
                        for providing access and acting as gatekeepers to particular materials
                        (2.75%), with another 5.5% asking IPs not to be <quote rend="inline"
                            >obstructive</quote> and to have a better attitude about sharing
                        resources and listening to the needs of DHers. 2.75% said that IPs need to
                        improve their own technical skills before they can be helpful. And 12.84%
                        simply said wanted archivists and librarians to keep positively supporting
                        their work: IPs should <quote rend="inline">keep being awesome;</quote> they
                        should <quote rend="inline">keep doing exactly what they have been doing,
                            which is being well-trained, interested colleagues open to new form[s
                            of] digital scholarship;</quote> and noting that <quote rend="inline"
                            >librarians and archivists are historians' best friends :-)</quote></p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The role of IPs, according to IPs</head>
                    <p>Turning now to the perspective of information professionals on their role in
                        digital humanities projects, I asked them a series of questions about their
                        experiences. First, I asked archives and library respondents whether they
                        felt digital humanities projects were part of their role. The results were
                        overwhelmingly positive: 55.84% said yes, that these projects were
                        explicitly part of their role; another 24.68% said they were somewhat or
                        tangentially related to their role; and another 3.90% said they built
                        digital humanities projects into their role. Only 14.29% said DH projects
                        fell outside the scope of their work. These answer demonstrate that
                        information professionals now expect to do this work as part of the course
                        of their librarianship.</p>
                    <p>I then asked information professionals about the ways they might have altered
                        their workflows to accommodate the needs of DH projects. First, I asked,
                            <quote rend="inline">Did your work on the project contribute to any of
                            the traditional archival life cycle steps, such as Arrangement,
                            Description, Preservation, or Providing Access? Please explain.
                            (Examples include digitizing analog text for the project that could
                            provide increased access, or taking steps to ensure digital preservation
                            of a website created as part of a DH project.)</quote> I parsed the
                        results to yield 122 answers. Most respondents highlight ways they provided
                        all or most of these. Some used the word <quote rend="inline"
                            >digitization</quote> in general, but it's not clear whether they felt
                        this was associated with access, preservation, or another step that I
                        highlighted; I classified those responses as <term>other</term>. 34.43% of
                        the responses mention access; 18.85% mention preservation; 24.59% mention
                        arrangement/description; 12.30% were classified as <term>other</term>; and
                        the remainder (9.84%) said No or N/A.</p>
                    <p>For the next question, I asked information professionals, <quote
                            rend="inline">Did you change any of your standard archival workflows to
                            accommodate this project, or in anticipation of future similar projects?
                            (For example, did you switch to higher quality OCR software to support
                            text mining? Did you embed geographical metadata into a digitized map to
                            allow for geodata visualizations?)</quote> First, I broke the 69
                        responses from information professionals down into <term>yes</term>
                        (44.93%), <term>no</term> (36.23%), <term>N/A</term> (8.7%), and
                            <term>other</term> (5.8%). A number of the respondents explained their
                        answers; I parsed these answers into 108 responses, the most popular answers
                        of which broke down as follows. 9.82% made changes in the realm of metadata;
                        7.14% made changes in their work with mapping and geodata; 4.46% made
                        changes to their digitization workflows; 2.68% changed their staffing to
                        accommodate the new projects; 1.79% made changes with OCR; 1.79% changed
                        their data visualization procedures; and 1.79% reported that they didn’t
                        have standard workflows in place before this project, but the project helped
                        to implement them.</p>
                    <p>Finally, I asked information professionals whether they planned to provide
                        long-term access or preservation for this project. There were 69
                        respondents. The vast majority (64.38%) said Yes, they plan to ensure
                        ongoing access or preservation in some form or fashion, with another 12.32%
                        percent saying that they are still working it out. 15.07% percent said no,
                        though several of these said it's because their projects were pedagogical in
                        nature or proofs of concept, so they were not designed to be kept for the
                        future. 5.48% responded in some other way.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>The survey results and analysis provide a number of conclusions and suggestions
                    for further research. First, it seems clear that collaborations between subject
                    researchers and information professionals are happening, and happening
                    frequently. Secondly, while information professionals generally see digital
                    humanities projects as within their purview, they are not initiating these
                    collaborations nearly as frequently as their digital humanities scholar
                    colleagues. Why are the information professionals not initiating as often? This
                    is an area for further research, but responses in this survey suggest that
                    information professionals are often so limited in their available staff time and
                    resources that they will work with a colleague when approached but are not able
                    to prioritize these projects from within their own departments.</p>
                <p>Next, this survey lends support to Rosenblum and Dwyer’s (2016) argument that in
                    collaborations between subject researchers and information professionals, tasks
                    do not necessarily break down into expected categories in which the subject
                    expert is in charge of the academic research questions and interpretation, and
                    the information professional is in charge of tools, implementation, and support.
                    Based on my analysis of the projects described here, information professionals
                    and subject specialists shared many tasks, and sometimes did tasks outside of
                    what would traditionally have been their expected purview. For example, one
                    academic researcher wrote, <quote rend="inline">My archivist colleague
                        participated in the design of metadata fields, tutorials for appraisal,
                        finding additional sources of funding. I was responsible for the design and
                        development of the digital archive, outreach, funding and securing a home
                        for it.</quote> In many projects, however, archivists and librarians are
                    serving in a more <q>support</q> role, doing project management, digitizing
                    materials, working on metadata, and learning and teaching new tools or software
                    products.</p>
                <p>This survey revealed intriguing responses regarding the impressions information
                    professionals and digital humanist researchers had of working with each other.
                    While, generally speaking, the researchers felt that their projects were
                    successful and the information professionals were supportive colleagues with
                    whom they enjoyed working and whose expertise they valued, responses from the
                    information professionals were more mixed. Many felt that they had difficulty
                    working collaboratively with researchers, had trouble setting appropriate
                    expectations and communicating clearly. This may support Schaffner and Erway’s
                    contention that collaborations might be difficult because many humanities
                    scholars are very used to working on their own, and may not have much practice
                    successfully negotiating a collaborative research project <ptr
                        target="#schaffner2014" loc="8"/>. On the other hand, many information
                    professionals responded that they felt their collaborative work was very
                    successful, but it would have been improved with more administrative buy-in or
                    support in the form of staff time, funding, or other resources.</p>
                <p>The survey results indicate that these collaborations, on average, tend to be
                    viewed as successful and mutually beneficial by both parties, especially when
                    institutional support is available. However, information professionals do report
                    more difficulties with the collaboration, with resources, and with
                    administrative buy-in. Institutional conditions must adapt to support more of
                    these projects, and in particular funnel resources toward archivists and
                    librarians to do this work and support long-term sustainability of these
                    projects.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="appendix">
                <head>Full Survey</head>
                <figure xml:id="survey">
                    <graphic url="resources/images/survey.pdf"/>
                    <figDesc>Image file of Qualtrics survey used in study</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bryson2011" label="Bryson et al. 2011">Association of Research
                        Libraries. <title rend="italic">SPEC Kit 326: Digital
                    Humanities</title>. Tim Bryson, Miriam Posner, Alain St. Pierre, and Stewart
                    Varner (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="braunstein2015" label="Braunstein et al. 2015">Braunstein, L.R.,
                    Carini, P., &amp; Dumpert, H.D. <title rend="quotes">“And There Was a Large
                        Number of People”: The Occom Circle Project at the Dartmouth College
                        Library</title>. In Arianne Hartsell-Gundy, A., Braunstein, L., and Golomb,
                    L., <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in the Library: Challenges and
                        Opportunities for Subject Specialists</title> (pp. 225-240). [Chicago]:
                    Association of College and Research Libraries, a division of the American
                    Library Association (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clement2013" label="Clement et al. 2013">Clement, T., Hagenmaier, W.,
                    &amp; Levine Knies, J. <title rend="quotes">Toward a Notion of the Archive of
                        the Future: Impressions of Practice by Librarians, Archivists, and Digital
                        Humanities Scholars</title>. <title rend="italic">The Library Quarterly:
                        Information, Community, Policy</title>, 83.2 (2013): 112-130.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="green2016" label="Green 2016">Green, H. <title rend="quotes">Fostering
                        Assessment Strategies for Digital Pedagogy through Faculty–Librarian
                        Collaborations: An Analysis of Student-Generated Multimodal Digital
                        Scholarship</title>. In White J. &amp; Gilbert H. (Eds.), <title
                        rend="italic">Laying the Foundation: Digital Humanities in Academic
                        Libraries</title> (pp. 179-204). West Lafayette, Indiana: Purdue University
                    Press (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="keener2015" label="Keener 2015">Keener, A. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Arrival Fallacy: Collaborative Research Relationships in the Digital
                        Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title>, 9:2 (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="logsdon2017" label="Logsdon et al. 2017">Logsdon, A., Mars, A., &amp;
                    Tompkins, H. <title rend="quotes">Claiming Expertise from Betwixt and Between:
                        Digital Humanities Librarians, Emotional Labor, and Genre Theory</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">College &amp; Undergraduate Libraries</title>, 24.2-4
                    (2017): 155-170.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lorang2015" label="Lorang and Johnson 2015">Lorang, E., &amp; Johnson,
                    K.A. <title rend="quotes">A Checklist for Digital Humanities
                    Scholarship</title>. In Arianne Hartsell-Gundy, A., Braunstein, L., and Golomb,
                    L., <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities in the Library: Challenges and
                        Opportunities for Subject Specialists</title> (pp. 83-102). [Chicago]:
                    Association of College and Research Libraries, a division of the American
                    Library Association (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="muñoz2016" label="Muñoz 2016">Muñoz, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Recovering a Humanist Librarianship through Digital Humanities</title>. In
                    White J. &amp; Gilbert H. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Laying the Foundation:
                        Digital Humanities in Academic Libraries</title> (pp. 3-14). West Lafayette,
                    Indiana: Purdue University Press (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2013" label="Nowviskie 2013">Nowviskie, B. <title
                        rend="quotes">Skunks in the Library: A Path to Production for Scholarly
                        R&amp;D.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Journal of Library Administration</title> 53 (2013):
                    53–66.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="poole2018" label="Poole and Garwood 2018">Poole, A.H., &amp; Garwood,
                    D.A. <title rend="quotes">‘Natural Allies’: Librarians, Archivists, and Big Data
                        in International Digital Humanities Project Work</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Documentation</title>, 74.4 (2018): 804-826.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="poremski2017" label="Poremski 2017">Poremski, M.D. <title
                        rend="quotes">Evaluating the landscape of digital humanities
                        librarianship</title>. <title rend="italic">College &amp; Undergraduate
                        Libraries</title>, 24.2-4 (2017): 140-154.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="porter2014" label="Porter 2014">Porter, D. <title rend="quotes">What
                        If We Do, In Fact, Know Best?: A Response to the OCLC Report on DH and
                        Research Libraries</title> [Blog Post]. 12 February 2014. Retrieved from
                        <ref
                        target="https://acrl.ala.org/dh/2014/02/12/what-if-we-do-in-fact-know-best-a-response-to-the-oclc-report-on-dh-and-research-libraries/"
                        >https://acrl.ala.org/dh/2014/02/12/what-if-we-do-in-fact-know-best-a-response-to-the-oclc-report-on-dh-and-research-libraries/</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="posner2013" label="Posner 2013">Posner, M. <title rend="quotes">No
                        Half Measures: Overcoming Common Challenges to Doing Digital Humanities in
                        the Library</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Library
                        Administration</title> 53.1 (2013): 43-52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosenblum2016" label="Rosenblum and Dwyer 2016">Rosenblum, B., &amp;
                    Dwyer, A. <title rend="quotes">Copiloting a Digital Humanities Center: A
                        Critical Reflection on a Libraries–Academic Partnership</title>. In White J.
                    &amp; Gilbert H. (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Laying the Foundation: Digital
                        Humanities in Academic Libraries</title> (pp. 111-126). West Lafayette,
                    Indiana: Purdue University Press (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schaffner2014" label="Schaffner and Erway 2014">Schaffner, J., &amp;
                    Erway, R. <title rend="quotes">Does Every Research Library Need a Digital
                        Humanities Center?</title> Dublin, Ohio: OCLC Research (2014). Retrieved
                    from <ref
                        target="http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf"
                        >http://www.oclc.org/content/dam/research/publications/library/2014/oclcresearch-digital-humanities-center-2014.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shirazi2014" label="Shirazi 2014">Shirazi, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Reproducing the Academy: Librarians and the Question of Service in the
                        Digital Humanities</title> [Blog Post]. 15 July 2014. Retrieved from <ref
                        target="http://roxanneshirazi.com/2014/07/15/reproducing-the-academy-librarians-and-the-question-of-service-in-the-digital-humanities"
                        >http://roxanneshirazi.com/2014/07/15/reproducing-the-academy-librarians-and-the-question-of-service-in-the-digital-humanities</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vehovar2017" label="Vehovar and Manfreda 2017">Vehovar, V. &amp;
                    Manfreda, K. <title rend="quotes">Overview: online surveys</title>. In Fielding,
                    N., Lee, R., &amp; Blank, G. <title rend="italic">The SAGE Handbook of online
                        research methods</title> (pp. 143-161). 55 City Road, London: SAGE
                    Publications Ltd. (2017). DOI: <ref
                        target="https://dx.doi.org/10.4135/9781473957992.n9"
                        >10.4135/9781473957992</ref></bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vinopal2013" label="Vinopal and McCormick 2013">Vinopal, J., &amp;
                    McCormick, M. <title rend="quotes">Supporting digital scholarship in research
                        libraries: Scalability and sustainability</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Journal of Library Administration</title> 53.1 (2013): 27-42.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
