<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Transmediation as
               Radical Pedagogy in Building Queer and Trans Digital Archives</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Elspeth <dhq:family>Brown</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5977-7186<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Elspeth.Brown@utoronto.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Elspeth H. Brown is Professor of History, University of Toronto, Canada, and is the Director, LGBQT Oral History Digital Collaboratory. Elspeth.brown@utoronto.ca.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Cait <dhq:family>McKinney</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Simon Fraser University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>cait_mckinney@sfu.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Cait McKinney is a former postdoctoral fellow with the LGBQT Oral History Digital Collaboratory and is currently Assistant Professor in the School of Communication, Simon Fraser University, Canada.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Dan <dhq:family>Guadagnolo</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-5216-6545<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>daniel.guadagnolo@utoronto.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dan Guadagnolo is Assistant Professor, Institute for Communication, Culture and Technology, University of Toronto</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Juan Carlos <dhq:family>Mezo Gonzalez</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>jc.mezogonzalez@mail.utoronto.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Juan Carlos Mezo Gonzalez is a doctoral candidate in the history of sexuality at the University of Toronto</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Sid <dhq:family>Cunningham</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>York University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>sidney.cunningham@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Sid Cunningam is a doctoral candidate at York University in Ontario, Canada.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Caleigh <dhq:family>Inman</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <!--<dhq:affiliation/>-->
               <email>caleighinman@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Caleigh Inman is a former undergraduate student at the University of Toronto and is currently an occupational therapist in Ontario.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Zohar <dhq:family>Freeman</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>Harvard Law School</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>zohar.freeman@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Zohar Freeman is a former undergraduate student at the University of Toronto and is currently a student at Harvard Law School.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Amal <dhq:family>Khurram</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <!--<dhq:affiliation/>-->
               <email>amal.khurram@mail.utoronto.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Amal Khurram is a former undergraduate student at the University of Toronto and is a recent graduate of the Master of Teaching program at the Ontario Institute for Studies in Education (OISE).</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Alisha <dhq:family>Krishna</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <!--<idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!-\-if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-\-></idno>-->
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto Faculty of Law</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>alisha.krishna@mail.utoronto.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Alisha Krishna is a former undergraduate student at the University of Toronto and is currently a student at the University of Toronto Faculty of Law.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mackenzie <dhq:family>Stewart</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
               	>https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9149-1076<!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Mackenzie.stewart@utoronto.ca</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Mackenzie Stewart is a former undergraduate student at the University of Toronto and is currently Research Coordinator at Dalla Lana School of Public Health, University of Toronto</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000610</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
            <date when="2022-05-18">18 May 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2022-08-03" who="BRG">added ORCIDs, resolved encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
               <p>This article analyzes a one-month, intensive digital collections lab focused on
                  queer and trans community history, in partnership with the LGBTQ Oral History
                  Digital Collaboratory, and based at Toronto’s The ArQuives: Canada’s LGBQT+
                  Archives. This collaboration between ten intergenerational scholars and two
                  community organizations produced three digital exhibitions, focusing on post-1945
                  Toronto-based queer and trans activist history: <quote rend="inline">Not a Place on the Map: The Desh
                  Pardesh Project,</quote> an oral history project about the queer South Asian diasporic
                  arts and culture festival Desh Pardesh (1988 - 2001); the Foolscap Gay Oral
                  History Project, a 1980s community-based oral history project of Toronto gay life
                  pre Stonewall; and <title rend="italic">gendertrash from hell</title>, an early 1990s zine published by
                  transsexual artists, sex workers, and activists Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra
                  Phillipa McKay. </p>
               <p>In analyzing our work within the context of radical pedagogy and critical DH
                  practice, we focus on how we mapped spaces, (dis)inherited metadata, and designed
                  interfaces that would offer tactile, affective engagements with these histories.
                  We analyze our work through the lens of trans(affective)mediation, an approach
                  that understands the conversion of analog to digital objects for online archives
                  in relationship to anti-racist trans studies, affect, and the collaborative
                  potential of community-engaged DH. We argue that this concept offers queer and
                  trans community-based DH scholars and practitioners a means of challenging the
                  ways in which white, cis-normativity is naturalized within both LGBTQ+ community
                  archives and digital humanities tools and practices. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>Analyzing an intensive digital collections lab focused on queer and trans community 
            history by focusing on mapped spaces, metadata, and designed interfaces.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head></head>
         <figure>
            <head>poster by Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillips, 8.5 x 11”, published on the
               back cover of <title rend="italic">gendertrash from hell</title> 2, 1993.</head>
            <graphic url="resources/images/Figone.jpg"/>
            <figDesc>poster by Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillips, 8.5 x 11”, published on the
               back cover of <title rend="italic">gendertrash from hell</title> 2, 1993.</figDesc>
         </figure>
         
         <p><quote rend="inline">Hey faggots,</quote> the hand-made poster shouts, <quote rend="inline">if you’re going to call us trannies or
            transies, then we’ll call you stupid dicks and wee-wees...time for you to grow up</quote> (Fig.
            1). Made by transsexual artists, sex workers, and activists Mirha-Soleil Ross and
            Xanthra Phillipa McKay for their 1990s zine <title rend="italic">gendertrash from hell</title>, the poster
            hilariously reproduces the cut-letter aesthetic of a ransom demand, using schoolyard
            argot to threaten “stupid dicks and wee-wees” while, at the same time, admonishing their
            faggot readers to “grow up.” The carefully cut-and-pasted magazine lettering references
            anonymity (the form uses mechanically printed lettering to shield the individualizing 
            <q>tell</q> of the hand-written), as well as the circulation of media: demands such as this
            one show up ominously — in the movies anyway — in the target’s mailbox. Appearing in
            <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title>, Ross and McKay repurpose this older media form — the ransom note — as part
            of a zine, a paper DIY publication that circulated to trans activists and others in 
            Canada, the U.S. and Europe in the 1990s. Now, our collaborative team transitions the
            media once more, from analogue to digital, as we digitize <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> for an open-source
            queer and trans community archive and digital exhibition. To borrow from Jessica Marie
            Johnson, we are recreating trans feeling in digital form: by gently releasing an
            artifact of trans femme becoming into a digital environment, this zine will become
            mediated through devices, metadata, <q>likes,</q> retweets, and a network of trans
            commenters, creating in the process an instance of trans femme digital practice.<ptr target="#johnson2018"/></p>
         <p>This essay is about how ten diverse queer and trans DIY digital humanists, mostly
            students and all social justice oriented, created three digital exhibitions on queer and
            trans history, with accompanying podcasts, over the course of four weeks. Our project
            was based at The ArQuives, the largest independent LGBTQ+ community archive in the
            world, and the three projects focused on a wide range of Toronto-based queer and trans
            activist history: <title rend="quotes">Not a Place on the Map: The Desh Pardesh Project,</title> an oral history
            project about the queer South Asian diasporic arts and culture festival Desh Pardesh
            (1988 - 2001); the Foolscap Gay Oral History Project, a 1980s community-based oral
            history project of Toronto gay life pre-Stonewall; and <title rend="italic">gendertrash from hell</title>, the trans
            zine published by Ross and MacKay in the early 1990s. We worked together daily on a
            collaboration that brought together the LGBTQ Oral History Digital Collaboratory (the
            Collaboratory), a multi-year project on US and Canadian queer and trans oral history
            directed by Prof. Elspeth H. Brown; The ArQuives; the South Asian Visual Arts Centre (SAVAC); the
            University of Toronto; and York University.</p>
     
         <p>Our collaboration emerges from the recognition that many gay and lesbian community
            archives founded in the 1970s are no longer necessarily outside the mainstream and, in
            fact, now benefit from varying forms of structural inequality. Projects like ours are
            necessary in intervening in the <q>symbolic annihilation</q> of trans and BIPOC people within
            the queer community archive <ptr target="#caswell2014"/> <ptr target="#caswell2017"/> <ptr target="#brown2020"/>. These gay and lesbian archives, radical in their time in
            many ways, are also bound up in histories of cisnormativity, whiteness, and settler
            colonialism; this history leaves a complex affective terrain that QTBIPOC
            activists-students-scholars must necessarily navigate as they encounter materials in the
            queer community archive. This work requires not only the labour of everyday DH praxis —
            digitizing, writing metadata, building exhibitions and podcasts — but also the affective
            labour of navigating the archival silences and information taxonomies built for
            documenting cis, white, gay and lesbian social movements. As Marika Cifor has argued,
            the turn to recognizing the distinctive affective experiences of LGBQT persons and
            collections within the archive can surface the specific needs of queer and trans people
            whose histories have been long-denied through processes of marginalization and
            non-recognition.<ptr target="#cifor2016a"/> <ptr target="#cifor2016b"/> <ptr target="#cifor2017"/> While some of these affective encounters can produce a radical empathy
            as project members encounter materials that are personally meaningful, other encounters
            can produce more complex responses of disidentification and refusal <ptr target="#caswell2016"/>. </p>
         <p>We understood our work to be in dialogue with other scholars who bring questions of
            critical humanities scholarship to bear on digital praxis: projects that are motivated 
            by questions of social transformation and radical politics.<note> The work here is growing, but see scholars and activists networked with #transformDH and the
               FemTechNet collective, as well as <ptr target="#nieves2018"/> <ptr target="#earhart2016"/> <ptr target="#lothian2013"/> <ptr target="#chun2014"/> <ptr target="#conghuyen2015"/> <ptr target="#posner2015"/></note> As an intergenerational,
            multi-institutional, queer, trans, and racially diverse gathering of DIY critical digital
            humanists, our work is an experiment in radical pedagogy that cuts across the
            institutional boundaries of both the liberal, LGBTQ+ community archive and the
            neoliberal university. Indeed, if part of the point of doing queer/trans digital histories is providing meaningful access to generational knowledge transfer,
            then involving undergraduate students, graduate students, postdoctoral scholars, senior
            faculty, archivists, and community members as makers is key to expanding our
            understanding of cultural and political inheritance, both in terms of what histories,
            politics and cultures are remembered and what histories, politics, and cultures can be
            inherited. </p>
         <p>Our thinking about the complex affective landscapes of DH praxis has been shaped by the
            concept of <q>trans(affective)mediation,</q> a term we borrow from Daniel C. Brouwer and
            Adela C. Licona to explore the relationship between anti-racist queer and trans studies,
            affect, and the collaborative potential of community-engaged DH. Brouwer and Licona
            rework the idea of transmediation — the transformation of one medium to another — to
            account for the <quote rend="inline">affective stakes in the process of moving between print and digital</quote> <ptr target="#brouwer2016"/>.
            Their work has focused on the affective terrain of both zine makers and zine readers,
            who experienced contradictory feelings of affirmation and loss as digital preservation
            intervened in zine culture’s attributes of immediacy, material vulnerability, and haptic
            intimacy. We have drawn from this work to consider the affective terrain of the queer,
            trans, and BIPOC DIY archivists who have engaged with QTBIPOC archival objects en route
            to building DH public humanities projects. Trans(affective)mediation, we argue, is a
            valuable tool for archival and DH activists whose project goals, like ours, seek to
            decenter whiteness, destabilize assumptions about ability, value horiztontal digital
            labour structures, and elevate the experiences of trans and nonbinary peoples of colour.
            In migrating media in this way, we consider transmedia as about both media and
            embodiment: trans studies asks us to consider <q>trans</q> as not simply about embodied
            histories, but also about movement and migration more broadly — in this particular case,
            the migration of media from analogue to digital. Our projects have addressed two forms
            of silences: the silencing of specific voices and
         experiences within the LGBTQ+ community archive and the erasure of marginalized,
            non-white community members who do the daily work of curating, maintaining, researching,
            analyzing, writing, digitizing, recording, and making within these archives <ptr target="#boellstorff2014a"/>. At the
            same time, this work has provoked mixed feelings. A methodology of
            trans(affective)mediation has enabled us to account for this contradictory emotional
            terrain as we both transform one medium into another and encounter both affirming
            archival objects and those that naturalize systemic inequalities based on race, gender
            expression, and ability. By documenting the processes that informed the mounting of
            these three projects, this article argues that through its call to focus and reflection
            in digital praxis and process, trans(affective)mediation offers queer and trans
            community-based DH scholars and practitioners a means of challenging the many ways that white
            cis-normativity becomes naturalized within both LGBTQ+ community archives and digital
            humanities tools and practices. </p>
         <p>In what follows, we reflect upon and document the various methods, practices, and
            mediations that came together in the mounting of our three projects. Through
            trans(affective)mediation, we offer <q>lessons learned,</q> so to speak, the varying
            affective engagements that emerged, as well as a set of protocols for what we
            nonetheless believe is a radical, community-engaged vision of queer and trans-positive
            DH. The first portion of our article contextualizes our work with two sections on
            radical pedagogy and critical DH practice, as well as the challenges of <quote rend="inline">inheriting
            [archival] data</quote> within radical DH work. The second portion of our essay delves more
            deeply into the specifics of the work we did together, including the ambivalences,
            frustrations, and utopian visions of intergenerational and inter-community solidarities
            which emerged. Following this, a section entitled <title rend="quotes">Mapping Space and Time</title> reflects on
            how digital explorations of spaces using the open-source GIS platform integrated with
            Omeka can spatialize histories of gentrification and colonization as they shape queer
            communities over
         time; in this section we reflect on the limits of our project for achieving the
            intersectional results we sought. The following section, <title rend="quotes">Making Data,</title> reports on our
            discussions and evolving practices around queering metadata description as a
            materialization of complex identity formations through the deceptively simple choices we
            make about tagging. Our final section, <title rend="quotes">Trans(affective)mediation and Tactile Digital
            Histories,</title> discusses the affective dimensions of working in <soCalled>analog</soCalled> archives in which
            our own racial, ethnic, sexual, or gender identities are implicated, and reflects and
            reports on both content and interface design choices we made in order to offer users of
            our digital collections potential entries into these experiences with the past. Drawing
            together the method, the making, and the digital materials that resulted, this essay
            argues for a trans(affective)medial vision of critical DH: an approach that is deeply
            reflective upon process; maintains a robust community-engaged praxis; and that
            challenges both DH and archival scholars alike to consider how normative forms of DH and
            archival making, maintenance, and curation enforce dominant structures of power. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Radical Pedagogy, Intersectionality, and Critical DH Protocols &amp; Praxis</head>
            <p>Radical
            pedagogy that values horizontal, shared leadership and open, democratic exchange is
            central to building a critical DH praxis that is socially just and meaningfully engaged
            in feminist, anti-racist, and anti-ableist perspectives. Early in our time together, we
            discussed our ethical commitments as a diverse collaboration of queer, trans, and
            non-binary scholars and activists, reflecting upon how we wanted these commitments to
            shape our digital methods, our practices, our project development, and our final
            outcomes. We wanted to develop what Anthony Bayani Rodriguez has described as a
            <q>guerilla praxis,</q> one that <quote rend="inline">allows students to approach academic knowledge production
               as a public good and a form of social movement activism relevant to the material conditions of our times</quote> <ptr target="#rodriguez2017"/> <ptr target="#yao2018"/>. These reflections proved central to developing a
            shared DH practice defined by 1) horizontal work relations and a meaningful division of
            labour, 2) drawing from DH’s roots in feminist pedagogy, a shared commitment to
            intersectionality, and 3) a recognition of critical disability studies’ important role
            in the development of socially just digital projects. We sought modes of DH protocol and
            practice (transmediation) that reflected our affective-ethical commitments as DH
            scholars and activists. As we argue here, these methodological commitments challenge
            underlying, normative assumptions in popular DH research and teaching projects. </p>
         <p>In our case, we have followed a feminist pedagogy that is both anti-racist and trans
            centric, and which has brought together digital humanities praxis with community-engaged
            queer and trans history. As Jessica DeSpain has argued, digital humanities’ emphasis on
            experiment, making, and collaboration is deeply indebted to a longer history of feminist
            pedagogy, even though so much of recent digital humanities work occludes this history <ptr target="#despain2016"/>.
            Feminist DH pedagogy foregrounds the goal of collaboration over hierarchy; designs the
            research environment so that a range of abilities are welcomed; examines the
            relationship between technology, media, and structural inequality as the work unfolds;
            and works closely with communities beyond the classroom. These feminist principles have
            been central to how many progressive digital humanists have understood their praxis,
            including our own, even if they are often dismissed for their DIY roots. </p>
         <p>We designed our work together as a feminist, trans-positive and anti-racist intervention
            into DH and community archive projects. As Roopika Risam has argued, drawing on the work
            of legal scholar Kimberlé Crenshaw, an intersectional approach — one that foregrounds
            the intersections of race, gender, and class in the analysis of structural inequality —
            allows digital humanities practitioners to overcome the field’s current divisions of making/programming
            vs. analysis and criticism <ptr target="#risam2015"/> <ptr target="#crenshaw1991"/> <ptr target="#nowviskie2014"/> <ptr target="#nash2017"/>. Yet pursuing an intersectional approach within digital
            humanities projects is to work against the grain because, as Tara McPherson has argued,
            the difficulty in bringing together an analysis of race with an engagement with
            technology is <quote rend="inline">an effect of the very designs of our technological systems, designs that
               emerged in post-WWII computational culture</quote> <ptr target="#mcpherson2012"/>. We recognized that this seeming
            difficulty in bringing together race and technology is itself a problem of privilege.
            Scholars of color working at the intersections of media, technology and race, such as
            Anna Everett, Lisa Nakamura, Wendy Chun, Kara Keeling, Simone Browne, and Safiya Noble,
            among others, foreground questions of race and racism in the context of white supremacy, 
            both within the academy and outside of it.<note> The scholarship on race, media, and technology is growing quickly, but see <ptr target="#everett2002"/>
               <ptr target="#everett2009"/> <ptr target="#nakamura2008"/> <ptr target="#nakamura2013b"/> <ptr target="#chun2006"/> <ptr target="#chun2009"/> and <ptr target="#noble2019"/>.</note> </p>
         <p>We have also approached our work together with insights drawn from Critical
            Disability Studies (CDS), a field of study that one of the students has particular
            expertise in. CDS examines why and how certain body-minds are deemed normal and natural,
            while others are not.<note> <q>Body-minds</q> is Eli Clare’s term, see <ptr target="#clare2017"/></note> The field challenged us to conjure up alternative
            material-discursive, labour, and digital spaces in which disability is both anticipated
            and desired. Disabled scholars and activists have long used digital tools to participate
            in humanities scholarship as their work has often been excluded from more traditional
            avenues of publication.<note>See for example, Mia Mingus, <title rend="italic">Leaving Evidence</title> (blog),
               <ref target="https://leavingevidence.wordpress.com/">https://leavingevidence.wordpress.com/</ref>; AJ Withers, stillmyrevolution (blog),
               <ref target="https://stillmyrevolution.org/">https://stillmyrevolution.org/</ref>; Lydia X. Z. Brown, Autistic Hoya (blog),
               <ref target="http://www.autistichoya.com/">http://www.autistichoya.com/</ref></note> Recently, digital humanities scholars have begun to consider the
            importance of building accessible digital tools and spaces as part an intersectional DH
            practice, rejecting a view of DH <q>tools of the trade</q> as neutral technological objects
            existing within complex power structures, rather than as technologies constituted
            through relations of power <ptr target="#risam2015"/> <ptr target="#mcpherson2014"/>. Bringing digital humanities into conversation with
            disability studies pushes critically engaged digital humanities practitioners to
            reimagine the form of digital tools, work, and spaces. This commitment reminded us to
            contest digital tools which function only within a system of compulsory able-bodiedness and to welcome the difference in form our tools and projects
            will take when they are designed to embrace disability <ptr target="#williams2012"/> <ptr target="#godden2016"/> <ptr target="#mcruer2006"/>. </p>
         <p>The questions raised by CDS very quickly reshaped our thinking. During our work
            together, we recognized the silences which an ableist model of digital space can
            enforce. As such, we took several steps to increase the accessibility of our three
            exhibitions. First, any audio materials in our collections were uploaded along with full
            transcripts. Second, we used ABBYY Finereader software to apply optical character
            recognition to all of the text-based archival materials in our collections. This allows
            the texts to be read by screen readers, a technology which reads texts out loud and is
            used by many people who are blind or low-vision. And third, we included image
            descriptions for any image based materials in our digital collections, and embedded
            alt-text for images whenever possible. We used these three accessibility tools as they
            applied to the particular needs of each collection. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Inheriting Data </head>
         <p>Working with archival collections, we soon recognized our three projects as a form of
            transmedial intergenerational cultural and political transfer and inheritance, and yet
            we also recognized how both the archival collections we selected and our group itself
            looked decidedly different from the kinds of white, cis, and heteronormative narratives
            which are often celebrated in LGBTQ+ community archival practice. The data we inherited,
            and the DH practices that we undertook, would have an uneasy relationship to where many
            of us understood our own position to be in LGBTQ+ history and life. We recognized these
            tricky encounters as precisely the kinds of trans(affective)mediations described by
            Brouwer and Licona. Where they documented the various affects that emerged when using
            queer ephemera that had been digitized, we sought to
         explore trans(affective)mediation through the process of digitization and mounting.
            Practically speaking, our projects drew on a range of analog and born-digital objects.
            In some cases, we digitized oral history interviews from cassette tapes that had not
            been listened to since the early 1980s. Other interviews conducted more recently came to
            us as digital audio, and in these cases, our <q>digitizing work</q> meant creating
            transcripts, abstracts, metadata, and streaming audio. Across all three projects, we
            accessed larger, paper-based archival collections to curate the exhibitions, choosing
            appropriate material to digitize and finding documents, images, photographs, and other
            ephemera that would bring these rich histories to life for users. We designed three
            creative exhibitions using Omeka and its Neatline plugin, an open source platform for
            digital collections designed by the Roy Rosenzweig Center for History and New Media at
            George Mason University. All three exhibitions were accompanied by podcasts, specific to
            the content and process of collaborative, critical DH praxis. Our undergraduate
            participants curated the digital exhibitions and made the podcasts while more senior
            members of the lab provided mentorship, including scholarly and technical support. In
            addition to the podcasts, we also took turns creating reflective social media content
            (blogs for The ArQuives and the Collaboratory websites; Facebook, Twitter and Instagram
            posts) about our work in progress: a form of public-facing outreach to the communities
            we hoped to reach with our digital projects. To learn all of these technical processes,
            we came up with a series of workshops on topics such as writing abstracts, creating
            metadata, and using Omeka. We taught each other skills that were specific to particular
            collections, such as digitizing cassette tapes and records, or scanning photographs. In
            many cases we learned together. For example, Neatline was new to all of us, as was
            writing, recording, and producing podcasts. We sought support from the GitHub community
            when we were truly stumped by Neatline, and we reached out to the Queer Zine Archive
            Project, and a few DH librarians, via Twitter and Facebook when we wanted to learn best practices
            around document accessibility. Through these practices, all of us explored the wider,
            collaborative DH world. </p>
         <p>All of our work together took place off-campus, in the second-floor gallery space of The
            ArQuives, Canada’s LGBTQ+ Archives. Founded in 1973, The ArQuives is primarily run by
            its 100+ volunteers, some of who have volunteered on a weekly basis for 40 years. As the
            largest independent and community-based LGBTQ+ archives in the world, The ArQuives
            houses records related to LGBTQ+ activism, art, and community life in Canada and around the
            world. The archives holds a significant periodicals collection, along with oral
            histories and other audio; film and video; books; banners and other textiles; a modest
            art collection; and other forms of ephemera crucial to queer world-making, such as
            pin-buttons and nightclub matchbooks. Building the archives’ trans collections has been
            a significant focus in recent years, through partnership with the Collaboratory. Like
            many other community archives, The ArQuives has invested heavily in developing digital
            infrastructures, as a way of doing outreach beyond the archives’ doors. </p>
         <p>The ArQuives is an activist archive that documents social movements and activist
            campaigns for social justice <ptr target="#flinn2009b"/> <ptr target="#flinn2011"/> <ptr target="#flinn2009a"/> <ptr target="#caswell2014"/>. Community archives like this one exploded in the 1970s,
            as activists in the civil rights, feminist, anti-war, and gay liberation movements
            sought to collect and preserve the records that emerged from these protests <ptr target="#barriault2009"/> <ptr target="#brown2011"/> <ptr target="#bastian2009"/>
            <ptr target="#sheffield2017"/>. This
            longer gay and lesbian history presents specific challenges to contemporary queer and
            trans archival activism, however. The ArQuives, like many 1970s gay organizations, was
            founded by a generation of gay, white, cis gendered men whose organization and activism
            helped end the criminalization of same-sex desire and who helped found keys institutions
            of gay and lesbian sociality, politics, and history during this period. It can be
            difficult for activist archivists, perhaps for some white gay men in particular, to understand how and why histories and methods imbricated with a heroic narrative of
            <q>gay and lesbian</q> sacrifice and struggle can, at the same time, be a site for the
            ongoing preservation of white, middle-class, cis values. Left unexamined, these embedded
            narratives, which shape decisions around collections and resource allocation,
            re-marginalize queer and trans people of color, Two-Spirit people, rural and poor
            members of the LGBTQ+ community, those who are disabled, and other marginalized groups <ptr target="#brown2020"/>.
            Our collective work on these three collections, exhibitions, and podcasts —
            especially the Desh Pardesh and <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title>/Mirha-Soleil Ross projects — is part of a
            larger effort to shift The ArQuives towards a less exclusionary future. We
            conceptualized the digital exhibitions as a place where students, activists, and others
            can learn about our intersectional, queer, and trans past while at the same time
            learning about the The ArQuives and its extensive holdings. </p>
         <p>As a team, we spent a lot of energy reflecting on how our critical ethical commitments
            should intersect with praxis and protocol. We are an intergenerational group with
            different relationships to the university, to gay and lesbian archives, and to the labor
            of making digital collections. Each of us contributed in significant ways to the
            intellectual design of the digital collections we worked on. At the same time, students
            expressed some frustration with the theory/praxis divide in DH and our projects, and
            reflected in their evaluations that as we progressed, more and more time was spent
            <quote rend="inline">learning technologies and putting together the exhibits.</quote> As one student wrote in their
            evaluation, these technical tasks were <quote rend="inline">challenging in and of themselves. But I
            definitely [think] we could have done more to make links — like how are power relations
            reproduced in the creation of metadata? How does our exhibition <q>trans-mediate</q> these
            materials?</quote> That students left the lab able to frame these kind of questions in
            relationship to the digital humanities is impressive, but it is also clear that the
            practical work of building digital collections, which is often repetitive or even mundane, overshadowed the theoretical
            outcomes we hoped for. This article is, in part, a way of bringing those threads
            together, to create that space and time. </p>
         <p>Even as the data we inherited bore little resemblance to our own queer and trans lives,
            our team brought together faculty, community members, undergraduate, and graduate
            students into work models that emphasized collaboration, presence, and co-creation. As
            one student wrote in their evaluation of the lab, <quote rend="inline">It was really great to have
            undergrads, graduate students, postdoc, and professors all in the room together learning
            from one another. I witnessed some really beautiful moments of mentorship, and to me this
            was an example of the way we can combat this individualistic [neoliberal] culture of
            academia in which we are told to consistently put ourselves and our careers first.</quote>
            Students noted that they chose projects they cared about because they aligned with their
            own interests or identity formations. At the same time, students expressed some
            frustration with working on three separate collections, instead of drawing connections
            across projects. As one student wrote, <quote rend="inline">I also hoped that we would do more collaboration
            in the larger group of five rather than entirely working in the sub-groups. I had hoped
            there would be a bit more inter-group exchange. It was hard to facilitate that as we
            were short on time!</quote> This student’s critique of collaboration illuminates some of the
            problems that come along with grant or task based DH projects that pursue ambitious
            outcomes in short periods of time. Sometimes <q>the work</q> gets in the way. </p>
         <p>Our group’s partnerships with community organizations such as The ArQuives and SAVAC
            exemplify how the digital has transformed the traditional learning space of the
            classroom, rendering students active participants and collaborators on research that can
            take new forms, as traditional research papers make room for digital exhibitions,
            Wikipedia articles, and other DH research outcomes <ptr target="#burdick2012"/> <ptr target="#kill2012" loc="389–406"/>. In some cases, as in our work together at The ArQuives,
            collaborative work takes place outside the classroom altogether. In moving outside the
            classroom to engage in digital humanities praxis, our work together unfolds in dialogue
            with community engaged scholarship, public history and public humanities, fields that
            have long sought to decenter the classroom as the sole site of learning about
            the past, especially in LGBTQ+ contexts. </p></div>
         
         <div>
         <head>Digital Mapping Space and Time </head>
         <p>In our work with the Foolscap Gay Oral History collection, we drew on digital mapping
            technologies to understand overlapping spatial histories of the city. Making maps
            allowed us to draw connections across Toronto’s queer communities, for example, by
            connecting gay men’s cruising spaces to histories of colonization. At the end of the
            project, we found that while these connections were often visible to us as makers, they
            did not necessarily come across for users of these discrete collections: our materials,
            research design, and tools did not always align in the ways we had hoped. Because we’d
            organized our work into three distinct projects based on the specific fonds we were
            working with, the original archival logics of separating whiteness from colonialism, for
            example, found their way into our mapping work. In our analysis of our collaborative
            work, we were reminded of how, as Jen Jack Gieseking has argued, GIS can reproduce the
            military logics of its origins as a technology. Like Gieseking, we felt this affective
            tension acutely. We found ourselves in need of <quote rend="inline">new and easier-to-use technologies,
            algorithms, and tools</quote> that worked more effectiuvely against the grain of colonial
            logics <ptr target="#gieseking2018"/>. </p>
         <p><title rend="italic">Mapping Foolscap</title> is a digital exhibition that provides insights into the Toronto gay
            scene between the 1940s and late 1960s. The main primary source is a series of oral
            history interviews that John Grube and Lionel Collier conducted between 1981 and 1987, known as
            the <title rend="italic">Foolscap Oral History Project.</title> The project produced over 100 interviews with
            Canadian gay men born in the first half of the twentieth century, who had spent most of
            their lives in Toronto. The respondents — mostly white, middle-class, and
            English-speaking — were part of Grube’s and Collier’s social circle, and ranged in age
            from 36 to 92. The interviews covered the respondents’ early lives, coming out experiences, initiations into the <q>gay community,</q> interpersonal
            relationships, sex lives, interactions with police or psychiatric therapy, contact with
            and opinions on the gay liberation movement, among other themes. </p>
            <p>The authors’ digital exhibition, <title rend="quotes"><ref target="https://digitalexhibitions.arquives.ca/exhibits/show/mapping-foolscap">Mapping Foolscap</ref></title>, offers some of
            the digitized audio recordings and transcripts of the interviews, as well as an
            interactive map that locates the venues where gay men gathered, cruised, and socialized
            in pre-1970s Toronto. <note> The digital collection only draws on interviews with narrators who are deceased or have given
               their permission for audio to be shared online.</note> The map locates popular movie theatres such as The Bay and The
            Rio; public spaces and cruising sites such as High Park, Allan Gardens, and Queen’s
            Park; bars and <q>beverage rooms</q> such as the King Cole Room in the Park Plaza Hotel, the
            King’s Plate Room in the King Edward Hotel, Letros, the Quest, and the St. Charles and
            the Parkside taverns. We supplemented the map entries with photographs and other graphic
            materials, as well as with audio clips from the interviews. Through these clips, the
            Foolscap narrators describe these spaces in their own words, or discuss their social and
            sexual interactions therein. <title rend="italic">Mapping Foolscap</title> is in dialogue with the work of David
            Churchill, George Chauncey, John Grube, and other North American scholars, and seeks to
            provide a significant tool for researchers and the general public interested in
            Toronto’s gay history by facilitating the access to a rich, first-hand source that only
            a few people have heard about <ptr target="#churchill2004"/> <ptr target="#grube1986"/> <ptr target="#grube1991"/> <ptr target="#grube1997"/>. </p>
            <p>The Foolscap Gay Oral History Project offers an astonishingly rich and detailed portrait
           of Toronto’s gay scene before Stonewall. Yet the project was far from intersectional:
            almost all of the 100 narrators are cis-gendered, gay white men, many of whom were
            middle class at the time of the interview. This does not accurately reflect the
            increasing diversity of Toronto’s gay community during the 1980s. These white
            interviewees are mostly silent on race, even though the mid-1980s was a heated political
            moment for building anti-racism in Toronto’s gay liberation community. <note>As quoted in <ptr target="#mccaskell2016"/>; for further writing about racism in Toronto's gay community during these years, see 
               <ptr target="#ha2017"/></note> Despite this
            rich contemporaneous debate about race within the lesbian and gay community, the
            Foolscap interviewers did not pose questions to their narrators that would ask them to
            reflect on race, gender, and other markers of difference, and we were left to figure out
            how to map these erasures in the present <ptr target="#moraga1983"/> <ptr target="#ross1995"/>. </p>
         <p>To address such silences, contemporary activist and community historian Río Rodríguez,
            whose work is affiliated with the Marvellous Grounds project, has developed digital maps
            in collaboration with queer and trans Black, Indigenous and people of colour in Toronto.
            Rodríguez’s research in Mapping QTBIPOC Toronto demonstrates how GIS maps represent <quote rend="inline">the
            city not as defined by history projects that intend to commemorate institutional
            success, nor as places that have a single history,</quote> but rather their maps value <quote rend="inline">the
            multiplicity of voices that are often erased from understandings of public history due
            to racism, classism and transphobia</quote> <ptr target="#rodriguez2016" loc="74"/>. Rodríguez’ critical mapping work intervenes into 
            dominant narrative of Toronto’s queer past, one that has privileged the life histories
            of white gay men and their activism, of which Foolscap is a part. </p>
         <p>In visualizing the social geography of Toronto’s QTBIPOC histories, Rodríguez’ work
            dovetails with other critical DH projects that have brought an intersectional lens to
            understanding the history and politics of place. The FemTechNet’s <title rend="quotes">Situated Knowledges
            Mapping Project,</title> for example, explores how working with GIS systems can become a way
            for students to engage with these complex histories. Designed as a classroom activity, this project prompts students
            to become mapmakers, answering questions such as <quote rend="inline">How are places racialized, gendered,
            classed, designated or felt as safe or dangerous? …What knowledges come from being part
            of a dominant culture in a place? And from a minoritized culture in a place?</quote>. <note>Femtechnet Situated Knowledges Map, <ref target="https://femtechnet.org/docc/feminist-mapping/situatedknowledge-map/">https://femtechnet.org/docc/feminist-mapping/situatedknowledge-map/</ref></note>
            Engagement with the politics of gentrification is common to DH mapping projects that draw on
            interviews and oral histories, and recent notable examples include Kristy Kang’s Seoul
            of Los Angeles: Contested Identities and Transnationalism in Immigrant Space, and the
            Bay-area based Anti-eviction Mapping Project <ptr target="#kang2013"/> <ptr target="#antiEvictionMappingProject"/>.</p>
         <p>DH has enabled public history projects to reach outside of the archive or museum to
            produce visitor itineraries that map onto the physical places within the city. Some of
            these spatial humanities approaches bring viewers and listeners, physically, into the
            urban environment through GPS-enabled mobile devices that provide digital access to
            localized <quote rend="inline">tales of the city.</quote><note>There are numerous examples of these data landscape projects; in Toronto, one of the earliest,
               and most successful projects has been [Murmur], a documentary aural project that records stories
               and memories told about specific geographic locations (see <ref target="http://murmurtoronto.ca/">http://murmurtoronto.ca/</ref>)</note> Immersed in our critical DH work at The ArQuives, we 
            pursued an <soCalled>old-school</soCalled> approach to learning about these histories: Rodríguez led us on
            an real-life <title rend="quotes">Radical Queer Walking Tour</title> shaped by their research for the GIS-enabled
            Mapping QTBIPOC Toronto project. With this tour, Rodríguez and their collaborators seek
            to displace white supremacist histories of Toronto’s <q>Gay Village</q> with stories focused
            on BIPOC activism, sex work, gentrification, and other ongoing struggles as they might
            be connected to the past. <note>Rodríguez discusses how they developed this tour in some detail in <ptr target="#rodriguez2016"/></note> The tour provided students with a model for translating 
            their own critical engagements with lived space to the histories they were working on.
            Ideally, this intersectional approach to mapping Toronto’s queer and trans past would
            inform the curatorial approach to the students’ digital cultural mapping. </p>
         <p>Rodríguez’s model enabled us to see new relationships between empire and sexuality as
            they came together in the physical space of the city. For example, as the Foolscap oral
            histories show, one of the city’s key spaces for gay cruising and public sex had been
            the bandstand located in (the appropriately named) Queen’s Park.<note>For further history about Queen’s Park and public sex, see <ptr target="#maynard1994"/> <ptr target="#churchill2004"/></note> But in 1969 the city dismantled the 
            bandstand and installed, in its place, a five-ton equestrian statue of King Edward VII
            donated by the Indian government while <quote rend="inline">in the process of getting rid of reminders of
               the days of British rule</quote> <ptr target="#wencer2014"/>. Working with maps allowed us to understand how the
            landscape itself functioned as a material palimpsest for overlapping histories of both
            global and local structures of power: one concerning the histories of British
            imperialism, the Commonwealth, and the South Asian diaspora; the other concerning
            illicit sexualities in the space of the city.<note>For some recent work that is bringing together oral history and queer and trans urban culture, 
               <ptr target="#boyd2012"/> <ptr target="#johnson2016"/> <ptr target="#moore2014"/> <ptr target="#murphy2016"/> <ptr target="#ruiz2014"/> <ptr target="#twincitiesglbt2020"/></note> These overlapping histories were visible 
            to us, as makers, to some extent, but the decision to keep the three digital collections
            separate renders these connections invisible to users. At the end of our project, we
            concluded that what had began as a division of labour aimed at <q>getting as much done</q> as
            possible over the course of the month reinscribed the original archival logics of each
            collection in digital space. We knew going into this project that the design of digital
            collections would impact how users learn about Toronto’s queer and history from the The
            ArQuives’s Digital Collections site; we didn’t realize until the end of the project that
            achieving the intersectionality we sought at a deep, technological level would have
            required us to think outside existing models for building archives and organizing work. </p>
         <p>In our contributions to the The ArQuives’ digital exhibitions site, we decided to
            digitize collections that included histories of queer and trans people of colour, namely
            the Mirha Soleil Ross and Desh Pardesh collection. Because we organized our work around
            already existing collections, rather than a set of thematics that linked all of them,
            our research design maintains the liberal tokenism of <q>adding</q> QTBIPOC to the historical
            record <ptr target="#ware2017"/>. It was not until after the lab that we realized a critical
            trans(affective)mediation praxis could break the <q>reproduction</q> logics that often
            inundate digital archives with the same oppressive dynamics as their physical counterparts by imagining movements across <q>separate</q> collections.
            Trans(affective)mediation processes that use digital tools to draw thematic, spatial,
            and descriptive associations between apparently discrete historical moments or groups is
            one way digital archives might sort through these problems and challenge the <q>grain</q> of
            existing archival logics. <note> The idea of an <soCalled>archival grain</soCalled> references <ptr target="#stoler2010"/>. Anti-colonial and anti-racists critiques of archives that explore using multimedia to undo archival logics include <ptr target="#gumbs2011"/> along with Rodríguez’s work, cited
               above. </note> </p> 
         <p>How might we create new research designs that both accommodate the strategic
            essentialisms that are sometime useful at the level of pedagogy where, for example,
            students work on the projects that most closely match their identities while, at the
            same time, interrogating and complicating the stability of such identity categories? As
            one of the students who worked on the Foolscap collection wrote in their evaluation of
            the lab, while they felt ready to challenge the racism and misogyny built into the
            collection’s logic, they needed more interaction with their peers and mentors working on
            other collections in order to find the tools to do this. In retrospect we wonder what
            this experiment would look like if we had, instead, developed a project not around
            existing archival collections that were already organized by identity categories but
            instead had focused on a thematic that crossed these categories — queer arts organizing
            in Toronto in the 1980s and 90s, as one example. While our digital collections don’t
            begin from this kind of productive schema, our interventions in writing metadata
            achieved some success in using digital tools to undo some of the logics that govern
            (white) <q>gay and lesbian</q> archives. We explore this work in the next section. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Making Queer and Trans Metadata </head>
         <p>Most digital collections depend on text-based descriptions, such as tagging objects by
            subject and keyword, in order to be search-retrievable, and ultimately intelligible and
            meaningful for the communities they represent. Yet standards practices in metadata
            description often fail to adequately index the complex histories, identities and embodiments contained within
            queer and trans cultural heritage materials. Standard subject heading vocabularies —
            databases of terms that creators can use to tag objects within a digital collection —
            sometimes use outdated or pejorative language to describe queer and trans subjects <ptr target="#berman2008"/>. Standard vocabularies oriented toward
            whiteness might not drill-down to the level of granularity required for the archives of
            queer diasporas. Queer and trans metadata initiatives such as the Homosaurus project,
            for example, assist in addressing the failures of descriptive standards for queer and
            trans cultural heritage materials by putting forward new, community generated standard
            vocabularies as linked data.<note>The Homosaurus vocabulary is available at <ref target="http://homosaurus.org/">http://homosaurus.org/</ref>. The Homosaurus has since moved to Northeastern University under the direction of K.J. Rawson, and has transitioned to a linked data vocabulary; the editorial board has been working on it steadily to address some of the 2017 shortcomings described in this section.</note> </p>
         <p>Doing community-based digital collections work from a queer, trans, and anti-racist
            perspective meant finding ways to revise standard, normative metadata vocabularies for
            our particular collections. We did this work with an understanding that queer and trans
            users have been some of the most adamant critics of metadata standards within the
            libraries and archives field. <note>See, for example, <ptr target="#roberto2011"/></note> Our first workshop as a lab group focused on learning
            how to write metadata for oral history interviews on Omeka. As a group, we explored the
            political implications imbued in processes of making and revising data, weighing both
            the necessity and limitations of standard classification practices, and discussing the
            need to critique and demystify how databases are built <ptr target="#bowker1999"/>. We found it necessary to
            improvise and bend some of rules that guide best practices in using controlled
            vocabularies <ptr target="#wolfe2008"/>. By talking about metadata, and practicing making data together, we
            oriented our work toward each of our political commitments and ideas about
            identity-based terminologies. As we added objects to our digital collections and came up
            against the inevitable compromises that invoking standards requires, we moved toward a
            more flexible understanding of description <ptr target="#duff2002"/>. Our lab was an immersive experience in
            data as something that is made through small, singular acts that add up to larger
            infrastructures of intelligibility. While the Homosaurus worked well for The Foolscap and Mirha-Soleil Ross collections, digitizing the Desh
            Pardesh oral history project made us aware of the vocabulary’s 2017 limitations for
            describing the archives of queer of color diasporas. We discovered, for example, how
            LGBTQ+ metadata interventions such as Homosaurus had been organized around
            whiteness as a structuring logic. </p>
         <p>The Desh Pardesh exhibition emerged as a metadata and curatorial collaboration between
            The ArQuives, the South Asian Visual Arts Centre (SAVAC), and the University of Toronto. Desh Pardesh (<q>home away from home</q>) was a groundbreaking multidisciplinary
            queer South Asian arts festival that operated in Toronto from 1988-2001. Bakirathi Mani
            has written that <quote rend="inline">for the decade of its existence, Desh Pardesh was a monument to the
            possibility of creating diasporic communities that worked through national, linguistic,
            and religious differences in order to create a queer, anti-racist, and activist South
            Asian collectivity</quote> <ptr target="#mani2001"/>. Since its closure in 2001, the festival has become a relic for
            the Toronto South Asian arts community. While the festival has been sporadically
            commemorated with a few events, reflections, and critical essays over the past 15 years,
            there had yet to be any sustained investigation into this queer diasporic festival which
            took hold of the Canadian arts scene in the 1990s <ptr target="#fernandez2006"/>. In part, this is due to the paucity
            of archival sources; as Gayathri Gopinath has argued, events such as Desh Pardesh often
            resist textualization because the <quote rend="inline">queer spectatorial practice and the mercurial
            performances and more informal forms of sociality</quote> that occur at queer diasporic night
            clubs, festivals, and community events are not easily documented <ptr target="#gopinath2005"/>. To address this
            archival silence, in 2013 Indu Vashist, SAVAC’s Executive Director, created <title rend="quotes">Not a Place
            on the Map: The Desh Pardesh Project,</title> a three-year oral history project about queer
            South Asian history in Toronto focused on Desh Pardesh. Hired in May 2014, SAVAC’s Anna
            Malla mobilized the festival’s networks to complete 36 oral interviews over two years.
            Coinciding with the month-long research lab, the accessioning of the Desh Pardesh research material at The ArQuives gave us the opportunity to tease out the
            complexities of writing metadata for archives of queer diasporic communities and lives.
            In using the Homosaurus to write metadata for the Desh Pardesh Project, we encountered
            many examples that show how whiteness as normativity is embedded within LGBTQ projects.
            <q>Asian Cultures</q> and <q>Anti-racism</q> drawn from the Homosaurus, for example, would only
            scrape the surface of this project’s descriptive needs. The team lamented that the
            Homosaurus could only tag queer South Asian dance practices that involved dance
            traditions such as Bharata Natyam or Giddha as <q>exotic dancers,</q> for example; they
            bristled at how distinctions between events and projects involving Tamil, Goan or
            Punjabi communities would be conflated into <q>Asian Cultures,</q> <q>Asian Religions</q> or
            <q>Asian Studies.</q> Beyond its Anglophone commitment, the use of <q>Asian</q> as a cultural and
            racial referent exposes the Homosaurus’ Anglo-European roots. In wrestling with these limits, team members
            encounteresed and navigated what Brandon Walsh, drawing on Sianne Ngai, has described as
            the <q>ugly feelings</q> of failure as epistemology, where <quote rend="inline">frustration and anxiety are
               central components of the classroom, not experiences to be delicately avoided</quote> <ptr target="#walsh2019"/>. While
            we initially considered writing to create a new standard vocabulary for writing queer
            South Asian diasporic metadata, this proved far too ambitious for a month-long lab. In
            the end, we took a DIY approach, blending the Homosaurus with a modest, standard
            vocabulary that two members of our team generated out of listening to the oral history
            interviews, and considering the language used across narrators to describe queer and
            trans South Asian diasporic experience. Further considering the
            cultures-religions-studies triad used to complicate <q>Asian</q> in Homosaurus, we thought
            about the ways in which the practice of writing metadata in (white) LGBTQ archives has
            been historically marked and continues to be marked by Orientalist imaginations of the
            (Asian) Other. In the face of these LGBT archival practices, we opted to contextualize the
            project by writing into the digital collection an analysis of the further entrenchment
            of neoliberal governmentality in Ontario under the Mike Harris government of the 1990s.
            We hope that this reframing encourages alternative reading practices of this queer
            diasporic archive. Since taking over the Homosaurus, Rawson has been addressing critiques such as this one by working with collaborators to expand the vocabulary in key areas, such as slang, BDSM, Indigenous and Black terms; the Homosaurus welcomes collaborators in strengthening the project overall.</p>
         <p>For the Mirha-Soleil Ross collection, another team created a page about their own
            relationships to identification and the terminology used in <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> to describe
            trans people and trans community. As K.J. Rawson has shown, digital humanities projects
            provide methodological tools for tracking shifting terminologies within trans
            communities across literary and cultural production. For Rawson, DH tools are entries to
            doing community-based etymologies, which matter for understanding the shifting cultural
            conditions in relation to which trans communities make themselves intelligible <ptr target="#rawson2014"/>. In the
            <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> <ref target="http://digitalcollections.clga.ca/exhibits/show/gendertrash/a-note-on-terminology">exhibition</ref>’s <title rend="quotes">A Note On Terminology,</title> three team members identify,
            respectively, as a <quote rend="inline">bisexual trans man, a queer cis femme, and a queer trans man</quote> who
            <quote rend="inline">encounter <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title>’s unusual terminology not merely as an historical artifact, but
            as a radical challenge to the way we understand identity, community, and attraction that
            remains just as relevant and necessary today.</quote> Narrating our own reading practices
            around identity labels and search terms makes more transparent the role of makers in 
            community-driven databases, emphasizing our subjective investments in materials as a
            force that inevitably shapes how trans histories become intelligible in the present.
            Weaving these self reflexive discussions about terminology and its categorizing effects
            into our digital collections mirrors the care with which we have written metadata — with
            knowledge that these terms orient users to the histories they encounter. While tags and
            keyword classification often operate in the background of user’s search retrieval and
            navigation experiences, our outward reflections on description seek to bring these
            behind-the-scenes processes to the fore of the interface. </p></div>
            <div>
            <head>Trans(affective)mediation and Tactile Digital Histories</head>
         <p>Trans(affective)mediation was central to our deliberate engagement with remediation as
            an active, and often uncomfortable process that is an inevitable part of making digital
            objects from paper documents. As Jay Bolter and Richard Grusin have argued, remediation
            is a primary characteristic of digital media; digital media reproduce, adapt, or
            otherwise reference older forms <ptr target="#bolter2000"/>. While remediation is a temporal phenomena that
            describes the relation between <q>old</q> and <q>new</q> media, the idea of transmediation
            explored by Henry Jenkins and others points to the difficulty of conceptually or
            technically sustaining divisions between media forms in the context of digital
            platforms. Techniques and aesthetics from <q>print,</q> <q>video,</q> and <q>the web</q> productively
            converge <ptr target="#jenkins2017"/>. Digital archives present a peculiar kind of transition across media in that
            they at once seek to promote and obscure the digital object’s status as reproduction.
            Online archives promise wide access to audiences who might not ever visit a
            brick-and-mortar archive and they do this, in part, by separating digital objects from
            their referents. On the other hand, digital archives are invested in creating
            experiences for users that are <quote rend="inline">as good as the real thing,</quote> a promise that rests, in
            part, on denying the digital encounter’s status as substitute. Most members of our group
            are millennials accustomed to encountering queer and trans historical materials through
            platforms such as Instagram; for many of us, the lab presented a first encounter with
            archival research, and we learned basic practices in handling documents well, alongside
            some more critical introductions to archival arrangement. We were at once captivated by
            the aura of these objects and invested in their presentation in the age of digital
            reproduction, to paraphrase Walter Benjamin <ptr target="#benjamin1969" loc="217–251"/>. Playing with the relationship between
            digital objects and their analog <q>originals</q> was, for us, a purposeful practice. It
            became a significant focus when we considered selection, description and display,
            accessibility, but also the affective encounters we were staging for ourselves, and others. </p>
         <p>Brouwer and Licona’s <q>trans(affective)mediation</q> is one way of marking the affective
            dimensions of digitized versions of queer, trans, and P.O.C. cultural heritage
            materials. Transmediation, which they define <quote rend="inline">as the translation, or transformation, of
            one medium into another medium, a crossing over and a conversion of one already existing
            medium into another,</quote> is here marked with affective potentiality, as digitization may
            provide opportunities for distinct sensory possibilities <ptr target="#brouwer2016"/> <ptr target="#jenkins2021"/>. Brouwer and Licona capture,
            in part, the ambivalence of digitization with this term, thinking through how online
            reproductions of queer, trans, and P.O.C. zines offer wider access and preservation, but
            also the loss of tactility, material records of use, and encounters with embodied others
            who are also readers <ptr target="#brouwer2016" loc="73"/>.<note>For ambivalence about digitizing in the LGBQT2+ context, see
               <ptr target="#cowan2018"/> and <ptr target="#chenier2015"/></note> This ambivalent position guided our protocols for both
            collaboration and digitization, and we searched out ways of reproducing more meaningful
            encounters for users through experimentation with the Omeka platform, as we describe
            below. The anecdote about Mirha-Soleil Ross and Xanthra Phillippa MacKay’s <title rend="quotes">Dicks and
            Weewees</title> collage that opens this article gives a sense of how our work brought this
            attention to form, and the affective dimensions of working with paper zines, to bear on
            both digital collection design and encoding queer and trans life against the normativity
            of metadata. </p>
         <p>Ross is a transsexual artist, activist, and sex worker best known
            for her video and performance art, her role as editor of the 1993-1995 zine <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> and as 1997-1999 organizer of Counting Past 2 – the first international trans
            film festival in Canada. Her sizable personal fonds at The ArQuives consists of books,
            periodicals, videos, physical artifacts, correspondence, working papers, and periodical
            clippings that represent not only her own work and interests as a collector, but also
            material traces of the collaborative and more broadly social aspects of much of her
            work. The <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> series that became the focus of our digital collection contains a large amount of correspondence with retailers,
            subscribers (including prisoners who received the zine for free), and hopeful or
            successful contributors — as well as draft manuscripts, clip art, zine pasteups, and
            financial documents. The correspondence, more than anything else, demonstrates how much
            Ross’s practice built upon networks of trans activists, artists, and publishers across
            North America and Europe who supported each other by the transnational exchange of
            information, social connections, subscriptions and advertising space, despite a lack of
            complete consensus around issues like sex work, prison reform, medico legal gatekeeping,
            and activist strategies. Our digital collection sought to reproduce, or at least gesture
            toward these networks in some way, building upon Brouwer and Licona’s assertion that
            digitized zines ought to be understood and experienced within extensive, complex
            networks that reproduce but also depart from paper circulation methods <ptr target="#brouwer2016" loc="80"/>. </p> 
         <p>As part of this project, Ross gave archives volunteers permission to digitize and share
            all issues of <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> online. Previously, only the first issue, edited by Xanthra
            Phillips, had been accessible online (through the Queer Zine Archive Project). <note>See <ref target="http://archive.qzap.org/index.php/Detail/Object/Show/object_id/337">http://archive.qzap.org/index.php/Detail/Object/Show/object_id/337</ref></note> In
            itself, the periodical represents an aesthetically and historically significant
            assemblage of news, resource listings, art, and commentary, tied together by the radical
            queer politics of Ross and her partner/collaborator Xanthra Mackay. In addition to our
            use of ABBYY to make <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> scans compatible with screen readers, we were also
            motivated by questions of accessibility in deciding what material to make public; we
            wanted to provide a scholarly rigorous discussion of <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title>’s historical context
            that would be compelling for a broad public while providing easier access to important
            related objects from the Ross fonds. Our team felt this would align our digital
            presentation of <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> more with the claimed purpose of the original <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> :
            <quote rend="inline">giv[ing] a voice to gender queers, who’ve been discouraged from speaking out &amp;
               communicating with each other</quote> <ptr target="#mackay1993"/>.</p> 
        
         <p>As we were attempting to digitally publish our Omeka exhibit, we had some difficulty
            finding materials to share that wouldn’t require lengthy consultations around privacy
            and rights (i.e. correspondence).<note>With funding from the <ref target="http://lgbtqdigitalcollaboratory.org/">LGBQT Oral History Digital Collaboratory</ref>, some members of our team worked for about 8 months
               to organize, describe, and archive the Mirha-Soleil Ross holdings at The ArQuives. This work has
               involved extensive collaboration with Ms. Ross, based in Montreal, as well as indispensable
               assistance from Nora Butler and Trish Salah.</note> We ultimately decided to begin with a small exhibit
            centered around images of the original artwork and paste-ups used to produce the zines,
            and activist buttons (made by Ross and Mackay) that could be ordered through forms
            published in <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> and other trans periodicals. We furthermore uploaded a modified
            version of one of these order forms to the Neatline plugin for Omeka, and made it so
            that clicking on individual issues or buttons on the form would allow online visitors to
            access the digitized zines and buttons (Fig. 2). The small selection of objects in the 
            exhibit are eye-catching and representative of the politics of the zine overall while
            the Neatline navigation serves as a reminder of the way a single print artifact may have
            been able to serve as a material link for isolated trans people to connect both with a
            wider community and also with a larger body of trans material culture. </p>
            
            <figure>
               <head>Interactive order form as part of <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> exhibition, The ArQuives Digital
                  Collections</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/590a8437896ec7a56b2d1779e2e67534.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>interactive order form as part of <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> exhibition, The ArQuives Digital
                  Collections</figDesc>
            </figure>
            
         
         <p>This order form uses simple image-mapping technologies built into the Neatline plugin in
            order to remediate the affective experience of receiving, completing, and mailing a
            paper order form, for <q>born digital</q> users who may never have had to send away for a
            publication this way. As Brouwer and Licona, but also Kate Eichhorn and Jenna Freedman,
            have all argued, tactility, records of wear, use, of making, reading, and photocopying
            together, or for others, are fundamental to the status of zines as media <ptr target="#eichhorn2013"/>. Recreating this order form online
            reproduces the experience of touching, choosing, sifting and sorting within a digital
            interfaces, or at the very least, shows users that this experience might have taken
            place by organizing the collection around the pre-printed form as a media infrastructure
            of engagement. These are affective gestures that form part of what it means to
            participate in trans material cultures. </p>
         <p>Like our reflections on making data, a critical transmediation practice required us to
            insert our own processes of encountering <q>the originals</q> in the stories we told to users
            about making these digital collections. To launch and contextualize each collection, we
            produced podcasts, through a workshop format lead by Stacey Copeland, a feminist
            podcast-maker, radio host, and doctoral candidate at Simon Fraser University. As Hannah
            McGreggor argues, learning podcasting develops technical skills from which queer, trans,
            and racialized communities, outsiders to normative representations of <q>maker cultures,</q>
            are often excluded. Podcasting is not actually that difficult, technically speaking, and
            allows students to engage with processes of making that enrich humanities education and
            provides opportunities for self-expression. In each of these podcasts, students found
            ways to place themselves within the stories they told about making digital collections. </p>
         <p>For the <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> podcast, two team members narrated the process of unboxing some of
            the Ross fonds in real-time, in a recording that captures the excitement that comes
            along with touching trans historical documents for the first time. They digitized
            selections from Ross’s collection, in order to include audio from Vaginal Davis and Robespierre’s 1994 punk
            anthem, <title rend="italic">Queens (Make the World Go Round)</title>, situating their unboxing processes in an
            immersive engagement with what Ross’ acoustic environment might have been like while
            making <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title> <ptr target="#mcgreggor2017"/>. Mapping of the Foolscap interviews led another set of team members
            to understand the importance of space for gay men in a transnational context, as one of
            the grad students revisited his own memories of these geographies in Mexico City. Their
            podcast edited original interview clips in ways that brought stories of being in these
            spaces to life, for example, adding the sounds of a summer thunderstorm to a clip in
            which a narrator describes seeking shelter from the rain in a bandstand with another man
            who would quickly become a lover. Two members of the team described what it felt like
            being brown and queer and encountering these records of a history in which you might
            locate yourself. As one of our group described it in their podcast, <quote rend="inline">I wish that a
            community as large and as strong as Desh still existed. What amazes me is that in 2017,
            I don’t feel the same sense of empowerment as Natasha. With Desh, people weren’t alone,
            and had the space to explore their identity within the safety of a group that feels the
            same way.</quote> Through these podcast stories, creating queer, trans, and P.O.C.-centred
            digital collections became precisely about critical forms of inheritance, finding an
            explicitly queer, trans, brown, or anti-racist history of the city that mirror
            experiences today, while recognizing differences that matter. </p></div>
         <div>
         <head>Conclusion </head>
         <p>Our experiments with trans(affective)mediation techniques drew on critical approaches to
            digital mapping, writing queer and trans metadata, and building online interfaces in
            order to offer users engagements with the past that were also engagements with how
            digital collections get made. Our work together and our reflections on collaboration
            brought forward some challenges, which will shape our work in the future. As we have suggested here, while aspects of our research
            design limited the ability of our finished collections to fully realize the anti-racist,
            intersectional approach to queer and trans history we aimed for, we believe our approach
            offers critical DH practitioners many entries to thinking about digital archives and the
            labouring conditions that shape how queer and trans scholars, students, and activists do
            research together. Our work is one instance of how social justice-engaged university
            researchers from all stages of academic life can collaborate with community groups to
            produce digital collections that transmediate our relationships to the past: this
            aspirational process draws connections across communities of struggle by breaking down
            more rigid archival logics; it can re-write the database forms and standards used to
            describe and mediate access to collections; and in turn, can offer ways to re create the
            tactile and affective dimensions of <q>touching</q> queer and trans histories. </p></div>
         
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
         	<bibl xml:id="antiEvictionMappingProject" label="The Anti-Eviction Mapping Project" sortKey="AntiEvictionMappingProject"><title rend="italic">The Anti-Eviction Mapping Project: Documenting the Dispossession and Resistance of SF Bay Area Residents</title>, <ref target="http://www.antievictionmap.com/">http://www.antievictionmap.com</ref></bibl>  
         	<bibl xml:id="barriault2009" label="Barriault 2009"> Barriault, M. <title rend="quotes">Archiving the Queer and Queering the Archives: A Case Study of the Canadian Lesbian and Gay Archives (CLGA),</title> <title rend="italic">Community Archives: The Shaping of Memory</title>. Facet, London (2009): 97–108.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benjamin1969" label="Benjamin 1969"> Benjamin, W. <title rend="quotes">The Work of Art in the Age of Mechanical Reproduction,</title> in <title rend="italic">Illumination</title>s, Schocken, New York (1969): 217-251.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boellstorff2014a" label="Boellstorff et al. 2014a"> Boellstorff, T. Cabral, m. cardenas, M. Cotten, T. Stanley, E.A. Young, K. and Aizura, A.Z. <title rend="quotes">Decolonizing Transgender: A Roundtable,</title> <title rend="italic">TSQ: Transgender Studies Quarterly</title>, 1.3 (2014): 419-439.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berman2008" label="Berman 2008"> Berman, S. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Cataloging Reform, LC, and Me,</title> In <title rend="italic">Radical Cataloging: Essays at the Front</title>, edited by K.R. Roberto, 5–11. Jefferson NC and London: MacFarland and Company, 2008.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bolter2000" label="Bolter 2000"> Bolter, J.D. and Grusin, R. <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding New Media. </title>MIT Press, Cambridge (2000).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowker1999" label="Bowker 1999"> Bowker, G. and Star, S.L. <title rend="italic">Sorting Things Out.</title> MIT Press, Cambridge (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brouwer2016" label="Brouwer 2016"> Brouwer, D.C. and Licona, A.C. <title rend="quotes">Trans(Affective)Mediation: Feeling Our Way from Paper to Digitized Zines and Back Again,</title> <title rend="italic">Critical Studies in Media Communication</title>, 33.1 (2016): 72.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brown2011" label="Brown 2011"> Brown, A. <title rend="quotes">How Queer ‘Pack Rats’ and Activist Archivists Saved Our History: An Overview of Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer (LGBTQ) Archives, 1970–2008,</title> <title rend="italic">Serving LGBTIQ Library and Archive Users: Essays on Outreach, Service, Collections and Access</title> (2011): 121–35.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brown2020" label="Brown 2020"> Brown 2020. Brown, E. <title rend="quotes">Archival Activism, Symbolic Annihilation, and the LGBTQ2+ Community Archive,</title> <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 89 (2020):6-32.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boellstorff2014b" label="Boellstorff et al. 2014b"> Boellstorff, T. Cabral, m. cardenas, M. Cotten, T. Stanley, E.A. Young, K. and. Aizura, A.Z. <title rend="quotes">Decolonizing Transgender: A Roundtable,</title> <title rend="italic">TSQ: Transgender Studies Quarterly</title> 1.3 (2014): 419-439.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boyd2012" label="Boyd 2012"> Boyd, N.A. and Ramírez, H.N.R. eds., <title rend="italic">Bodies of Evidence: The Practice of Queer Oral History,</title> Oxford Oral History Series. Oxford University Press, New York City (2012).
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick 2012"> Burdick, A. Drucker, J. Lunenfeld, P. Presner, T. and Schnapp, J. <title rend="italic">Digital_Humanities</title>. MIT Press, Cambridge (2012): 24.</bibl>
           
            <bibl xml:id="caswell2014" label="Caswell 2014b"> Caswell, M. <title rend="quotes">Seeing Yourself in History: Community Archives and the Fight against Symbolic Annihilation,</title> <title rend="italic">The Public Historian</title> 36.4 (2014): 26–37.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="caswell2016" label="Caswell 2016"> Caswell, M. and Cifor, M. <title rend="quotes">From Human Rights to Feminist Ethics: Radical Empathy in the Archives,</title> <title rend="italic">Archivaria</title>, 81 (2016): 23.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="caswell2017" label="Caswell 2017"> Caswell, M. Migoni, A. Geraci, N. Cifor, M.. <title rend="quotes">‘To Be Able to Imagine Otherwise’: Community Archives and the Importance of Representation,</title> <title rend="italic">Archives and Records</title> 38.1 (2017): 5–26</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chauncey1994" label="Chauncey 1994"> Chauncey, G. <title rend="italic">Gay New York: Gender, Urban Culture, and the Makings of the Gay Male World, 1890-1940.</title> New York: Basic Books, New York City (1994).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chenier2015" label="Chenier 2015"> Chenier, E. <title rend="quotes">Privacy Anxieties: Ethics versus Activism in Archiving Lesbian Oral History Online,</title> <title rend="italic">Radical History Review</title>, 122 (2015): 129–41.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chun2006" label="Chun 2006"> Chun, W.H.K. <title rend="italic">Control and Freedom: Power and Paranoia in the Age of Fiber Optics.</title> MIT Press, Cambridge (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chun2009" label="Chun 2009"> Chun, W.H.K. <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Race and/as Technology; or, How to Do Things to Race,</title> <title rend="italic">Camera Obscura</title>, 24.1.70 (2009): 7–35.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chun2014" label="Chun 2014"> Chun, W.H.K. and Rhody, L.M. <title rend="quotes">Working the Digital Humanities: Uncovering Shadows between the Dark and the Light,</title> <title rend="italic">Differences</title>, 25.1 (2014): 1–25.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="churchill2004" label="Churchill 2004"> Churchill, D. <title rend="quotes">Mother Goose’s Map,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Urban History</title>, 30.6 (2004): 826-852.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cifor2016a" label="Cifor 2016a"> Cifor, M. <title rend="quotes">Affecting Relations: Introducing Affect Theory to Archival Discourse,</title> <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title> 16.1 (2016): 13. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cifor2016b" label="Cifor 2016b"> Cifor, M. <title rend="quotes">Aligning Bodies: Collecting, Arranging, and Describing Hatred for a Critical Queer Archives,</title> <title rend="italic">Library Trends</title>; Baltimore, 64.4 (Spring 2016): 756–75.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cifor2017" label="Cifor 2017"> Cifor, M. <title rend="quotes">Stains and Remains: Liveliness, Materiality, and the Archival Lives of Queer Bodies,</title> <title rend="italic">Australian Feminist Studies</title>, 32.91–92 (2017): 5–21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="clare2017" label="Clare 2017"> Clare E. <title rend="italic">Brilliant Imperfection: Grappling with Cure.</title> Duke University Press, Durham (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bastian2009" label="Bastian and Alexander 2009"> Bastian, J.A. and Alexander, B. <title rend="quotes">Community Archives: the Shaping of Memory</title> In Bastian, J.A. and Alexander, B. (eds), <title rend="italic">Facet Publishing</title>, London (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="conghuyen2015" label="Cong-Huyen 2015"> Cong-Huyen, A. <title rend="quotes">Toward a Transnational Asian/American Digital Humanities: A #transformDH Invitation,</title> in <title rend="italic">Between Humanities and the Digital</title>, Svensson, P. and Goldberg, D.T. (eds). MIT Press, Cambridge (2015):109-120.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cowan2018" label="Cowan 2018"> Cowan, T.L. <title rend="quotes">The Internet of Bawdies: Transmedial Drag and the Onlining of Trans-Feminist and Queer Performance Archives, a Workshop Essay,</title> <title rend="italic">First Monday</title>, 23.7 (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="crenshaw1991" label="Crenshaw 1991"> Crenshaw, K. <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Margins: Intersectionality, Identity Politics, and Violence Against Women of Color,</title> <title rend="italic">Stanford Law Review</title> 43 (1991): 1241-1299.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="despain2016" label="DeSpain 2016"> DeSpain, J. <title rend="quotes">A Feminist Digital Humanities Pedagogy beyond the Classroom,</title> <title>Transformations: The Journal of Inclusive Scholarship and Pedagogy</title>, 26.1 (2016): 66. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="duff2002" label="Duff 2002"> Duff W.M. and Harris, V. <title rend="quotes">Stories and Names: Archival Description as Narrating Records and Constructing Meanings,</title> <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 2.3 (2002): 263–285.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="earhart2016" label="Earhart 2016"> Earhart, A.E. <title rend="quotes">Digital Humanities Futures: Conflict, Power, and Public Knowledge,</title> <title rend="italic">Digital Studies / Le Champ Numérique</title>, 0.0 (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eichhorn2013" label="Eichhorn 2013"> Eichhorn, K. <title rend="italic">The Archival Turn in Feminism: Outrage in Order.</title> Temple University Press, Philadelphia (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="everett2002" label="Everett 2002"> Everett, A. <title rend="quotes">The Revolution Will Be Digitized: Afrocentricity and the Digital Public Sphere,</title> <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>, 20.2 (2002): 125–46.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="everett2009" label="Everett 2009"> Everett, A. <title rend="italic">Digital Diaspora: A Race for Cyberspace.</title> State University of New York Press, Albany (2009).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fernandez2006" label="Fernandez 2006"> Fernandez, S. <title rend="quotes">More Than an Arts Festival: Communities, Resistance, and the Story of Desh Pardesh.</title> <title rend="italic">Canadian Journal of Communication</title>, 31.1 (2006): n. pag. Web.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flinn2009a" label="Flinn 2009a"> Flinn, A. Stevens, M. and Shepherd, E. <title rend="quotes">Whose Memories, Whose Archives? Independent Community Archives, Autonomy and the Mainstream,</title> <title rend="italic">Archival Science</title>, 9.1–2 (2009): 71–86.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flinn2009b" label="Flinn 2009b"> Flinn, A. and Stevens, M. <title rend="quotes">‘It Is Noh Mistri, Wi Mekin Histri.’Telling Our Own Story: Independent and Community Archives in the UK, Challenging and Subverting the Mainstream,</title> <title rend="italic">Community Archives: The Shaping of Memory, Principles and Practice in Records Management and Archives.</title> Facet Publishing, London (2009): 3–27.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="flinn2011" label="Flinn 2011"> Flinn, A. <title rend="quotes">Archival Activism: Independent and Community-Led Archives, Radical Public History and the Heritage Professions,</title> <title rend='italic'>InterActions: UCLA Journal of Education and Information Studies </title>7.2 (2011). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="freedman2012" label="Freedman 2012"> Freedman, J. <title rend="quotes">Self-publication with Riot Grrrl ideals,</title> in Bly, L. and Wooten, K. (eds), <title rend="italic">Make Your Own History: Documenting Feminist and Queer Activism in the 21st Century</title>. Litwin Books, Sacramento (2012).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gieseking2018" label="Gieseking 2018"> Gieseking, J.J. <title rend="quotes">Where Are We? The Method of Mapping with GIS in Digital Humanities,</title> <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 70.3 (2018): 642.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="godden2016" label="Godden 2016"> Godden, R. and Jonathan, H. <title rend="quotes">Universal Design and Its Discontents.</title> <title rend="italic">Disrupting the Digital Humanities.</title> Last modified (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gopinath2005" label="Gopinath 2005"> Gopinath, G. <title rend="italic">Impossible Desires: Queer Diasporas and South Asian Public Cultures.</title> Duke University Press, Durham (2005).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grube1997" label="Grube 1997"> Grube, J. <title rend="quotes">‘No More Shit’: The Struggle for Democratic Gay Space in Toronto,</title> In <title rend="italic">Queers in Space: Communities/Public Places/Sites of Resistance</title>, In Ingram, G.B. Bouthillette, A. and Retter, Y. (eds) Bay Press, San Francisco (1997): 127–45. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grube1986" label="Grube 1986"> Grube, J. <title rend="quotes">Queens and Flaming Virgins: Towards a Sense of a Gay Community,</title> <title rend="italic">Rites</title>, 2.9 (1986): 14-17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grube1991" label="Grube 1991"> Grube, J. <title rend="quotes">Natives and Settlers: An Ethnographic Note on Early Interaction of Older Homosexual Men with Younger Gay Liberationists,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Homosexuality</title>, 20.3-4, (1991): 119-136.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gumbs2011" label="Gumbs 2011"> Gumbs, A.P. <title rend="quotes">Seek the Roots: An Immersive and Interactive Archive of Black Feminist Pratice,</title> <title rend="italic">Feminist Collections: A Quarterly of Women’s Studies Resources</title>, 32.1 (2011): 17.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ha2017" label="Ha 2017"> Ha, V. and Daulet, M. <title rend="quotes">The Invisible Visibles and CelebrAsian,</title> in Stephanie Chambers et al., eds., <title rend="italic">Any Other Way: How Toronto Got Queer</title>. Coach House Books, Toronto (2017): 224-226.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jenkins2017" label="Jenkins 2017"> Jenkins 2017. Jenkins, H. <title rend="italic">Transmedia Education: The 7 Principles Revisited,</title> <title rend="italic">Henry Jenkins</title>, accessed July 1, 2017, <ref target="http://henryjenkins.org/blog/2010/06/transmedia_education_the_7_pri.html">http://henryjenkins.org/blog/2010/06/transmedia_education_the_7_pri.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jenkins2021" label="Jenkins 2021"> Jenkins, H. <title rend="quotes">Transmedia Education: The 7 Principles Revisited,</title> Henry Jenkins, accessed May 14, 2021, <ref target="http://henryjenkins.org/blog/2010/06/transmedia_education_the_7_pri.html">http://henryjenkins.org/blog/2010/06/transmedia_education_the_7_pri.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="johnson2011" label="Johnson 2011"> Johnson, E.P. <title rend="italic">Sweet Tea: Black Gay Men of the South</title>. University of North Carolina Press, Chapel Hill (2011).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="johnson2016" label="Johnson 2016"> Johnson, E.P. <title rend="quotes">Put a Little Honey in My Sweet Tea: Oral History as Quare Performance,</title> <title rend="italic">WSQ: Women’s Studies Quarterly</title>, 44.3–4 (2016): 51–67.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018"> Johnson, M. <title rend="quotes">4DH+ 1 Black Code/Black Femme Forms of Knowledge and Practice,</title> <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 70.3 (2018): 666–67.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kang2013" label="Kang 2013"> Kang, K. <title rend="italic">Seoul of Los Angeles: Contested Identities and Transnationalism in Immigrant Space</title>, PhD Thesis, University of Southern California (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="keeling2014" label="Keeling 2014"> Kara Keeling, <title rend="quotes">Queer OS,</title> <title rend="italic">Cinema Journal</title>, 53.2 (2014): 152–157.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kill2012" label="Kill 2012"> Kill, M. <title rend="quotes">Teaching Digital Rhetoric: Wikipedia, Collaboration, and the Politics of Free Knowledge</title> in Brett D. Hirsch, ed. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities Pedagogy: Practices, Principles and Politics</title>. Open Books Publisher, Cambridge (2012): 389-406.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lothian2013" label="Lothian 2013"> Lothian, A. and Phillips, A. <title rend="quotes">Can Digital Humanities Mean Transformative Critique?,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of E-Media Studies</title>, 3.1 (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mackay1993" label="Mackay 1993"> Mackay, X.P. <title rend="italic">gendertrash</title>, 1.1 (1993): 2.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mani2001" label="Mani 2001"> Mani, B. <title rend="quotes">Destination Culture.</title> <title rend="italic">SAMAR Magazine</title> 14 (2001): n. pag. Web. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maynard1994" label="Maynard 1994"> Maynard, S. <title rend="quotes">Through a Hole in the Lavatory Wall: Homosexual Subcultures, Police Surveillance, and the Dialectics of Discovery, Toronto, 1890-1930,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of the History of Sexuality</title>, 5.2 (1994): 207–42. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mccaskell2016" label="McCaskell 2016"> McCaskell, T. <title rend="italic">Queer Progress: from Homophobia to Homonationalism</title>. Toronto, ON: Between the Lines (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2012" label="McPherson 2012"> McPherson, T. <title rend="quotes">Why Are the Digital Humanities So White? Or, Rethinking the Histories of Race and Computation,</title> <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. University of Minnesota Press, Minnesota (2012): 139–60. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcgreggor2017" label="McGreggor 2017"> McGreggor, H. <title rend="quotes">Women, Podcasting, and Maker Culture,</title> Conference Paper at <title rend="italic">Canadian Society for Digital Humanities</title>. Ryerson University, Toronto (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2014" label="McPherson 2014"> McPherson, T. <title rend="quotes">Designing for difference,</title> <title rend='italic'>differences</title>. 25.1 (2014): 177-188.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mcruer2006" label="McRuer 2006"> McRuer, R. <title rend="italic">Crip Theory: Cultural Signs of Queerness and Disability.</title> New York University Press, New York City (2006).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moore2014" label="Moore 2014"> Moore, D.L. et al., <title rend="quotes">A Community’s Response to the Problem of Invisibility: The Queer Newark Oral History Project,</title> <title rend="italic">QED: A Journal in GLBTQ Worldmaking</title>, 1.2 (2014): 1–14.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moraga1983" label="Moraga 1983"> Moraga C.L., <title rend="quotes">Bringing the Strains Together,</title> from <title rend="italic">Loving in the War Years</title>, South End Press, Boston (1983): 123-126.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="munoz1999" label="Muñoz 1999"> Muñoz, J.E. <title rend="italic">Disidentifications: Queers of Color and the Performance of Politics.</title> University of Minnesota Press, Minnesota (1999).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murphy2016" label="Murphy 2016"> Murphy, K.P. Pierce, J.L. and Ruiz, J. <title rend="quotes">What Makes Queer Oral History Different,</title> <title rend="italic">Oral History Review</title>, 43.1 (2016): 1–24.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nakamura2008" label="Nakamura 2008"> Nakamura, L. <title rend="italic">Digitizing Race: Visual Cultures of the Internet.</title> University of Minnesota Press, Minnesota (2008). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nakamura2013a" label="Nakamura 2013"> Nakamura, L. <title rend="italic">Cybertypes: Race, Ethnicity, and Identity on the Internet</title>. Routledge, Oxfordshire (2013).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nakamura2013b" label="Nakamura and Chow-White 2013"> Nakamura, L. and Chow-White, P. <title rend="italic">Race After the Internet.</title> Routledge, Oxfordshire (2013)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nash2017" label="Nash 2017"> Nash, J.C., <title rend="quotes">Intersectionality and its Discontents,</title> <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 69.1 (2017): 117-129.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nieves2018" label="Nieves 2018"> Nieves, A.D. <title rend="quotes">Race, Critical Theory and Archive-Making in the Digital Humanities,</title> in D. Kim and J. Stommel (eds), <title rend="italic">Disrupting Digital Humanities</title>. New York, Punctum Books (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="noble2019" label="Noble 2019"> Noble, S. <title rend="italic">Algorithms of Oppression: How Search Engines Reinforce Racism.</title> New York University Press, New York City (2018).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nowviskie2014" label="Nowviskie 2014"> Nowviskie, B. <title rend="quotes">On the Origin of ‘Hack’ and ‘Yak,</title> nowviskie.com <ref target="http://nowviskie.org/2014/on-the-origin-of-hack-and-yack/">http://nowviskie.org/2014/on-the-origin-of-hack-and-yack/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="posner2015" label="Posner 2015"> Posner, M. <title rend="quotes">What’s Next: The Radical, Unrealized Potential of Digital Humanities,</title> MiriamPosner.com (2015):
               <ref target="http://miriamposner.com/blog/whats-next-the-radical-unrealized-potential-of-digital-humanities/"> http://miriamposner.com/blog/whats-next-the-radical-unrealized-potential-of-digital-humanities/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rawson2014" label="Rawson 2014"> Rawson, K.J. <title rend="quotes">The ‘Trans + Gender’ Project,</title> (2014) <ref target="http://kjrawson.net/trans-gender-timeline/">http://kjrawson.net/trans-gender-timeline/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2015" label="Risam 2015"> Risam, R. <title rend="quotes">Beyond the Margins: Intersectionality and the Digital Humanities,</title> <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 9.2 (2015). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rodriguez2017" label="Rodriguez 2017"> Rodriguez, A.B. <title rend="quotes">Teaching Guerilla Praxis: Making Critical Digital Humanities Research Politically Relevant,</title> <title rend="italic">Transformations: The Journal of Inclusive Scholarship and Pedagogy</title>, 27.2 (2017): 216. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rodriguez2016" label="Rodríguez 2016"> Rodríguez, R. <title rend="italic">Mapping QTBIPOC Toronto</title>, Master’s Thesis, York University (2016).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roberto2011" label="Roberto 2011"> Roberto, K.R. <title rend="quotes">Inflexible Bodies: Metadata for Transgender Identities,</title> <title rend="italic">Journal of Information Ethics</title> 20.2 (2011): 56–64.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ross1995" label="Ross 1995"> Ross, B. <title rend="italic">The House that Jill Built: A Lesbian Nation in Formation.</title> Toronto, ON: University of Toronto Press (1995).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ruiz2014" label="Ruiz 2014"> Ruiz, J. and Johnson, E.P. <title rend="quotes">Pleasure and Pain in Black Queer Oral History and Performance: E. Patrick Johnson and Jason Ruiz in Conversation,</title> <title rend="italic">QED: A Journal in GLBTQ Worldmaking</title> 1.2 (2014): 160–180.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sheffield2017" label="Sheffield 2017"> Sheffield, R. <title rend="quotes">Community Archives,</title> In MacNeil H. and Eastwood, T. (eds), <title rend="italic">Currents of Archival Thinking</title>, 2nd edition, Santa Barbara CA: Libraries Unlimited, ABC-CLIO (2017).</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="stoler2010" label="Stoler 2010"> Stoler, A.L.  <title rend="italic">Along the Archival Grain: Epistemic Anxieties and Colonial Common Sense.</title> Princeton University Press, Princeton (2010). </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="twincitiesglbt2020" label="Twin Cities GLBT Oral History Project 2020"> Twin Cities GLBT Oral History Project, 2020. Twin Cities GLBT Oral History Project ed., <title rend="italic">Queer Twin Cities</title>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press (2010)</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="walsh2019" label="Walsh 2019"> Walsh, B. <title rend="quotes">Frustration Is a Feature: Ugly Feelings and the Digital Humanities,</title> <title rend="italic">Pedagogy: Critical Approaches to Teaching Literature, Language, Composition, and Culture</title>, 19.3 (2019): 521.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ware2017" label="Ware 2017"> Ware, S.M. <title rend="quotes">All Power to All People? Black LGBTTI2QQ Activism, Remembrance, and Archiving in Toronto,</title> <title rend="italic">TSQ: Transgender Studies Quarterly</title>, 4.2 (2017): 170–80.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wencer2014" label="Wencer 2014"> Wencer, D. <title rend="quotes">Historicist: Here Comes the Equestrian Statue,</title> Torontoist, 6 December 2014, <ref target="http://torontoist.com/2014/12/historicist-here-comes-the-equestrian-statue/">http://torontoist.com/2014/12/historicist-here-comes-the-equestrian-statue/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="williams2012" label="Williams 2012"> Williams, G.H. <title rend="quotes">Disability, universal design, and the digital humanities.</title> <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2012): 202-12.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wolfe2008" label="Wolfe 2008"> Wolfe, J. <title rend="quotes">Playing Fast and Loose with the Rules: Metadata Cataloging for Digital Library Projects</title> In Roberto, K.R. (ed), <title rend="italic">Radical Cataloging: Essays at the Front.</title> McFarland and Company, London (2008): 69–74.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="yao2018" label="Yao 2018"> Yao, C. <title rend="quotes"># Staywoke: Digital Engagement and Literacies in Antiracist Pedagogy,</title> <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title> 70, 3 (2018): 439–54.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
