<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Radically Accessible Shakespeare: Cripping the
               Digital Shakespeare Canon through Universal Design and Disability Studies</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Christine M. <dhq:family>Gottlieb</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Cal State East Bay</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>christine.gottlieb@csueastbay.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Christine M. Gottlieb is an Assistant Professor of English at California State
                     University, East Bay. Support for this project was provided by a 2018-19
                     Faculty Support Grant from the California State University, East Bay Division
                     of Academic Affairs.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
         	<idno type="DHQarticle-id"
         		><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000659</idno>
         	<idno type="volume"
         		><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->017</idno>
         	<idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->1</idno>
         	<date when="2022-12-22">22 December 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Shakespeare</item>
                  <item>Universal Design</item>
                  <item>Disability Studies</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000659/000659.xml"
               >GitHub </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources, as well as the
               range of materials included in the Shakespeare canon. Online Shakespeare resources
               often focus on making Shakespeare more accessible to educators, students, and general
               audiences. Accessibility for people with disabilities, however, is not often
               mentioned. This article argues for making Shakespeare resources radically accessible
               and inclusive by incorporating both Universal Design approaches and Disability
               Studies perspectives. This dual approach emphasizes the importance of accessible
               technologies and the necessity of incorporating Disability Studies theories and
               methods, including contributions of Deaf and disabled artists and scholars and
               critical analyses of cultural representations of disability. While the
               overrepresentation of Shakespeare in digital space is problematic, the massive scope
               of Shakespeare’s online presence provides opportunities for radically transforming,
               or cripping, the digital canon. Cripping the digital Shakespeare canon involves
               centering accessibility, incorporating anti-ableist content, and promoting new
               methods of engaging with Shakespeare and digital spaces. Due to Shakespeare’s
               outsized presence, cripping the digital Shakespeare canon provides a significant
               avenue for advancing the accessibility and inclusivity of digital resources
               generally.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article argues for making Shakespeare resources radically accessible and
               inclusive by incorporating both Universal Design approaches and Disability Studies
               perspectives.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>The internet has vastly expanded access to Shakespeare resources and has led to the
               proliferation of born-digital Shakespeareana. Shakespeare exists online in archival
               materials, digital texts, apps, films, recordings of theatrical performances, YouTube
               videos, and other digital media. Shakespeare has enough of a digital presence to
               justify considering online Shakespeare a subset of the Digital Humanities field <ptr
                  target="#carson_kirwan2014" loc="pp. 1–2"/>. Articles in <title rend="italic"
                  >DHQ</title> testify to the innovations of Digital Humanities projects focused on
               Shakespeare and early modern studies (<ptr target="#lee_lee2017"/>; <ptr
                  target="#giglio_venecek2009"/>; <ptr target="#mueller2014"/>; <ptr
                  target="#jenstadetal2017"/>; <ptr target="#kelley2017"/>; <ptr target="#boyd2021"
               />). In addition to disseminating established forms of Shakespeare scholarship to
               wider audiences, online modalities allow opportunities for radically new
               interpretations, perspectives, and ways of interacting with Shakespeare to
               emerge.</p>
            <p>Making Shakespearean texts, performances, and scholarship more accessible to wider
               audiences motivates much of the online Shakespeare world. This view of Shakespeare’s
               accessibility often focuses on making materials more engaging, comprehensible, and
               freely available; accessibility for people with disabilities, however, is not often
               mentioned. While there has been productive scholarly dialogue between Disability
               Studies and Shakespeare studies (<ptr target="#hobgood_wood2013"/>; <ptr
                  target="#iyengar2015"/>; <ptr target="#rowheyveld2018"/>; <ptr target="#love2018"
               />; <ptr target="#dunn2020"/>; <ptr target="#loftis2021"/>; <ptr
                  target="#hobgood2021"/>; <ptr target="#schaapwilliams2021"/>), between Digital
               Humanities and Shakespeare studies (<ptr target="#hirsch_craig2014"/>; <ptr
                  target="#carson_kirwan2014"/>; <ptr target="#estill_jakacki_ullyot2016"/>; <ptr
                  target="#jenstadetal2018"/>; <ptr target="#oneill2019"/>; <ptr
                  target="#squeo_pennacchia_winckler2021"/>), and between Disability Studies and
               Digital Humanities (<ptr target="#williams2012"/>; <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018"/>;
                  <ptr target="#ellcessor2016"/>; <ptr target="#ellcessor2018"/>; <ptr
                  target="#hamraie2018"/>), it is necessary to foster further collaboration across
               these three interdisciplinary fields. Words like <q>accessible</q> and
                  <q>democratized</q> are often applied in discussions of online Shakespeare.
               However, until the world of online Shakespeare fully includes people with
               disabilities, it will not be truly accessible or democratized. Following Carson and
               Kirwan, I consider <quote rend="inline">the importance of Shakespeare as a case study
                  to understand the developing nature of the digital world</quote>
               <ptr target="#carson_kirwan2014" loc="p. 1"/>. In addition to providing a <q>case
                  study,</q> the world of online Shakespeare can be a site in which interventions
               are implemented and shared to enhance the accessibility and inclusivity of digital
               worlds more broadly.</p>
            <p>Scholars have illustrated the need for more inclusivity in Digital Humanities. The
               #TransformDH movement has drawn attention to how <quote rend="inline">Questions of
                  race, class, gender, sexuality, and disability should be central to digital
                  humanities and digital media studies</quote>
               <ptr target="#Baileyetal2016"/>. At the same time, Shakespeare’s outsized presence in
               Digital Humanities projects has been interpreted as a key example of the field’s
                  <quote rend="inline">canon problem</quote>
               <ptr target="#estill2019"/>. Laura Estill writes: <quote rend="inline">It has been
                  well-documented that major digital literary studies projects often focus on
                  canonical authors. [...] yet comparatively few scholars have critiqued how digital
                  humanities overrepresents perhaps the most canonical figure in all of English
                  literature: Shakespeare</quote>
               <ptr target="#estill2019"/>. While the overrepresentation of Shakespeare in digital
               space is problematic, the massive scope of Shakespeare’s online presence makes it a
               useful entry point for critically evaluating accessibility and advocating for the
               accessibility and inclusivity of digital resources generally. It is crucial to fund
               and build Digital Humanities projects that focus on marginalized authors and
               communities. In addition to supporting projects that decenter the canon, it is also
               useful to critically analyze how the Shakespeare canon is continually reimagined in
               digital environments, and to work toward making this expanding canon as diverse,
               inclusive, and accessible as possible.</p>
            <p>Digitization has already significantly transformed the Shakespeare canon. Douglas M.
               Lanier writes: <quote rend="inline">The disciplinary field of <q>Shakespeare</q> has
                  expanded dramatically in recent decades. […] <q>Shakespeare</q> now includes
                  performances, translations, transmediations, adaptations, appropriations, and even
                  memes, not just in English but also in myriad languages from around the
                  world</quote>
               <ptr target="#lanier2017" loc="p. 293"/>. Digital projects, such as the MIT Global
               Shakespeares Video &amp; Performance Archive, highlight the diversity of
               Shakespearean performance and curate an ever-expanding canon <ptr
                  target="#mitglobalshakespeares"/>. As digital projects related to Shakespeare
               continue to grow, it is crucial to continually reflect upon who is included in and
               excluded from the digital corpus that comprises <q>Shakespeare.</q> Productions of
               Shakespeare’s plays by Deaf and disabled artists and Shakespearean criticism by Deaf
               Studies and Disability Studies scholars<note>For a discussion of intersections and
                  tensions between Deaf Studies and Disability Studies, see <ptr
                     target="#burch_kafer2010"/>. I follow the convention of capitalizing Deaf,
                  which <quote rend="inline">distinguish[es] <term>deaf</term> (signifying an
                     auditory condition) from <term>Deaf</term> (signifying a coherent culture based
                     on shared language, identity, and history)</quote>
                  <ptr target="#burch_kafer2010" loc="p. xxi"/>. Bradbury <ptr
                     target="#bradbury2022"/> has critiqued distinctions between Deaf and deaf that
                  align the former with using ASL and the latter with not using ASL, writing: <quote
                     rend="inline">As someone who grew up oral (speaking and using assistive
                     listening devices) but is now fluent in ASL and immersed in the deaf community
                     professionally and personally, I find this nomenclature reductive and
                     exclusionary in its oppositional binaries</quote>
                  <ptr target="#bradbury2022" loc="pp. 49–50"/>.</note> are an integral part of the
               ever-expanding Shakespeare canon; these performances and perspectives can be further
               highlighted in digital projects.</p>
            <p>Since digital Shakespeare resources are widely used pedagogical tools, critical
               reflection upon their accessibility and inclusivity is especially urgent. A recent
               special issue in <title rend="italic">Research in Drama Education</title> examines
               the <quote rend="inline">diversity of pedagogical approaches to Shakespeare</quote>
               borne through Shakespeare’s overrepresentation in educational and digital spaces
               globally <ptr target="#bell_borsuk2020" loc="p. 1"/>. The special issue <quote
                  rend="inline">aim[s] to illustrate the cultural hegemonies present in teaching
                  Shakespeare on a global scale, and how digital technologies potentially maintain
                  these hegemonies, or confront them</quote>
               <ptr target="#bell_borsuk2020" loc="p. 3"/>. In a similar vein, this article argues
               that Shakespeare pedagogy and digital technologies can maintain or confront ableism.
               The <quote rend="inline">canon problem</quote>
               <ptr target="#estill2019"/> that Shakespeare’s massive online presence encapsulates
               also presents an opportunity to <quote rend="inline">crip the canon,</quote> to use
               Ann M. Fox’s phrase <ptr target="#fox2010"/>.<note>Fox explains the use of
                     <q>crip</q> as a reclaimed term that expresses pride, and as a verb that has
                  been used, like <q>queer,</q> to deconstruct binaries, writing: <quote
                     rend="inline"><q>to queer</q> or <q>to crip</q> the known is to twist our
                     expectations of it, defamiliarize it, and render it anew in ways that open up
                     new kinds of possibility. That promise is built on denying the very binarism
                     that would establish queer and crip identities as that against which,
                     respectively, <q>norms</q> of sexuality and ability can be defined</quote>
                  <ptr target="#fox2010" loc="p. 39"/>.</note> Universal Design and Disability
               Studies can be employed to crip the digital Shakespeare canon, transforming both
               Shakespeare studies and digital spaces. I argue that cripping the digital Shakespeare
               canon includes two main components: (1) incorporating Universal Design to create
               digital environments that are as accessible as possible and (2) incorporating
               Disability Studies perspectives and disability representation to create anti-ableist
               content. This dual approach emphasizes both the importance of accessible technology
               and the necessity of incorporating Disability Studies theories and methods, including
               highlighting the contributions of Deaf and disabled artists and scholars and
               critically analyzing cultural representations of disability. Integrating Universal
               Design and Disability Studies approaches can improve the accessibility of Shakespeare
               resources, create engaging and empowering instructional technologies, and allow
               interpretations of Shakespeare’s works by Deaf and disabled scholars and artists to
               reach wider audiences.</p>
            <p>In the following section, I provide an overview of Universal Design, review how it
               has been critiqued from Disability Studies perspectives, and discuss its continued
               importance for Digital Humanities projects. I then argue for centering disability in
               the digital Shakespeare canon and provide an overview of accessibility in Shakespeare
               studies. Following that, I analyze a key example of a digital work that expands the
               Shakespeare canon. I then analyze how YouTube functions as a digital Shakespeare
               archive with significant accessibility failures and discuss how Shakespeare’s
               overrepresentation in digital spaces can be utilized to improve accessibility.
               Finally, I discuss how crowdsourcing has been used and can continue to be used to
               improve accessibility. By highlighting both work that has been done to expand the
               canon and work that still must be done to make the expanding canon more accessible,I
               argue for engaging in ongoing critical reflection on the accessibility and
               inclusivity of the digital Shakespeare canon. Because of its canonicity, cripping
               online Shakespeare has the potential to impact digital archives generally by
               promoting increasingly accessible digital environments and anti-ableist content.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Universal Design</head>
            <p>Originally an architectural concept, Universal Design was developed by Ronald Mace
               who described it as <quote rend="inline">a way of designing a building or facility,
                  at little or no extra cost, so it is both attractive and functional for all
                  people, disabled or not</quote> (<ptr target="#mace1985"/> qtd. in <ptr
                  target="#hamraie2013"/>). George H. Williams has called for Digital Humanities
               projects to incorporate Universal Design, which he defines as <quote rend="inline"
                  >design that involves conscious decisions about accessibility for all</quote>
               <ptr target="#williams2012"/>.</p>
            <p>Aimi Hamraie’s critical analysis of Universal Design defines its key features in the
               following quote:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block"><list type="ordered">
                     <item>Accessibility by design (design that prioritizes accessibility)</item>
                     <item>Broad accessibility (accessibility for the greatest number of people
                        possible)</item>
                     <item>Added value (design that benefits disabled people also has benefits for
                        nondisabled people)</item>
                  </list></quote><ptr target="#hamraie2013"/></cit>
            <p>Drawing from feminist and disability theories, Hamraie critically analyzes these
               principles and discusses how Universal Design can be <quote rend="inline">a broad and
                  intersectional social justice method through which designers can address more
                  collective, overlapping, and intersectional exclusions from the built
                  environment</quote>
               <ptr target="#hamraie2013"/>.</p>
            <p>The purported <q>universality</q> of Universal Design has been critiqued (<ptr
                  target="#godden_hsy2018"/>; <ptr target="#hamraie2013"/>; <ptr
                  target="#hamraie2017"/>). Hamraie writes: <quote rend="inline">When the content of
                  the universal is unspecified, UD can slip into vague notions of <q>all</q> or
                     <q>everyone</q> that assume normate users and de-center disability</quote>
               <ptr target="#hamraie2013"/>. Hamraie emphasizes the importance of intersectional,
               disability justice-oriented approaches to design and focuses on <quote rend="inline"
                  >broad accessibility,</quote> writing: <quote rend="inline">Broad accessibility
                  serves as a more complex notion of inclusion, showing that UD must still center
                  disability access in order to avoid lapsing into the normate template</quote>
               <ptr target="#hamraie2013"/>.</p>
            <p>Richard H. Godden and Jonathan Hsy’s <title rend="quotes">Universal Design and Its
                  Discontents</title> is a Digital Humanities-focused critique of Universal Design.
               Godden writes: <quote rend="inline">Although UD arose out of a real social and
                  political response to the disabling aspects of everyday life for People with
                  Disabilities, I want to suggest that the <q>Universal</q> in UD can carry with it
                  some unintended and unexpected assumptions about normalcy and our physical
                  orientation to the world</quote>
               <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="p. 92"/>. Godden argues <quote rend="inline">we
                  need to move forward by balancing the Universalist and utopian aims of UD with a
                  more local, attentive approach to individual use</quote>
               <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="p. 100"/>. Hsy writes: <quote rend="inline">Both
                  UD and DH advocates often invoke an unrealized and idealized conception of
                  collective space (physical or online) in order to challenge dominant beliefs and
                  practices and to encourage people to join in a newly reconfigured sense of common
                  purpose</quote>
               <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="p. 101–2"/>.</p>
            <p>As Hamraie argues in a section entitled <title rend="quotes">Cripping Universal
                  Design,</title> while disability is often elided in Universal Design discourse,
               subsumed by an undertheorized concept of <q>universality,</q> the term <q>crip</q>
               powerfully centers disability, highlighting its critical, political, and cultural
               resonance <ptr target="#hamraie2017" loc="pp. 11–14"/>. Hamraie writes:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">in the early twenty-first century, around the time that
                  Universal Design became a predominantly disability-neutral discourse, critical and
                  crip theories of disability emerged to challenge the social model for
                  overemphasizing the environmental construction of disability oppression over
                  embodied experiences of disablement. <q>Crip,</q> a reclamation of the term
                     <q>cripple</q> dating to the 1970s independent living movement, resists
                  imperatives for normalization and assimilation. Crip theories contribute that
                  disability is a valuable cultural identity, a source of knowledge, and a basis for
                  relationality.</quote><ptr target="#hamraie2017" loc="p. 12"/></cit>
            <p>Following Hamraie, I use the term cripping in its radical reclaimed sense to address
               the problem of discussions of universality and accessibility frequently eliding
               disability. When universality and accessibility are discussed generally, in both
               Shakespeare studies and Digital Humanities discourse, people with disabilities are
               often left out. Cripping Universal Design centers people with disabilities in the
               project of building an inclusive digital Shakespeare world — or any digital or
               physical world.</p>
            <p>As Tanya Titchkosky <ptr target="#titchkosky2011"/> has shown, the structures and
               spaces of universities, and even bureaucratic attempts to create more <q>access,</q>
               are laden with and constitutive of conceptions about who belongs and what disability
               signifies. The same is true for digital spaces, and particularly academic digital
               spaces. As the physical and the virtual spaces of universities and knowledge
               circulation are increasingly blurred, attending to the digital worlds being created
               and analyzing who is constructed as <quote rend="inline"><emph>essentially
                     excludable</emph></quote>
               <ptr target="#titchkosky2011" loc="p. 39"/> is crucial. Titchkosky writes: <quote
                  rend="inline">I am particularly interested in how disability is socially produced
                  as something that is not yet considered an essential participant in social life.
                  Still, including disability as excludable is a scene where the meaning of the
                  concept of <q>all people</q> is forged</quote>
               <ptr target="#titchkosky2011" loc="p. 14"/>.</p>
            <p>Rather than promoting utopian fantasies of Shakespeare as <q>accessible to all</q> or
               design that is truly universal, I call for more attention to be paid to exclusions of
               disability in the world of digital Shakespeare, and in digital worlds generally.
               While truly Universal Design may be impossible, it is still a useful framework for
               pursuing increased accessibility. While truly universal access may be unattainable,
               we can still critique and correct inaccessibility, moving in the direction of
               broadened access.</p>
            <p>Similarly, cripping the digital Shakespeare canon entails critiquing, rather than
               reinforcing, Shakespeare’s purported <q>universality.</q> In advocating for inclusive
               Shakespeare programs and performances, Sonya Freeman Loftis cautions against <quote
                  rend="inline">the failure of universal design and the way in which universal
                  design may become bound up with notions about <q>universal</q> Shakespeare</quote>
               <ptr target="#loftis2021" loc="p. 79"/>. The salience of <q>universality</q> and
                  <q>access</q> in Shakespeare studies highlights the need to incorporate the
               Disability Studies critiques of these concepts in the interdisciplinary field.</p>
            <p>My argument for cripping the digital Shakespeare canon is founded on Shakespeare’s
               ubiquity, not universality. Considering the size of Shakespeare’s massive presence
               online and how often these resources are used for educational purposes, the world of
               online Shakespeare should be a driving force in advancing Universal Design
               approaches. When Shakespeare resources are not fully accessible, people with
               disabilities — scholars and non-scholars alike — are excluded from exploring and
               co-creating the digital Shakespeare canon. Moreover, incorporating Universal Design
               principles into online Shakespeare resources enhances their pedagogical potential for
               a broad range of users. Captions on videos of Shakespearean performances make the
               work accessible to Deaf and hard-of-hearing audiences, while also aiding
               comprehension for hearing audiences. Descriptions of visual images make paintings
               accessible to blind users and can provide significant details to sighted audiences as
               well. While incorporating Universal Design increases accessibility and can deepen
               engagement for a broad range of users, attentiveness to Disability Studies theory is
               necessary to combat the tendency to reproduce notions of <q>universal</q> and
                  <q>access</q> that exclude disability (<ptr target="#hamraie2013"/>; <ptr
                  target="#hamraie2017"/>; <ptr target="#titchkosky2011"/>; <ptr
                  target="#godden_hsy2018"/>).</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Cripping the Digital Shakespeare Canon</head>
            <p>In addition to designing digital resources that are more accessible, cripping the
               digital Shakespeare canon must also include analyzing how disability is represented
               in online content. Shakespeare’s plays are full of characters with disabilities that
               require critical analysis, as Allison P. Hobgood and David Houston Wood discuss in
               their introduction to <title rend="italic">Recovering Disability in Early Modern
                  England</title>:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">Shakespeare’s creative output encompasses a broad range of
                  disabled selfhoods: it moves across a spectrum from bodily to metaphysical
                  disfigurement, ranging from instances of blindness to limping, from alcoholism to
                  excessive fat, from infertility to war wounds, from cognitive impairments to
                  epilepsy, from senility to <q>madness,</q> and from feigned disability to
                  actual.</quote><ptr target="#hobgood_wood2013" loc="p. 11"/></cit>
            <p>Shakespeare’s representations of disability can either reinforce or challenge ableism
               depending on how the plays are taught in classrooms, performed on stage and in film,
               and — crucially — presented online. Online resources may reinforce stereotypes by
               presenting Shakespeare’s representations of physical and mental differences without
               the critical awareness that Disability Studies provides. Cripping the digital
               Shakespeare canon entails both correcting inaccessible digital forms and confronting
               ableist content.</p>
            <p>Digital humanists can learn from pedagogical and theatrical experiments in cripping
               content and increasing accessibility. In <title rend="quotes">How to Crip the
                  Undergraduate Classroom: Lessons from Performance, Pedagogy, and
                  Possibility,</title> Fox outlines methods to center disability in courses and on
               campuses <ptr target="#fox2010"/>. In a section entitled <title rend="quotes"
                  >Cripping the Canon,</title> Fox asks: <quote rend="inline">how do we make the
                  knowledge about and creative work of disabled people (including activists,
                  educators, artists, scholars, and thinkers) available to our students within our
                  classrooms?</quote>
               <ptr target="#fox2010" loc="p. 39"/>. She poses the question: <quote rend="inline"
                  >Where could I locate the presence of disability into that which I was already
                  teaching?</quote>
               <ptr target="#fox2010" loc="p. 39"/>. These questions can animate not only
               classrooms, but also the world of online Shakespeare and Digital Humanities projects
               generally. Digital humanists can <quote rend="inline">locate the presence of
                  disability</quote>
               <ptr target="#fox2010" loc="p. 39"/> by making accessibility, inclusivity, and
               critical analysis of representations of disability integral parts of their projects.
               Cripping the canon involves not only giving critical attention to disability-related
               content, but also to expanding academic epistemologies; Fox writes: <quote
                  rend="inline">To crip the canon might also mean cripping our rather canonical ways
                  of reading, researching, and otherwise approaching and engaging an individual
                  discipline, its core ideas and subject matter, introducing or framing them instead
                  with a disability perspective</quote>
               <ptr target="#fox2010" loc="p. 40"/>. Cripping the digital Shakespeare canon requires
               going beyond making digital materials usable by people with disabilities; it entails
               incorporating critical Disability Studies perspectives, increasing disability
               representation, analyzing how digital materials are reinforcing or combatting
               ableism, and considering whose perspectives are represented or omitted. This can be
               applied to not only to digital Shakespeare resources, but also to digital projects
               generally. The range and volume of Shakespearean material online makes it a useful
               site for evaluating accessibility and inclusivity, developing practices that can be
               applied more widely, and, more radically, reimagining and reinventing both the canon
               and methods of engaging with it. Cripping Shakespeare — the center of the English
               literary canon — transforms our understanding not only of Shakespeare’s poems and
               plays, but also of literary studies and digital environments more broadly.</p>
            <p>Sonya Freeman Loftis’s recent book, <title rend="italic">Shakespeare and Disability
                  Studies</title>, makes a compelling case for <title rend="quotes">Cripping
                  Shakespeare Studies</title>
               <ptr target="#loftis2021" loc="p. 15"/>. Loftis analyzes how Shakespeare’s canonicity
               and ubiquity have promoted a focus on accessibility, writing:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">Over the past twenty years, Shakespeare theatres have been
                  particularly innovative in the area of accessibility. This is, in part, because
                  modern Shakespearians have always been driven by the need for access. Shakespeare
                  has a central place in the curriculum, and making Shakespeare accessible to
                  students has long been a goal in the modern classroom. […] four hundred years have
                  already reduced the accessibility of the source text for lay readers and
                  audiences. Indeed, popular culture often depicts Shakespeare as inherently
                  difficult to understand. Shakespeare has become the classic symbol of that which
                  is highbrow, and teachers and directors are charged with making his work
                  accessible for everyone — from popular audiences to reluctant high schoolers. This
                  means that Shakespearians are in a natural position to consider disability access;
                  it makes sense that Shakespeare theatres would approach disability as just one
                  more point of potential inaccessibility.</quote><ptr target="#loftis2021"
                  loc="p. 11–12"/></cit>
            <p>As Loftis has shown, a commitment to making Shakespeare accessible has led to
               Shakespeare theaters becoming leaders in inclusive performance. Loftis writes: <quote
                  rend="inline">it is natural that an emphasis on general accessibility would lead
                  to increased disability awareness — in the wake of the disability rights movement
                  and in light of the growing neurodiversity movement, the endeavour to create
                     <q>access for all</q> must also include those with physical and mental
                  disabilities</quote>
               <ptr target="#loftis2021" loc="p. 53"/>. People working on online Shakespeare
               projects, and indeed, digital humanists generally, should have the same goal of
               becoming leaders in accessibility. Access is not only a key term in Shakespeare
               studies, it is also a central concept in Digital Humanities discourse. Ellcessor
               writes: <quote rend="inline">Digital tools and services are routinely lauded for
                  their ability to increase <emph>access</emph> to texts, resources, educational
                  experiences, and new forms of pedagogy. Yet, merely making material available is
                  insufficient to promote genuine access</quote>
               <ptr target="#ellcessor2018" loc="p. 108"/><note>In <title rend="italic">Restricted
                     Access: Media, Disability, and the Politics of Participation</title>, Ellcessor
                  provides an <q>access kit</q> to facilitate studying media access <ptr
                     target="#ellcessor2016" loc="pp. 17–19"/>.</note></p>
            <p>In discussing inventive approaches to accessibility by Shakespeare’s Globe, the Royal
               Shakespeare Company, and the Oregon Shakespeare Festival, Loftis writes: <quote
                  rend="inline">Access can be artistic — it can be an integral part of the
                  performance experience, shaping the interpretation both of the show and of
                  Shakespeare’s text</quote>
               <ptr target="#loftis2021" loc="p. 12"/>. The same spirit of accessibility as
               innovation can be foregrounded in digital Shakespeare projects, and in Digital
               Humanities projects generally. Loftis writes: <quote rend="inline">an understanding
                  of disability theory is essential for scholars, teachers, and directors of
                  Shakespeare. Statistics suggest that as many as one out of four people could
                  potentially be considered as disabled. Since providing quality accommodations and
                  pedagogical materials for users with disabilities requires a basic understanding
                  of disability theory, teachers and directors of Shakespeare who wish to reach
                  general audiences have a good reason to engage with disability studies</quote>
               <ptr target="#loftis2021" loc="p. 10"/>. Similarly, it is essential that creators of
               digital Shakespeare resources — and indeed, all digital resources — have an awareness
               of Disability Studies. As Loftis notes, incorporating disability theory entails
               valuing the knowledge that comes from lived experience, and thus including people
               with disabilities in projects’ leadership positions <ptr target="#loftis2021"
                  loc="p. 11"/>. In her review of inclusive Shakespeare theaters, Loftis notes that
                  <quote rend="inline">accessibility is always a work in progress, never a static
                  end goal that can be achieved</quote>
               <ptr target="#loftis2021" loc="p. 66"/>. Working toward making performances as
               accessible as possible requires ongoing collaboration with people with disabilities
               and a commitment to welcoming audience members with disabilities into the theater,
               which often begins by highlighting access through the theater’s website <ptr
                  target="#loftis2021" loc="pp. 70–72"/>. Jill Marie Bradbury <ptr
                  target="#bradbury2022"/> provides a critical account of theatrical performances of
               Shakespeare that include ASL, written from her perspective as a deaf audience member.
               Bradbury writes: <quote rend="inline">I argue that hearing directors who work with
                  deaf actors and ASL have an ethical responsibility to be inclusive of deaf
                  audiences. This can be accomplished by centering deaf perspectives and experiences
                  both onstage and in front-of-house practices</quote>
               <ptr target="#bradbury2022" loc="p. 45"/>.</p>
            <p>What would it mean to truly welcome Deaf and disabled people into the world of online
               Shakespeare? How could the digital Shakespeare canon be more accessible and
               inclusive? I have been arguing that this process includes incorporating Universal
               Design to increase the accessibility of digital content and incorporating Disability
               Studies perspectives to confront ableism in both form and content. In the next
               section, I will analyze a digital work that expands the Shakespeare canon through
               Universal Design and Deaf studies perspectives.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Expanding the Digital Shakespeare Canon: Tyrone Giordano and Jill Marie Bradbury’s
                  <title rend="italic">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title></head>
            <p>Tyrone Giordano and Jill Marie Bradbury’s <title rend="italic">Digit(al)
                  Shakespeares</title>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015"/> is a work of digital scholarship at the
               intersection of Deaf studies, Digital Humanities, and Shakespeare studies.The project
               consists of a 10-minute film, presented in ASL with English subtitles, and without
               audio. Crucially, the project also consists of a transcript and description of the
               video, which has been provided by Giordano and Bradbury as an integral part of the
               digital work. This delivery of the content through multiple forms exemplifies the
               Universal Design approach of <title rend="italic">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title>: it
               is designed, from the start, with accessibility built in. The high-quality transcript
               and description of the video makes the content accessible to screen reader users and
               provides rich descriptions of and contextual information for video clips included in
               the film, which enhances the learning experience for all users.</p>
            <p>The description of the project states:</p>
            <cit><quote rend="block">Digit(al) Shakespeares brings Deaf studies perspectives to bear
                  on both disability studies and digital humanities. Deaf studies focuses on what
                  the experience of deafness enables, rather than disables. Just as we can
                  reconceptualize hearing loss as deaf gain, so we can reframe Shakespeare’s works
                  as being at heart visual rather than auditory. This can lead to a richer
                  experience of Shakespeare for everyone, regardless of hearing status. Throughout
                  the video, clips illustrate the power of sign language to convey the Bard’s
                  virtuosity in creating images through words. New media and technology allow Deaf
                  people to share translations and performances of Shakespeare’s works across the
                  globe. Digital archives can collect and preserve these, so they are available for
                  Deaf, hard of hearing, and hearing people to study and appreciate. Deaf and hard
                  of hearing people also need access to digital Shakespeare archives based on spoken
                  language via high quality captioning. Access should be built into digital archives
                  from the start, so that it becomes a central element of the overall project
                  design, rather than a problem to be solved at the end.</quote><ptr
                  target="#giordano_bradbury2015"/></cit>
            <p>This description highlights the pedagogical and scholarly value that a Universal
               Design approach adds for all users, a centerpiece of Universal Design philosophy,
               through the claim that <quote rend="inline">This can lead to a richer experience of
                  Shakespeare for everyone</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015"/>. However, rather than tacitly endorsing an
               undertheorized <q>universal</q> subject, as Universal Design approaches have
               frequently done, the project powerfully centers Deaf perspectives, both in
               representational content (through curating and presenting a performance history of
               Shakespeare in ASL) and through digital design (by featuring built-in accessibility
               that centers ASL and by advocating for digital archives to be accessible to Deaf and
               hard of hearing people).</p>
            <p>The content, methodology, and design of Giordano and Bradbury’s project illuminate
               the scholarly, artistic, and social value of approaching Shakespeare from a Deaf
               perspective. The Universal Design of the project welcomes a broad range of users to
               engage with and respond to this significant and underrepresented approach to
               Shakespeare. Giordano and Bradbury highlight the need for more accessible digital
               archives while showcasing what is gained from studying Shakespeare from Deaf studies
               perspectives.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title> goes beyond Universal Design to
               decenter the customary privileging of hearing audiences. The lack of audio in the
               video both highlights the methodology of centering the visual over the auditory in
               the project’s approach to Shakespeare and decenters audist privilege. While the
               content of the digital work can be accessed by a broad range of users, hearing
               audiences are informed: <quote rend="inline">NOTE: There is no sound throughout the
                  video</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015"/>.</p>
            <p>Hsy has explored how the <title rend="italic">Deaf Studies Digital Journal</title>
                  (<title rend="italic">DSDJ</title>) decenters the privileging of hearing audiences
               by providing video of scholarship in ASL that is not always accompanied by English
               translations <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="pp. 107–109"/>. Hsy describes the
               productive tension of exploring <title rend="italic">DSDJ</title> in a workshop
               focused on increasing the accessibility of Digital Humanities projects: <cit><quote
                     rend="block">An intriguing aspect of the group discussion of <title
                        rend="italic">DSDJ</title> in the <title rend="italic">Accessible
                        Future</title> workshop in Austin in 2014 was the sense that the lack of
                     audio or captions in these videos make the content <q>inaccessible</q> by one
                     set of embodied norms (that is, a set of UD principles that would call for
                     embedded features for internet users who have visual impairments). As I reflect
                     on this conversation afterwards, I have come to realize that the uneven media
                     functionality of the journal suggested a discomforting social reality for those
                     of us who were present at that particular workshop: much of the content of this
                     Deaf-oriented journal was at the time rendered <emph>inaccessible to a hearing
                        majority</emph> (or, to put things more precisely, the online journal’s
                     content was only partially accessible to non-ASL users).</quote>
                  <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="p. 108"/></cit> As Hsy analyzes, this is an
               instance in which a digital work’s non-adherence to Universal Design principles is
               revelatory: <quote rend="inline">the current user interface appropriately forces me
                  to confront my own audiocentric (and Anglophone) privilege and I find myself
                  navigating an online linguistic environment that is only unevenly or partially
                  configured for my use</quote>
               <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="p. 109"/>. </p>
            <p>While <title rend="italic">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title> is broadly accessible due
               to its Universal Design approach, it still powerfully decenters the privilege of
               non-ASL users. While English subtitles appear during experts’ statements and some ASL
               Shakespeare performances, many clips of actors performing Shakespeare in ASL are not
               subtitled. The transcript and description of the video provide information about all
               of the clips included in the film, cataloguing a rich archive of ASL Shakespeare
               performance history. This combination of providing broad accessibility while
               centering Deaf perspectives makes <title rend="italic">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title>
               a strong example of a Digital Humanities work that incorporates Universal Design
               principles without tacitly endorsing a <q>universal</q> user and audist
               privilege.</p>
            <p>Giordano and Bradbury’s project highlights the potential of combining Digital
               Humanities and Deaf Studies approaches. Hsy analyzes how Giordano and Bradbury’s
               project <quote rend="inline">deftly exploits the manifold valence of the <q>digit</q>
                  in its pluralized title <title rend="italic">Digit(al)
                  Shakespeares</title></quote>
               <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="p. 107"/>. Viewing Shakespeare from a visual
               perspective fundamentally transforms the Shakespeare canon and opens up new modes of
               engagement that utilize possibilities that digital environments provide. Miako Rankin
               explains: <quote rend="inline">So much has happened in the last 15 years, with
                  smartphones, touchpad technology, video-to-video interaction, Deaf people are
                  interacting and communicating with one another more than ever before</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015" loc="06:33–06:48"/>. As Jill Bradbury discusses,
               this technology has a significant impact on Deaf approaches to Shakespeare: <quote
                  rend="inline">Digital technology is fast and cheap now, enabling Deaf people the
                  world over to experience Shakespeare’s poetry and create films and translations to
                  share so others might enjoy that work</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015" loc="06:48–07:00"/>.</p>
            <p>Bradbury continues: <quote rend="inline">It is paramount that we collect those films
                  and experiences, essentially forming a digital archive for us, not only to
                  preserve this work for future generations, but also to create a space where deaf
                  and hearing people both can study and appreciate the work</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015" loc="07:16–07:34"/>. Ethan Sinnott explains the
               enormous potential of digital archives: <quote rend="inline">All this becomes a
                  library, one that the Deaf community can access regardless of their background:
                  whether their interests lie in theatre, education, English, or if they are
                  interested in improving bilingual ASL-English access</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015" loc="07:00–07:16"/>.</p>
            <p>Online spaces provide significant opportunities to present and preserve ASL
               translations of Shakespeare. The ASL Shakespeare Project’s website <ptr
                  target="#ASLShakespeare"/>, which documents the process of translating
               Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">Twelfth Night</title> into ASL, is <quote
                  rend="inline">the first bilingual and bicultural website on Shakespeare on the
                  internet</quote>
               <ptr target="#novak2008" loc="p. 74"/>. The ASL Shakespeare Project, like Giordano
               and Bradbury’s <title rend="italic">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title> project, employs
               digital technologies to expand the Shakespeare canon.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Inaccessible Shakespeare Archive on YouTube</head>
            <p>The world of online Shakespeare includes spaces that encourage productive exchange
               between humanities scholars and the broader public. This traffic is not one-way:
               while scholars can reach wider audiences online, scholars and students routinely use
               online content created by non-academics. The Shakespeare canon is curated, adapted,
               and expanded in these digital spaces. For the evolving Shakespeare canon to be
               inclusive, these sites of exchange and engagement must be fully accessible.</p>
            <p>YouTube is a key platform on which this exchange occurs. Christy Desmet refers to
               YouTube as <quote rend="inline">what for the past decade has been one of the most
                  popular, most prevalent, and most innovative sources for teaching Shakespearean
                  drama</quote>
               <ptr target="#desmet2016" loc="p. 223"/>. Indeed, YouTube has transformed Shakespeare
               performance studies, as John Lavagnino writes: <quote rend="inline">YouTube was not
                  founded for the purpose of transforming the study of Shakespeare in performance by
                  providing a vastly larger range of material to see than had ever been available
                  before, but that was one of its effects. In this as in other areas of study,
                  digital approaches became prominent because they had vast numbers of people
                  outside the academy behind them</quote>
               <ptr target="#lavagnino2014" loc="p. 21"/>. YouTube users are producing a
               seemingly-democratized Shakespearean archive, as Stephen O’Neill describes: <quote
                  rend="inline">the small screens of YouTube grant access to an accidental archive
                  of Shakespeareana, to user-generated Shakespeares and to such genres as the video
                  mashup (combining one or more audio tracks with moving images, sometimes with
                  ironic effect), the vlog (or video diary) and the fan-made movie trailer</quote>
               <ptr target="#oneill2014" loc="pp. 2–3"/>.</p>
            <p>YouTube’s seemingly-democratized Shakespeare archive, however, is failing miserably
               when it comes to accessibility. Many Shakespeare videos do not have captions or use
               automatically generated captions that are grossly inaccurate when attempting to
               capture Shakespeare’s verse.<note>Rikki Poynter began the #NoMoreCRAPtions campaign
                  to raise awareness about rampant problems with automatically-generated captions
                  and the need for high-quality captions (<ptr target="#besner2019"/>; <ptr
                     target="#virdi2021" loc="p. 31"/>. For discussion of the importance of
                  captioning Shakespeare resources, see <ptr target="#giordano_bradbury2015"
                  />.</note> It is crucial that these videos are captioned accurately, especially
               since they are often used as educational resources. Accurate captions are both an
               essential accessibility feature and an aid to all users’ comprehension of
               Shakespearean language.</p>
            <p>Williams has surveyed ways in which the accessibility of Digital Humanities projects
               could be improved and offered suggestions, including crowdsourcing the captioning and
               transcriptions of video content <ptr target="#williams2012"/>. Shakespeare’s texts
               are freely available in Open Access digital formats,<note>For a discussion of open
                  source Shakespeare texts, see <ptr target="#murphy2010"/>. For a discussion of
                  teaching with digital Shakespeare texts, see <ptr target="#rowe2014"/>.</note>
               which can aid the captioning of Shakespeare videos. Crowdsourcing the captioning and
               transcriptions of digital Shakespeare videos could make use of the abundance of
               Shakespeare material online to significantly improve accessibility. This is an
               example of how Shakespeare’s overrepresentation in digital spaces (in both text and
               video) can be utilized to improve accessibility and model best practices for digital
               archives.</p>
            <p>YouTube’s community captions feature had the potential to be used to crowdsource
               captions in this way and radically improve the accessibility of the digital
               Shakespeare archive, yet this feature was discontinued on September 28, 2020 <ptr
                  target="#lyons2020"/>. Deaf YouTuber and advocate for captions Rikki Poynter has
               discussed the importance of this feature in Deaf, hard of hearing, and disability
               communities and critiqued YouTube’s failure to promote the feature, make it
               accessible on mobile devices, or improve the feature rather than dismantling it <ptr
                  target="#poynter2020"/>. While more YouTube users are now submitting their own
               captions due to increased awareness <ptr target="#odell2021"/>, much more remains to
               be done. Especially since YouTube has been transformative in Shakespeare studies, it
               is imperative that Shakespeareans raise awareness about accurately captioning the
               Shakespeare performance archive on YouTube. Doing so will not only improve the
               accessibility of the ever-growing Shakespeare canon, but will also increase awareness
               about the importance of captioning videos generally.</p>
            <p>In addition to captions, audio descriptions are needed to make the Shakespeare
               archive on YouTube accessible. Hamraie writes: <quote rend="inline">Miele’s
                  crowdsourcing technology, YouDescribe.org, enlists sighted people to
                  audio-describe YouTube videos, creating a database of integrated narrative tracks,
                  providing information not included in YouTube’s automatic textual captions</quote>
               <ptr target="#hamraie2018" loc="p. 476"/>. At the time of this writing, two
               audio-described videos were available when <q>Shakespeare</q> was searched on <title
                  rend="italic">YouDescribe</title>
               <ptr target="#youdescribe"/>. Especially since Shakespeare videos on YouTube are
               often used as educational resources, crowdsourcing audio descriptions for more
               Shakespeare content would be a valuable digital accessibility project.</p>
            <p>In addition to improving the accessibility of YouTube materials, it is important to
               critically analyze how disability is represented and performed in YouTube content.
               Ayanna Thompson has demonstrated that YouTube’s <quote rend="inline">large and
                  complex archive of classroom-inspired Shakespeare performances</quote> provides
                  <quote rend="inline">a window onto production and reception that highlights
                  uncomfortable aspects of the texts […] specifically, the dynamics of race and
                  gender</quote>
               <ptr target="#thompson2010" loc="p. 338"/>. Scholars have critically analyzed
               representations of race, gender, and sexuality in YouTubers’ Shakespeare adaptations
                  (<ptr target="#thompson2010"/>; <ptr target="#oneill2014"/>; <ptr
                  target="#iyengar_desmet2012"/>). More scholarship is needed on how physical and
               mental disability is represented and metatheatrically performed in
               Shakespeare-related YouTube videos. As the user-generated Shakespeare archive of
               YouTube continues to evolve, ongoing research into how intersections of race, gender,
               sexuality, and disability are represented is essential.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Crowdsourcing Shakespearean Accessibility</head>
            <p>In addition to improving the accessibility of YouTube videos, crowdsourcing can be
               used to make a wide range of digital content more accessible. Melissa Terras, in an
               introduction to <title rend="quotes">Crowdsourcing in the Digital Humanities,</title>
               writes: <cit><quote rend="block">Alongside the widespread success of collaboratively
                     produced resources such as <title rend="italic">Wikipedia</title> came a
                     movement in the cultural and heritage sectors to trial crowdsourcing – the
                     harnessing of online activities and behavior to aid in large-scale ventures
                     such as tagging, commenting, rating, reviewing, text correcting, and the
                     creation and uploading of content in a methodical, task-based fashion (Holley,
                     2010)–to improve the quality of, and widen access to, online
                     collections.</quote><ptr target="#terras2016"/></cit> While a general view of
                  <q>access</q> is highlighted here, crowdsourcing methods can be used to improve
               accessibility for people with disabilities <ptr target="#williams2012"/>.</p>
            <p>Victoria Van Hyning <ptr target="#vanhyning2019"/> has discussed how crowdsourcing
               can increase the accessibility of digital archives, particularly for archives of
               early books and manuscripts that cannot be rendered accurately through OCR. Van
               Hyning writes: <quote rend="inline">Virtual volunteers all around the world are eager
                  to learn and contribute to the vast project of making the world’s textual records
                  more widely accessible, not only for search, but for those, such as blind and
                  partially sighted people, who use screen readers</quote>
               <ptr target="#vanhyning2019" loc="p. 1"/>.</p>
            <p>Van Hyning discusses her work on the <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s World</title>
               project, a collaboration between Zooniverse (at which she was Humanities Principal
               Investigator), the Folger Shakespeare Library, and the <title rend="italic">Oxford
                  English Dictionary</title>. The project used crowdsourcing to transcribe early
               modern handwritten recipes and letters, which increases the accessibility of these
               texts for all users, expands the searchable digital archive, and provides early
               modern manuscript sources to be considered in the <title rend="italic">Oxford English
                  Dictionary</title>, which can increase the representation of women writers <ptr
                  target="#vanhyning2019" loc="p. 8"/>. Van Hyning writes: <cit><quote rend="block"
                     >The primary goal of <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s World</title> is to
                     create base transcriptions for <title rend="italic">Early Modern Manuscripts
                        Online</title> (https://emmo.folger.edu/) at the Folger Library, which
                     provides manuscript images and word searchable diplomatic, semi-diplomatic, and
                     regularized transcriptions. Manuscript curator Heather Wolfe and the creators
                     of <title rend="italic">EMMO</title> intend for it to democratize access to
                     manuscripts and to give manuscripts parity with print: the name is a deliberate
                     homage to <title rend="italic">EEBO and ECCO</title>.</quote><ptr
                     target="#vanhyning2019" loc="pp. 7–8"/></cit> Whitney Sperrazza’s review of
                  <title rend="italic">Early Modern Manuscripts Online</title> notes <quote
                  rend="inline">its unprecedented ability to bring together early modern scholars,
                  students, and wider public audiences around a digital resource</quote>
               <ptr target="#sperrazza2020" loc="p. 335"/>. Sperrazza discusses the project’s
               implications in relation to the democratization of paleography and accessibility of
               manuscripts.</p>
            <p>The success of the <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s World</title> project, and its
               media coverage, including Roberta Kwok’s <title rend="quotes">Crowdsourcing for
                  Shakespeare</title> article in <title rend="italic">The New Yorker</title>
               <ptr target="#kwok2017"/>, demonstrate how Shakespeare can motivate volunteers to
               participate in significant crowdsourcing projects, such as the transcription of
               non-Shakespearean materials produced during Shakespeare’s era. Building upon this, it
               is crucial to ensure that ever-growing online Shakespeare archives are fully
               accessible to people with disabilities. What would it look like to apply the
               crowdsourcing techniques of the <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s World</title>
               project to make the entire world of Shakespeare online more accessible? From
               manuscripts to YouTube, centering accessibility will expand access for people with
               disabilities and benefit all users. Centering accessibility is essential to
               recognizing the goal of democratizing access so often seen in online Shakespeare
               discourse, and in Digital Humanities discourse generally.</p>
            <p>Tyrone Giordano’s thesis, <title rend="quotes">Toward a Crowdsourced Model for ASL
                  Translations of Shakespeare’s Works</title>
               <ptr target="#giordano2013"/>, explores the possibilities that current digital
               technologies offer for sharing and preserving ASL translations of Shakespeare. The
               thesis <quote rend="inline">attempts to address the problem of lack of translation
                  material by proposing an internet-based crowdsourcing model to create and allow
                  for a multiplicity of and successive generations of ASL translations of
                  Shakespeare’s plays to exist</quote>
               <ptr target="#giordano2013" loc="p. viii"/>. Giordano writes: <cit><quote
                     rend="block">The increasing digitization of Shakespeare, and the market for
                     localization of Shakespeare’s texts, illustrates the need for an online
                     resource utilizing ASL in connection with Shakespeare. This leads to the
                     not-yet-realized vision of what I believe is the next level in ASL translation:
                     an open source internet-based project where anybody can input his or her own
                     translations of Shakespeare’s works, and those seeking a translated body of
                     work can pick and choose from among these translations, making the translations
                     their own.</quote><ptr target="#giordano2013" loc="pp. 5–6"/></cit> Giordano’s
               proposal balances collaboration and sharing of content with respect for translators’
               intellectual property and attentiveness to the exploitation Deaf communities have
               faced <ptr target="#giordano2013" loc="pp. 73–80"/>.</p>
            <p>Hamraie describes bringing a disability justice perspective to crowdsourcing in a
               Digital Humanities project mapping campus accessibility, writing: <quote
                  rend="inline">Critical accessibility mapping yields new modes of subjectification
                  around accessibility, reconceptualizing the labor of critical publics and
                  participants such that marginalized users retain leadership as experts who devise
                  accessibility <emph>criteria</emph>, while allies collaborate on data
                  collection</quote>
               <ptr target="#hamraie2018" loc="p. 469"/>. While Hamraie <ptr target="#hamraie2018"/>
               focuses on mapping the accessibility of physical spaces, a similar approach could be
               applied to make online spaces more accessible. Iranowska <ptr target="#iranowska2019"
               /> has analyzed users’ experiences with platforms used for crowdsourcing projects,
               such as <title rend="italic">Shakespeare’s World</title>. It would be useful to
               include perspectives of users with disabilities in reviews of digital projects and
               platforms, for Shakespeare resources and for digital projects generally.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>Incorporating Disability Studies perspectives and methodologies into the wide-ranging
               and ever-expanding digital Shakespeare archive will ensure that this critical
               awareness reaches a larger audience. Shakespeare has a massive audience, as Sylvia
               Morris notes: <cit><quote rend="block">It’s been estimated that his work is studied
                     by 50 per cent of schoolchildren worldwide, and at all educational levels. He’s
                     read and performed in translation [...] and his plays are constantly
                     re-invented by groups from all over the world. There is huge potential for
                     digitised versions of his work, for images and video of plays in performance,
                     to be enjoyed as they are, or to be reinterpreted by creative artists and users
                     of social media, not just by an academic audience.</quote><ptr
                     target="#morris2014" loc="p. 180"/></cit> Shakespeare’s immense audience
               highlights both the <quote rend="inline">canon problem</quote>
               <ptr target="#estill2019"/> and the urgency of creating a more accessible and
               inclusive digital Shakespeare canon. Because of Shakespeare’s wide-ranging impact in
               education, the arts, and popular culture, it is crucial to increase the accessibility
               and inclusivity of online Shakespeare resources. Cripping the digital Shakespeare
               canon can impact how Shakespeare is taught, engaged with, and performed. Due to
               Shakespeare’s outsized influence, it will also impact how other digital environments
               are constructed.</p>
            <p>Disability Studies and other cultural studies approaches to Shakespeare must reach
               beyond academic subfields to general readers who engage with Shakespeare’s texts and
               to the actors, artists, and educators who mediate and re-create these texts for
               future generations. Online environments are ideal for this type of outreach. Alan Liu
                  <ptr target="#liu2012"/> has argued that advocating for the humanities can be a
               key contribution of the Digital Humanities field. He writes: <quote rend="inline">The
                  digital humanities […] can create, adapt, and disseminate new tools and methods
                  for reestablishing communication between the humanities and the public</quote>
               <ptr target="#liu2012"/>. Liu calls for digital humanists to <quote rend="inline"
                  >move seamlessly between text analysis and cultural analysis</quote>; he writes:
                  <quote rend="inline">Truly to partner with the mainstream humanities, digital
                  humanists now need to incorporate cultural criticism in a way that shows
                  leadership in the humanities</quote>
               <ptr target="#liu2012"/>. Incorporating Universal Design approaches and Disability
               Studies awareness in Digital Humanities projects can create truly accessible and
               inclusive resources and further projects’ public humanities impact.</p>
            <p>Godden and Hsy <ptr target="#godden_hsy2018"/> have discussed how Universal Design
               was not intended to be limited to adding accessibility features; it is far more
               radical. As Hsy puts it: <cit><quote rend="block">I wonder if a general discursive
                     tendency to conflate UD with narrower discourses of <q>accessibility</q> risks
                     enacting the reverse of what UD initially envisions. Rather than attending to
                     embodied variance as a way to multiply and sustain diverse modes of interaction
                     with physical or digital environments, a narrowly conceived notion of UD as a
                     set of separate (or supplemental) <q>accessibility features</q> conceives the
                     challenge of UD as one of integrating disabled people into an existing set of
                     nondisabled norms.</quote><ptr target="#godden_hsy2018" loc="pp. 103"/></cit>
               Rather than merely adding accessibility features to Shakespeare resources, cripping
               the digital Shakespeare canon requires designing accessible and inclusive resources
               from the start, bringing critical attention to characters with disabilities, and
               centering performances, scholarship, and resources created by and for Deaf and
               disability communities. It entails promoting diverse ways of reading Shakespeare,
               performing Shakespeare, and responding to Shakespeare. It demands continually
               evaluating and expanding the Shakespeare canon as it evolves online.</p>
            <p>Conversations about Shakespeare’s accessibility in online spaces, and digital access
               in general, will always be insufficient if accessibility for people with disabilities
               is overlooked. As Shakespeare continues to be reinvented in digital space, as
               streamed videos and remixes inspire educators and filmmakers of the future, let’s
               ensure that these spaces are not only fully accessible, but also incorporate
               perspectives from Disability Studies. Doing so will not only benefit Shakespeare
               studies, but will also promote the creation of more accessible and inclusive digital
               environments more widely.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ASLShakespeare" label="ASL Shakespeare">ASL Shakespeare. <title
                  rend="italic">ASL Shakespeare: The American Sign Language Shakespeare
                  Project</title>. Available at: <ref target="http://aslshakespeare.org/"
                  >http://aslshakespeare.org/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="Baileyetal2016" label="Bailey et al. 2016"> Bailey, M., Cong-Huyen, A.,
               Lothian, A., and Phillips, A. (2016) <title rend="quotes">Reflections on a Movement:
                  #transformDH, Growing Up</title> in Gold, M.K.and Klein, L.F. (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2016</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/debates-in-the-digital-humanities-2016"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/debates-in-the-digital-humanities-2016</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bell_borsuk2020" label="Bell and Borsuk 2020">Bell, H. and Borsuk, A.
               (2020) <title rend="quotes">Teaching Shakespeare: Digital Processes</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Research in Drama Education: The Journal of Applied Theatre and
                  Performance</title>, 25(1): pp.1-7. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/13569783.2019.1704241"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/13569783.2019.1704241</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="besner2019" label="Besner 2019">Besner, L. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                  >When Is a Caption Close Enough?</title>, <title rend="italic">The
                  Atlantic</title>, 09 August. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2019/08/youtube-captions/595831/"
                  >https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2019/08/youtube-captions/595831/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bradbury2022" label="Bradbury 2022">Bradbury, J.M. (2022) <title
                  rend="quotes">Audiences, American Sign Language, and Deafness in Shakespeare
                  Performance</title>, <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Bulletin</title>, 40(1), pp.
               45-67.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boyd2021" label="Boyd 2021">Boyd, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Digital
                  Stages for Old Plays: A Review of Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old
                  Words, New Tools</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>, 15(3). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/3/000572/000572.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/15/3/000572/000572.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="burch_kafer2010" label="Burch and Kafer 2010">Burch, S. and Kafer, A.
               (2010) <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Interventions, Investments, and
                  Intersections</title>, in Burch, S. and Kafer, A. (eds), <title rend="italic">Deaf
                  and Disability Studies: Interdisciplinary Perspectives</title>. Washington, DC:
               Gallaudet University, pp. xiii-xxvii.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="carson_kirwan2014" label="Carson and Kirwan 2014">Carson, C. and Kirwan,
               P. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Shakespeare and the Digital World:
                  Introduction</title> in Carson, C. and Kirwan, P. (eds.),<title rend="italic"
                  >Shakespeare and the Digital World: Redefining Scholarship and Practice</title>,
               Cambridge: Cambridge University Press (2014), pp. 1-7.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="desmet2016" label="Desmet 2016">Desmet, C. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Shakespeare and the Digitized World</title>, <title rend="italic">CEA
                  Critic</title>, 78(2), pp. 213-22.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dunn2020" label="Dunn 2020">Dunn, L.C. (2020) <title rend="italic"
                  >Performing Disability in Early Modern English Drama</title>. Cham, Switzerland:
               Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ellcessor2016" label="Ellcessor 2016"> Ellcessor, E. (2016) <title
                  rend="italic">Restricted Access: Media, Disability, and the Politics of
                  Participation</title>. New York: New York University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ellcessor2018" label="Ellcessor 2018"> Ellcessor, E. (2018) <title
                  rend="quotes">A Glitch in the Tower: Academia, Disability, and Digital
                  Humanities.</title> In Sayers, J. (ed.),<title rend="italic"> The Routledge
                  Companion to Media Studies and Digital Humanities</title>. New York: Routledge,
               pp. 108-116.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="estill2019" label="Estill 2019">Estill, L. (2019) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Digital Humanities’ Shakespeare Problem</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Humanities</title>, 8(1). Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.3390/h8010045">https://doi.org/10.3390/h8010045.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="estill_jakacki_ullyot2016" label="Estill, Jakacki, and Ullyot 2016"
               >Estill, L., Jakacki, D.K., and Ullyot M. (eds.) (2016) <title rend="italic">Early
                  Modern Studies after the Digital Turn</title>. New York: Iter Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fox2010" label="Fox 2010">Fox, A. M. (2010) <title rend="quotes">How to
                  Crip the Undergraduate Classroom: Lessons from Performance, Pedagogy, and
                  Possibility</title>, <title rend="italic">Journal of Postsecondary Education and
                  Disability</title>, 23(1), pp. 38-47.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="giglio_venecek2009" label="Giglio and Venecek 2009">Giglio, K. and
               Venecek, J. (2009) <title rend="quotes">The Radical Historicity of Everything:
                  Exploring Shakespearean Identity with Web 2.0</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ:
                  Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3(3). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/3/3/000063/000063.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/3/3/000063/000063.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="giordano2013" label="Giordano 2013"> Giordano, T. (2013) <title
                  rend="quotes">Toward a Crowdsourced Model for ASL Translations of Shakespeare’s
                  Works.</title> M.A. Thesis. California State University, Northridge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="giordano_bradbury2015" label="Giordano and Bradbury 2015"> Giordano, T.
               and Bradbury, J. M. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Digit(al) Shakespeares</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">#transformDH.</title> Available at: <ref
                  target="http://www.transformdh.org/2015-video-showcase/digital-shakespeares-tyrone-giordano-and-jill-marie-bradbury/"
                  >www.transformdh.org/2015-video-showcase/digital-shakespeares-tyrone-giordano-and-jill-marie-bradbury/.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="godden_hsy2018" label="Godden and Hsy 2018"> Godden, R. and Hsy, J. (2018)
                  <title rend="quotes">Universal Design and Its Discontents</title> in Kim, D. and
               Stommel, J. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Disrupting the Digital Humanities</title>,
               Punctum Books, pp. 91-112. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://punctumbooks.com/titles/disrupting-the-digital-humanities/"
                  >https://punctumbooks.com/titles/disrupting-the-digital-humanities/</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hamraie2013" label="Hamraie 2013">Hamraie, A. (2013) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Designing Collective Access: A Feminist Disability Theory of Universal
                  Design</title>, <title rend="italic">Disability Studies Quarterly</title>, 33(4).
               Available at: <ref target="http://dx.doi.org/10.18061/dsq.v33i4.3871"
                  >http://dx.doi.org/10.18061/dsq.v33i4.3871</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hamraie2017" label="Hamraie 2017">Hamraie, A. (2017) <title rend="italic"
                  >Building Access: Universal Design and the Politics of Disability.</title>
               Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hamraie2018" label="Hamraie 2018">Hamraie, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Mapping Access: Digital Humanities, Disability Justice, and Sociospatial
                  Practice</title>, <title rend="italic">American Quarterly</title>, 70(3), pp.
               455-482.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hirsch_craig2014" label="Hirsch and Craig 2014"> Hirsch, B. D. and Craig,
               H. (eds.) (2014) <title rend="italic">The Shakespearean International Yearbook,
                  Volume 14: Special Section: Digital Shakespeares: Innovations, Interventions,
                  Mediations.</title> Burlington: Ashgate.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hobgood2021" label="Hobgood 2021">Hobgood, A.P. (2021) <title
                  rend="italic">Beholding Disability in Renaissance England</title>. Ann Arbor:
               University of Michigan Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hobgood_wood2013" label="Hobgood and Wood 2013">Hobgood, A.P. and Wood,
               D.H. (eds.) (2013) <title rend="italic">Recovering Disability in Early Modern
                  England</title>. Columbus: Ohio State University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iranowska2019" label="Iranowska 2019">Iranowska, J. (2019) <title
                  rend="quotes">Greater good, empowerment and democratization? Affordances of the
                  crowdsourcing transcription projects</title>, <title rend="italic">Museum &amp;
                  Society</title>, 17(2), pp. 210-228.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iyengar2015" label="Iyengar 2015">Iyengar, S. (ed.) (2015) <title
                  rend="italic">Disability, Health, and Happiness in the Shakespearean Body</title>.
               New York: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="iyengar_desmet2012" label="Iyengar and Desmet 2012">Iyengar, S. and
               Desmet, C. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Rebooting Ophelia: Social Media and the
                  Rhetorics of Appropriation</title> in Peterson, K. L. and Williams, D. (eds.)
                  <title rend="italic">The Afterlife of Ophelia</title>. New York: Palgrave
               Macmillan, pp. 59-78.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jenstadetal2018" label="Jenstad, Kaethler, and Roberts-Smith 2018">
               Jenstad, J., Kaethler, M., and Roberts-Smith, J. (eds.) (2018) <title rend="italic"
                  >Shakespeare’s Language in Digital Media: Old Words, New Tools</title>. New York:
               Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jenstadetal2017" label="Jenstad, McLean-Fiander, and McPherson 2017">
               Jenstad, J., McLean-Fiander, K. and McPherson, K.R. (2017) <title rend="quotes">The
                     <title rend="italic">MoEML</title> Pedagogical Partnership Program</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11(3). Available
               at: <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/3/000302/000302.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/3/000302/000302.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kelley2017" label="Kelley 2017">Kelley, S. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Getting on the Map: A Case Study in Digital Pedagogy and Undergraduate
                  Crowdsourcing</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</title>,11(3). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000330/000330.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/3/000330/000330.html</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kwok2017" label="Kwok 2017">Kwok, R. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Crowdsourcing for Shakespeare</title>, <title rend="italic">The New
                  Yorker</title>. 16 January. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/crowdsourcing-for-shakespeare"
                  >https://www.newyorker.com/tech/annals-of-technology/crowdsourcing-for-shakespeare</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lanier2017" label="Lanier 2017"> Lanier, D.M. (2017) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Shakespeare/Not Shakespeare: Afterword.</title> In Desmet, C., Loper, N. and
               Casey, J. (eds.), <title rend="italic">Shakespeare/Not Shakespeare</title>. Cham,
               Switzerland: Palgrave Macmillan, pp. 293-306.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lavagnino2014" label="Lavagnino 2014">Lavagnino, J. (2014) <title
                  rend="quotes">Shakespeare in the Digital Humanities</title> in Carson, C. and
               Kirwan, P. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Shakespeare and the Digital World: Redefining
                  Scholarship and Practice</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, pp.
               14-23.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lee_lee2017" label="Lee and Lee 2017"> Lee, J. and Lee, J. (2017) <title
                  rend="quotes">Shakespeare’s Tragic Social Network; or Why All the World’s a
                  Stage,</title>
               <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 11(2). Available at:
                  <ref target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/2/000289/000289.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/11/2/000289/000289.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="liu2012" label="Liu 2012">Liu, A. (2012) <title rend="quotes">Where Is
                  Cultural Criticism in the Digital Humanities?</title> in M.K. Gold (ed.) <title
                  rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/debates-in-the-digital-humanities"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/debates-in-the-digital-humanities</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="loftis2021" label="Loftis 2021">Loftis, S.F. (2021) <title rend="italic"
                  >Shakespeare and Disability Studies</title>. New York: Oxford University
               Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="love2018" label="Love 2018">Love, G. (2018) <title rend="italic">Early
                  Modern Theatre and the Figure of Disability</title>. London: Bloomsbury.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lyons2020" label="Lyons 2020">Lyons, K. (2020) <title rend="quotes"
                  >YouTube is Ending its Community Captions Feature and Deaf Creators Aren’t Happy
                  About It</title>, <title rend="italic">The Verge</title>, 31 July. Available at:
                  <ref
                  target="https://www.theverge.com/2020/7/31/21349401/youtube-community-captions-deaf-creators-accessibility-google"
                  >https://www.theverge.com/2020/7/31/21349401/youtube-community-captions-deaf-creators-accessibility-google</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mace1985" label="Mace 1985">Mace, R. (1985) <title rend="quotes">Universal
                  Design: Barrier-Free Environments for Everyone</title>, <title rend="italic"
                  >Designers West</title>, 33(1), pp. 147-152.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitglobalshakespeares" label="MIT Global Shakespeares">Global Shakespeares
               Video &amp; Performance Archive. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://globalshakespeares.mit.edu/"
                  >https://globalshakespeares.mit.edu</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="morris2014" label="Morris 2014">Morris, S. (2014) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Gamekeeper or Poacher? Personal Blogging/Public Sharing</title> in Carson, C. and
               Kirwan, P. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Shakespeare and the Digital World: Redefining
                  Scholarship and Practice</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, pp.
               176-187.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mueller2014" label="Mueller 2014">Mueller, M. (2014) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Shakespeare His Contemporaries: Collaborative Curation and Exploration of Early
                  Modern Drama in a Digital Environment</title>, <title rend="italic">DHQ: Digital
                  Humanities Quarterly</title>, 8(3). Available at: <ref
                  target="http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/8/3/000183/000183.html"
                  >http://digitalhumanities.org:8081/dhq/vol/8/3/000183/000183.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="murphy2010" label="Murphy 2010">Murphy, A. (2010) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Shakespeare Goes Digital: Three Open Internet Editions</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title>, 61(3), pp. 401-414.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="novak2008" label="Novak 2008">Novak, P. (2008) <title rend="quotes"
                     ><q>Where Lies Your Text?</q>: Twelfth Night in American Sign Language
                  Translation</title> in Holland, P. (ed.), <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Survey
                  61</title>, Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, pp. 74-90. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CCOL9780521898881.006"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/CCOL9780521898881.006</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="odell2021" label="O’Dell 2021">O’Dell, L. (2021) <title rend="quotes"
                  >YouTube Pulled its Community Captions Feature, So Now More Creators are Making
                  Their Own</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Verge</title>, 21 May. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.theverge.com/2021/5/21/22443577/youtube-captions-increased-deaf-campaigners"
                  >https://www.theverge.com/2021/5/21/22443577/youtube-captions-increased-deaf-campaigners.</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oneill2014" label="O’Neill 2014">O’Neill, S. (2014) <title rend="italic"
                  >Shakespeare and YouTube: New Media Forms of the Bard</title>. London:
               Bloomsbury.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oneill2019" label="O’Neill 2019">O’Neill, S. (ed.) (2019) <title
                  rend="quotes">Special Issue: Shakespeare and Digital Humanities: New Perspectives
                  and Future Directions</title>, <title rend="italic">Humanities</title>, 8(1-2).
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://www.mdpi.com/journal/humanities/special_issues/Shakespeare"
                  >https://www.mdpi.com/journal/humanities/special_issues/Shakespeare</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="poynter2020" label="Poynter 2020">Poynter, R. (2020) <title rend="italic"
                  >YouTube is Officially Getting Rid of Community Captions</title>. 08 August.
               Available at: <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wh5sxszpGog"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wh5sxszpGog</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rowe2014" label="Rowe 2014">Rowe, K. (2014) <title rend="quotes">Living
                  with Digital Incunables, or: A <q>Good-Enough</q> Shakespeare Text</title> in
               Carson, C. and Kirwan, P. (eds.) <title rend="italic">Shakespeare and the Digital
                  World: Redefining Scholarship and Practice</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge
               University Press, pp. 144-159.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rowheyveld2018" label="Row-Heyveld 2018">Row-Heyveld, L. (2018) <title
                  rend="italic">Dissembling Disability in Early Modern English Drama</title>. Cham,
               Switzerland: Palgrave Macmillan.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schaapwilliams2021" label="Schaap Williams 2021">Schaap Williams, K.
               (2021) <title rend="italic">Unfixable Forms: Disability, Performance, and the Early
                  Modern English Theater</title>. Ithaca: Cornell University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sperrazza2020" label="Sperrazza 2020">Sperrazza, W. (2020) <title
                  rend="quotes">Early Modern Manuscripts Online. Other,</title>
               <title rend="italic">Renaissance and Reformation / Renaissance et Réforme</title>,
               43(2), pp. 335–38. Available at: <ref target="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26977617"
                  >https://www.jstor.org/stable/26977617</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="squeo_pennacchia_winckler2021"
               label="Squeo, Pennacchia, and Winckler 2021">Squeo, A., Pennacchia, M. and Winckler,
               R. (eds.) (2021) <title rend="quotes">Special Issue: Experiencing Shakespeare in
                  Digital Environments</title>,<title rend="italic">Lingue e Linguaggi</title>, 45.
               Available at: <ref
                  target="http://siba-ese.unisalento.it/index.php/linguelinguaggi/article/view/24524"
                  >http://siba-ese.unisalento.it/index.php/linguelinguaggi/article/view/24524</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="terras2016" label="Terras 2016">Terras, M. (2016) <title rend="quotes"
                  >Crowdsourcing in the Digital Humanities</title> in Schreibman, S., Siemens, R.
               and Unsworth, J. (eds.) <title rend="italic">A New Companion to Digital
                  Humanities</title>, Chichester: Wiley, pp. 420-438.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thompson2010" label="Thompson 2010">Thompson, A. (2010) <title
                  rend="quotes">Unmooring the Moor: Researching and Teaching on YouTube</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Quarterly</title>, 61(3), pp. 337-356.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="titchkosky2011" label="Titchkosky 2011"> Titchkosky, T. (2011) <title
                  rend="italic">The Question of Access: Disability, Space, Meaning</title>. Toronto:
               University of Toronto Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vanhyning2019" label="Van Hyning 2019">Van Hyning, V. (2019) <title
                  rend="quotes">Harnessing Crowdsourcing for Scholarly and GLAM Purposes</title>,
                  <title rend="italic">Literature Compass</title>, 16(3-4), pp. 1-11. Available at:
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1111/lic3.12507"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1111/lic3.12507</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="virdi2021" label="Virdi 2021">Virdi, J. (2021) <title rend="quotes">Black
                  Bars, White Text</title>, <title rend="italic">Literature and Medicine</title>,
               39(1), pp.29-33. Available at: <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2021.0004"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1353/lm.2021.0004</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="williams2012" label="Williams 2012">Williams, G. H. (2012) <title
                  rend="quotes">Disability, Universal Design, and the Digital Humanities</title> in
               Gold, M.K. (ed.) <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title>.
               Available at: <ref
                  target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/debates-in-the-digital-humanities"
                  >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/projects/debates-in-the-digital-humanities</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="youdescribe" label="YouDescribe">YouDescribe. Available at: <ref
                  target="https://youdescribe.org/">https://youdescribe.org/</ref>. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
