<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Deformin' in the Rain: How (and Why) to Break a Classic
          Film </title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Jason <dhq:family>Mittell</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>Middlebury College</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>jmittell@middlebury.edu</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Jason Mittell is Professor of Film &amp; Media Culture and American Studies, and
              co-founder of the Digital Liberal Arts Initiative at Middlebury College. His books
              include <title rend="italic">Complex Television: The Poetics of Contemporary
                Television Storytelling</title> (NYU Press, 2015), <title rend="italic">The
                Videographic Essay: Practice &amp; Pedagogy</title> (with Christian Keathley &amp;
              Catherine Grant, <ref target="http://videographicessay.org"
                >http://videographicessay.org</ref>), and <title rend="italic">How to Watch
                Television</title> (co-edited with Ethan Thompson; NYU Press, 2013; revised edition
              2020). He is project manager for <ref target="http://mediacommons.org/intransition/"
                  ><title rend="italic">[in]Transition: Journal of Videographic Film &amp; Moving
                  Image Studies</title></ref> and co-director of the NEH-supported workshop series
                <ref target="https://sites.middlebury.edu/videoworkshop/">Scholarship in Sound &amp;
                Image</ref>. </p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000521</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p>Digital source materials such as films can be transformed in ways that suggest an
          innovative path for digital humanities research: computationally manipulating sounds and
          images to create new audiovisual artifacts whose insights might be revealed through their
          aesthetic power and transformative strangeness. Following upon the strain of digital
          humanities practice that Mark Sample terms the <quote rend="inline">deformed
            humanities,</quote> this essay subjects a single film to a series of deformations: the
          classic musical <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title>. Accompanying more than
          twenty original audiovisual deformations in still image, GIF, and video formats, the essay
          considers both what each new version reveals about the film (and cinema more broadly) and
          how we might engage with the emergent derivative aesthetic object created by algorithmic
          practice as a product of the deformed humanities.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>Following upon the strain of digital humanities practice that Mark Sample terms the
            <quote rend="inline">deformed humanities,</quote> this essay subjects a single film to a
          series of deformations: the classic musical <title rend="italic">Singin' in the
            Rain</title>.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <div>
        <head/>
        <p>On its face, film and media studies would seem to be a natural space for digital
          humanities to grow and thrive, as it studies cultural objects that are either born digital
          in origination, or digitized from cinematic or analog video originals for contemporary
          distribution. Additionally, dedicated departments of film and media studies often include
          video production in their scope, meaning that there are usually more digital resources and
          expertise available than in other humanities departments. But in reality, most of the
          methods that have been adopted in digital humanities pose challenges to apply to moving
          images and sounds as an object of study, as with tricky technicalities of text mining from
          audiovisual sources or copyright restrictions curtailing expansive digital editions of
          films, or seem to work best when analyzing data outside of the media objects themselves,
          as with mapping exhibition patterns or doing network analyses of actors across films. But
          the existence of films and media texts as already-digital objects suggests another path
          for digital humanities research away from quantitative data analysis: computationally
          manipulating sounds and images to create new audiovisual artifacts whose insights might be
          revealed through their aesthetic power and transformative strangeness.<note>Such
            deformative videographic works seem to be a clear example of fair use transformations
            under U.S. copyright law, a topic I've discussed more in depth in <title rend="quotes"
              >But Is Any of This Legal?</title>
            <ptr target="#keathley2019"/></note></p>
        <p>I have previously written about how we might consider videographic criticism as a digital
          humanities research method, manipulating moving images and sounds to create new
          audiovisual texts that convey arguments and ideas that would otherwise be impossible to
          generate or articulate via the written word <ptr target="#mittell2019"/>. In that essay, I
          extended Mark Sample's <soCalled>deformed humanities</soCalled> to the videographic realm,
          proposing three deformative techniques and applying them to a range of films to seek
          discoveries within my research laboratory of Adobe Premiere. Such deformations apply
          patterns and parameters to cultural works, looking to <soCalled>break</soCalled> the bound
          object of a poem or film and create something new from the broken parts. As Sample argues,
          the resulting deformations, which typically defy norms of sense and logic, do not need to
          be returned into the rational realm of analysis to provide insights about the original's
          design or meaning; instead, the strange deformed version can function as a new media
          object, with aesthetic power and cultural resonances that are not circumscribed by their
          relationship to their original. As he writes, <quote rend="inline">the deformed work is
            the end, not the means to the end</quote>
          <ptr target="#sample2012"/>; see also <ptr target="#samuels1999"/>
          <ptr target="#ramsay2011"/>.</p>
        <p>Building upon my previous essay as well as other scholars' deformative videographic work
            <ptr target="#ferguson2019"/>
          <ptr target="#oleary2019"/>, this <soCalled>sequel</soCalled> takes a different approach:
          subjecting a single film to a broad range of deformations as a way to explore the wide
          array of deformative practices that might yield interesting results on a single object.
            <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title> is a particularly apt film to
          repeatedly deform for a number of reasons. Few films are as well-known, beloved,
          broadly-taught, and widely regarded as historically significant — if one effect of
          deformative work is to make the familiar strange, it's useful to start with a film that is
          quite familiar. Additionally, the film itself is about cinema at a moment of technological
          transition from silent to sound, and thus it is thematically resonant to place it into a
          technological laboratory to perform experiments with sounds and images, even if the film's
          diegetic technologies are resolutely analog. <emph>Singin</emph>' also features a broad
          array of reflexive formal techniques and moments, including color, black-and-white,
          dialogue, singing, dancing, film-within-film, and fantasy sequences, whose range and
          variety encourages a playful approach via deformative operations, and thus might be
          instructive and inspirational for other potential case studies. Finally, it is an unusual
          film because it contains its own internal deformative moment: during the test screening of
            <emph>The Dueling Cavalier</emph>, a synching glitch in the nascent sound film
          technology causes the dialogue of two characters to swap; the diegetic audience's reaction
          to this deformation via laughter and surprise highlights the pleasures of strangeness that
          hopefully some of my deformations will provoke.</p>
        <p>In providing an inventory of deformative practices, I do not aim to suggest
          comprehensiveness nor a progression toward <soCalled>better</soCalled> methods and
          revelations. This is a provisional list of techniques that I have found productive in
          creating new cultural objects that seem meaningful and/or pleasurable, but I fully expect
          many will find some of them uninteresting or unpleasant. I have thrown many techniques at
          the proverbial wall, but will not inventory the failures that did not stick — except one
          that might exemplify what a <soCalled>failure</soCalled> might mean in this context.
          Inspired by the film's internal deformation of unsynched sound, I experimented with
            <soCalled>re-synching</soCalled> that moment in <emph>Dueling Cavalier</emph> to line up
          the proper dialogue, and then playing the rest of the film with this new sonic
          synchronization — effectively making the strange moment normal, and the rest of the normal
          moments strange. But the result was neither sufficiently strange nor interesting —
          watching the film's dialogue and musical numbers with the sound lagging around two seconds
          behind was simply annoying, not revelatory nor pleasurable. Thus the bar that each of my
          subsequent deformations clears (at least to me) is to create something interesting and/or
          enjoyable to watch and hear. I hope the same holds for all who proceed through this
          strange wilderness of a broken classic film.</p>
        <p>I fully admit that these resulting works are difficult to categorize. Are they acts of
          scholarship? Do they contain or provoke arguments? Or are they creative works, more akin
          to experimental films? Certainly there are many parallels with the latter, where the use
          of algorithms and parameters on pre-existing footage creates new artworks, as with Martin
          Arnold's glitchy remixes of cinematic fragments or Cory Arcangel's collages of YouTube
          musical clips (see <ptr target="#bering2014"/>
          <ptr target="#zryd2004"/>
          <ptr target="#enns2012"/>). I present these deformations here not in the context of an art
          gallery or film festival, but rather embedded within a written scholarly essay, clearly
          signaling them as academic expressions over artistic works. As I previously wrote
          regarding the possibilities of videographic criticism, such works can embrace the poetic
          and experimental scholarly impulse of Robert Ray's writing <ptr target="#ray1995"/>,
          joining <quote rend="inline">scientific quantification and artistic poeticization
            together, creating works that transform films and media into new objects that are both
            data-driven abstractions and aesthetically expressive</quote>
          <ptr target="#mittell2019" loc="230"/>. While each deformation falls short of the bar for
          a piece of rigorous argument-driven scholarship, taken together I believe they do create
          an argument for approaching an audiovisual work as a site of experimentation and play,
          offering the possibility of revealing new dimensions and facets of a highly familiar
          text.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>#1: Still Frames</head>
        <p>One of the first (and most inspirational) examples of filmic deformations I know of is
          Kevin Ferguson's <soCalled>summed frames</soCalled> project. In <ref
            target="https://filmvis.tumblr.com/">a wide-ranging website</ref> and associated
          scholarly publications, Ferguson publishes still images of films that are derived from his
          deformative manipulations. Using Quicktime, he exports a feature film into an image set,
          typically a set of still frames sampled every few seconds of a film; Ferguson then
          repurposes the open-source medical imaging software ImageJ to overlay all of these still
          frames into a single <soCalled>summed frame</soCalled> image visual that distills all of
          the light and color typically experienced flickering in front of our eyes over the course
          of watching a film <ptr target="#ferguson2016"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure01">
          <head>Kevin Ferguson sums the frames of <title rend="italic">Singin’</title> into one
            still image, with subtle details referring to the original’s composition.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpeg"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Ferguson's summed frame image of <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title> (see
            <ref target="#figure01">Figure 1</ref>) is both beautiful and interesting. It presents
          an impressionistic residue of the film's composition, lighting, and production design that
          would be unidentifiable without context. Knowing the source material, we can see details
          that resonate with significance, as with the outline of the screen-within-a-screen image
          and red-tinted curtains on the margins that highlight the importance of cinematic
          presentation within the film. Ferguson's work becomes more meaningful in comparison, as
          the visual patterns and contrasts reveal insights into a corpus of films, as seen in his
          collection of summed images of Disney features, Westerns, and gialli films <ptr
            target="#ferguson2016"/>. Thus we could compare this image to those produced by summing
          the frames of other MGM musicals, Gene Kelly performances, or Hollywood films from 1952.
          But for the purposes of this project, I am less interested in using deformations to take
          us outside <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title> than to revel in the strange
          versions of the film that such methods produce.</p>
        <p>Once we have broken the film into its component parts of still frames — in this case, a
          folder of 925 still images sampling every six seconds of the film — we can perform other
          operations to see what they might yield. Fellow deformation-minded digital humanist Zach
          Whalen has developed <ref target="http://www.zachwhalen.net/pg/imj/">imj</ref>, a tool
          that allows for straightforward web-based graphical analytics from a corpus of images
          using three basic tools: plot, montage, and barcode <ptr target="#whalen2016"/>. Plot is
          by far the most analytical tool, offering data visualizations to plot an image corpus on a
          grid with a range of variables to map onto the X and Y axes, including brightness, hue,
          saturation, and luminance. Not surprisingly, the results create data-driven charts that
          reveal tendencies and patterns within the film's imagery, but do not produce compelling
          aesthetic objects in their own rights. The other two tools are more deformatively
          effective — the montage tool creates a visual grid of the film's frames laid out
          sequentially. The resulting distillation offers some analytical insights into the scene
          and shot breakdowns, but moreover it creates an experience that evokes
            <emph>Singin'</emph> as we have never seen it before, simultaneously watching all scenes
          at once but with a different visualization of temporality than Ferguson's summed frame
          (see <ref target="#figure02">Figure 2</ref>). If you know the film, you can identify
          scenes, dance numbers, and narrative moments from this image, but you can also admire
          designs that you could never see while watching the film.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure02">
          <head>The montage tool in imj creates a simultaneous view of the entire film from a
            distance.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The third tool in Whalen's software package is the most deformative, presenting the sum
          of the film's frames, but from a sideways perspective to create a barcode. The resulting
          image certainly bears markers from the film, and knowing the source allows viewers to
          identify scenes and even characters. But without knowledge of the source, it becomes a
          work of abstract art — generated algorithmically from another work of art (see <ref
            target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure03">
          <head>imj’s barcode offers a way to watch <title rend="italic">Singin’ in the Rain</title>
            from the side of the image</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Of course, algorithms can be altered to create different results. Whalen's tool can
          create a barcode that reduces each frame to its average or dominant color instead of
          maintaining its core image pattern, as with the above image. The resulting barcodes, as
          with this one below based on average colors of each frame, are much more abstract and
          completely unidentifiable as a derivative work from one of Hollywood's most iconic films.
          While such a barcode might be a more attractive pattern for a poster or pillowcase, as
            <ref
            target="https://www.redbubble.com/people/moviebarcode/works/6987368-moviebarcode-singin-in-the-rain-1952"
            >an online shop does sell merchandise based on movie barcodes</ref>, it falls outside of
          the nexus of aesthetic appreciation and analytic possibility where I contend most
          effective deformations can be found (see <ref target="#figure04">Figure 4</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure04">
          <head>The barcode version with average colors becomes more removed from the source film,
            sacrificing analytic possibilities for a more accessible aesthetic.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>A still frame itself could be thought of as a kind of manipulation of a film — even
          though <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title> was originally composed of
          approximately 146,000 still images projected sequentially, these frames were all designed
          to create the illusion of movement. The deformations I've presented thus far have all
          excluded movement as a design element, raising the question of how we might deform this
          set of still images by reintroducing movement into their aesthetic. This question arose in
          a conversation I had with Ferguson, as we brainstormed how to visualize the process of a
          summed frame accruing over time. Most processes we explored via video editing programs
          were underwhelming, as the accumulating image would coalesce into a composite blur after a
          few seconds, with subsequent developments building up too subtly to notice.<note>See
            Ferguson’s video summation of <title rend="italic">The Searchers</title> for an example
            of this effect: <ref target="https://vimeo.com/170473567"
              >https://vimeo.com/170473567</ref>.</note> It became clear to me that a more
          compelling version would require the images to slowly fade out, creating the effect of a
          rolling accumulation of images that was too complicated for me to figure out in Adobe
          Premiere. My solution, like with Ferguson's use of medical imaging software, involved
          repurposing a tool designed for far different purposes — StarStaX, an image blending
          program designed for star trail astronomical photography, proved to be the right tool to
          create the desired effect, and then screen capture the process to create a videographic
          deformation (see <ref target="#figure05">Figure 05</ref>).<note>StarStaX is available at
              <ref target="https://markus-enzweiler.de/software/starstax/"
              >https://markus-enzweiler.de/software/starstax/</ref> - special thanks to Ethan Murphy
            for suggesting this tool.</note></p>
        <figure xml:id="figure05">
          <head>A videographic summed frame demonstrates the process of overlaying images using
            StarStaX, along with a sonic rendering of such accumulation.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/206950599"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The resulting video summing the film's frames creates a hypnotic tour through the film's
          images in two minutes, creating an impressionistic collage effect that highlights color
          and composition over plot and character. But the image-only version seemed lacking without
          sound, so I tried to determine what the equivalent for <soCalled>summed frames</soCalled>
          would be for sound. This challenge highlighted a core differential that creates challenges
          for deformative videographic work: sound lacks clear units like
            <soCalled>frames</soCalled> or <soCalled>shots,</soCalled> meaning that the entire
          soundtrack is more continuous and fluid than the image track. My colleague David Miranda
          Hardy helped me design a soundtrack that mimicked the frame sampling idea by isolating
          sounds sequentially from the film, and using reverb effects to evoke the blurred
          overlapping images. Together, the video creates an evocative experience that clearly
          derives from the sequential film source, but creates far different aesthetic and affective
          responses. As with any successful deformation, the work builds on the source material in
          unexpected ways to create something that feels both derivative and original.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>#2: Motion</head>
        <p>Motion is a powerful transformative element in videographic deformations, whether imposed
          upon still sources, as with the previous summed frame video, or harnessed from a film's
          own motion. In thinking how to extract motion from a film as a deformative act, we can
          look to one of the most widespread formats to disseminate motion: GIFs. As a short
          repeating distillation of a moving image, a GIF can offer a tremendous tool for film
          criticism via digital publication, as argued by Michael Newman, where both form and affect
          can be captured for analytical purposes <ptr target="#newman2016"/>. For instance, this
          GIF of one of <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title>'s most iconic shots
          provides an opportunity to analyze the coordination between camera movement, dance
          choreography, props, sets, and special effects to create a breathtaking affective moment
          (see Figure 5).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure06">
          <head>Gene Kelly’s endless spinning reinforces the GIF’s looping aesthetic.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.gif"/>
        </figure>
        <p>But just as staring at a repeated word or phrase for long enough will cause meaning and
          sense to start to break down, the repetition and abstraction of this GIF eventually
          encourages a sense of disorientation, unfamiliarity, and strangeness that is familiar to
          the realm of deformations, as Gene Kelly spins endlessly and breathlessly in the rain.
          Thus choosing looped segments that promote such a sense of the strange can make new
          deformed objects out of more conventional moments (see <ref target="#figure07">Figure
            7</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure07">
          <head>Donald O’Connor’s manic dance becomes even more extreme on an infinite loop.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.gif"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In the midst of his show stopping number <title rend="quotes">Make 'Em Laugh,</title>
          Donald O'Connor's roll across the room is one of many entertaining moves that does,
          indeed, make us laugh. As an endlessly repeating decontextualized GIF, it suggests
          something more manic and disconcerting — perhaps an enchantment that O'Connor is doomed to
          roll with an astonished grin for all eternity, or a curse on us the viewer to watch his
          gleeful twirl for an equally long time. Other GIFs can capture a moment that is itself
          already innately odd (see <ref target="#figure08">Figure 8</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure08">
          <head>A moment from <title rend="quotes">Beautiful Girl</title> becomes a decontextualized
            loop of cheer.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.gif"/>
        </figure>
        <p>A tiny excerpt from <title rend="quotes">Beautiful Girl,</title> one of the film's most
          idiosyncratic numbers, creates a GIF that evokes no narrative, performance, or character
          resonances; instead, it just captures pure style and tone, poised to circulate in today's
          natural habitat for GIFs: as an affective response on social media, disconnected from its
          cinematic source.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure09">
          <head>A shot-reverse shot of mock dance at the film’s climax builds on character
            relationships.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.gif"/>
        </figure>
        <p>My personal favorite <emph>Singin</emph>' GIF captures a moment of fake dance, as Don,
          Cosmo, and Simpson mock Lena's attempt to perform a musical number (see <ref
            target="#figure09">Figure 9</ref>). As the interchange between the two shots repeats
          endlessly, the expressions feel more exaggerated, the mockery more pointed and severe. I
          can imagine ways to exaggerate and further deform the image, but the effect remains
          strange and off-putting even as the source material is left intact.</p>
        <p>A single GIF can transform a moment by repetition and decontextualization, but combining
          GIFs offers new deformative possibilities via spatial montage. Back in 2001, Lev Manovich
          predicted that <soCalled>broadband cinema</soCalled> of the internet era would foreground
          the multiplicity of frames and screens by juxtaposing images spatially as an alternative
          to temporal montage <ptr target="#manovich2001" loc="322–326"/>. More recently, Catherine
          Grant has theorized the function of spatial montage in videographic criticism, exploring
          how the meanings and signifiers coexist and resonate through juxtaposition via
          split-screen designs <ptr target="#grant2018b"/>. But applying spatial montage to GIFs
          pushes away from signification and meaning, as the decontextualized looping images bounce
          off one another to create affecting, engaging, and surprising compositions; as Jennifer
          Malkowski has productively analyzed, such compositions are popular in fan communities in
          the form of GIFsets, where users of sites like Tumblr create and curate carefully arranged
          groupings of GIFs to express affective connections between looping motion sequences. As
          Malkowski suggests, <quote rend="inline">Spatial montage displays multiple moving images
            on screen at once, granting the work's maker new powers of artistic juxtaposition and
            its viewer access to a broader and more complex visual field</quote>
          <ptr target="#malkowski2017"/>. Thus we might imagine a GIFset as a site of deformative
          possibility to create new ways to experience <emph>Singin' in the Rain</emph>'s
          motion.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure10">
          <head>To view this GIFset in motion, follow this <ref
              target="https://videographicsandbox.wordpress.com/2017/03/27/singin-in-the-gifs/"
              >link</ref>.</head>
          <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
        </figure>
        <p>I created a number of GIFs of dancing loops from across the film, each designed to
          approximate continuous motion (see <ref target="#figure10">Figure 10</ref>). In arranging
          them in a three-by-three GIFset, I focused on juxtaposing modes of motion that seemed to
          interact in interesting ways, considering both camera movement and the choreographed
          bodies of the performers. One of the interesting effects of the GIFset results from the
          varying lengths of each GIF, creating a phase effect among the repetitions of the loops
          that diverges over time. As the loops shift their sync, we can see unexpected resonances
          between the motions in neighboring frames, making the viewing experience quite variable,
          as spatial montage structures the productively arbitrary temporality.</p>
        <p>Of course, GIFs extract moving images from the film, discarding the soundtrack. Using the
          logic of the GIFset, I created a simulated GIFset within Adobe Premiere by arranging the
          video in a grid and copying clips to mimic the looping effect, thus providing an
          opportunity to add a soundtrack. Given the choreographic content of the GIFs, I excerpted,
          looped, and layered one of Gene Kelly's <title rend="quotes">Gotta Dance</title> lines
          from <title rend="quotes">Broadway Melody</title> to create what feels like a hypnotic, if
          arhythmic, sonic collage to accompany the grid of dancers (see <ref target="#figure11"
            >Figure 11</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure11">
          <head>A simulated GIFset with accompanying audio looping interweaves unexpected beauty and
            chaos.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/210426270"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Following the GIFset logic to its most chaotic conclusion, I created another simulated
          set of GIFs to loop both video and audio within a three-by-three grid. The opening to the
          musical number <title rend="quotes">Beautiful Girl</title> is the film's most chaotic,
          random, and arbitrary sequence, with snippets of technicolor dancing and singing to a
          patchwork of early movie musical numbers, created in tribute to 1930s Busby Berkeley
          musicals. I chose nine different visual moments and created a looped grid, allowing the
          audio to loop in a cacophonous sonic overlay (see <ref target="#figure12">Figure
          12</ref>). By making the film's strangest moments even stranger, the effect is certainly
          overwhelming and not necessarily pleasant, but seems to capture something of the
          original's disorienting tone.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure12">
          <head>The Busby Berkeley aesthetic emphasizes spectacle, taken here to its illogical
            conclusion.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/375152157"/>
        </figure>
        <p>There are certainly other means to emphasize and deform motion beyond extracting
          sequences into GIFs. Kevin Ferguson offers another instructive example in his video <title
            rend="quotes">Edge</title> (see <ref target="#figure13">Figure 13</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure13">
          <head>Kevin Ferguson’s <title rend="quotes">Edge</title> deforms the still images and
            reassembles them into a musical number that feels like it came from an abstract animated
            film.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/208869731"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Following from his summed frame work, Ferguson exported the frames of the musical number
            <title rend="quotes">You Were Meant for Me</title> and the opening credit sequence at
          twenty-four frames-per-second grouped into folders for each shot from the film. He then
          experimented with ten different ImageJ algorithms to perform <soCalled>edge
            detection</soCalled> operations on each set of stills, creating a variety of effects
          that resemble hand-drawn animation and other abstractions that emphasized the edges of the
          characters and set. Ferguson reassembled the video by placing the grouped still frames in
          sequence on top of the soundtrack in a video editor, literally animating the
          edge-abstracted images to reconstitute the film. The effect is a marvel of motion and
          blank space, provoking thoughts on how we perceive and constitute movement via cinema,
          while creating moments of expressive beauty hidden in the original film. Additionally,
          knowing the underlying process helps us remember the materiality of moving cinematic
          images as successive still frames, a digital transformation that evokes the analog
          original.</p>
        <p>Focusing on motion in a dance-centered film also raises questions about what movement in
          a cinematic dance sequence entails. Certainly much of the beauty in <title rend="italic"
            >Singin' in the Rain</title>'s choreography involves the coordination of moving bodies
          and moving cameras, as many of the GIFs highlight. But what if we force ourselves to focus
          more on bodies, and specifically body parts in motion — what will we see differently? With
          that question in mind, I deformed one of the film's most iconic dance numbers, the title
          track, by masking the image to only include Gene Kelly's hands and feet (see <ref
            target="#figure14">Figure 14</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure14">
          <head>The film’s iconic title number remains intact, but by only being able to see Kelly’s
            hands and feet, our attention is directed to the motion of his extremities that is
            otherwise invisible in the original.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/375501447/"/>
        </figure>
        <p>As the extremities of Kelly's body, his hands and feet explore the staged space most
          broadly, while eliminating his face and torso directs our attention to these abstracted
          movements in rhythm to his disembodied voice. To me, the effect of the video is cartoony,
          bringing out the animation inherent in dance, but in a more playful and almost inhuman way
          than Ferguson's <title rend="quotes">Edge</title> video. While we watch these body parts
          in motion, we see them as animated shapes on a black background, where the edges of the
          mask become noticeable much like Ferguson emphasizes the edges of the dancers' bodies. I
          find the captivating simplicity of his moving hands and feet to simultaneously capture and
          deny the beauty of Kelly's mastery of cinematic dance.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>#3: Shots</head>
        <p>Returning to the fundamental elements of film, we can look at specific shots as another
          type of raw material to create deformations. In my earlier essay, I suggested some
          deformative possibilities tied to shots, including a videographic version of Nicholas
          Rombes's <title rend="quotes">10/40/70</title> project <ptr target="#mittell2019"/>
          <ptr target="#rombes2014"/>. Rombes's protocol juxtaposes three still frames from a
          feature film, from the arbitrary 10, 40, and 70 minute marks, to see what meanings and
          insights might emerge; my videographic version compiles the shots that occur at those
          minute markers to create a short film composed of three arbitrary but chronological shots
          (See <ref target="#figure15">Figure 15</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure15">
          <head>The videographic 10/40/70 demonstrates the possibilities of arbitrary juxtapositions
            at the core of deformative work.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/151845898"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The three shots do present an effective mini-narrative, focused on Don's romantic life
          starting with the flashback scene of Don initially meeting Lena and her rebuffed attempt
          to silently court him once he is promoted from stuntman to movie star. The next shot is
          coincidentally the longest take in the entire film, as Don and Kathy escalate their
          romance while walking across the studio lot and he assures her that he's not involved with
          Lena. The sequence ends with a shot of Don gleefully dancing in the rain, celebrating his
          joy over finding love with Kathy. While this brief deformation lacks the interesting
          insights that some of the other videographic 10/40/70 examples I discussed in my earlier
          essay, it does highlight how the combination of arbitrary shots can create meaning and
          resonances.</p>
        <p>A more holistic approach to deformation considers how the film in its entirety is
          organized into shots. In Premiere, I segmented the entire film into its component 376
          shots (splitting dissolves and wipes in the middle of the transition) to create a corpus
          to experiment with. Although we don't typically think of a video editing platform like
          Premiere as a database, it effectively is — subclips are actually just metadata entries
          referencing the original video to indicate timecode in and out points, as well as any
          other effects or transformations. Because Premiere can include some of this metadata in
          its view of a folder of clips, it was easy to sort the 376 shots ascending by length with
          a single click; then I gathered the clips into a sequence that re-organizes the entire
          film by ascending length of shots (see <ref target="#figure16">Figure 16</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure16">
          <head>The entirety of <title rend="italic">Singin’ in the Rain</title>, rearranged in
            ascending length of each shot, creates a whirlwind marathon of a viewing
            experience.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/208873779"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The resulting edit forgoes narrative coherence for another organizing principle driven by
          shot length, yielding some intriguing moments. The video certainly starts frenetically,
          with fifty-nine shots in the first two minutes — many of these come from the <title
            rend="quotes">Beautiful Girl</title> number, the film's most disjointed, chaotic, and
          quick-cut sequence. The early moments are often amusing, with massive tonal shifts and odd
          juxtapositions, such as the audience reaction shots responding to random dance moves or
          lines; at around 1:30, a number of shots from <emph>The Dancing Cavalier</emph> premiere
          create a disjointed version of Lena's attempt to sing in front of an audience. As the
          shots increase in length, some of the arbitrary juxtapositions become more interesting, as
          with the cinematically reflexive sequence starting at 9:50, featuring shots of
            <emph>Variety</emph> newspaper headlines, the closing <title rend="quotes">The
            End</title> title, the opening credit of <emph>The Dueling Cavalier</emph>, and the MGM
          lion, all intercut with random shots from the film lasting around seven seconds each. At
          43:00, a sequence emerges with shots lasting around twenty-six seconds that sandwich two
          moments from Kathy and Don's first tempestuous meeting around their final kiss, contrasted
          with Don performing with the film's other two fictional romantic partners (Lena and the
          unnamed dancer played by Cyd Charisse), and the film's final shot of the happy couple
          looking at their own billboard for the film-within-a-film; while not narratively coherent,
          these arbitrary juxtapositions driven by shot length create a more compelling set of
          contrasts than the 10/40/70 sequence.</p>
        <p>The full recut film is hard to watch except as a detached analyst looking for patterns,
          as the feeling of random disjuncture overwhelms any sense of continuity. However, for some
          reason this is by far my most-watched video on Vimeo with over 15,000 views as of February
          2021, vastly exceeding full-fledged video essays that have been broadly disseminated and
          shorter experiments that seem more poised to go viral. It's hard to identify what the
          appeal of this deformative take on the entire film might be, but seemingly it has
          attracted an audience — the one theory I can imagine is that people are stumbling upon it
          while searching for an online version of the full film, although that does not explain how
          the video registers an average of 20% of the 100 minutes viewed and more than 190
            <soCalled>finished</soCalled> viewings.<note>I also uploaded this video to my YouTube
            account, curious if it would gain an audience there as well, but it was immediately
            blocked by copyright bots, highlighting the different approaches the two sites take to
            copyright enforcement.</note></p>
        <p>The biggest insight that I gained from this experiment comes toward the end of the video
          — prior to sorting by shot length, I had assumed that the longest takes in
            <emph>Singin'</emph> would be within dance numbers, as the moving camera would capture
          the choreography without frequent editing.<note>I asked a few other film scholars what
            they thought would be the longest takes in the film as well, and they all likewise
            presumed they would be musical numbers, a useful confirmation of my assumptions.</note>
          However, only one of the nine longest shots to conclude this video is from a musical
          number; the rest are lengthy dialogue sequences. The longest shot of almost two minutes,
          as mentioned before, follows Don and Kathy through the studio lot and thus feels
          choreographed without music, but the others (all longer than a minute) include Kathy
          driving Don in her car, Don and Lena's red carpet interview at the start of the film, the
          cast rehearsing the dialogue scene in <emph>Dueling Cavalier</emph>, and numerous
          discussions behind the scenes debating the film studio's next moves. I decided to capture
          this insight by creating another deformation highlighting these nine longest takes in
          tandem (see <ref target="#figure17">Figure 17</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure17">
          <head>The nine longest takes in the film surprisingly include only one dance sequence,
            with the rest featuring dialogue sequences that foreground other forms of
            movement.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/320830971"/>
        </figure>
        <p>When arranged next to each other via spatial montage, organized by when they appear in
          the film chronologically, we can see shared traits in the film's cinematography and
          blocking, highlighting how movement is featured within many scenes even without dancing.
          This grid highlights how <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title> functions as a
          long-take film, with an average shot length of 16.4 seconds, a cutting rate comparable to
          many filmmakers renowned for their long-take styles, such Max Ophüls, Stanley Kubrick, and
          Michelangelo Antonioni.<note>See <ref target="http://www.cinemetrics.lv"
              >http://www.cinemetrics.lv</ref> for data on average shot lengths for thousands of
            films.</note> Few critics would place Stanley Donen and Gene Kelly in such company as
          masters of a long-take aesthetic, as their films are best known for cinematic movement
          more than duration. But as this experiment reveals, <emph>Singin'</emph> is anchored by
          many long-take shots and single-take scenes that run longer than the dance sequences it is
          most renowned for, suggesting the film and broader genre may be due for a formalist
          reappraisal.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>#4: Speed</head>
        <p>As the discussion of shot length suggests, timing is a central facet of film technique,
          and thus a realm ripe for deformation. Since video editing platforms like Premiere can
          easily change the duration of a video by speeding it up or slowing it down, this is a
          useful tool for deforming footage. As I outlined in my 2019 essay, one way that speed can
          deform a film is by creating an <soCalled>equalized pulse</soCalled> that remaps the time
          of every shot to match the sequence's average shot length <ptr target="#mittell2019"/>. In
          that essay, I deformed a number of films and scenes this way to chart a range of outcomes;
          here we can look at a number of different sequences from a single film whose equalized
          pulses are suggestive.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure18">
          <head>The entire film equalized to its average shot length of 16.4 creates a truly strange
            effect that is hard to endure.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/206568845/"/>
        </figure>
        <p>We might start by watching the entire film equalized to its shot length of 16.4 seconds,
          but this is a true endurance test (see <ref target="#figure18">Figure 18</ref>). Many of
          the moments are overwhelmingly strange, such as the opening sequence of the <title
            rend="quotes">Beautiful Girl</title> number starting at the thirty-three-minute mark,
          where the montage of quick shots that runs just fifty seconds in the original film drags
          out in super slow-motion over five minutes. Other segments provide compelling contrasts,
          as the sequence starting at the thirty-one-minute mark: Don and Lena are shooting the
          silent version of <emph>Dueling Cavalier</emph> as Simpson runs in to announce the
          transition to sound in hyperspeed. The film cuts to Lena speaking in super slow-motion,
          distorting her already unacceptable voice before lingering on the dismayed reaction of the
          male characters. Another interesting sequence is at the fifty-three-minute mark, as the
          test screening deforms the audience members mocking the glitchy film, making their
          reactions even more strange and unexpected than the failed screening itself. This
          deformation can also redirect our attention, as at the forty-three-minute mark in the
          lead-up to the <title rend="quotes">You Were Meant for Me</title> number — the longest
          take in the film flies by, which draws our attention to the movement through the studio
          space rather than the dialogue or performances. In the soundstage, some slow shots
          highlight Kathy and Don's emotions as they launch into the song and romance, but the
          sped-up song, compressing a four-minute number into a single minute, directs our attention
          to the camera movement and blocking within the space, more than the subtleties of the song
          and dance.</p>
        <p>The equalized pulse approach yields the most interesting outcomes when applied to musical
          numbers, where the tempo and rhythm of visual editing overrides those elements in the
          music and dance. When each shot conforms to a single length, the music contracts or
          expands to fill the equalized length, and thus creates strange and often compelling
          moments of unintended oddity.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure19">
          <head><title rend="quotes">Broadway Melody</title> equalized makes an already experimental
            sequence even more unusual.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/151095736"/>
        </figure>
        <p>In my 2019 essay, I wrote about the equalized pulse version of <title rend="quotes"
            >Broadway Melody,</title> where stark contrasts between long and short takes result in
          radical juxtapositions, as with the opening few shots where the opening shot of Don's
          singing sprints through at 387% speed, followed by a pan through the crowd at a glacial
          12% speed (see <ref target="#figure19">Figure 19</ref>). These strange contrasts highlight
          the artificiality and lack of narrative coherence already present in this number.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure20">
          <head>The equalized pulse version of <title rend="quotes">Singin’ in the Rain</title>
            provides moments of insight into movements via their deformed speeds.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/151158066"/>
        </figure>
        <p>A more typical musical number is the title track, which uses long takes with an average
          shot length of twenty-nine seconds for the sequence (see <ref target="#figure20">Figure
            20</ref>). When equalized to this rate, the contrasts are less severe, but still
          highlight how there is some editing variability in the original sequence — the famous shot
          of Kelly twirling on the street gets drawn out to 35% speed, allowing us to linger on his
          expressions and command of the space. This shot is followed by Kelly dancing along the
          curb at 128% speed, highlighting the playful comedy of his joyful splashing. While this
          deformed version is not particularly compelling on its own, it does allow us to see an
          incredibly familiar sequence in a new light.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure21">
          <head><title rend="quotes">Make 'Em Laugh</title> equalized to its average shot length
            reveals details about gesture, expression, and energy.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/152071802"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The <title rend="quotes">Make 'Em Laugh</title> number is driven by Donald O'Connor's
          physical comedy and energetic performance. When equalized to the number's average shot
          length of twenty seconds, each shot reveals something about the original, with sped up
          shots capturing O'Connor's frantic energy, while the slower moments highlight his more
          subtle facial expressions (see <ref target="#figure21">Figure 21</ref>). But what none of
          these equalized musical numbers do is create a clear rhythm through the equalized pulse
          defined by the tempo of the shots — the average shot lengths are too long to convey such a
          pulse through the cutting speed, an outcome that I've only found through very fast cut
          sequences, as with the <title rend="quotes">Roxanne</title> number in <emph>Moulin
            Rouge!</emph>, as discussed in my 2019 essay.</p>
        <p>Equalized pulse videos make the video track dominant within the sequence, as the visual
          edits dictate the speed and pace of each deformation. As discussed with the summed frames
          approach, sound does not conform as easily to manipulable units like frame or shot, as the
          audio track is continuous and unbroken, and thus hard to quantify. One way that audio
          might guide a similar equalization experiment would be to focus on the number of words
          spoken or sung, and then equalize a sequence to a standard number of words per temporal
          unit. How might such an audio-driven equalized pulse differ from one based on video
          edits?</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure22">
          <head>Equalizing the pulse based on number of words rather than by visual edits allows us
            to experience how lyrics are unequally distributed across a musical number.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/206354368"/>
        </figure>
        <p>I performed such a comparison with <title rend="quotes">Make 'Em Laugh,</title> by
          equalizing twenty-four words to the same pulse as the film's average shot length of 16.4
          seconds — twenty-four words was an arbitrary number, but inspired by the film's
          twenty-four frames per second rate. Thus I broke up the sequence into subclips by cutting
          after every twenty-four words in the scene (using the caption track to help quantify
          words), and then treating each subclip as a <soCalled>shot</soCalled> to be equalized. By
          juxtaposing these two equalizations, where the speed of each subclip changes at the same
          time every 16.4 seconds, we can contrast the relative rates of video editing and audio
          speaking/singing in this number (see <ref target="#figure22">Figure 22</ref>). Most
          notably, the word rate is faster than average for most of the song, as every clip is
          slowed down on the audio equalized pulse for the first three minutes of the video;
          however, the final three shots compress the final 2:20 of the number into only fifty
          seconds, with one dance-heavy clip playing at 619% in order to squeeze twenty-four words
          into 16.4 seconds. While this experiment helps highlight how words are distributed
          unequally in a musical number, ultimately the deformative impact is not significantly
          different than the equalized pulse driven by visual editing.</p>
        <p>Manipulating speed can be used to deform films in many ways beyond equalized pulses, as
          changing a clip's speed is a noticeable and often playful deformation. Many deformative
          possibilities are already widespread in the wilderness of online meme culture, where fans
          mess with popular culture in transformative and imaginative ways; while such memes may not
          be designed to lead to scholarly insight, like with GIFs, we can adopt such pre-existing
          fan strategies to see what deformative possibilities might arise. One meme that I felt
          could be aptly applied to videographic deformation is what might be called the
            <soCalled>but faster</soCalled> video: a film or music video gets faster every time
          something specific is said or happens onscreen. Allegedly started by a video called <ref
            target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JMG1Nl7uWko"><quote rend="inline">The Entire
                <emph>Bee Movie</emph> but every time it says <q>bee</q> it speeds up by
            15%</quote></ref>, the trend has been applied broadly to many sources to create a range
          of playful and often silly deformed videos <ptr target="#dahir2016"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure23">
          <head>Playing with speed following the logic of an online meme highlights some temporal
            contrasts as well as creating a distinctly goofy experience.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/375272867"/>
        </figure>
        <p>I applied this meme logic to <title rend="quotes">Broadway Melody,</title> but speeding
          up by 10% every time somebody sang the word <soCalled>dance.</soCalled> The result is
          frantic by the end, reaching 350% speed as Kelly and company flail to keep pace with the
          manic music. The result is definitely more fun and goofy than deep or insightful (not that
          there's anything wrong with fun and goofy), but at high-speeds, the video highlights the
          different modes of dance embedded within this long number, as the slow and sultry segments
          with Cyd Charisse feel almost normally paced compared to the frenetic group dances
          throughout, even though the lengthy ballet segment is sped up to 300%. This video is
          certainly among the more frivolous of the deformations I have made, but given that the
          thirteen-minute <title rend="quotes">Broadway Melody</title> number is the one part of the
          film that some viewers find too slow, this six-minute version might be more palatable as
          an alternative.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>#5: Space</head>
        <p>Just as video editing can easily play with time, manipulating spatial relations can
          create videographic deformations as well. Catherine Grant is a leader in this work,
          especially in thinking about the role of spatial montage in videographic expression. I was
          inspired by her video <title rend="quotes">Fated to be Mated: An Architectural
            Promenade,</title> which deforms a Fred Astaire / Cyd Charisse dance number from the
          film <emph>Silk Stockings</emph> by <quote rend="inline">sawing [them] in half</quote>
          <ptr target="#grant2018a"/>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure24">
          <head>Catherine Grant’s <title rend="quotes">Fated to be Mated</title> creates an
            innovative effect of spatial montage within a dance sequence.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/300303270"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Grant's video remakes the space of the dance sequence via a simple manipulation:
          splitting the frame vertically and reducing the scale of the left half (see <ref
            target="#figure24">Figure 24</ref>). She further deforms the sequence by slightly
          slowing it down and replacing the original music with contemporary electronica, but the
          core visual deformation of scale has the most notable impact — we see the dance space as
          fractured and made strange, while the duo navigates the space by transforming their
          relative scale. The most notable moments are when Astaire and Charisse are on opposite
          sides of the split, thereby shrinking one of them until they swap sides to rescale
          themselves, as at the four-minute mark. When I viewed this, I immediately began to apply
          Grant's concept to <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title> (see <ref
            target="#figure25">Figure 25</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure25">
          <head>The <title rend="quotes">Good Morning</title> number deformed as a <soCalled>scaled
              triptych</soCalled> highlights some of the ways that the choreography interacts with
            the setting as well as resonating with various character and performer power
            dynamics.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/307534874"/>
        </figure>
        <p>I chose <title rend="quotes">Good Morning</title> to deform through Grant's scaled
          approach because it was the dance number that most consistently matched her design, with
          multiple dancers distributed horizontally across the frame in an interesting architectural
          space. Because this trio required a triptych approach, I broke the frame into thirds and
          scaled them proportionately to mimic Grant's effect. The resulting deformative video is
          particularly satisfying when the three characters line up evenly into the scaled zones, as
          at the three-minute mark, or when they cross between zones to grow and shrink, as at the
          one-minute mark. The choreography places Kathy in the center for most of the number, with
          the two men orbiting around her with more advanced dance moves (as Debbie Reynolds was a
          novice dancer when cast in the film). Aptly Gene Kelly towers over his co-stars at the
          largest scale for most of the number, as he was not only the film's star but also its
          co-director and choreographer — and he was particularly unkind to Reynolds in rehearsing
          and shooting this number, with harsh criticism of her dancing and a late-night shoot that
          caused her feet to bleed <ptr target="#saunders2016"/>. This scaled triptych calls
          attention to the relative power of the performers in the frame in a way that maps the
          behind-the-scenes struggles onto the effortless footage.</p>
        <p>Grant's scaled approach makes onscreen spatial relations strange to create something new.
          Another approach seeks to use deformative methods to reconstruct the space as it was
          during the film's shoot. A version of this deformative method can be seen in Jeff Desom's
          impressive <title rend="quotes"><emph>Rear Window</emph> Timelapse</title>
          <ptr target="#desom2012"/>. Whereas Desom reconstructs that film's apartment building as a
          compiled static image with embedded footage throughout the film's run, I am more
          interested in simultaneously visualizing the film footage and camera movement to create an
          original spatial reconstruction. I applied this method to <title rend="quotes">You Were
            Meant for Me,</title> the musical number that takes place in a mostly empty soundstage
          and with fairly simple choreography (but complex camera movement) through that space (see
            <ref target="#figure26">Figure 26</ref>).</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure26">
          <head>Deforming a dance number to keep the soundstage static with a moving frame reveals
            how camera movement and choreography are navigating the set.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/375744576"/>
        </figure>
        <p>I find the effect quite startling, inverting our standard understanding of camera
          movement and cinematic space. By moving the frame through the cinematic space as it
          follows the dancers, it disrupts our perception of camera movement — the viewpoint feels
          fixed with a variable frame, rather than our standard perception of a fixed frame with a
          moving camera viewpoint. The frame moving through cinematic space directs our attention to
          the soundstage more than the dancers, as we come to expect the sparse props to appear in
          the same spot on the screen (which is also how I mapped the shots to reference points like
          the ladder and fan). The choreography becomes about moving through the space and guiding
          the frame, rather than the camera following the dancers.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure27">
          <head>Juxtaposing the original and deformed versions of <title rend="quotes">You Were
              Meant For Me</title> highlights how the deformation works and what is particularly
            revealed and concealed by each version.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/376915279" width="640" height="206"/>
        </figure>
        <p>Based on a number of people I have shared this video with, this spatial deformation is
          challenging for most viewers to truly intuit that it is remapping the camera movement as a
          shifting frame visualizing the soundstage. Thus I created a side-by-side version,
          comparing the original footage with the moving frame deformation (see <ref
            target="#figure27">Figure 27</ref>). Although this juxtaposition loses the disorienting
          power of the standalone video, it does highlight the analytical dimensions of the
          deformation, revealing the camera movement in ways that are hard to discern in the
          original. While it is hard to imagine such a deformation working for most scenes, it is
          well suited to reveal the spatial possibilities of the empty soundstage in this
          number.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>#6: Sound</head>
        <p>Most of the deformations I've documented thus far prioritize the visual channel over
          audio, whether via camera movement, editing pacing, or single frames. Largely this
          emphasis stems from the difficulty in breaking the audio channel of a film into discrete
          units that might be algorithmically manipulated; despite the fact that the production and
          post-production of a film actually uses separate tracks for audio much more than video,
          the final product provides only a sophisticated mix of audio elements that are challenging
          to separate. The mixed audio track is easy to manipulate, as editing platforms offer
          dozens of effects we might apply to the soundtrack, from equalization to reverb to
          distortion. However in my experiments, such manipulations do little than create a sonic
          mess without revealing any insights into the clips or creating a compelling aesthetic
          object on its own. But I certainly believe that sound is the realm of deformation that
          needs more expansion and development, and I offer two more experiments with the caveat
          that these are far from exemplary of the wide-ranging possibilities of sonic deformation
          that might be explored in the future.</p>
        <p>Similar to the <soCalled>but faster</soCalled> meme, we can take inspiration from online
          remix culture to deform films. One sound-driven remix protocol focuses on alphabetizing
          footage by the words spoken and/or sung to create an algorithmic pattern that is both
          predictable and arbitrary. An early example of this approach is <ref
            target="https://vimeo.com/150423718"><title rend="quotes">Of Oz the
          Wizard</title></ref>, an alphabetized version of the entire <emph>The Wizard of Oz</emph>
          which Matt Bucy first made in 2004, but became an online sensation in 2016 <ptr
            target="#vanderwerff2016"/>. While watching the entire film this way is an endurance
          challenge, there are moments where the effect is truly impressive — for instance, the
          section for W starting at the 1:31:00 mark charts through many iconic words
            (<soCalled>wicked,</soCalled>
          <soCalled>witch,</soCalled>
          <soCalled>wizard</soCalled>) as well as common ones (<soCalled>we,</soCalled>
          <soCalled>with</soCalled>) to create a mosaic of the film that has some coherence but also
          reveals new rhythmic patterns and intriguing juxtapositions. Similar full-film effects can
          be seen in <ref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5GFW-eEWXlc"><title rend="quotes"
              >ARST ARSW: <title rend="italic">Star Wars</title> alphabetized</title></ref>, as well
          as smaller-scale alphabetized songs, such as <ref
            target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=82nqsksBH7M">Toto's <title rend="quotes"
              >Africa</title></ref> or, because it's meme culture, <ref
            target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1wN43RaaYhk">Smash Mouth's <title rend="quotes"
              >All Star</title></ref>.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure28">
          <head>Rearranging the song <title rend="quotes">Moses Supposes</title> in alphabetical
            order creates an even more tongue-twisting version as inspired by meme culture.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/375491885"/>
        </figure>
        <p>I chose <title rend="quotes">Moses Supposes</title> as the number to alphabetize, as the
          tongue-twisting song about wordplay seemed best suited to reorganize in a way that plays
          with words (see <ref target="#figure28">Figure 28</ref>). The effect is certainly playful,
          as common short words like <soCalled>a</soCalled> and <soCalled>his</soCalled> blur into a
          rapid-fire hard to discern sequence, especially because in the original song such words
          are practically swallowed in the fast-paced patter rhythm; however, longer repeated words
          like <soCalled>erroneously</soCalled> or <soCalled>supposes</soCalled> standout in
          pleasurable sequences charting their different articulations in the song. To me, the
          effect of this alphabetized video is to highlight how the words and their performance
          create the playful tone of the number, deemphasizing the excellent choreography that more
          obviously drives the energy of the original.<note>Since the final two minutes of the
            number are solely dance without any singing until the concluding <soCalled>A</soCalled>,
            I excised the dance sequence from this deformation, leading to a much shorter version as
            alphabetized.</note></p>
        <p>Another model of audio-driven deformation is the <ref
            target="https://soundcloud.com/listentotv"><title rend="quotes">Listen to
            TV</title></ref> project by Casey McCormick and Eric Powell, which takes advantage of
          the layering possibilities of sound. McCormick and Powell take a full season of a
          television series and simultaneously play the audio of all episodes at once, creating a
          chaotic experience of simultaneity. While most of these sound collages foreground dialogue
          and sound effects, musical moments shine through the chaos, as with the phased instances
          of Iris DeMent's theme song <title rend="quotes">Let the Mystery Be</title> toward the
          start of their deformation of <emph>The Leftovers</emph> season two. For a comparatively
          sparse sonic series like <emph>Leftovers</emph>, many lines of dialogue or sound effects
          stand out in this layered deformation, triggering memories for fans who know the season
          well. <emph>Seinfeld</emph> season nine offers a very different experience, as the sonic
          layers are far messier, with the iconic bass riffs and audience laughter sufficiently
          obscuring nearly all recognizable dialogue, until the twenty-three-minute mark when most
          episodes end, but the extra-long series finale endures alone to be heard clearly.</p>
        <p>A film lacks the multiple episodes of a television season to open up such layering
          possibilities, but I considered the individual musical numbers as a comparable unit to an
          episode to create a layered version from <title rend="italic">Singin'</title> (see <ref
            target="#figure29">Figure 29</ref>). With fourteen discrete numbers (including multiple
          versions of the title song) playing at once, we experience sonic chaos punctuated by some
          sounds that stand out, such as the high-pitched singing in <title rend="quotes">All I Do
            is Dream of You,</title> the loud repeated calls of <title rend="quotes">Moses</title>
          at the one-minute mark, or periodic refrains of <title rend="quotes">Gotta Dance.</title>
          The instrumentation can also become notable, when brass or drums burst through the chaos
          to offer recognizable fanfares and beats. The sonic collage becomes more discernible as
          each number ends — by the three-minute mark, only seven songs remain, allowing us to hear
          more details from the performances, and creating more specific interplay between numbers.
          By the four-minute mark, all songs have ended except <title rend="quotes">Broadway
            Melody,</title> which I stopped at the next cadence to avoid another eight minutes of
          that number playing solo.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure29">
          <head>Layering the film’s musical numbers creates an intense sonic collage that becomes
            clearer as each song ends.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/293882022"/>
        </figure>
        <p>While <title rend="quotes">Listen to TV</title> is an audio-only project, I wanted to
          incorporate visuals into my layered musical number deformation, allowing the sound design
          to reveal potential visual insights. Given that layering video is much more difficult than
          audio, and my attempts to create layers of opacity resulted in simply an undistinguished
          blur, I decided to create video <soCalled>ribbons</soCalled> of each number's visuals,
          arranged chronologically across the frame. This approach reveals some of the dancing and
          physical performance presented within each number, yet makes the individual sequences hard
          to discern until adjacent numbers end to reveal more of each sequence. There are some fun
          juxtapositions, as at 1:55 when Kathy and Don appear to be dancing together in adjoining
          clips from <title rend="quotes">Good Morning</title> and <title rend="quotes">Singin' in
            the Rain,</title> but in general the visual effect is less interesting than the sonic
          collage.</p>
        <figure xml:id="figure30">
          <head>The layers of musical numbers can be shifted to be additive over time to conclude
            all at once, revealing different juxtapositions.</head>
          <media mimeType="video/mp4" url="https://player.vimeo.com/video/376421600"/>
        </figure>
        <p>The <title rend="quotes">Listen to TV</title> collages all start simultaneously, with the
          episodes ending in a more staggered timing, an approach I mimicked for my layered numbers
          deformation; however, I also made an <soCalled>additive</soCalled> version where the
          fourteen numbers all end simultaneously instead, and thus appear in order of descending
          length (see <ref target="#figure30">Figure 30</ref>). The effect of this version is to
          start with more comprehensible moments, emphasizing the interplay between <title
            rend="quotes">Broadway Melody</title> and <title rend="quotes">Beautiful Girl,</title>
          until new layers emerge over the course of the video. At the one-minute mark, we start to
          hear more from <title rend="quotes">Make 'Em Laugh</title> and <title rend="quotes">Good
            Morning</title> before the sonic chaos becomes overwhelming. The closing seconds are
          rewarding, as we hear how many numbers end with boisterous cadences out of the
          polyrhythmic stew of the final minute. Neither of these two versions is
            <soCalled>correct,</soCalled> but highlights how changing one variable or parameter in a
          deformation can create another iteration that is potentially as impactful as the
          original.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Conclusion:</head>
        <p>This litany of experiments in deforming <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title>
          are not offered as a comprehensive list of what might be done with the film or any other
          source text. I offer them each as small (or sometimes long) curiosities that might inspire
          future experiments or provoke insights into a familiar film. In teaching and presenting
          videographic criticism, I often suggest that one key impact of any successful videographic
          piece is to help people see and hear a source film through the eyes and ears of the
          critic, conveying a new perspective on a text. Deformative videographic work also allows
          us to see and hear a familiar film in a new way, but one that reveals new perspectives to
          both the critic and the audience. I did not perform any of these experiments with a clear
          idea of how they might turn out, and I was usually surprised at what was revealed (or what
          did not work at all). As critics, we too often approach a case study with our conclusions
          already drawn, eager to apply existing theoretical paradigms or critical assumptions to a
          new instance that proves our predetermined point. Deformative criticism is a reminder of
          the joys of discovery, finding something distinct and refreshing even within the most
          familiar film, breaking apart our critical preconceptions to point us toward new, strange
          pathways. That seems like an apt mission for digital approaches to audiovisual
          criticism.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Acknowledgements:</head>
        <p>The author would like to thank Kevin Ferguson, Catherine Grant, Christian Keathley, Casey
          McCormick, Ethan Murphy, Alan O'Leary, and Mike Zryd for their feedback and support of
          this project.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="bering2014" label="Bering 2014">Bering-Porter, D. <title rend="quotes">The
            Automaton in All of Us: GIFs, Cinemagraphs and the Films of Martin Arnold,</title>
          <title rend="italic">The Moving Image Review &amp; Art Journal</title>, 3: 2 (2014):
          178–92. <ref target="https://doi.org/info:doi/10.1386/miraj.3.2.178_1"
            >https://doi.org/info:doi/10.1386/miraj.3.2.178_1</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="dahir2016" label="Dahir 2016">Dahir, I. <title rend="quotes">People Are Making
            Music Videos That Get Faster Every Time A Word Is Said And It's The Best Thing
            Ever,</title>
          <title rend="italic">BuzzFeed</title>, (December 4, 2016). <ref
            target="https://www.buzzfeed.com/ikrd/people-are-making-music-videos-that-get-faster-every-time-a"
            >https://www.buzzfeed.com/ikrd/people-are-making-music-videos-that-get-faster-every-time-a</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="desom2012" label="Desom 2012">Desom, J. <title rend="quotes"><title
              rend="italic">Rear Window</title> Timelapse</title>(2012). <ref
            target="https://vimeo.com/37120554">https://vimeo.com/37120554</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="enns2012" label="Enns 2012">Enns, C. <title rend="quotes">Navigating
            Algorithmic Editing: Algorithmic Editing as an Alternative Approach to Database
            Cinema,</title>
          <title rend="italic">Millennium Film Journal</title>, 56 (2012): 66–72.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ferguson2017" label="Ferguson 2017">Ferguson, K. <title rend="quotes"
            >Edge</title> (2017). <ref target="https://vimeo.com/208869731"
            >https://vimeo.com/208869731</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ferguson2016" label="Ferguson 2016">Ferguson, K. <title rend="quotes">The
            Slices of Cinema: Digital Surrealism as Research Strategy.</title>In C. Acland and E.
          Hoyt (eds), <title rend="italic">The Arclight Guidebook to Media History and the Digital
            Humanities</title>, Reframe Books, Sussex, UK (2016). <ref
            target="http://projectarclight.org/book/">http://projectarclight.org/book/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ferguson2019" label="Ferguson 2019">Ferguson, K. <title rend="quotes"
            >Volumetric Cinema.</title> In M. Gold and L. Klein (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates
            in the Digital Humanities 2019</title>, University of Minnesota Press, Minneapolis
          (2019). <ref
            target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-f2acf72c-a469-49d8-be35-67f9ac1e3a60/section/a214af4f-2d31-4967-8686-738987c02ddf#ch28"
            >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-f2acf72c-a469-49d8-be35-67f9ac1e3a60/section/a214af4f-2d31-4967-8686-738987c02ddf#ch28</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="grant2018a" label="Grant 2018a">Grant, C. <title rend="quotes">FATED TO BE
            MATED: An Architectural Promenade</title> (2018). <ref
            target="https://vimeo.com/300303270">https://vimeo.com/300303270</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="grant2018b" label="Grant 2018b">Grant, C. <title rend="quotes">Screen
            Memories : A Video Essay on <title rend="italic">Smultronstället</title> / <title
              rend="italic">Wild Strawberries</title>,</title> Cinergie – Il Cinema e Le Altre Arti
          7: 13 (2018): 21–29. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2280-9481/7914"
            >https://doi.org/10.6092/issn.2280-9481/7914</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="keathley2019" label="Keathley et al. 2019">Keathley, C., Mittell, J., and
          Grant, C. <title rend="quotes">The Videographic Essay: Practice and Pedagogy</title>
          (2019). <ref target="http://videographicessay.org/works/videographic-essay/index"
            >videographicessay.org</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="malkowski2017" label="Malkowski 2017">Malkowski, J. <title rend="quotes"
            >Spatial Montage, in Miniature: Movie GIF Sets on Tumblr,</title> Society for Cinema and
          Media Studies conference presentation, Chicago (2017).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="manovich2001" label="Manovich 2001">Manovich, L. <title rend="italic">The
            Language of New Media</title>. The MIT Press, Cambridge (2001).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="mittell2019" label="Mittell 2019">Mittell, J. <title rend="quotes"
            >Videographic Criticism as a Digital Humanities Method.</title> In M. Gold and L. Klein
          (eds), <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities 2019</title>, University of
          Minnesota Press, Minneapolis (2019): 224–42. <ref
            target="https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-f2acf72c-a469-49d8-be35-67f9ac1e3a60/section/b6dea70a-9940-497e-b7c5-930126fbd180#ch20"
            >https://dhdebates.gc.cuny.edu/read/untitled-f2acf72c-a469-49d8-be35-67f9ac1e3a60/section/b6dea70a-9940-497e-b7c5-930126fbd180#ch20</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="newman2016" label="Newman 2016">Newman, M. <title rend="quotes">GIFs: The
            Attainable Text.</title>
          <title rend="italic">Film Criticism</title>, 40: 1 (2016): R1–7. <ref
            target="http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/fc.13761232.0040.123"
            >http://dx.doi.org/10.3998/fc.13761232.0040.123</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="oleary2019" label="O'Leary 2019">O'Leary, A. <title rend="quotes">No Voiding
            Time: A Deformative Videoessay.</title> 16:9 filmtidsskrift (2019). <ref
            target="http://www.16-9.dk/2019/09/no-voiding-time/"
            >http://www.16-9.dk/2019/09/no-voiding-time/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ramsay2011" label="Ramsay 2011">Ramsay, S. <title rend="italic">Reading
            Machines: Toward an Algorithmic Criticism</title>. University of Illinois Press,
          Champaign (2011).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="ray1995" label="Ray 1995">Ray, R. <title rend="italic">The Avant-Garde Finds
            Andy Hardy</title>. Harvard University Press, Cambridge (1995).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="rombes2014" label="Rombes 2014">Rombes, N. <title rend="italic">10/40/70:
            Constraint as Liberation in the Era of Digital Film Theory</title>. Zero Books
          (2014).</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="sample2012" label="Sample 2012">Sample, Mark. <title rend="quotes">Notes
            towards a Deformed Humanities,</title> Sample Reality (blog) (2012). <ref
            target="http://www.samplereality.com/2012/05/02/notes-towards-a-deformed-humanities/"
            >http://www.samplereality.com/2012/05/02/notes-towards-a-deformed-humanities/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="samuels1999" label="Samuels and McGann 1999">Samuels, L. and McGann, J. <title
            rend="quotes">Deformance and Interpretation.</title>
          <title rend="italic">New Literary History</title>, 30:1 (1999): 25–56.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="saunders2016" label="Saunders 2016">Saunders, T. <title rend="quotes">Bleeding
            Feet and Gene Kelly's Tongue: How <title rend="italic">Singin' in the Rain</title>
            Nearly Broke Debbie Reynolds.</title>
          <title rend="italic">The Telegraph</title> (December 29, 2016). <ref
            target="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/films/2016/12/29/bleeding-feet-gene-kellys-tongue-singin-rain-nearly-brokedebbie/"
            >https://www.telegraph.co.uk/films/2016/12/29/bleeding-feet-gene-kellys-tongue-singin-rain-nearly-brokedebbie/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="vanderwerff2016" label="VanDerWerff 2016">VanDerWerff, E. <title rend="quotes"
            >This Man Remixed <title rend="italic">The Wizard of Oz</title> Word by Word — and the
            Result Is a Surprising Delight.</title>
          <title rend="italic">Vox</title> (January 7, 2016). <ref
            target="https://www.vox.com/2016/1/7/10728184/wizard-of-oz-alphabetical-order"
            >https://www.vox.com/2016/1/7/10728184/wizard-of-oz-alphabetical-order</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="whalen2016" label="Whalen 2016">Whalen, Z. <title rend="quotes">Imj: A
            Web-Based Tool for Visual Culture Macroanalytics.</title> Zach Whalen (blog) (2016).
            <ref
            target="https://www.zachwhalen.net/posts/imj-a-web-based-tool-for-visual-culture-macroanalytics/"
            >https://www.zachwhalen.net/posts/imj-a-web-based-tool-for-visual-culture-macroanalytics/</ref>.</bibl>
        <bibl xml:id="zryd2004" label="Zryd 2004">Zryd, M. <title rend="quotes">Alone: Life Wastes
            Andy Hardy.</title> Senses of Cinema (2004). <ref
            target="http://sensesofcinema.com/2004/cteq/alone_life_wastes_andy_hardy/"
            >http://sensesofcinema.com/2004/cteq/alone_life_wastes_andy_hardy/</ref>.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->

</TEI>
