<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Interpretative Quests in Theory and Pedagogy</title>
            <author>Jeff Howard</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Jeff <dhq:family>Howard</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Texas, Austin</dhq:affiliation>

               <email>jeffrey-howard@mail.utexas.edu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jeff Howard teaches at the University of Texas, Austin, where he studies New
                     Media and literature. He received his B.A. in English from the University of
                     Tulsa in May 2000 and his M.A. in English from the University of Texas in May
                     2002. He successfully defended his dissertation, entitled Heretical Reading:
                     Freedom as Question and Process in Postmodern American Novel and Technological
                     Pedagogy, in fall 2005 and will receive his Ph.D. in English in May 2007. He is
                     currently working on a book-length project called Quests: Design, Theory, and
                     History in Games and Narratives.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000002</idno>
            <idno type="volume">001</idno>
            <idno type="issue">1</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2007-04-03">3 April 2007</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2007-02-28" who="Julia Flanders">Final check and revisions</change>
         <change when="2007-01-16" who="Julia Flanders">Entered final corrections from author,
            responding to queries</change>
         <change when="2007-01-12" who="Julia Flanders">Entered corrections from author, responding
            to queries</change>
         <change when="2007-01-08" who="Julia Flanders">Encoded article</change>
         <change when="2007-01-04" who="Julia Flanders">Finished copyediting</change>
         <change when="2007-03-13" who="John Walsh">Added affiliation</change>
         <change when="2007-03-14" who="John Walsh">Added "#" to internal links</change>
         <change when="2007-03-25" who="Julia Flanders">Gave all italic titles explicit rend value;
            fixed spacing and punctuation errors; added cit encoding.</change>
         <change when="2007-03-30" who="Julia Flanders">Entered final corrections based on author
            review</change>
         <change when="2008-06-12" who="Ashwini">Updated revisionDesc format, added publicationStmt,
            added blank teaser, changed xref to ref for validation with new schema, added "#" to
            target attribute of internal ref and ptr elements</change>
         <change when="2009-03-05" who="CRB">Added bio from bios.xml</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>In this paper, I extend theoretical understandings of the gaming activity and
               literary form called the <q>quest</q> and its relationship to issues of
               interpretation, focusing primarily on game theory with concrete examples as well as
               some broadly applicable pedagogical uses of these ideas in literature classrooms. The
               argument contributes to a recent theoretical and practical discussion of
                  <q>quests</q> by scholars of games studies such as <ref target="#aarseth2004"
                  >Aarseth 2004</ref>, <ref target="#juul2005">Juul 2005</ref>, <ref
                  target="#tosca2003">Tosca 2003</ref>, and <ref target="#tronstad2001">Tronstad
                  2001</ref>. I build upon and revise these theorists’ understandings by approaching
               a “quest” as a goal-oriented activity in which players undertake a journey in search
               of meaning. By demonstrating similarities between the literary traditions in which
               quests are central and the practice of digital game design, I argue that quests can
               be better understood theoretically and more productively used in the classroom if
               meaning and action are regarded as complementary design principles instead of
               conflicting impulses. A revised understanding of quests can help to mediate between
               games and narratives by showing strategies by which game designers have created
               meaningful action, often in ways that are either unconsciously similar to or inspired
               by the literary traditions of mythology, epic, and romance. Specifically, game
               designers can use level design to create labyrinthine spaces that encode thematic
               implications, in the tradition of literary allegory. If these symbolic spaces are
               coordinated with significant obstacles and challenges, the apparent conflict between
               meaning and action can be resolved through engaging gameplay that allows players to
               enact a range of thematic ideas, contributing to the ongoing replay value of a
               digital game. I also suggest ways in which this understanding of quests can allow
               literature teachers to plan assignments where students transform literary narratives
               into interpretative quests taking the form of digital games. As a paradigmatic
               example, I describe one such assignment, in which my students adapted episodes from
               Pynchon’s <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title> into design documents and
               prototypes, and I suggest some theoretical implications of its results for other
               instructors. By adapting works of literature into quests, students learn to discover
               and create meaning through the active exertion of cognitive and imaginative effort
               rather than absorbing it passively. </p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Extends theoretical understandings of the gaming activity and literary form called
               the <q>quest</q> and its relationship to issues of interpretation, focusing primarily
               on game theory with concrete examples as well as some broadly applicable pedagogical
               uses of these ideas in literature classrooms.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Quests: Theoretical Background</head>
            <p>A quest is both a genre of gaming activity and a structure that operates throughout
               an extended tradition of ancient and modern literary works that have inspired games
               and may also be better understood when taught through the medium of games. While
               there are many more general applications of gaming in literary pedagogy, quests are
               worthy of extended, focused study because the need for general works on game design
               and game pedagogy has already been filled. These pioneering studies include the work
               of Henry Jenkins and the Education Arcade at MIT <ptr target="#jenkins2004"/>, the
               encyclopedic compendium of Salen and Zimmerman’s <title rend="italic">Rules of
                  Play</title>
               <ptr target="#salen2004"/>, and James Paul Gee’s foundational academic study of game
               pedagogy in <title rend="italic">What Video Games Have to Teach Us about Learning and
                  Literacy</title>
               <ptr target="#gee2004"/>. These works, as well as general works on game design like
               Rollings and Adams’ <title rend="italic">On Game Design</title>, tend to explore a
               wide variety of game genres and their applications in many fields of <q>serious
                  gaming</q>, from teaching chemistry concepts and rhetoric to modeling business
               ethics and economics. Yet within these works, there is usually the acknowledgment
               that some related genres of games share a similar form of gameplay that emphasizes
               the unraveling of a mysterious underlying story, the development of character through
               the gradual acquisition of more powerful objects and skills, as well as the pursuit
               of a goal by traveling through a fantastical landscape. Such games include both
               single-player role-playing games and massively multiplayer online role-playing games
               (MMORPGs), as well as adventure and action-adventure games. These games are sometimes
               set apart from other game genres because they contain quests, to the point that some
               games researchers refer to them collectively as <q>quest games</q>. There have been a
               few foundational articles dealing specifically with the issue of quests, including
               Espen Aarseth’s <title rend="quotes">Quest Games as Post Narrative Discourse</title>
               <ptr target="#aarseth2004"/> and Susana Tosca’s <title rend="quotes">The Quest
                  Problem in Computer Games</title>
               <ptr target="#tosca2003"/>. Yet there remains much more to be studied in relation to
               this particular type of game and gaming activity; indeed, it may be more productive
               in light of the plethora of high-quality general works on game design to focus on
               particular threads such as the quest that give coherence, focus, and originality to
               new inquiries.</p>
            <p> The concept of the quest is useful in both the theory and practice of game design,
               because it offers one way out of the debate between narratologists and ludologists
               and into a more productive focus on issues surrounding the goal-oriented pursuit of
               meaning in both games and literature. As most scholars of new media now know,
               narratologists analyze games as stories, while ludologists insist that games should
               be studied for the features that are distinctively related to play, such as rules and
               simulation. While the definition of both narrative and game are highly contested by
               both camps, these theorists tend to define a narrative as a sequence of events that a
               reader follows in time, while a game is a set of rules for interactive play. The
               debate between narratologists and ludologists occupied much of the first wave of game
               studies, such as the essays in the anthology <title rend="italic">First Person: New
                  Media as Story, Performance, and Game</title>, but many games researchers are now
               claiming to have moved beyond this conflict. However, what it means to move forward
               differs greatly from party to party. In some cases, this statement amounts to an
               explicit or implied argument that one side won, usually the ludologists, who are seen
               to have attained a victory based upon the increasing acceptance of studying games on
               their own terms rather than through cinematic or literary theories. Other key figures
               in the former ludology/narratology debate, such as Gonzalo Frasca, have recently
               dismissed the debate as unproductive, claiming that it was always founded upon the
               misconception that game theorists were inherently hostile toward stories. </p>
            <p> In effect, current debates about the ludology/narratology question often result in
               even fiercer arguments over whether the debate is in fact over, followed by
               meta-debates over who won and how to proceed. Some scholars, such as Elizabeth Losh
               in <title rend="quotes">Making Things Public: Democracy and Government-Funded Virtual
                  Reality Simulations,</title> argue that a second debate has replaced the
               ludology/narratology debate in the form of a clash between critics who analyze the
               merits of persuasive games for achieving political change versus critics who critique
               the role of games in maintaining the current status quo <ptr target="#losh2006"/>.
               Such an approach shifts emphasis away from games and stories, opting for a more
               politicized methodology akin to the work of New Historicists and cultural studies
               scholars in literature departments. However, another move has involved gestures of
               rapprochement between game and narrative on the part of games researchers such as
               Espen Aarseth and his colleagues Jesper Juul and Susana Tosca at the Center for
               Computer Games Research in Copenhagen. These reconciliatory gestures often involve
               the identification of a mediating term, such as <q>quests</q>, that suggests
               qualities of both games and narrative while exhibiting features that require a
               distinct theoretical name. </p>
            <p>As Jesper Juul explains in <title rend="italic">Half-Real: Video Games Between Real
                  Rules and Fictional Worlds</title>, many scholars of video games have written
               about the concept of the quest as one attempt to resolve the ludology versus
               narratology debate <ptr target="#juul2005"/>: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#juul2005">As an attempt at bridge-building between
                     the open structure of games and the closed structure of stories, the concept of
                     quests has been proposed by Ragnhild Tronstad (2001), Espen Aarseth (2004b),
                     and Susan Tosca (2003). Quests in games can actually provide an interesting
                     type of bridge between game rules and game fiction in that the games can
                     contain predefined sequences of events that the player then has to actualize or
                     effect. </quote>
                  <ptr target="#juul2005" loc="17"/>
               </cit> Juul concisely defines the difference between a quest and a narrative by
               focusing on the issue of performative activity, which requires the player of a game
               to cause events to occur through effort rather than passively observing as these
               events unfold. Instead of dispensing with the events of narrative altogether, as some
               radical ludologists propose, theorists of the quest suggest that a game can contain a
               strong story without losing its playability if the player must enact its events. This
               concept includes the idea of <q>interactivity</q>, by which a player can change a
               narrative through her actions, but the quest is not only an interactive narrative.
               Rather than playing in a simulated world where unplanned narratives spontaneously
               emerge out of the rules of the game, a player of a quest undertakes a goal-oriented
               activity that requires her to overcome challenges in order to cause a range of
               possible but specific events to occur.</p>
            <p> In other words, the concept of a quest synthesizes games and narratives by
               emphasizing that the events of a narrative will not occur unless a player actively
               overcomes obstacles through the exertion of effort within a rule-based system in
               order to accomplish a task. Aarseth offers the most succinct definition of a quest
               when he writes that <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth2004">a player-avatar must
                  move through a landscape in order to fulfill a goal while mastering a series of
                  challenges. This phenomenon is called a quest</quote> (368). Aarseth’s definition
               highlights two important features of the quest: it involves movement through space
               that is directed toward the accomplishment of a task, and it requires the overcoming
               of difficulties in order to reach this goal. However, Aarseth’s definition tends to
               strip the idea of the quest of its content, such as the meaning of the goal or the
               nature of the space traversed. Many games have objectives, spaces, and challenges,
               but not all designers and players tend to use the word <q>quest</q> to describe all
               of these games. Indeed, the word <q>quest</q> figures most prominently in
               role-playing games and adventure games, from early adventure games like King’s Quest
               to more recent role-playing games like <title rend="italic">The Elder Scrolls IV:
                  Oblivion</title> or MMORPGs like <title rend="italic">Everquest II</title> and
                  <title rend="italic">World of Warcraft</title>. These games in fact allude to a
               long tradition of literature about quests that has been theorized by comparative
               mythologists such as Joseph Campbell and formalist literary critics such as Northrop
               Frye. These figures belong firmly to the narratological tradition that ludologists
               have tended to oppose but that can complement their work rather than clashing with
               it. Viewed in this light, Joseph Campbell’s three-part description of the Hero’s
               Journey is closer to Aarseth’s definition than it might at first seem: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#campbell1949">A hero ventures forth from the world of
                     common day into a region of supernatural wonder: fabulous forces are there
                     encountered and a decisive victory is won: the hero comes back from this
                     mysterious adventure with the power to bestow boons on his fellow man. </quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell1949" loc="30"/>
               </cit> As in Aarseth, Campbell emphasizes a protagonist’s spatial movement and
               accomplishment of difficult tasks in order to attain goals in the form of the ability
               to share his rewards. Unlike Aarseth, Campbell maps the content of the spaces that
               the hero moves through, characterized by a pattern of <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#campbell1949">separation</quote> from the world of everyday nature and
               society, <quote rend="inline" source="#campbell1949">initiation</quote> into a
               separate, fantastic world, and <quote rend="inline" source="#campbell1949"
                  >return</quote> with the fruits of his labor. Technically, Campbell’s definition
               refers to a <quote rend="inline" source="#campbell1949">journey</quote> rather than a
                  <q>quest</q> — a distinction that has to do with his interest in comparative
               mythology of many cultures rather than the exclusively Western literary tradition of
               romance. However, the literary critic Northrop Frye argues that <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#frye1957">romance</quote> is the genre or <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#frye1957">mythos</quote> that both contains the quest and is contained by
               it in its overall structure. Frye writes that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#frye1957">the essential element of plot in romance
                     is adventure, which means that romance is naturally a sequential and
                     processional form, hence we know it better from fiction than from drama </quote>
                  <ptr loc="186" target="#frye1957"/>
               </cit>. Adventure is not synonymous with romance but is rather its content, and this
               content takes the form of a sequence. For Frye, the quest is the climactic episode in
               a series of adventures, distinguished from minor events by its size and centrality.
               At the same time, the quest is also the formal principle by which the romance is
               structured, without which it would only be a sequence of adventures. Frye concisely
               summarizes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#frye1957">We may call this major adventure, the
                     element that gives literary form to the romance, the quest</quote>
                  <ptr loc="187" target="#frye1957"/>
               </cit>. Frye explains, <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#campbell1949">The complete form of the romance is
                     clearly the successful quest, and such a completed form has three main stages:
                     the stage of the perilous journey and the preliminary minor adventures; the
                     crucial struggle, usually some kind of battle in which either the hero or his
                     foe, or both, must die; and the exaltation of the hero.</quote>
                  <ptr target="#campbell1949" loc="30"/>
               </cit> Frye’s structure, like Campbell’s, has three parts, but Frye collapses the
               second of Campbell’s stages (<quote rend="inline" source="#campbell1949"
                  >initiation</quote>) into the first stage of his schema. Frye also ends the quest
               at the conclusion of Campbell’s second stage, directly after what Campbell would call
               the hero’s greatest battle or <quote rend="inline" source="#campbell1949"
                  >ordeal</quote> and his subsequent <quote rend="inline" source="#campbell1949"
                  >apotheosis</quote> or elevation to divinity.</p>
            <p> Because of the relationship of Aarseth’s and Tosca’s definitions of the quest to an
               extended ancient and modern literary tradition, this gaming activity has wide
               research and pedagogical implications. Susana Tosca observes the relevance of the
               genres of epic and romance as well as Joseph Campbell’s hero’s journey to the <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#tosca2003">background</quote> of quest games though she
               brackets the question of how closely the literary and gaming traditions can be
               related, arguing primarily that such theories are <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#tosca2003">not pointless</quote> to the study of games <ptr loc="4.1"
                  target="#tosca2003"/>. Tosca’s claim is insightful but deserves further
               development, since a more detailed and forceful statement of the relationship between
               the literary tradition of quests and their operation as a gaming activity would allow
               the quest concept to fulfill its bridge-building function more effectively. Stronger
               connections between the literary history of quest narratives and quest games can also
               offer strategies for how to teach a rich tradition of literature through technologies
               associated with a more recent but equally valuable selection of games, from early
               adventure games of the 1980’s to next-generation RPG’s. I have given an assignment in
               which I taught Thomas Pynchon’s <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title> by
               having students design quests, and there is vast lineage of narratives about quests
               that includes a variety of genres and periods. This includes ancient epics like
                  <title rend="italic">The Odyssey</title>, medieval romances like <title
                  rend="italic">Parzival</title> or <title rend="italic">The Quest for the Holy
                  Grail</title>, Renaissance allegory, nineteenth century novels patterned on the
               romance such as Jane Eyre, modern detective stories, and some postmodern narratives.
               This lineage of literature is indeed only a selection of possible works, but it is a
               rich, broad selection that is relevant to almost anyone in the humanities with an
               interest in canonical literature. It is certainly the case that some works of
               literature would be better taught through the analytical lens of the quest than
               others. For example, Charlotte Brontë’s <title rend="italic">Jane Eyre</title> would
               be productively understood as a protagonist’s voyage toward a meaningful goal across
               the obstacle-ridden, symbolic landscape of Thrushcross Grange, while the complex
               negotiations of power relations and parlor-room social maneuvering of <title
                  rend="italic">Pride and Prejudice</title> might be better taught through a
               simulation game like <title rend="italic">The Sims</title>. Nevertheless, there is an
               important feature of literary study in general that can be better understood through
               the paradigm of the quest than in any other game type: the pursuit of meaning as an
               active cognitive and imaginative enterprise rather than passive consumption, aimless
               social interaction, or uncommitted exploration of indeterminacy. </p>
            <p> The critical studies of the <q>quest</q> are increasingly becoming more than just a
               middle ground between game and narrative, focusing on the relationship between
               meaning and action, and revolving around the issue of significant gameplay.
               Theoretical and pedagogical understandings of the quest will increase if we focus
               further on the issue of meaning in quests, extending the idea of meaning beyond
               semiotic indications of function to thematic implications. For Tronstad, <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#tronstad2001">to do a quest is to search for the
                     meaning of it</quote>
                  <ptr target="#tronstad2001" loc="4.1"/>
               </cit>. However, Tronstad’s use of <quote rend="inline" source="#tronstad2001"
                  >meaning</quote> is primarily functional rather than thematic in that it is
               concerned with signs as indicators of a game object’s function rather than the ideas
               associated with it. Hence, she argues that when a player finds a new object, she must <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#tronstad2001">decode its significance in relation to
                     the quest, to come closer to the quest’s solution</quote>
                  <ptr target="#tronstad2001" loc="4.1"/>
               </cit>. In other words, if a player discovers a key, the <q>meaning</q> of this key
               is that there will be something for it to open, such as a chest. If the player then
               discovers a sword in the chest upon opening it, this sword might have the
                  <q>meaning</q> that a dragon must be fought and slain. This concept of meaning
               ignores the possibility of deeper thematic significance, in which the player must
               enact not only events, but also ideas and insights. Tronstad does argue that the
               motivation for the quest is the <quote rend="inline" source="#tronstad2001"
                  >promise</quote> of meaning, but she also argues that quests must withhold this
               meaning if they are to keep their status as quests. She explains that quests are
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#tronstad2001">promising their solution, promising
                     <emph>meaning</emph>. But as meaning is also the death of the quest, it is
                  frequently breaking this promise, in order to prolong the questing
                  experience</quote>
               <ptr target="#tronstad2001" loc="3"/>. By setting up a false binary between meaning
               and action, Tronstad overlooks the idea that players can enact meaning if the
               elements of the quest have thematic implications that are revealed through play. </p>
            <p> Because Tronstad’s focus on meaning is strictly functional, she views the movement
               from quest to narrative as uni-directional and unrepeatable. Thus, she argues that <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#tronstad2001">the paradox of questing is that as soon
                     as meaning is reached, the quest stops functioning as <emph>quest</emph>. When
                     meaning is found, the quest is <emph>history</emph>. It cannot be done again,
                     as it is simply not the same experience to solve a puzzle quest for the second
                     time. </quote>
                  <ptr target="#tronstad2001" loc="4.1"/>
               </cit> This analysis is only true if meaning is conceived of in the utilitarian
               manner that Tronstad suggests. It is true that once a player has determined what
               chest a key unlocks, the meaning of the key ceases to be interesting in subsequent
               playing sessions. However, if the key has greater, multivalent allegorical and
               symbolic connotations, then these might be productively and enjoyably enacted
               multiple times by different players, as they deepen their understanding of this
               meaning or seek a different interpretation. The performance of the quest multiple
               times would result in the production of different or more richly developed
               constatives. Conversely, the constatives of literary narratives can be transformed
               into quests, which has the advantage both of making literature interactive and of
               bringing deeper symbolic meaning to the actions of the quest. Tosca raises the
               possibility of literary narratives inspiring quests but temporarily brackets the
               issue, noting that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#tosca2003">this is more a question of adaptation
                     from one medium to another, and as such is beyond the limits of this
                     paper</quote>
                  <ptr target="#tosca2003" loc="4.1"/>
               </cit>. At the same time, she does raise a series of interesting questions about to
               what extent such an adaptation would re-create the book’s <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#tosca2003">story-world,</quote> its events, or be a <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#tosca2003">thematic adaptation</quote> of the work. The <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#tosca2003">thematic adaptation</quote> possibility
               highlights the importance of meaning in quests, the feature that Tosca explores least
               in her criticisms of existing quests and her suggestions for new ones. Tosca’s
               students criticized many existing quests in games for being <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#tosca2003">too linear, boring, repetitive, and
                     unrelated to the character’s <q>physical</q> and emotional development.</quote>
                  <ptr loc="1" target="#tosca2003"/>
               </cit> In response to these critiques, they created quests that were non-linear,
               emotionally involving, and had surprising plot twists. While these are positive
               pedagogical accomplishments, a key aspect of interesting quests is not just emotion
               or surprise but rather meaning, something that Tosca acknowledges but does not expand
               upon in her statement that <cit>
                  <quote rend="inline" source="#tosca2003">the quest or mission format allows for a
                     contextualization of the game’s actions in a more or less meaningful
                     story</quote>
                  <ref target="#tosca2003">Tosca 2003, abstract</ref>
               </cit>. This raises the question of how to make quests more meaningful rather than
               less, and also of how to analyze the ways in which both designers and players create
               and enact meaning. Because critics often already treat spaces and objects in works of
               literature as having dense potential meaning, quests based on these narratives can
               inherit these meanings or complicate and challenge them. Designing a quest based on a
               work of literature is itself an act of interpretation by which the designer considers
               how a player will enact a meaning or range of possible meanings available in a
               text.</p>
            <p> Because meaning is a highly difficult and complex concept, it deserves further
               theorization in order to function effectively both in the theory and practice of
               games generally and of quest games more specifically. Tronstad’s emphasis on the
               promise of meaning as the motivation of a quest is the beginning of such a movement,
               but she and Aarseth tend to see meaning and action as conflicting principles. Aarseth
               puts this conflict in the most extreme terms in his declaration that the quest games
               with most replay value are those that have no meaning at all. In order to better
               understand the operation of quests and their pedagogical function within literature
               classrooms — whose goal is often the interpretation of meaning — it would be
               productive to regard meaning and action not as opposed elements of quests but as
               complementary components that can be synthesized in meaningful action. Moreover, such
               a claim is borne out by close study of the games whose designers and players focus
               most overtly on quests as a gaming activity, such as contemporary role-playing games.
               Game designers, teachers, and students can better understand how to create a context
               in which meaning can emerge in quests by studying two aspects of this gaming activity
               and literary structure: its spaces and challenges, with particular emphasis on the
               objects sought out by players and questing heroes. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Spaces of the Quest</head>
            <p> Quests gain much of their interest and meaning from the player’s movement through
               simulated space, which acquires meaning as the environment upon which and within
               which the player must act. Jenkins offers a useful context for the role of space in
               quests in his article <title rend="quotes">Game Design as Narrative
                  Architecture,</title> where he argues that game designers do not create linear
               narratives but rather spaces that contain either <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#jenkins2004">embedded</quote> narratives suggested by the arrangement of
               space or <quote rend="inline" source="#jenkins2004">enacted</quote> narratives that
               the player may perform in various orders <ptr target="#jenkins2004" loc="124–8"/>. A
               quest is more structured than what Henry Jenkins calls <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#jenkins2004">emergent narrative</quote> and more focused on the
               overcoming of challenge than Jenkins’ <quote rend="inline" source="#jenkins2004"
                  >enacted narrative.</quote> An emergent narrative is a sequence of events that
               develops spontaneously out of a player’s rule-based interactions with a simulated
               world, such as <title rend="italic">The Sims</title>. Once the player has performed a
               series of events within a playing session or series of sessions in such a game, she
               could recount them in the past tense and describe their relationship to each other or
               emotional significance to her. An <quote rend="inline" source="#jenkins2004">enacted
                  narrative</quote> is a game structure that allows a player to perform an event in
               a story that she is already familiar with as a spectator, such as Jenkins’s example
               of picking up a lightsaber and defeating Darth Maul in a game adaptation of <title
                  rend="italic">Star Wars: Episode I</title>. </p>
            <p> A quest is more structured than an emergent narrative because it has a predefined
               structure of events that will occur if the player succeeds, but it requires more
               effort from a player than an enacted narrative because these events will not occur
               unless the player overcomes certain challenges. Moreover, in a quest a player is not
               only bringing a story to fulfillment but is also enacting a set of thematic ideas and
               implications associated with the events of this story and experienced on the level of
               gameplay. The word <q>quest</q> implies the search for a valuable goal, a goal with
               significance to the player or to her virtual identity as avatar within a simulated
               world. One would not probably not speak of a <q>quest</q> to take out the trash in
                  <title rend="italic">The Sims</title> or to gobble all of the white dots in <title
                  rend="italic">Pac-Man</title>, except ironically. However, both designers and
               players have long referred to goals with special significance in the gameworld as
                  <q>quests</q>, such as Sir Graham’s search in <title rend="italic">King’s Quest
                  I</title> for the three magical treasures that will save the Kingdom of Daventry,
               or the player’s attempt to close the gateway to the hellish plane of Oblivion in
                  <title rend="italic">The Elder Scrolls IV</title>. Even the <q>side quests</q> of
               role-playing games, which are distinguished from a <q>main quest</q> by their lack of
               an epic underlying storyline, have significance to the player in terms of either the
               acquisition of greater skills for her virtual identity or the benefit of her guild.
               Because quests are associated with significant objectives, it is also possible for
               them to convey thematic meaning in the form of allegory and symbolism that operates
               not only through the representational strategies of the game but also through the
               actions that each player performs within space.</p>
            <p> Indeed, the spaces through which players move as they overcome challenges and
               fulfill the goals of quests can themselves encode meaning through the time-tested
               strategies of spatial allegory that have operated in quest narratives (and literary
               allegories more generally) since <title rend="italic">The Quest of the Holy
                  Grail</title> and <title rend="italic">The Faerie Queene</title>. In <title
                  rend="italic">Mapping the Faerie Queene: Quest Structures and the World of the
                  Poem</title>, Erickson argues that the vertical and horizontal spatial
               configuration of Spenser’s fictional cosmos conveys much of the thematic implications
               of the virtues embodied by the knights and their nation-building or ethical quests
                  <ptr target="#erickson1996"/>. This scheme of meaningful landscapes <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#bolter1999">remediates</quote> allegory, to use Bolter and
               Grusin’s terms for the reworking of one medium in terms of another. Bolter and Grusin
               observe that in digital art <quote rend="inline" source="#bolter1999">naïve allegory
                  is common, as we see, for example, in the computer game Myst with its allegory of
                  the end of the book</quote>
               <ptr target="#bolter1999" loc="136"/>. By <quote rend="inline" source="#bolter1999"
                  >naïve allegory,</quote> they refer to art with an <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#bolter1999">obvious message,</quote> presumably to be contrasted with
               heavily ironized, ambivalent allegory, such as that theorized by Paul de Man. They
               regard the <quote rend="inline" source="#bolter1999">losing</quote> endings of the
               computer game <title rend="italic">Myst</title>, in which the player is entrapped
               within imprisoning books instead of being able to move freely through the space of
               computer graphics, as an allegorical critique of the book at the same time that the
               game remediates the book through its interface and plot.</p>
            <p> However, the tradition of creating meaningful spaces originates in literary
               allegories that are far from naïve, and which encourage a degree of engagement that
               prefigures digital games. As Erickson argues, the starting and ending points of the
               knights’ quests in Spenser’s poems themselves convey meaning. These quests begin in
               historical sixth-century Britain and then proceed into Faeryland, thereby conjoining
               the historical and political concerns of epic poetry with the private, fantastic
               themes of chivalric romance. Moreover, Erickson points out that Gordon Teskey’s
               recent theories of Spenserian allegory emphasize a <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#erickson1996">game of <q>interpretative play</q>,</quote> in which
               readers learn not just by example but <quote rend="inline" source="#erickson1996">by
                  becoming engaged, through the play of interpretation, in the theory of
                  virtue.</quote> While Erickson and Teskey are not discussing New Media, the
               combination of Erickson’s focus on the imaginative spaces of the poem and Teskey’s
               interest in its elicitation of readers’ active involvement suggests that Spenser was
               already striving for the synthesis of <quote rend="inline" source="#ryan2001"
                  >immersion and interactivity</quote> that Marie-Laure Ryan upholds as the ideal of
               digital art <ptr target="#ryan2001"/>. Aarseth’s evocative phrase for video game
               representations of space, <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth2000">allegories of
                  space,</quote> turns out to have another dimension besides the one that he focuses
               on <ptr target="#aarseth2000"/>. Aarseth argues that the spaces of digital games can
               only be <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth2000">allegories</quote> of space
               because they consist of digital implementations of automated rules necessary to
               create a game rather than actual physical or social laws. As he puts it, <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#aarseth2000">[i]n other words, the topology of even
                     the most ‘open’ computer generated landscapes makes them quite different from
                     real space, and controlled in ways that are not inherent in the original
                     physical objects they are meant to represent. This makes them allegorical: they
                     are figurative comments on the ultimate impossibility of representing real
                     space. </quote>
                  <ptr loc="169" target="#aarseth2000"/>
               </cit> While the unbridgeable gap between representation and an unattainable
               objective reality has been well explored in De Man’s theories of allegory, the spaces
               of quests are also <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth2000">figurative
                  comments</quote> on a wide variety of actions and ideas other than the
               self-reflexive problems of representing space, such as the goals of the player and
               their relationship to a larger simulated world. For example, in the classic
               role-playing game, <title rend="italic">Ultima IV: The Quest of the Avatar</title>,
               designer Richard Garriott deliberately sets up an intricate system of correspondences
               between a set of moral virtues and the representational features of the game’s
               simulated world, including its colors, villages, and directions of the compass. As
               players battle monsters, seek out hidden shrines, and search for magical artifacts in
               each of the game’s sub-quests, they are acting out the game’s allegorical meanings
               (or failing to act them out), in such a way that gameplay gradually reveals these
               correspondences, and successful completion of the quests necessitates an
               understanding of them. </p>
            <p> Following both Spenser’s literary allegories and Garriott’s allegorical games, the
               environment of the maze is a key spatial principle whose organization can instantiate
               multiple interpretative paths as well as the search for a significant object through
               the active descent into a treacherous environment. Quests in games and literature
               often take place in mazes, which proliferate in the <q>descents into the
                  underworld</q> of myth and the <q>dungeon crawls</q> of role-playing games.
               However, as Natkin argues in his analysis of level design, the coordination of the
               maze model with other gameplay elements is crucial to create immersive gameplay <ptr
                  target="#natkin2006"/>. Distributed through this maze must be spatial obstacles to
               be overcome, such as locked doors and chasms, as well as objects and scripted events
               that specify the rules for overcoming these challenges and rewards for doing so.
               Indeed, Natkin draws much of his analysis of level design from Guardiola, who
               suggests that <quote rend="inline" source="#natkin2006">a level is made up of a
                  collection of quests,</quote> reinforcing the idea that contemporary game design
               is increasingly leaning toward a quest-based understanding of game space <ptr
                  target="#natkin2006"/>. Without obstacles and rewards combined through logical
               event scripting, a level runs the risk of becoming aimless wandering, which in
               interpretative terms equates to a navigation of many possible meanings without ever
               arguing for their relative merits or analyzing them in depth. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Challenges of the Quest</head>
            <p> In order to progress through the spaces of quests, the player must overcome trials,
               and quests can thus be classified in part by the challenges that they provide and the
               initiations that result from overcoming these obstacles. A typology of quests would
               also include features such as the player’s objective, the actions that he must
               undertake, and the quest’s location. To construct a <q>typology</q> and
                  <q>grammar</q> of these quests like that proposed by Aarseth, one would also need
               to examine the ways in which plot-lines inspired by literary genres give rise to
               quests or develop out of them. Although quests are not synonymous with narratives,
               story-lines offer an important motivation for undertaking quests as well as a reward
               for completing them. Taking into account features of both action and narrative,
               online communities of players have developed semi-formal classifications for quests,
               which have been further formalized in official <q>strategy guides</q>. These schemes
               can be strengthened through close analysis of quests in games with a great variety of
               quests, like <title rend="italic">World of Warcraft</title> and <title rend="italic"
                  >Oblivion</title>. </p>
            <p> In-game text and gaming communities tend to classify quests as <q>fetch quests</q>,
                  <q>delivery quests</q>, <q>dungeon crawls</q>, <q>escort quests</q>, and <q>kill
                  quests</q>, a typology that is reinforced by R.V. Kelly’s similar list of quest
               types in <title rend="italic">Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing games</title>
               <ptr target="#kelly2004"/>. These categories can be further divided into
               sub-categories, combined with each other, and melded with narrative back stories to
               produce a wide variety of possible quests. In a <q>fetch quest</q>, a character must
               find a valuable, often magical object and return it to a non-player character (NPC)
               for a reward. While the term <q>fetch quest</q> is often used critically by gamers
               because this device has become ubiquitous and sometimes seems clichéd, the original
                  <q>quest for the holy grail</q> is itself a <q>fetch quest</q>. Indeed, the
               etymological origins of quest in <q>questare</q> (Latin: to seek) implies that the
               search for something absent or hidden is fundamental to questing. Vladimir Propp
               argued that this motif was the distinguishing feature of quests, which allowed them
               to take a central role in the morphology of folktales <ptr target="#propp1968"/>.
               Despite the familiarity of the form, the interest of such a quest depends upon the
               value and meaning of the object sought as well as the challenges that must be
               surmounted to reach it. Items necessary for the completion of a quest are often set
               aside in a player’s inventory as <q>quest items</q>, which cannot be destroyed or
               discarded because doing so would bring the plot to a stand-still. Such artifacts are
               distinguished from the proliferation of objects in the game that have strictly
               utilitarian or ornamental functions, such as ordinary weapons, tapestries, and
               furniture. Unlike these items, quest items are either unique (like the Holy Grail) or
               a component of a larger item, like the seven pieces of a magical staff or the three
               portions of the Triforce in the <title rend="italic">Legend of Zelda</title> games.
               These objects are invested with significance as objects playing a key role in
               unfolding storylines, like the <q>McGuffins</q> of film but with an interactivity
               that comes from the player’s ability to use them to cause a narrative to progress.
               They often also accrue personal, political, and even cosmic meaning as instantiations
               of the battling demonic and divine forces seeking to control the simulated world of
               the game. For example, in <title rend="italic">The Elder Scrolls IV:
               Oblivion</title>, the four middle quests in the main quest-line involve finding
               Azura’s star, the armor of Tiber Septim, a great Welkynd stone, and a great Sigil
               stone for the emperor’s heir. Fetch quests in <title rend="italic">Oblivion</title>
               range from mundane but sometimes charming <q>collection quests</q>, such as looking
               for twelve scales from a rare breed of Slaughterfish, to cosmic, such as the search
               for a Great Sigil Stone. The slain emperor’s heir uses this stone to close one gate
               to hell and open a doorway to the <q>paradise</q> where the final battle between good
               and evil takes place. A frequent variant on the <q>fetch quest</q> could be referred
               to as the <q>delivery quest</q> (less formally known as the <q>fedex quest</q>), in
               which a player must carry an item from one character to another. <q>Kill quests</q>
               or <q>assassination quests</q> require the player to slay monsters or hostile NPC’s,
               either as an end in itself that remedies an injustice or as a means to an end, since
               the gaining of an item in a fetch quest often requires the defeat of many enemies. </p>
            <p> Kill quests involve extensive combat with monsters, resulting in the intense
               violence that many opponents of video games decry. But they also allow a context in
               which players can confront, reflect upon, and in some cases refrain from battles with
               the forces regarded as <q>Evil</q> or <q>Other</q> by a given society. This violence
               is no more intense, detailed, or gratuitous than that practiced by Odysseus as he
               engages in his <q>kill quest</q> to slay the Cyclops or the suitors. Looking back
               over a long history of quest narratives, scenes in works of literature now considered
                  <q>classic</q> revolve around brutal violence that equals or outstrips the <title
                  rend="italic">Grand Theft Auto</title> series. Combat pervades chivalric romance,
               since large parts of the action in these narratives involve ritualized jousting and
               swordplay between knights, not to mention the slaying of roving beasts and dragons.
               Indeed, Frye saw <q>dragon-killing</q> as the central, defining motif of quests in
               romances (189). Digital games simply put the responsibility for this violence on the
               player, who must acquire the dexterity and persistence necessary to destroy her
               enemies and may (in the case of games like <title rend="italic">Fable</title> or
                  <title rend="italic">Oblivion</title>) determine the role of violence in the
               development of her player-character and the game’s simulated world. As with all
               quests, the purpose and meaning of the violence determines the consequences of the
               player’s actions. It is equally possible in Oblivion to murder random citizens or to
               destroy a demonic lord, but one action will put the player’s avatar in jail while the
               other will result in a quest reward. Video games are often criticized for their
               violence, yet combat constitutes one of the key trials by which the meaningful
               conflicts of quest narratives are manifested, as well as one of the most fruitful
               opportunities for the conversion of narrative into action. </p>
            <p> Similar opportunities for meaningful action can emerge from an <q>escort quest</q>,
               in which the player must guide an NPC from one location to another while protecting
               this character from enemies. In Oblivion, one early such quest involves bringing the
               slain emperor’s heir, Martin Septim, from the besieged town of Kvatch to a refuge in
               Weynon Prior. Participation in such a quest results in an emotional investment toward
               the charge that the player protects, resulting at first involuntarily from the need
               to shield the non-player character in order to progress in the game. Yet, such a
               quest can have larger implications concerning the degree of one’s complicity with a
               prevailing political regime in a game (for example, the opportunity to respect or
               abandon the Emperor in the opening quest of <title rend="italic">Oblivion</title>),
               or the strength of a personal connection, such as the potentially poignant or tragic
               escort quest of Hero’s mother in <title rend="italic">Fable</title>. </p>
            <p> Thematic implications can occur with even greater subtlety in quests involving
               puzzles, which refer to any cognitive problem that must be solved in order to
               progress further in the game. Puzzles often take the form of navigating mazes,
               unlocking secret doors, answering riddles, deciphering codes, and finding and using
               unfamiliar objects or <q>treasures</q>. Puzzles most commonly appear in certain
               genres, such as adventure games or designated <q>puzzle games</q>, but Juul argues
               that the challenges exemplified in puzzles are characteristic of games in general
                  <ptr target="#juul2005"/>. A well-designed puzzle has both thematic and cognitive
               aspects, since it requires designers and players to enact themes from the work at the
               same time that they solve an informational or mechanical problem. In <title
                  rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages</title>, Montfort offers an excellent example
               of how players may enact themes in games. In his analysis of Andrew Plotkin’s
               experimental interactive fiction <title rend="italic">So Far</title>, Montfort
               argues, <quote rend="inline" source="#montfort2003">the workings of the IF world and
                  the themes of <title rend="italic">So Far</title> must be enacted [. . .] for the
                  interactor to make progress</quote>
               <ptr target="#montfort2003" loc="210"/>. Montfort is discussing a text-based game in
               which the solutions of puzzles require the player to both uncover and act out a theme
               of relationships that are <quote rend="inline" source="#montfort2003">so close to but
                  so far from</quote> perfection by moving various items (like the two posts of a
               gate or two radioactive bricks) into proximity without allowing them to touch.
               Montfort’s example is representative of a larger tradition of games that conjoin
               meaning and action in gameplay rather than putting them in conflict, including both
               early role-playing games like <title rend="italic">Ultima IV</title>, more recent
               ones like <title rend="italic">The Elder Scrolls</title>, and experimental
               action-adventure games like <title rend="italic">The Indigo Prophecy</title>. Rather
               than having to <q>break</q> the promise of meaning in order to maintain the interest
               of the quest, these games have replay value precisely because fulfillment of their
               challenges allows players to contemplate nuances of thematic implication through
               their active effort rather than through passive spectatorship. In such a game, the
               distance between Aarseth’s <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997"
                  >interpretative</quote> and <quote rend="inline" source="#aarseth1997"
                  >configurative</quote> functions diminishes, as does the difference between
               Zimmerman’s <quote rend="inline" source="#zimmerman2004">cognitive
                  interactivity</quote> involved in processing narratives (which he associates with
               readers' <quote rend="inline" source="#zimmerman2004">interpretative participation
                  with a text</quote>) and the <quote rend="inline" source="#zimmerman2004">explicit
                  interactivity</quote> of designed choices (which he associates with games) <ptr
                  target="#zimmerman2004" loc="158"/>; <ptr loc="64–65" target="#aarseth1997"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Pedagogical Implications of Interpretative Quests</head>
            <p>By deliberately merging the interpretative and gameplay function performed by
               players, game design can be taught as a form of interpretative writing within
               literature classrooms. Such an assignment could involve transforming virtually any
               literary narrative into a quest, and any work that falls within the paradigmatic
               selection running from ancient epic to postmodern quest narrative would be
               particularly amenable to this form of adaptation. I have given one such assignment to
               my sophomore English literature class in which I asked students to adapt Thomas
               Pynchon’s postmodern novel <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title> into a
               quest. </p>
            <p>The assignment to design an interpretative quest has two components: a six page
               written paper combining features of a game design document and a traditional
               interpretative essay, as well as a small multimedia prototype of one part of the
               game. The practice of constructing design documents is familiar to practitioners of
               contemporary game design, as explained in books such as <title rend="italic">Andrew
                  Rollings and Ernest Adams on Game Design</title>
               <ptr target="#rollings2003"/>. A design document is a verbal and graphical
               presentation of the core elements of a game, such as its gameplay, levels, and
               narrative. In the game industry, such a document is usually prepared as a
               presentation to be given to potential investors, since commercial games often require
               millions of dollars, vast teams of designers with diverse skills, and years of
               planning, execution, and marketing. Hence, game designers need presentations to show
               others that their designs are sound as well as to keep the team focused on an overall
               plan.</p>
            <p> The design document in an English class differs from one made for the game industry
               in that it focuses more explicitly on meaning. However, the influential game design
               theorists Salen and Zimmerman do see meaning as a high priority in game design, and
               in documentation more generally, as when they write that <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#salen2004">meaning, play and games are intimately related concepts. The
                  goal of successful game design is <hi rend="bold">meaningful play</hi>
               </quote>
               <ptr target="#salen2004" loc="37"/>. Indeed, they define design in terms of <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#salen2004">the creation of meaningful experience,</quote>
               explaining that <quote rend="inline" source="#salen2004">
                  <hi rend="bold">design</hi> is the process by which a <hi rend="bold"
                     >designer</hi> creates a <hi rend="bold">context</hi> to be encountered by a
                     <hi rend="bold">participant</hi>, from which meaning emerges</quote>
               <ptr loc="37" target="#salen2004"/>. Students create a context in which meaning can
               emerge by designing the aspects of a game that correspond to the most theoretically
               distinctive features of quests, including the spaces, challenges, and objects. The
               design document should contain descriptions and analyses of these elements, including
               textual and contextual evidence explaining what they mean as well as reflection on
               how the students’ own interpretative perspective helps to create this meaning.</p>
            <p> Because of the role of space in shaping quests, adaptations of literary texts work
               best when the designer does not reproduce the events of the narrative in a strictly
               linear fashion, but instead re-creates spaces in which players can bring about some
               of these events and their meanings. Building on a fictional world already created by
               an author, the student translates these geographic features into a world of ideas
               that can be explored by players. This requires interpretative decisions, since a
               location like the surrealist painting of Remedios Varo’s tower described in <title
                  rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title> could be read as an emblem of Oedipa’s
               inescapable solipsism, as a foreshadowing of her escape through the use of
               imagination, or as a range of intermediate possibilities. Many of the most successful
               essays based their game concepts around spaces represented in Varo’s art, since
               Pynchon prominently alludes to her painting <title rend="quotes">Embroidering Earth’s
                  Mantle</title> as a recurrent, ekphrastic metaphor in the novel. This topic helped
               to generate game ideas because Varo’s painting represents a dreamlike space conducive
               to a quest plot: a tower in which a group of captive girls weaves a tapestry that,
               paradoxically, contains the world. Moreover, the sequence of three paintings in the
                  <q>triptych</q> that Pynchon alludes to suggests the structure of a journey in
               three stages (approaching the dreamlike world, imprisonment, and escape), which
               provides the potential outline for a quest. </p>
            <p> Students produced three different analytical approaches to the thematic significance
               of these paintings and three different ways of enacting these interpretations in
               gameplay, all of them taking place within the metaphorical <q>space</q> of Varo’s
               paintings. One student argued that the paintings suggest the mind’s ability to escape
               the confines of socially constructed reality through the higher reality of the
               imagination — the etymological meaning of the <q>sur-real</q> as practiced by Varo. A
               second student used the space of the Varo painting as the setting for a different
               game that takes the opposite interpretative stance, in which the weaving of the
               tapestry reflects Oedipa’s solipsistic entrapment within a reality entirely created
               by her own mind. A third student synthesized these two interpretations, suggesting
               that her game design will reward players who remain open to both surrealistic and
               solipsistic views of the space of the Varo painting. In a highly nuanced thesis
               statement, this student writes, <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#neugebauer2006">if Oedipa could easily choose a side,
                     she would then cease to touch the <q>real world</q> that she so longs to find —
                     creating the paradox that as long as Oedipa looks for <q>reality</q>, or <hi
                        rend="italic">life</hi>, she lives in it; but as soon as she assumes she has
                     found it, it ceases to exist for her. </quote>
                  <ptr target="#neugebauer2006"/>
               </cit> Neugebauer’s thesis suggests one way in which visualizing <title rend="italic"
                  >The Crying of Lot 49</title> spatially allowed a student to develop stylistically
               nuanced and argumentatively self-conscious writing that was flexibly open to the idea
               of interpretative indeterminacy. Other teachers could benefit from this result by
               allowing students to design spaces that map the world of ideas onto simulated
               geographical space, including imagined and artistic spaces within the work of
               literature, such as Jane Eyre’s ambiguously emblematic paintings or Achilles’
               encyclopedically engraved shield in <title rend="italic">The Iliad</title>.
               Encouraging students to design these conceptual spaces as well as <q>actual</q> or
                  <q>realistic</q> locations within literary narratives could also help accommodate
               literature from a variety of periods to the constraints of role-playing toolsets,
               which often feature fantastic medieval landscapes that lend themselves to allegory. </p>
            <p> Despite the richly multivalent signifying potential of spatial allegories, students
               who are adapting literary works into interpretative quests need to be reminded that
               an awareness of labyrinthine indeterminacy should not become an excuse for an utter
               lack of interpretative commitment. In other words, students should design their
               spaces to balance openness and rule-based constraint, one of the recurrent features
               of level design advocated by Natkin. One example of the rationale for this
               pedagogical principle appears in students’ readings of the end of <title
                  rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title>, in which Oedipa confronts four
                  <q>symmetrical</q> choices about the secret society she has been pursuing: it is
               real, it is a hallucination, it is a hoax, or it is the hallucination of a hoax <ptr
                  target="#pynchon1964" loc="171"/>. These choices resemble the paths through a
               labyrinth, each of which gives rise to further choices and multiple, disorienting
               endings. Thinking of <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title> as the basis
               for an adventure or role-playing game, in which players often explore labyrinths, led
               several students to embrace this indeterminacy as an opportunity for the exploration
               of multiple meanings rather than frustration. However, students sometimes tended to
               come to rest complacently in this image, or to assert it dogmatically, often as a
               criticism of scholars who had developed well-supported arguments about a particular
               interpretation. While these students were well-intentioned, they sometimes seemed to
               use the image of the labyrinth as an excuse to avoid crafting their own thesis, as
               when one student wrote that <quote rend="inline" source="#alonzo2006">Through
                  creating this game, I realize that the entire book, <title rend="italic">The
                     Crying of Lot 49</title>, was just a labyrinth itself!</quote>
               <ptr target="#alonzo2006"/>. Alonzo’s phrase <quote rend="inline"
                  source="#alonzo2006">just a labyrinth</quote> suggests that she is satisfied with
               multiple interpretative paths rather than a single interpretation. Yet, her
               suggestion that <quote rend="inline" source="#alonzo2006">the entire</quote> book can
               be understood in this way is itself a totalizing argument that contradicts her other
               idea: that multiple readers can take different paths through the text. Such a view
               sometimes resulted in a lack of interpretative focus, as students celebrated
               different readers’ abilities to choose a path through the space of the quest without
               themselves committing to such a path. This tendency in some student essays serves as
               a reminder that simulated space is only one part of a well-designed quest, which must
               also pose goal-oriented and rule-based challenges to the player in order to produce
               an immersive game and allow the enactment of meaning. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Prototypes</head>
            <p>Based on their design documents, the students built prototypes that combined aspects
               of their individual designs to form playable games through which players would enact
               the students’ interpretations of a portion of the novel. Students worked in four
               in-class game workshops and were instructed to meet two to three times out of class.
               The initial workshops were devoted primarily to planning and note-taking regarding
               the game concepts, while later workshops involved working with computers in the
               classroom to make the games. There were four group projects in my class that used
               three different major software applications and a mixture of other programs. Students
               produced two small but functional role-playing quests made with the Aurora Toolset,
               an application that comes with the role-playing game Neverwinter Nights and allows
               designers to make three-dimensional worlds. This toolset is a <q>modding</q> engine
               with which users create their own <q>modules</q> to share with other players. At the
               same time, it is a high-powered, sophisticated tool that can be used in the game
               design industry, since Jeannie Novak in <title rend="italic">Game Development
                  Essentials</title> also recommends it for prototyping commercial games <ptr
                  target="#novak2005"/>. While the toolset is complex, it can be used to make
               three-dimensional environments without either rendering these graphics in Maya or 3D
               Studio Max or programming them in OpenGL or DirectX. Through mastering the menus and
               buttons of such a toolset as well as a system of dragging and dropping objects, both
               instructors and students can construct an explorable environment in a relatively
               short amount of time. A third group produced a web-based Alternate Reality Game made
               with Dreamweaver, Photoshop, and digital cameras. Another produced one part of a
               puzzle game in Macromedia Flash. This was the least successful project because Flash
               is the most difficult of the programs to master, which meant that large amounts of
               student work translated into a rough final product. If I had the opportunity to do
               this assignment again, I might exclusively use the Aurora Toolset because it yields
               visibly exciting end results that encourage students and because its <q>Plot
                  Wizard</q> and journal system is built entirely around the idea of quests. </p>
            <p>One group’s prototype, called <title rend="italic">Oedipa’s Quest</title>, centered
               around the <q>dreaming children</q> episode in <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot
                  49</title>, in which Oedipa encounters a group of children warming themselves at
               an <quote rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">imaginary fire,</quote> who tell her
               that they are <quote rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">dreaming the
                  gathering</quote>
               <ptr target="#pynchon1964" loc="118"/>. After they do not answer her questions
               satisfactorily, Oedipa <quote rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">to
                  retaliate</quote> stops <quote rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">believing in
                  them</quote>
               <ptr target="#pynchon1964" loc="119"/>. To allow players to act out this scene, the
               students used the Aurora toolset to build a small city with a town square. In this
               square, they constructed a circle of runes to represent the <q>hieroglyphic</q>
               posthorns that the children have scrawled on the ground, along with an <q>imaginary
                  fire</q> made of magical sparks. Around this fire they placed children and then
               scripted conversations for them, creating dialogue trees with multiple forking paths
               of possible interaction with the children. The students also gave the children
                  <q>invisibility spells</q> so that they would disappear when attacked, thereby
               representing Oedipa’s refusal to believe in them. After this encounter, players could
               enter a tower that the students also built in order to represent the environment of
               Remedios Varo’s <title rend="quotes">Embroidering Earth’s Mantle</title> painting.
               The students furnished this space with mysterious and arcane accoutrements, and then
               they placed an old man in the tower to represent Genghis Cohen, the stamp collector
               who Oedipa encounters just before she sits down to await <q>the crying of lot 49</q>
               and the book’s indeterminate ending in the auction room. Again using dialogue trees,
               the group scripted a conversation in which Cohen asks Oedipa to interpret her
               encounter with the children and gives her three possible answers: <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">solipsism,</quote>
               <quote rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">surrealism,</quote> and <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">there is no answer. The point is to keep
                  searching for the truth.</quote> The first two answers result in a rebuke from
               Cohen because of the player’s excessive certainty in the face of ambiguity, while the
               third response earns the player praise and encouragement to continue gaining
               knowledge by exploring further. Students were pleased with this final product, but
               they sometimes showed frustration when the toolset could not accommodate aspects of
               their design document, such as allowing players to fill in blanks rather than select
               multiple choice answers in conversation. In future classes, an introduction to the
               capabilities of the toolset before writing the document would help to circumvent
               these disappointments.</p>
            <p> A second group used the Aurora toolset to create the most extensive and functional
               prototype of the class, the humorously titled <title rend="italic">Polar Inverarity’s
                  Overtly Symbolic Quest</title>. This prototype was highly creative and could
               actually be played as a game, in part because the students made excellent use of the
               Aurora toolset’s <q>plot wizard</q> to create quest objectives without having to
               master a scripting language. This group built their project around a series of
                  <q>fetch quests</q>, in which players retrieve an item and bring it to another
               non-player character for a reward or to advance further in the game. Players of this
               group’s game had to acquire a key from Pierce Inverarity to open an armoire
               containing a page from <title rend="italic">The Courier’s Tragedy</title> (a book
               discovered by Oedipa in <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title>), which
               offers a clue to talk to a dreaming child from chapter five. The child sends the
               player to talk to the drunken sailor, who asks the player (as he asks Oedipa) to
               deliver a letter through the underground postal service or <q>W.A.S.T.E. system.</q>
               After the player does this, the sailor gives the player a golden posthorn, which must
               be returned to Pierce Inverarity. Each of the non-player characters’ dialogue gives
               some explanation of the significance of the player’s tasks, which the student group
               elaborates on in the notes for their presentation. The students write, <q>Our focus
                  was on polar opposites in the novel, with an extreme emphasis on sacred and
                  profane images. This is reflected in our setting, characters, and humor.</q> The
               students thus organized their project around the religious subtext of Pynchon’s
               novel, as first analyzed by Edward Mendelson in <title rend="quotes">The Sacred, the
                  Profane, and <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title>
               </title>. The game is filled with clever allusions to the novel, and (as its name
               suggests) is strongly symbolic. </p>
            <p> However, the relationship between meaning and action in the second group's game is
               not as well integrated as in <title rend="italic">Oedipa’s Quest</title>, in part
               because the students became a little too immersed in the whimsical humor of their
               game. Students created a world in which Pierce Inverarity has been transformed into a
               polar bear, and random creatures such as talking penguins periodically appear.
               Nevertheless, because the group also strove to be faithful to the details of
               Pynchon’s text, they found that elements they originally intended to be humorous
               acquired meaning within the context of the quest. Indeed, Pynchon’s idea of a <quote
                  rend="inline" source="#pynchon1964">high magic to low puns</quote> suggests that
               his own aesthetic draws its own power from seemingly absurd jokes that reveal serious
               thematic implications upon a second look <ptr target="#pynchon1964" loc="129"/>.
               Thus, the <q>polar</q> bear in the group’s prototype lead them to think about
                  <q>polar</q> opposites running through the organization of their game, in which
               each object, character, and setting has its mirrored, symmetrical counterpart. The
               students write: <q>We split the geography into two separate but equal parts. Where
                  one side has a very nice house, the other side has a slummy inn. One side has a
                  nice garden with children and flowers; the other side contains ruins and skeletal
                  remains. [...] The areas are separated by the river, water, a polar molecule. A
                  single bridge connects the two, representing how sacred and profane are eternally
                  linked within the novel’s universe.</q> Chance puns on the word <q>polar</q> yield
               an organizational principle for the quest, in which the player must help an isolated,
               marginalized sailor to communicate through an underground postal box in the middle of
               town, thereby bridging the sacred and the profane both figuratively and literally. </p>
            <p> In addition to this successful use of emblematic spaces, students wrote not only
               about the spaces of the quest but also about its rules and challenges, in order to
               emphasize that a quest is a goal-oriented search for meaning rather than unfocused
               wandering through multiple interpretations. Classroom game design need not consist
               primarily of a set of rules that the instructor imposes upon a class in order to
               guide discussion, but rather students should be at least partially responsible for
               designing these rules if gaming is to fulfill the promise of interactivity. When
               students supported their ideas about gameplay with interpretative analysis of the
               book, they produced a context for meaning that was both creative and interpretative.
               For example, Jason Kimbrell designed an action game about Pynchon’s use of Jungian
               shadow archetypes. In this game, players would have not only standard combat moves
               but also an <q>interpret</q> move, akin to the <q>combo</q> or <q>finishing</q> moves
               in martial arts games. The <q>interpret</q> move would give characters the
               opportunity to experience sympathy for a demonized and shadowy Other, thereby
               humanizing an enemy instead of defeating it. Kimbrell writes: <cit>
                  <quote rend="block" source="#kimbrell2006">As enemies in the game, the Shadow will
                     be portrayed as monsters. Oedipa has two options while fighting these
                     creatures. She can kill them, like a normal action game, or she can ‘interpret’
                     them. Once she initiates the command, a quick cut-scene plays revealing the
                     monster as a human being and Oedipa learns a special move specific to that
                     monster. The downside to this is that interpretation has a high fail rate,
                     which makes execution difficult. </quote>
                  <ptr target="#kimbrell2006"/>
               </cit> Kimbrell thus retained the challenge and violence of the typical <q>kill
                  quest</q> with gameplay that required players to enact subtle, postmodern, and
               self-reflective ideas about tolerance for the demonized Other. His gameplay is
               meta-interpretative, introducing interpretation as itself a move in the game: one
               that is rendered not only as an abstract cognitive maneuver but also as a difficult
                  <q>combo move</q> in a well-designed martial arts combat game. Instructors
               uncomfortable with the violence of video games or seeking to encourage readings of
               bloody epic and romance through the more reflective lens of postcolonial or feminist
               theory could use this student’s idea as a template for alternative approaches to
               Beowulf, the Arthurian legends, or any text that prominently features a protagonist
               challenged with slaying a monstrous Other. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p> Further inquiry into the theory and practice of quest design will allow literary
               scholars, games researchers, and game designers to find linkages between a tradition
               of games extending from King’s Quest to <title rend="italic">The Elder Scrolls IV:
                  Oblivion</title>, as well as from Homer’s Odyssey to <title rend="italic">The
                  Crying of Lot 49</title>. As the academic study of games matures, the study of
               quests offers a possible bridge between games and narratives that can help us to
               progress beyond the divisive ludology versus narratology debate without losing sight
               of the venerable, implied questions about interpretative freedom, imagination, and
               the human search for meaning that made this debate so fierce in the first place.
               Moreover, further research into the history and theory of quests can take its place
               among a variety of studies of particular game genres that emerge as New Media
               researchers move past the first discipline-founding steps of game studies and into
               the specific inquiries that will bear the fruit of this discipline. The importance of
               studying quests specifically can only increase as MMORPG’s and RPG’s for the
               next-generation consoles boast of <q>quest systems</q> that contain thousands of
                  <q>side quests</q>, often interlaced with an epic main quest whose dramatic sweep
               still corresponds to the ancient model of the hero’s journey. Because quests are also
               a structural paradigm that connects hundreds of literary works from myriad periods
               and genres, pedagogical applications of quests can potentially benefit humanities
               teachers in a broad range of educational situations. These applications could range
               from honors seminars introducing students to ancient epic, to thematic classes about
               the relationship between New Media and literature, to single-author <q>major
                  figures</q> courses on authors as diverse as Edmund Spenser and Thomas Pynchon.
               Moreover, the most productive questions about quests may come from a design
               perspective, addressing the issue of how to relate theoretical understandings of
               quests with their enactment in gameplay. Since quests operate as a formal structure
               in narrative and an activity in games, the adaptation of narratives into games
               requires not just a theoretical consideration of interactivity but of the practical
               action that scholars, educators, and designers can themselves take in order to
               produce this interactivity. New Media theorists need to consider what technological
               skill-sets might be required in order to produce meaningful action in games, and how
               strategies derived from the literary tradition of quest games could be used to create
               this action. My own book in progress, <title rend="italic">Quests: Design, Theory,
                  and History in Games and Narratives</title>, discusses ways that a literary
               technique of symbolic correspondences derived from medieval romance and Renaissance
               allegory can help designers to construct games in which meaning emerges from
               gameplay. Four components of a theory of quests (a quest system of journal updates
               and conversations with non-player characters, spaces, objects, challenges) can
               themselves "correspond" to another set of design skills (journal management and
               dialogue construction, level design, creation of quest items, and programming within
               game engines or <q>scripting</q>). If we treat the quest in its etymological sense as
               a kind of <q>inquest</q> or <q>inquiry</q> in which players and designers produce
               meaning rather than passively consuming it, then the next step in this inquiry may be
               to ask how we can actively create meaning through our design decisions. </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aarseth1997" label="Aarseth 1997" key="aarseth1997"> Aarseth, Espen.
                  <title rend="italic">Cybertext: Perspectives on Ergodic Literature</title>.
               Baltimore: Johns Hopkins University Press, 1997. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aarseth2000" label="Aarseth 2000" key="aarseth2000"> Aarseth, Espen.
                  <title rend="quotes">Allegories of Space: The Question of Spatiality in Computer
                  Games</title>. In <editor>Markku Eskelinen</editor> and <editor>Raine
                  Koskimaa</editor> (eds.), <title rend="italic">Cybertext Yearbook 2000</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Jyväskylä, Finland</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of
                  Jyväskylä</publisher>, <date>2000</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="aarseth2004" label="Aarseth 2004" key="aarseth2004b"> Aarseth, Espen.
                  <title rend="quotes">Quest Games as Post-Narrative Discourse.</title> In
                  <editor>Marie-Laure Ryan</editor> (ed.), <title rend="italic">Narrative Across
                  Media: The Languages of Storytelling</title>. <pubPlace>Lincoln</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>University of Nebraska Press</publisher>, <date>2004, </date>
               361-76.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alonzo2006" label="Alonzo 2006" key="[unlisted]"> Alonzo, M. <title
                  rend="quotes">Overcome Entropy.</title> Student paper, <date>2006</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bateman2005" label="Bateman 2005" key="bateman2005"> Bateman, Chris.
                  <title rend="italic">21st Century Game Design</title>. <pubPlace>Hingham,
                  MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Charles River Media</publisher>, <date>2005</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bolter1999" label="Bolter and Grusin 1999" key="bolter1999"> Bolter, Jay
               David and Richard Grusin. <title rend="italic">Remediation: Understanding New
                  Media</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT
                  Press</publisher>, <date>1999</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="campbell1949" label="Campbell 1949" key="campbell1949"> Campbell, Joseph.
                  <title rend="italic">The Hero with a Thousand Faces</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>: <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>,
                  <date>1949</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cowart1977" label="Cowart 1977" key="cowart1977"> Cowart, David. <title
                  rend="quotes">Pynchon’s <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title> and the
                  Paintings of Remedios Varo.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Critique</title>, 18.3 (<date>1977</date>): 19-26.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="davis1998" label="Davis 1998" key="davis1998"> Davis, Erik. <title
                  rend="italic">Techgnosis: Myth, Magic, and Mysticism in the Age of
                  Information</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
               <publisher>Harmony</publisher>, <date>1998</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="elder2006" label="Elder Scrolls 2006" key="elder2006">
               <title rend="italic">The Elder Scrolls IV: Oblivion</title>. [Microsoft Xbox 360]
                  <pubPlace>Rockville, Maryland</pubPlace>: <publisher>Bethesda Softworks
                  LLC</publisher>
               <date>2006</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="erickson1996" label="Erickson 1996" key="erickson1996"> Erickson, Wayne.
                  <title rend="italic">Mapping the <title rend="italic">Faerie Queene</title>: Quest
                  Structures and the World of the Poem</title>. <pubPlace>New York and
                  London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Garland Publishing</publisher>,
               <date>1996</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eskelinen2004" label="Eskelinen 2004" key="eskelinen2004"> Eskelinen,
               Markku. <title rend="quotes">Towards Computer Game Studies.</title> In <editor>Noah
                  Wardrip-Fruin</editor> and <editor>Pat Harrigan</editor> (eds.), <title
                  rend="italic">First Person: New Media as Story, Performance, and Game</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>,
                  <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fable2005" label="Fable 2005" key="fable2005">
               <title rend="italic">Fable: The Lost Chapters</title>. [Microsoft Xbox]
                  <pubPlace>Redmond, WA</pubPlace>: <publisher>Microsoft</publisher>,
                  <date>2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="frasca2003" label="Frasca 2003" key="frasca2003"> Frasca, Gonzalo. <title
                  rend="quotes">Ludologists Love Stories, Too: Notes from a Debate That Never Took
                  Place.</title> Level Up Conference <date>2003</date>. <ref
                  target="http://ludology.org/articles/frasca_levelup2003.pdf"
                  >http://ludology.org/articles/Frasca_LevelUp2003.pdf</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="frye1957" label="Frye 1957" key="frye1957"> Frye, Northrop. <title
                  rend="italic">Anatomy of Criticism: Four Essays</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Princeton</pubPlace>: <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>,
                  <date>1957</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kelly2004" label="Kelly 2004" key="kelly2004"> Kelly 2, Richard V. <title
                  rend="italic">Massively Multiplayer Online Role-Playing Games: The People, the
                  Addiction, and the Playing Experience</title>. <pubPlace>Jefferson, NC</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>McFarland &amp; Company, Inc., Publishers</publisher>,
                  <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gee2004" label="Gee 2004" key="gee2004"> Gee, James Paul. <title
                  rend="italic">What Video Games Have to Teach Us About Learning and
                  Literacy</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Palgrave
                  MacMillan</publisher>, <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kucklich2006" label="Kucklich 2006" key="kucklich2006"> Kucklich, Julian.
                  <title rend="quotes">Game Studies 2.0.</title>
               <title rend="italic">DIGRA Hardcore Column 12</title>, <date>2006</date>. <ref
                  target="http://www.digra.org/hardcore/hc12"
                  >http://www.digra.org/hardcore/hc12</ref>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="glassner2004" label="Glassner 2004" key="glassner2004"> Glassner, Andrew.
                  <title rend="italic">Interactive Storytelling: Techniques for 21st Century
                  Fiction</title>. <pubPlace>Wellesley, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>A K
                  Peters</publisher>, <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jenkins2004" label="Jenkins 2004" key="jenkins2004"> Jenkins, Henry.
                  <title rend="quotes">Game Design as Narrative Architecture.</title> In
                  <editor>Noah Wardrip-Fruin</editor> and <editor>Pat Harrigan</editor> (eds.),
                  <title rend="italic">First Person: New Media as Story, Performance, and
                  Game</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT
               Press</publisher>, <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="juul2005" label="Juul 2005" key="juul2005"> Juul, Jesper. <title
                  rend="italic">Half-Real: Video Games between Real Rules and Fictional
                  Worlds</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT
                  Press</publisher>, <date>2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="king2003" label="King 2003" key="king2003b"> King, Brad and John Borland.
                  <title rend="italic">Dungeons and Dreamers: The Rise of Computer Game Culture from
                  Geek to Chic</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>McGraw-Hill</publisher>, <date>2003</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kimbrell2006" label="Kimbrell 2006" key="[unlisted]"> Kimbrell, J. <title
                  rend="quotes">Quest Structures and Shadows in <title rend="italic">The Crying of
                     Lot 49</title>.</title> Student paper, <date>2006</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="losh2006" label="Losh 2006" key="losh2006"> Losh, Elizabeth. <title
                  rend="quotes">Making Things Public: Democracy and Government-Funded Virtual
                  Reality Simulations.</title> ACM SIGGRAPH Sandbox Symposium on Digital Games 2006,
               Boston, <date>2006</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mendelson1978" label="Mendelson 1978" key="mendelson1978"> Mendelson,
               Edward. <title rend="quotes">The Sacred, the Profane, and <title rend="italic">The
                     Crying of Lot 49</title>.</title> In Edward Mendelson (ed.), <title
                  rend="italic">Pynchon: A Collection of Critical Essays</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Englewood Cliffs, NJ</pubPlace>: <publisher>Prentice-Hall</publisher>,
                  <date>1978</date>, 97-111.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="montfort2003" label="Montfort 2003" key="montfort2003"> Montfort, Nick.
                  <title rend="italic">Twisty Little Passages: An Approach to Interactive
                  Fiction</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>,
                  <date>2003</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="neugebauer2006" label="Neugebauer 2006" key="[unlisted]"> Neugebauer, A.
                  <title rend="quotes">Quest of Life.</title> Student paper,
               <date>2006</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="natkin2006" label="Natkin 2006" key="natkin2006"> Natkin, Stephane. <title
                  rend="italic">Video Games and Interactive Media: A Glimpse at New Digital
                  Entertainment</title>. <pubPlace>Wellesley, MA</pubPlace>: <publisher>A K
                  Peters</publisher>, <date>2006</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="novak2005" label="Novak 2005" key="novak2005"> Novak, Jeannie. <title
                  rend="italic">Game Development Essentials: An Introduction</title>. <pubPlace>New
                  York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Thomson</publisher>, <date>2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="propp1968" label="Propp 1968" key="propp1968"> Propp, Vladimir. Morphology
               of the Folktale. <pubPlace>Austin and London</pubPlace>: <publisher>University of
                  Texas Press</publisher>, <date>1968</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pynchon1964" label="Pynchon 1964" key="pynchon1964"> Pynchon, Thomas.
                  <title rend="italic">The Crying of Lot 49</title>. <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>Harper and Row</publisher>, <date>1964</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rollings2003" label="Rollings 2003" key="rollings2003"> Rollings, Andrew
               and Ernest Adams. <title rend="italic">Andrew Rollings and Ernest Adams on Game
                  Design</title>. <pubPlace>Indianapolis</pubPlace>: <publisher>New
                  Riders</publisher>, <date>2003</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ryan2001" label="Ryan 2001" key="ryan2001"> Ryan, Marie-Laure. <title
                  rend="italic">Narrative as Virtual Reality: Immersion and Interactivity in
                  Literature and Electronic Media</title>. <pubPlace>Baltimore and
               London</pubPlace>: <publisher>Johns Hopkins University Press</publisher>,
                  <date>2001</date>. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salen2004" label="Salen 2004" key="salen2004"> Salen, Katie and Eric
               Zimmerman. <title rend="italic">Rules of Play: Game Design Fundamentals</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>,
                  <date>2004</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="szulborski2005" label="Szulborski 2005" key="szulborski2005"> Szulborski,
               David. <title rend="italic">This is Not a Game: A Guide to Alternate Reality
                  Gaming</title>. <pubPlace>Macungle, PA</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>New-Fiction</publisher>, <date>2005</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tosca2003" label="Tosca 2003" key="tosca2003"> Tosca, Susana. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Quest Problem in Computer Games.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the First International Conference on
                  Technologies for Interactive Digital Storytelling and Entertainment TIDSE
                  ’03</title>. <publisher>Fraunhofer IRB Verlag</publisher>, <date>2003</date>. <ref
                  target="http://www.it-c.dk/people/tosca/quest.htm"
                  >http://www.it-c.dk/people/tosca/quest.htm</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tronstad2001" label="Tronstad 2001" key="tronstad2001"> Tronstad,
               Ragnhild. <title rend="quotes">Semiotic and Nonsemiotic MUD Performance.</title>
               COSIGN. <pubPlace>Amsterdam</pubPlace>, <date>2001</date>. <ref
                  target="http://www.cosignconference.org/cosign2001/papers/tronstad.pdf"
                  >http://www.cosignconference.org/cosign2001/papers/Tronstad.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ulmer2002" label="Ulmer 2002" key="ulmer2002"> Ulmer, Gregory. <title
                  rend="italic">Internet Invention: From Literacy to Electracy</title>.
                  <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>: <publisher>Longman</publisher>,
               <date>2002</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="vogler1998" label="Vogler 1998" key="vogler1998"> Vogler, Christopher.
                  <title rend="italic">The Writer’s Journey: Mythic Structures for Writers</title>.
                  <pubPlace>Studio City, CA</pubPlace>: <publisher>M. Wiese Productions</publisher>,
                  <date>1998</date>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="zimmerman2004" label="Zimmerman 2004" key="zimmerman2004"> Zimmerman,
               Eric. <title rend="quotes">Narrative, Interactivity, Play, and Games: Four Naughty
                  Concepts in Need of Discipline.</title> In <editor>Noah Wardrip-Fruin</editor> and
                  <editor>Pat Harrigan </editor>(eds.), <title rend="italic">First Person: New Media
                  as Story, Performance, and Game</title>. <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>:
                  <publisher>MIT Press</publisher>, <date>2004</date>. </bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
