<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Explaining Events to Computers: Critical Quantification,
                    Multiplicity and Narratives in Cultural Heritage</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Stuart <dhq:family>Dunn</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>King’s College London</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>stuart.dunn@kcl.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Stuart Dunn is Lecturer in Digital Humanities at King's College London,
                            where he teaches digital approaches to cultural heritage, and GIS
                            applications in the humanities. He contributes to several projects in
                            these areas, and is also interested in humanities crowdsourcing, and
                            public participation in humanities research. He graduated from the
                            University of Durham with a PhD in Aegean Bronze Age Archaeology in
                            2002, conducting fieldwork and research visits in Melos, Crete and
                            Santorini. Having developed research interests in GIS, Stuart
                            subsequently became a Research Assistant on the AHRC’s ICT in Arts and
                            Humanities Research Program. In 2006, he became a Research Associate at
                            the Arts and Humanities e-Science Support Centre at King’s College
                            London, and Research Fellow in the Centre for e-Research.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Mareike <dhq:family>Schumacher</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Hamburg University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>mareike.schumacher@uni-hamburg.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Mareike Schumacher is a research assistant and PhD candidate at the
                            Humanities Department of the University of Hamburg. She works for the
                            efoto-Hamburg project, where she is involved in the development of a
                            mobile application which provides access to historical images of the
                            city of Hamburg. During her Master Studies she assisted the foundation
                            of the Association for Digital Humanities in the German speaking
                            Countries in 2012. She is an active member of the Interdisciplinary
                            Centre for Narratology (ICN) and the Northern Narratology Network
                            (triple*N). She studied Cultural Theory at the University of Lüneburg
                            and Literature at the University of Hamburg and graduates in the fields
                            of Digital Humanities and Narratology. Her PhD project focusses on the
                            specification of the narratological categories of space and place in
                            novels.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000262</idno>
                <idno type="volume">010</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2016-07-12">12 July 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>cultural heritage</item>
                        <item>event</item>
                        <item>narrative</item>
                        <item>multiplicity</item>
                        <item>tellability</item>
                        <item>event extraction</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2018-07-09" who="DD">validation check</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <p>Digital Humanities provide the means and methods to research topics in a
                    transdisciplinary and multilayered way. In this paper we combine perspectives
                    from historical research and literary criticism to problematize the
                    categorization, computation and representation of events in cultural heritage.
                    Combining methodologies of narratology, historic research and Digital Humanities
                    we aim to extract, classify and quantify events in a way that preserves their
                    inherent multiplicity and multivocality. In two case studies we exemplify that
                    narrative may be seen as a means to mediate events rather than a classical
                    media-centred tradition to preserve an authorized version of cultural
                    heritage.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Combines perspectives from historical research and literary criticism to
                    problematize the categorization, computation and representation of events in
                    cultural heritage.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Explaining Events to Computers: Critical Quantification, Multiplicity and
                Narratives in Cultural Heritage</head>
            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <epigraph>
                    <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#sellar1930">History is not what you thought.
                                <emph>It is what you can remember</emph>. All other history defeats
                            itself.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#sellar1930"/>
                    </cit>
                </epigraph>
                <p>Sellar and Yeatman’s <title rend="italic">1066 and All That</title> is a
                    tongue-in-cheek parody which sends up a (perceived) preoccupation in the British
                    education system of the pre-Second World War period with iconic historical
                    events, including the Battle of Hastings of 14th October 1066, when the Norman
                    army under William I (<q>The Conqueror</q>) landed close to the modern town of
                    Battle, and defeated the Anglo Saxon army under Harold II. </p>
                <p>This view places <emph>the event</emph> at the heart of discourse. Many
                    humanities disciplines remain fundamentally concerned with events, their
                    interpretation, and their description. It follows therefore that narrative, as
                    the primary means of making events meaningful, is key to the way in which
                    information becomes knowledge in the humanities; and therefore has a fundamental
                    role to play in the definition of how an <q>event</q> should be defined in those
                    domains. Until the emergence of the ubiquitous World Wide Web, most narrative in
                    humanities communication was mounted almost exclusively in text. In this paper,
                    we review recent discussions of how web technologies have changed the way
                    narrative events are formulated, described, connected, received and transmitted
                    in humanities discourse; and explore how an <q>event</q> that is
                        <soCalled>meaningful</soCalled> from a narrative point of view might be
                    described as structured data, rather than in text. We also consider how this
                    approach might be used to support <emph>multivocal</emph> narratives. The study
                    itself is explorative and sometimes even experimental. It thus follows more than
                    one research question. We focus on nevertheless how multiplicity and
                    multivocality in the narration of events is represented in traditional and
                    non-traditional narrative media. Is there a difference in value between the
                    narration of events in textual representations and in other forms of cultural
                    objects, such as monuments and landscapes? We therefore have to ask how events
                    can be made machine readable and how they can be evaluated in terms of
                    narrativity.</p>
                <p>There is a growing recognition that narratives do not have to be
                        <soCalled>told</soCalled> in the textual medium, or at least by text alone.
                    A museum exhibition, for example, might present the narrative of how a
                    particular class of object, such as a pottery typology, develops over time and
                    across space, either through emphasising the artefacts as linked entities rather
                    than their physical attributes (upon which conventional approaches to museum
                    display rests) <ptr target="#cuno2008"/>, or through the cultural elaboration of
                    museum spaces themselves. The role of maps as instances of geographic and
                    cartographic narrative has been extensively explored in recent years <ptr
                        target="#taylor2005"/>
                    <ptr target="#caquard2011"/>, as has the curation and presentation of heritage
                    spaces <ptr target="#azaryahu2008"/>. Archaeological sequences have been
                    explored as narrative memes <ptr target="#hodder1993"/>, as has their
                    interpretation as ways of telling the stories of the past <ptr
                        target="#pluciennik1999"/>. All of these approaches take as their starting
                    point the definition (and distinction) of events, and how they are rendered
                    meaningful through contextualisation with one another. It follows that events
                    can be told through various media in various ways.</p>
                <p>However, one key aspect that they do not address is that of
                        <emph>multiplicity</emph> or <emph>multivocality</emph>. Each approach, to
                    one degree or another, applies the textual paradigm of the single author, the
                    single narrator, the single point of view -- whether this be the author of an
                    historical treatise; the framer of an archaeological sequence (as reported
                    through the authorship of an archaeological report); the curator of a museum
                    collection; the designer of a museum space, or the designer of the visitor
                    infrastructure of a heritage site. In each case the analogy of multiple
                    authorship can be applied; however, in such cases any joint responsibility for
                    the narrative is funnelled through a single point and platform of authorship:
                    the narrative is <soCalled>authoritative</soCalled>, produced in a top-down (or
                    rather centre-out) manner, and its coherence relies on these attributes.</p>
                <p>In the 1990s to early 2000s, the <soCalled>operationalisation</soCalled> of
                    narrative as a process by which events are made readable by machines tended to
                    concentrate on hypertext, and the possibilities for readers to use its
                    affordances to reorganize text according to their own expectations and
                    requirements.The inception of Web 2.0, which can be dated to approximately
                    2007-2009, promised a multivocal platform for narrative expression; and it can
                    be said that the mooted possibilities of hypertext as a vehicle for multiplicity
                    have not been realised (much the same can be said in the present day of blogging
                    and other social media). This is for two reasons: firstly, the use of hypertext
                    to link one part of one document to another still relies on the
                    single-authorship model: one user makes one decision to select one part of one
                    document, and link it to one other. This is closely related to the second
                    reason, namely that since 2007-2009, focus of linking material online has
                    shifted away from the hypertext web to the semantic web. The latter implicitly
                    rejects the notion of multiplicity, and concentrates instead on linkages between
                    monovocal information, structured into data according to predefined schemata.
                    For the study presented here, two approaches to the phenomenon of eventnarration
                    are of particular interest. First, we hypothesize that there can be multiplicity
                    and multivocality even in single-author narration. Second we state that one
                    single event can be narrated in multiple ways.</p>
                <p>By comparing narrative models arising from a) factual and fictional text about
                    crime in twentieth century Hamburg and b) the curated monumental and
                    archaeological space of Hadrian’s Wall, we argue that web-readable data
                    structures gives humanists the means to look beyond text, and the analogies of
                    textual paradigm that are applied to non-textual narrative of the kind described
                    above, to provide multiple insights into events, as well as the process of
                    research itself. Instead of following a single research hypothesis, or a
                        <soCalled>single authored</soCalled> narrative, digital narratology can
                    explore multiple research data, told in multiple voices from multiple sources.
                    This reflects the truth that through innovative research settings in
                    collaborative work, re-usability of research data or citizen science projects
                    often come up with more than one possible interpretation.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Narrative and historic events</head>
                <p>The possibility of viewing events in cultural heritage as data equating to
                    narrative elements rather than as text opens up the possibility to analyse them
                    from multiple perspectives. However, in past decades, they have often been
                    delivered or distributed in textual form, or as narratives following the
                    traditions and parameters of textual delivery, which means that even though
                    alternative modes of narrative communication, such as oral storytelling, might
                    be an important means of delivery, there are still
                        <soCalled>authoritative</soCalled> ways of producing historic narratives,
                    for example, by museum curators. In order to build up databases of narrative
                    events, one possibility is to gather as many texts on them as possible and to
                    extract the most significant events from them in a quantifiable way. As historic
                    events are often represented in different kinds of sources - fictional and
                    factual texts as well as representations in different media, installations in
                    museums or performances - it is helpful to use the term <q>event</q> in a
                    transdisciplinary way in order to find an apparatus of tools to extract
                    individual events from those sources, put them into a database, and give them
                    attributes according to narratological traits such as tellability and meaning.
                    This allows us to accommodate multiplicity and multivocality. The term
                        <q>event</q> has very specific meanings in narratology and history, and it
                    is to those that we now turn.</p>
                <p>The importance of events in narrative studies is undoubted, although there are
                    slightly different definitions of the term in different traditions of analysis.
                    In a broad sense, the term, or similar terms, is used (for example) to explain
                    why people tend to tell stories in general, such as in disciplines like
                    sociological narratology or cognitive narratology; rhetoric and literary
                    criticism events play a central role in theories about storytelling and
                    interpretation techniques as a fundamental part of human meaning making <ptr
                        target="#ryan2007"/>. However, in linguistic approaches to narrative, the
                    term <q>event</q> is more quantitative, referring to the smallest element of
                    stories. Our approach here requires that we encompass both these traditions.</p>
                <p>In rhetoric narratology, the core definition of narrative is <cit><quote rend="inline"
                        source="#phelan2007">somebody telling somebody else on some occasion and
                        for some purpose(s) that something happened</quote>
                    <ptr target="#phelan2007"/></cit>. In this definition, the happening or event is the
                    central necessary condition for the rhetorical act. A similar notion of event as
                    the motivation of storytelling can be found in literary studies <ptr
                        target="#martinez2009"/> and also in anthropological approaches to narrative
                        <ptr target="#ochs2001"/>. The ambiguity of the term is stressed not only by
                    the initiation of a story but also the smallest element of action, and thus also
                    of the plot <ptr target="#martinez2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#meister2013"/>. On one side we thus find a notion of event as
                    being something which is closely linked to the act of storytelling, or more
                    precisely the tellability, or <q>that
                        which is worth telling</q> in an event. The more structure-orientated
                    perspective on events starts with the definition of a single event as a change
                    of state. A number of single events is organized according to the parameters of
                    time (such as frequency, duration and order) to build an action. A number of
                    actions is organized to build the plot. In this article we focus on events which
                    are linked to motivation, and thus to the tellability aspect of storytelling.
                    Nevertheless it is important to keep the ambiguity of the term in mind, which
                    has also been the object of important narratological research.</p>
                <p>In narratology the double meaning of the term event forms the basis of a
                    distinction between two types of events, referred to as Event I and Event II
                        <ptr target="#hühn2014"/>. The first of these refer to the <soCalled>smallest element</soCalled> of story in
                    literary terms, and are defined as change of state. The second is the motivation
                    of the story, and is broadly outlined by describing several conditions that it
                    has to fulfill (although not all of the conditions must be fulfilled). Both
                    types of event are found to have certain properties, such as having an inherent
                    motivation <ptr target="#martinez2009"/>, being presented in a certain mode of
                    narration <ptr target="#bonheim1982"/>, being at least indirectly attached to
                    space through the characters involved, and having an ontological status in
                    reference to the story world <ptr target="#ryan1991"/>. But only Event II has
                    been characterised with six conditional properties being: <list type="ordered">
                        <item>relevance for the storyworld, </item>
                        <item>unpredictability (what cannot be foreseen by the characters of a
                            storyworld), </item>
                        <item>irreversibility (again the term refers to the storyworld - death
                            usually is irreversable, unless it occurs in a fantasy storyworld where
                            the dead may return), </item>
                        <item>non-iterativity (something which results logically from an event is
                            not eventful in itself - If somebody rings a bell, pushing the button
                            will be an event but the ringing resulting from it will have no
                            eventfulness. If somebody pushes the button in order to ring a bell but
                            then hears someone shooting rather than hearing a bell, this would have
                            some eventfulness as it is non-iterative and interrupts the order of the
                            storyworld) </item>
                        <item>effect (if we stick to the shooting example, the effect on the
                            storyworld will be high if a main character gets shot, so this would be
                            considered a highly eventful event) <ptr target="#schmid2008"/>
                        </item>
                        <item>script violation, an additional term introduced by Hühn as a condition
                            of tellability, which classifies events which do not follow usual
                            cultural procedures (there is, for example, a cultural script for
                            visiting a restaurant which tells us to follow certain steps such as
                            entering, greeting, being led to a table, checking the menu, ordering,
                            testing wine, and so on, so again if the waiter suddenly turns around
                            and shoots one of the characters, this would be a script-violation and
                            therefore eventful) as highly tellable <ptr target="#hühn2008"/>. These
                            conditions have been termed eventfulness. The conditions are scalable,
                            e.g. a more or less relevant event is stated as more or less eventful.
                            In addition to that, an event can be more or less eventful in relation
                            to its context <ptr target="#hühn2008"/>, a fact that will be clearly
                            proven by the following case studies. </item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Following the ideas of relativity and multiplicity developed above, we propose to
                    use the term <q>eventfulness</q> in relation to two questions; and thus to
                    explore whether these types of event can be categorised in such a way as to
                    support a multivocal discourse in humanities contexts, while maintaining the
                    attributes of tellability, contestability and reproducibility that are essential
                    to scholarship. First, we ask whether or not a condition of eventfulness is
                    fulfilled, and second, whether it is found to have a lower or higher value of
                    that condition, according to its contextualization. By doing so we open up an
                    interpretive field in which each single event may be analysed according to each
                    of the conditions of eventfulness and tellability, and therefore displaying
                    multiple perspectives on it. An event will thus no longer be a homogeneous unit,
                    but rather a unifying frame of different aspects. Each aspect is given a value
                    from zero (0) to high (3) so that in the end the multiple conditions of
                    eventfulness may be evaluated in numbers which opens up the possibility to
                    compare different events in their factor of eventfulness and tellability. We
                    take it as fact that the terms <emph>event, eventfulness and tellability</emph>
                    can be used in a non-literary context. The storyworld referred to above thus
                    becomes either fictional or factual. Further on, we highlight the interpretive
                    character of events and open up the process of deciding whether to evaluate an
                    event in relation to a condition with a lower or higher number. By so doing, we
                    admit that other interpreters or readers might (or might not) end up with other
                    values for a particular event, but nevertheless would probably come to similar
                    conclusions. This approach in itself is shaped by the idea of multiplicity.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>2.1. Eventfulness and Tellability</head>
                    <p>In theorizing the role of events in collective memory, the question of
                        remembrance and forgetting arises. Despite the fact that forgetting is a
                        cultural technique of equal importance for cultural heritage as remembrance
                            <ptr target="#luhmann1997"/>, our approach here also addresses the
                        question of why certain events are more likely to be constantly retold and
                        others are not. One answer lies in authoritative deliverance by a single
                        narrator or narrating institution; however, a more complex and
                        under-researched approach lies in multiplicity and multivocality. This leads
                        us back to the discussion of eventfulness and tellability, because both
                        terms may help to define why an incident turns into an event (in this case
                        incident means an occurrence in the real, historic world whereas event might
                        be an event I or II in a story world) <ptr target="#baroni2014"/> and also
                        why and how people tell stories about certain cultural heritage artifacts,
                        scenarios or other objects. </p>
                    <p>The concept of tellability was first developed in research on conversational
                        storytelling <ptr target="#baroni2014"/>. It emphasises the personal <ptr
                            target="#fludernik1996"/> and interpersonal <ptr target="#ochs2001"/>
                        relevance of <q>what can be told</q> to eventfulness, which is useful for
                        the analysis of narrative in cultural storytelling. While in structuralist
                        and post-structuralist narratology the focus mostly lies on literary
                        narratives, this perspective widens it to include oral storytelling. More
                        than in literary criticism (although in literary criticism there are also
                        attempts to give the reader a co-authoring role <ptr target="#fludernik2003"/>
                        <ptr target="#fludernik1996"/>), it becomes clear in the theory of
                        conversational narratives that a narrative act is produced by the agents of
                        both sender and receiver in a certain context. Furthermore roles and
                        relations of sender and receiver may vary <ptr target="#ochs2001"/>.
                        Narrative storytelling might be distributed among numerous authors, or oral
                        storytellers, or bodies, or objects, or texts, meaning that the narrative is
                        detachable from one author or even an authoritative instance. This forces us
                        to assume that agency itself is not an irreducible constant: one may also
                        include other ways of agentive storytelling or receiving, for example,
                        through visual or object bound narratives, spatial narratives or even
                        narratives of bodily experience. </p>
                    <p>Whereas the term eventfulness may be directly connected to tellability <ptr
                            target="#hühn2008"/>, the term tellability may not lead back directly to
                        eventfulness (a disjuncture that is highlighted in both our case studies).
                        This is emphasised in Literary Criticism research on oral storytelling
                        traditions and performances, where the fact that stories may be told for
                        entertainment, or because of a collective experience <ptr
                            target="#norrick2000"/> or as an art has been described. In fact there
                        are some examples of literary texts which show how the paradigm of
                        eventfulness could be eluded by telling stories without events, thus showing
                        that they are still tellable <ptr target="#ryan2005"/>. Whether or not their
                        aim really fully excludes eventfulness from their kind of storytelling
                        cannot be revealed in this paper.</p>
                    <p>Similar approaches from more sociologically oriented narratological research
                        disciplines show that something becomes tellable for different reasons. One
                        of those reasons can be eventfulness, but there are others, i.e. the
                        creation of a narrative identity by the means of small stories, which can
                        but must not include events <ptr target="#bamberg2008"/> or communicative
                        interaction in everyday life in general <ptr target="#ochs2001"/>. All of
                        these attempts show that narratives cannot be regarded solely in terms of
                        eventfulness but that there are more conditions of story, especially
                        personal and interpersonal dimensions of significance. </p>
                    <p>Reflecting the distinction between the <soCalled>non-eventful</soCalled> and
                            <soCalled>highly eventful</soCalled> described earlier, tellability can
                        also be seen as a scalable value ranging from untellable to highly tellable.
                        Logically, stories which are not tellable are/can not be told. In the
                        context of cultural heritage, these untold stories may be of some importance
                        because what is not told indicates certain cultural conditions <ptr
                            target="#baroni2014"/>, which restrict the ability of telling, and thus
                        conserving them. In addition to which, it has been stated that certain
                        components of everyday-life seem to have no tellability, such as daily
                        routines <ptr target="#ochs2001"/>. </p>
                    <p>In this paper we use the term tellability to augment eventfulness with
                        aspects of significance, and unite all possible properties that may be
                        attached to cultural heritage issues (events, objects, artifacts and so
                        forth), in order to describe their likeliness of being put into narrative.
                        We thus add to the six properties of eventfulness named above the properties
                        of tellability those of (7) personal significance and (8) interpersonal
                        significance. In the same way that we hold eventfulness to be scalable, we
                        propose to use tellability in a similar way. The generic properties of
                        tellability may be equated with values describing the factor of
                        significance. For reasons of quantification, we propose to establish four
                        stages on an ordinal scale of eventfulness/tellability. We acknowledge that
                        this is a very basic and simple way to numerate the scale, as it is beyond
                        the scale of this paper to develop a theory on whether or not values of
                        significance, effect or iterativity increase in a linear way. Broadly
                        adopting the definition of historical events given by Mostern and Johnson as
                            <cit><quote rend="inline" source="#mostern2008">an instantiation of
                            information about the past in the form of a named, spatially located,
                            temporally circumscribed entity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#mostern2008"/></cit> – which, by implication can be operationalized
                        in such a way as to be analyzable by a machine - we analyse the utility of
                        this approach in constructing narratives in a socio-historical setting, and
                        in a spatial one and, in particular, evaluate whether this approach
                        effectively allows the representation of multiple viewpoints of those
                        events.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.2. Historic events</head>
                    <p>Just as the disciplines of history and narratology share narration of events
                        as central concerns, the two genres of historiography and literary narration
                        share common roots, with the two being largely undifferentiated until the
                        18th century <ptr target="#lützeler1992"/>. However, we acknowledge that
                        there have been several recent attempts to distinguish the two. Besides
                        stating that historic texts have a different ontological status than
                        literary texts, being factual rather than fictional, it has been stated
                        that, in narratological terms, historical narratives must have a different
                        focalization, because no historically credible <soCalled>narrator</soCalled>
                        would have access to the minds of historical characters <ptr
                            target="#pavel1992"/>. This reflects the criticisms of phenomenological
                        approaches in archaeology (e.g. <ptr target="#tilley1994"/>
                        <ptr target="#brück2005"/>, which holds that monuments and other landscape
                        features can only be understood by direct personal experience in the
                        contemporary world (and thus, by extension, of <soCalled>events</soCalled>
                        in which contemporary observers participate) <ptr target="#barrett2009"/>.
                        Furthermore, there seems to be no direct need to differentiate between
                        author and narrator in historical texts, and the (general) reader tends to
                        assume that the author-narrator of historical text is reliable <ptr
                            target="#cohn1989"/>. Despite those distinctions, we take it as fact
                        that there are some similarities in the representation techniques of
                        historic and literary narratives, if only from a purely functional point of
                        view: i.e. both the author of fiction and the historiographer put a number
                        of events into a sequence by building up connections <ptr
                            target="#lützeler1992"/>, and extrapolate from them a
                            <soCalled>meaningful</soCalled> point of view. It is on these aspects of
                        literary and historiographic narratives we want to concentrate on in this
                        article.</p>
                    <p>Above all, we emphasize the role of narrative as a means of human meaning
                        making. From this perspective, the difference between factual, fictional and
                        fictionalized events becomes limited. Therefore we would like to enrich the
                        narratological view on eventfulness and tellability outlined above with the
                        historic perspective (and vice versa). </p>
                    <p>An especially suitable attempt to define the historical event with regard to
                        the possibility of operationalizing it and using it for computational
                        research has been made by <ptr target="#mostern2008"/>. Instead of
                        describing events by their properties, as done in narratological research,
                        they see events as named entities with a spatial and a temporal anchorage.
                        These three variables – name, space, time – might be seen as parts of a
                        grammatical structure which frames an action on the content level (following
                            <ptr target="#heise2014"/> they involve agents, objects and instruments
                        on this level). Contrary to the narratological perspective, the levels of
                        content and representation are very clearly distinguished, which might be
                        explained by the fact that narratology is never really interested in the
                        event itself, but rather tends to focus on the representation or more
                        specifically the telling of it. We are taking two additional factors to our
                        list of eventfulness/tellability properties from this attempt which are (9)
                        spatial outreach and (10) temporal relations. However, the idea of event as
                        named entity suggests that by focusing on the event as such one can single
                        them out more easily. Afterwards one may turn to more interpretive decisions
                        as to whether an event relates to others, and how or whether its ontological
                        status remains possible or is realized in the actual world (be it a
                            <soCalled>real</soCalled> world or a fictional (story-)world). In both
                        narratology and historiography, this interpretive dimension of events is
                        stressed <ptr target="#ryan1991"/>
                        <ptr target="#lützeler1992"/>, so we propose to follow two lines of
                        investigation. First, we try to concentrate on events as units or entities
                        of cultural heritage. As this approach tends to turn events into black boxes
                        excluding their properties and the characteristics of their narration, we
                        will interpret the findings in terms of eventfulness and tellability. </p>
                    <p>This consideration of theories of narratives in Digital Humanities suggests
                        the need for two approaches to cultural events in order to use computational
                        methods and tools. First, is that we need to find a way to extract events
                        from the different modes of narrative media identified above. Here the
                        approach to events as named entities seems to be very suitable. Second, is
                        that we will have to find a way to represent this data in a way that
                        includes interpretive multiple and multivocal perspectives.</p>
                    <p>Facing the first challenge one must state that computational methods provide
                        us with the possibility to look at a critical mass of text and therefore
                        unify multiple single authored texts (see, for example, the University of
                        Leipzig’s Canonical Text Services project: <ref
                            target="http://www.cts3.sourceforge.net"
                            >http://www.cts3.sourceforge.net</ref>). Instead of looking at one
                        single text by one author on one topic, we can use computational methods to
                        do research on many texts by many authors on a topic, event or series of
                        events. Following the idea of multiplicity and multivocality it does not
                        make any sense to limit this approach to textual representations or
                        ontologically homogenous narratives only. The scope is thus widened to
                        include different media, as well as fictional and factual narratives. </p>
                    <p>In an attempt to operationalize events and make them traceable with
                        computational means, we developed the following model. This model is based
                        on a tag-set developed in the context of the CATMA (Computer Aided Textual
                        Markup and Analysis) project in order to visualize different attempts to
                        specify the significance of events for (and within) narrative. It shows a
                        perspective on events as singled out units, the multiple properties they may
                        have, the connection to tellability and the ability to operationalize them
                        in order to use them with digital tools.</p>
                    <figure xml:id="figure01">
                        <head>Model of Events and tellability employed in the following case
                            studies</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <p>This approach reappraises structural and poststructural approaches to
                        narratives in a radical way, in order to define categories of significance
                        which are both operationalizable and interpretive, such as the properties of
                        eventfulness and tellability. The importance of operationalizing categories
                        of literary criticism both for doing Digital Humanities and finding new ways
                        to analyse literary texts has been pointed out very clearly by <ptr
                            target="#moretti2013"/>.</p>
                    <p>These categories may be used in a computer-based analysis according to their
                        categorization. Those properties of events that highlight their status as
                        named entities are extracted from narratives to be quantified and analyzed.
                        Afterwards the interpretative categories are used to evaluate eventfulness
                        and tellability of the events. In this sense, narratology itself becomes a
                        toolbox which helps to find out what kind of evidence in a text leads us to
                        assume that a certain category is used as a part of the structure of a
                        certain narrative. And it provides us with the necessary theoretical
                        framework to contextualize the raw data.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Der Fall Pinzer (The case of Werner Pinzner)</head>
                <p>For this case study the main question is what kind of multi-textual evidence is
                    needed to approach the essential narrative category of events; and how this
                    evidence can be operationalised and visualized by computational means. The
                    corpus includes fictional as well as factual texts and is put together in a
                    transmedial approach, following the cultural studies paradigm that the term
                        <q>text</q> is extended to other media and cut loose from a written
                    representation (an idea that is developed further in our second case study
                    below). The corpus is therefore set together by one novel <ptr
                        target="#göhre2011"/>, one journalistically written book <ptr
                        target="#lindlau1992"/>, one TV movie <ptr target="#hofman1995"/> and one TV
                    documentary <ptr target="#harrich-zandberg2002"/>. Each of these texts
                    represents a special form of narrative and therefore has to be seen as an
                    exemplary choice.</p>
                <p>The case is a true crime story from the 1980s that took place in Hamburg. We have
                    selected this case because the factual act of crime is found to have a high
                    eventfulness and follows the additional paradigm of tellability, by virtue of
                    its significance to the community of Hamburg. The texts all deal with the case
                    of Werner Pinzner, who murdered at least five men living and working in the
                    surroundings of the red light district in St. Pauli, Hamburg, an area well known
                    for crime. The case became famous because of two central events: Firstly, this
                    was one of the first acts known or acknowledged to exist in Hamburg, or even in
                    Germany, of organized murder, which is at least partly due to the fact that
                    Pinzer started to talk to the police very openly once he was caught. Secondly,
                    is the fact that he committed an extended suicide killing not only himself, but
                    also his wife and the prosecutor inside the police office during an
                    interrogation. This extended suicide led to several developments in the works
                    and procedures of the police in Hamburg (such as regular screenings of visitors
                    of criminals and other increased security measures). In terms of eventfulness
                    and tellability we argue that the case matches all ten conditions (relevance,
                    unpredictability, irreversibility, non-iterativity, effect, script-violation,
                    personal and interpersonal significance, spatial outreach and temporal
                    relations) to a very high degree. It is therefore not surprising that it was
                    used in factual and fictional narrative representations in different media. </p>
                <p>As we have noted, there have been a few attempts to model events using
                    computational means. On an abstract level, trying to prove that the notion of
                    event regardless of its eventfulness always is interpretive, which is
                    underpinned by the use of a computational tool revealing how in the surrounding
                    text of manually identified events other interpretive decisions could have been
                    made <ptr target="#meister2013"/>. Another approach was developed by
                    computational linguists, who attempted to extract events on a spatio-temporal
                    basis <ptr target="#strötgen2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#shrestha2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#wang2013"/>. The last is very similar to the approach presented in
                    this paper, but supplemented by an interdisciplinary perspective, adding the
                    properties of historic events.</p>
                <p>If we take for example the definition of historic events proposed by <ptr
                        target="#mostern2008"/> instead of a very complex structure of properties
                    and possibilities as found in narratological models, we get a set of surface
                    markers which will lead us to the historic event as named entity when put into
                    the right grammatical structure. Following their argumentation the historic
                    event combines three properties: name, place and time. All three of them will be
                    tied together very closely, each one of them evoking the other when being named. </p>
                <p>In our example the historic event could be named <title rend="quotes">Der Fall
                        Pinzner</title> (literally translated to <title rend="quotes">the Pinzner
                        Case</title>). In this case the name functions as a unique identifier for
                    the event whereas place and time are less likely to evoke thinking of this
                    specific event immediately. But of course this event is really a series of
                    events. The more concrete an event becomes, the more identifiable will it become
                    by its location and time. So if we take the suicide of Pinzner and the murder of
                    his wife and the prosecutor as one central event of the top-event Pinzner-case,
                    the place will be as concrete as an address with a room number (police office
                    Berliner Tor, Room 418), the exact date will be 29th July 1986. The fact that
                    this specific event has no name as unique identifier brings us back to the more
                    unspecific narrative event. What we can take from the definition of historic
                    events is the possibility of identifying events by a set of surface markers.
                    Furthermore, the characters involved are also good objects to identify an event.
                    The ensemble of characters, place and time altogether will be as unique as a
                    name. The problem in automatic extraction, however, will be that in opposition
                    to our example one will most often not know all of the entities involved. But
                    one can at least be sure that there will be one or more characters, a place and
                    a time attached to an event. So the unique event identifier would be <list
                        type="simple">
                        <item>specific character(s) involved + specific place + specific point in
                            time</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Especially when dealing with fictional texts, we face the problem that there will
                    not always be all of the variables in this formula explicitly named in the text.
                    Nevertheless we can take them as hints to events. The more of these hints can be
                    collocated in a text passage the more likely they will lead us to events.</p>
                <p>All of these ideas still do not provide a solution to compute all kinds of events
                    in a narrative. But it does provide us with a categorized set of clues, which
                    are likely to lead us to most of the narrative events in a text, and thus
                    providing the possibility to interpret and categorize them according to
                    narratological models. The next step therefore is to identify and collocate the
                    variables of the above named formula in stories, and to interpret them according
                    to their narrative function. In order to do this we developed a semi-automated
                    workflow or pipeline including Digital Humanities tools as well as manual steps.
                    As one possibility for finding named entities is Named Entity Recognition (NER),
                    we applied the Stanford NER tool to the corpus. This tool provides a script for
                    the German language which was trained on a corpus of journalistic texts. As the
                    corpus focused in this case study contains a journalistic text as well as a
                    fictional text, the tool will not work equivalently well on both texts but, as
                    we do not attempt to extract <emph>all</emph> the events from one text but
                    rather a critical mass of events altogether, this fact does not seriously
                    detract from the interpretation and conclusion found here. In the end what we
                    get in this step is a text document enriched by HTML tags highlighting names,
                    places and organizations (this last entity being one excluded from this study). </p>
                <p>As NER does not include time, we used a second tool called Heideltime to extract
                    temporal data in a similar way. Again, the result is a text document enriched
                    with HTML tags. We stress this point here as it is desirable in Digital
                    Humanities to have cross-tool compatibility in different domains. In this
                    application we normalized our outcome data to create a <soCalled>real</soCalled>
                    HTML file. However the next tool we used is CATMA, which satisfies the
                    requirement for cross-domain compatibility by accepting HTML files with
                    intrinsic markup. With CATMA we could do several collocation analyses. Thus, we
                    first looked at all three entities being name, place and time found in a textual
                    surrounding of 20 words. In this analysis CATMA is detecting automatically
                    passages of text in which all three entities are found in proximity to each
                    other and lists all possible variations into a spreadsheet of keywords in
                    context. We repeatedly run queries changing the parameters from all three
                    entities to just two of them and changing pairs. In the end we exported all
                    keyword-in-context-lists to search them manually for the events told in the text
                    and to exclude duplicates. </p>
                <p>However, as the tools named above do not work on audio-visual medial
                    representations the whole process was manually performed when it came to the
                    analysis of the two movies included in the corpus. This means nothing else than
                    noting down each entity named in the movies into a table. <q>Naming</q> in this
                    case can be differentiated into being told acoustically or visually which could
                    be either textually or through showing characters or places (we followed Kuhn's
                    attempt <ptr target="#kuhn2011"/> to movie narratology here by assuming an
                    audio-visual narrative instance replacing the narrator). Afterwards the lists
                    were again searched manually for events in the surrounding of the named entities
                    characters, place and time. </p>
                <p>As stated above the collocation of all three identified surface markers of events
                    (characters, place, time) leads to the most precise outcome, but unfortunately
                    this approach proved very unsatisfactory regarding recall. On the other side a
                    collocation of two of the variables was not very precise but a lot more events
                    could be found in the outcome data. The automatically produced outcomes were
                    manually analysed and events in the surrounding text passages were identified.
                    Despite the fact that this method is not sufficiently productive to use it on
                    larger corpora it led us to a number of events of different eventfulness and
                    tellability, and thus provided us with a starting point for interpretation. </p>
                <p>In the corpus, a totality of about 350 events were identified as explained above.
                    They were evaluated according to the ten properties of eventfulness and
                    tellability following the key 0=none, 1=low, 2=medium and 3=high. The findings
                    were set according to the output data and put into tables, one for each of the
                    texts (the following table exemplifies the first five thus processed events of
                    Lindlau’s <title rend="quotes">Lohnkiller</title>: <table xml:id="table01">
                        <head>Narrative events in Der Fall Pinzer.</head>
                        <row>
                            <cell>Event</cell>
                            <cell> Trial against Giovanny Falcone </cell>
                            <cell> Body is found </cell>
                            <cell> Witness talked about organised crime scene </cell>
                            <cell> Brothel keeper gets shot </cell>
                            <cell> Death of prosecutor </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Relevance </cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> script-violation </cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Irreversibility </cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Effect </cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> unpredicatbility </cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> non-iterativity </cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>0</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> personal significance </cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> interpersonal significance </cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> spatial outreach </cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> temporal relation </cell>
                            <cell>2</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>1</cell>
                            <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <cell> Value </cell>
                            <cell>20</cell>
                            <cell>15</cell>
                            <cell>18</cell>
                            <cell>17</cell>
                            <cell>26</cell>
                        </row>
                    </table></p>
                <p>The outcome of the analysis shows the different values of eventfulness of the
                    events in the narratives and it gives some hints on narration techniques. This
                    kind of output data cannot lead to any absolute statements about narrated
                    events, as it is not extracted from a sufficiently large corpus, nor is the
                    method stable enough to let us assume that a significant percentage of all
                    events in the text could be extracted. However, the data represents events of
                    diverse degrees of eventfulness/tellability and thus shows a stable variety of
                    the construction of narratives with events.</p>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>Events in textual representations of the Pinzner-Case and their
                        values</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The most important findings for this paper are, firstly, that the six major
                    events (the 5 paid murders and the extended suicide) of the case were narrated
                    through a much larger number of events and, secondly, that these events differ
                    in value of eventfulness. These findings underline the theoretical hypothesis
                    that narrative can be a means to exploit multiplicity and multivocality in
                    events. It is also interesting that in this case study there was neither found
                    an event with no eventfulness at all, nor any kind of
                        <soCalled>super-event</soCalled> reaching the highest possible score of
                    eventfulness. The visualization above shows this multiplicity of eventfulness
                    values quite clearly.</p>
                <p>It also shows that there are more events with low eventfulness and that the means
                    of eventfulness is altogether a bit lower in the fictional representation. In
                    addition to that the fictional representation tends to use more eventful events
                    towards the end. On the other side the factual representations shows quite a lot
                    more events on less tokens which means that there is a higher density of events
                    in that text. (However, this finding could also be due to the fact that the tool
                    works better on journalistic texts, so it should not be evaluated too highly.)
                    In both representations one can see that there are passages in the text which
                    show more events than others; one significant finding of such a local event
                    density in both examples being the end, although only the factual representation
                    narrates the historic situation with the extended suicide and murder of the
                    prosecutor (whereas in the novel text, the <soCalled>St. Pauli Killer</soCalled>
                    kills himself and his wife in his cell). It is also interesting that both
                    textual representations end with an event of medium eventfulness.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Events in audio-visual representations of the Pinzner-Case and their
                        values</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>
                <p>The data found in the filmic representations shows similar trends. Again, the
                    main event is told by a number of smaller events of differing eventfulness.
                    Again, the means of the eventfulness values is higher in the factual
                    representation and again the event density is higher in the factual
                    representation showing more events per second than the fictional movie (as in
                    this case the extraction was not done automatically, there is no measuring error
                    to be kept in mind here). The TV movie, though, is the only representation
                    showing a structure which tends to the Aristotelic order of beginning, middle
                    and ending using highly eventful events in these parts of narration. Both films
                    start with a very eventful event <soCalled>in medias res</soCalled> which could
                    be interpreted as a typical narrative opening for this medium whereas the texts
                    in this corpus tend to start with rather low-level events. In contrast to the
                    textual representations the filmic narratives both also end with highly eventful
                    events, which might also be medium specific. It is also interesting that the
                    filmic factual representation does not keep one level of eventfulness throughout
                    the whole narration but shows a slight trend to more eventful events towards the
                    end as in the textual representations only the fictional text did. </p>
                <p>In order to get hold of the multivocality of these four texts one has to step
                    back from the data presented above and look into the representations itself. One
                    example which shows this aspect quite well is the spatial narration concerning
                    the street <q>Reeperbahn</q>, which is where the red light district of Hamburg
                    is situated. Especially in the journalistically written text <title
                        rend="quotes">Der Lohnkiller</title> (literally translated <q>the paid
                        killer</q>), the <q>Reeperbahn</q>, is presented as if it was a character of
                    its own having its own will, making its own decisions, and its own narrative.
                    But the spatial narrative of this street is presented in all the texts of the
                    corpus as a collective narrative which many people living in Hamburg and
                    especially in the area around the <q>Reeperbahn</q> share and some relate to in
                    a special way, because they take part in it. By doing this they create a
                    collective identity so closely linked to a space that it may seem as if the
                    place was the agent of the narrative, whereas in reality the spatial narrative
                    is a multiplicity of individually experienced events and collectively chosen
                    decisions. What is special about places like this and also about the one
                    presented later on in the second case study of this paper, is that there are
                    different layers of connections to the individually experienced events. The
                    Pinzner case takes the perspective of somebody desperately wanting to take part
                    in the spatial narrative, but never fully getting there, because Pinzner,
                    despite his <soCalled>job</soCalled>, never really achieved the respect for
                    which he aimed. Further on, the narratives in the corpus also show other
                    characters that take part in the criminal surrounding of the Reeperbahn. The
                    narratives show police, prosecutor and lawyer being inside the spatial narrative
                    and outside of the collective identity of it at the same time. And finally, and
                    no less importantly, the mention of the spatial entities (in addition to
                    Reeperbahn, the area St. Pauli takes a similar role as well as the nickname of
                    it <q>Kiez</q>) evoke an experience-centred connection to events in the
                    individual memory of the recipient, be it that s/he has heard rumours about it
                    before, visited it before or even takes part in the life-world connected to it. </p>
                <p>Despite the fact that the narratives in the corpus represent the event of the
                    Pinzner case in a traditional way using traditional media such as books and
                    movies, they do add multi-perspective and multivocal narratives to the cultural
                    heritage of this specific area of Hamburg. They also add historic events to the
                    experience-based spatial narrative an individual might connect to places like
                    the <q>Reeperbahn</q>. They even preserve some narratives of places which have
                    vanished from the city today, as the old police headquarters which was situated
                    in the city centre and not as it is now in a highly secured area in the
                    periphery. In the end the events not only structure the narrative, the narrative
                    is also connecting events to other entities (as characters, spaces and dates)
                    and thus adding significance to them. The events vary in eventfulness and
                    tellability as well as in functionality, and thus a narrative multiplicity is
                    not only acknowledged but supported actively. </p>
                <p>The Pinzner case is an especially good example for showing multiplicity and
                    multivocality of narrative events, but it is arguably too recent to be
                    especially significant for illustrating historic events. Therefore, in the
                    following we now introduce a second case study, which examines Hadrian’s Wall.
                    The Wall is a spatial entity which is less constrained than the Reeperbahn in
                    terms of size as well as in terms of history. From here on we will focus less on
                    traditional representations in modern media and complement the above shown point
                    of view by other storytelling traditions such as oral storytelling, cultural
                    heritage delivery and personal and interpersonal experience and interaction.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Hadrian’s Wall</head>
                <p>As noted above, text is only one medium through which narrative can be conveyed.
                    Another is in the curation and presentation of monuments <ptr
                        target="#azaryahu2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#nesbitt2009"/>. This is a particularly interesting environment in
                    which to test the theory of narrative categorisation and non-binary
                    operationalisation, as monuments have multiple <soCalled>narrators</soCalled> of
                    their spaces and significance – the designers, the builders, those who occupied
                    the landscape at the time, and those who occupy it now. Hadrian’s Wall is one of
                    the UK’s most iconic ancient monuments. It is a place in its own right, but it
                    is also a place made up of multiple locations (much as the events in Der Fall
                    Pinzner combine to form a larger event), some of which are specific and
                        <soCalled>tellable</soCalled>, and others more abstract. Its tellable
                    significance derives not only from its size and scale, stretching some 84 miles
                    between the coasts of Northern England, with good preservation of the monument
                    in the middle sections; but also from its context as a key section of the
                    frontier of the Roman Empire from AD 122 until late antiquity. Many writers and
                    observers throughout history have seen it, as a whole, as embodying narratives
                    of separation and division; despite more recent archaeological researches which
                    have stressed its role as a mediator between the (occupying) Roman population in
                    the south and the unoccupied populations to the north <ptr target="#dobson2000"
                    />. However, as <ptr target="#hingley2010"/> has demonstrated, the separation
                    narratives persist; in fact one might say they were imposed on the monument
                    after the Roman period by later authors, appearing and reappearing in the
                    writings of multiple witnesses throughout subsequent generations. Following
                    Hingley, one might quote the German historian of the Roman Frontiers, Theodor
                    Mommsen: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#breeze2009">[The German limes] had not, like
                            the Britannic Wall, the object of checking the invasion of the enemy …
                            the Romans in Upper Germany did not confront their neighbours as they
                            confronted the Highlanders of Britain, in whose presence the province
                            was always in a state of siege.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#breeze2009"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>Or the English historian and travel writer, John Collingwood Bruce, who describes
                    the Wall as: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#hingley2010">a great fortification intended to
                            act not only as a fence against a northern enemy, but to be used as the
                            basis of military operations against a foe on either side of it</quote>
                        <ptr target="#hingley2010"/>
                    </cit>.</p>
                <p>Both these readings of Wall narrative stress its narrative
                        <soCalled>wholeness</soCalled>, read in the context of the nineteenth
                    century nation state, with firm notions of <soCalled>inside</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>outside</soCalled>, and a concept of
                        <soCalled>civilisation</soCalled> and <soCalled>barbarism</soCalled>, drawn
                    largely from a reading of Classical authors. It reflects the employment of two
                    individuals’ spatial literacy in the understanding of the Wall.</p>
                <p>The concept of spatial literacy is a useful one here, as it implicitly invokes
                    the metaphor of <q>reading</q> when it comes to geography, and allows us to
                    develop the concept of the <soCalled>spatial narrative</soCalled>, in parallel
                    to that of textual narrative. As will be seen, it also supports a similar
                    non-binary operationalisation of events as that demonstrated in Der Fall Pinzer.
                    It also allows us to consider particular embodied interactions with the Wall in
                    terms of their <soCalled>eventfulness</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>tellability</soCalled>, in much the same ways as the Hamburg
                    sequence above is composed of <soCalled>eventful</soCalled> and
                        <soCalled>tellable</soCalled> happenings at different scales. The idea of
                    the spatial narrative has been theorised in recent years by scholars such as
                    Bodenhamer, Corrigan and Harris <ptr target="#bodenhamer2010"/>, and in relation
                    to the curation of heritage sites by <ptr target="#azaryahu2008"/>. For the
                    present purposes, it may be most usefully defined as <q>a meaningful statement, or set of linked
                        statements, whose fundamental structure is geographical</q>, where each
                    statement tells an event. Or, to put it in the context of the poststructuralist
                    theory of narrative developed above, a narrative is a <q>spatial</q> one when
                    its <soCalled>eventfulness</soCalled> and <soCalled>tellability</soCalled> stem
                    from the description of events which happen in, and relate to, a location, which
                    is specifiable to a greater or lesser degree. The statement may stem from
                    experience, proximity, association, or some extrinsic geographical (or
                    archaeological) feature. <soCalled>Reading</soCalled> such a narrative is the
                    making of personal meaning as <soCalled>told</soCalled> by the place, as opposed
                    from a narrative that is told by another human agent. In this case,
                        <soCalled>the other</soCalled> is not a human narrator or agent, but the
                    Wall itself. It follows logically that a spatial narrative cannot be read in any
                    light other than that of multiplicity. The more points that are added in terms
                    of time, character and (smaller) places, the definition of the event becomes
                    clearer.</p>
                <p>The <soCalled>embodied</soCalled> narrative of Hadrian’s Wall has been described
                    by <ptr target="#nesbitt2009"/>, who operationalise the monument in terms of its
                    narrative, and how its narrative significance is shaped by the authority
                    structures of English Heritage and the National Trust, who regulate physical
                    access to the Wall, and thus the embodied experience of it. They state: <cit>
                        <quote rend="block" source="#nesbitt2009">English Heritage and the National
                            Trust delimit and control access to the Wall. These authoritative
                            interpretations and recommended route ways delimit the bodily encounter
                            with the Wall and this affects the physical intelligibility of the
                            experience of the landscape.</quote>
                        <ptr target="#nesbitt2009"/>
                    </cit></p>
                <p>We have here an example of events which can happen in relation to the monument
                    being regulated by an external actor. This exemplifies the
                        <soCalled>authoritative</soCalled>, or <soCalled>single-author</soCalled>
                    model of narrative construction described above, and how such a model can relate
                    to corporate as well as individual human authorship. </p>
                <p>However, this narrative is only part of the broader spatial narrative of the
                    monument, as may be illustrated by considering the case of the fort at
                    Birdoswald, in Cumbria. This, fort number 11 in the official English Heritage
                    listing, was not described in Camden’s Britannia, although Camden himself was
                    clearly aware of it, as John Warburton, in his 1778 treatise on Hadrian’s Wall,
                    noted that Camden had mistakenly believed the fort to have been situated at the
                    nearby town of Willowford <ptr target="#warburton1753"/>. Our narrative begins
                    with the establishment of the fort, which is connected by the Wall to milecastle
                    49 and, further on, to the extant Wall structure to the east of the river at
                    Willowford. Approximately 800 meters to the east of the present-day course of
                    the river is a bridgehead of Roman date, indicating that the course of the river
                    has moved to the west in the intervening centuries. The present-day National
                    Trail, curated by English Heritage, which follows the approximate line of the
                    Wall, diverts to the south, crosses the modern river, and then climbs a steep
                    hairpin bend to the fort itself. </p>
                <p>This specific section of the Wall relates to the narrative of Momsen, Collingwood
                    Bruce and Camden in a way which is tellable, but not eventful. There are no
                    specific events or happenings in the history of this section which can be
                    invoked to support the narrative of separation. On the other hand, as Nesbitt
                    and Tolia-Kelly note, the embodied experience of the Wall, and of its
                    constituent forts, is conditioned by English Heritage curation, and this is
                    expressible through the individual embodied experiences of those who visit or
                    interact with the section, at any point in its history <ptr
                        target="#nesbitt2009"/>. In the context of the present day, its impact on
                    visitors, as recorded by how they move along and through the monument, can be
                    rendered visually in GPS traces uploaded to OpenStreetMap, the Open Source
                    online mapping platform. Here, people have the opportunity to capture the
                    pathways they take using their mobile devices, and share them on the map
                    platform. They are thus adding specific and individual narrative events to
                    abstract spatial narrative of the Wall as a whole. The traces shown in <ref
                        target="#figure03">Figure 3</ref> indicate little or no engagement with the
                    Wall or the trail, rather they all lead from the nearby car park. Once at the
                    site, the highly conditioned nature of the experience, and thus of the
                    narrative, become apparent: most of the visitors’ movements are confined to the
                    north of the fort, with much less movement in the south. Most of the embodied
                    engagement is therefore with the visitors’ centre and shop, and prior to that
                    the car park. One can also detect that some visitors moved a few meters to the
                    north, perhaps for the purposes of getting a longer view of the site. <figure
                        xml:id="figure04">
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                    </figure>
                    <figure xml:id="figure05">
                        <head>Individual encounters with Hadrian’s Wall shared on OpenStreetMap
                                (<ref target="#figure04">figure 4</ref>) and detail of the
                            interactions with Birdoswald Fort.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure> This section of the Wall may therefore be related as a set of events
                    linked by geography. </p>
                <p>Individual parts of the topography may be easily mapped and entered in a
                    gazetteer-like database: the spatial footprint of the fort, the visitors’
                    centre, the car park, the line of the Wall, the Turf Wall, the bridgehead, the
                    modern bridge, the extant Willowford section etc. All of these relate to the
                    abstract whole of the Wall, and its associated narratives of separation through
                    time and are <soCalled>tellable</soCalled> in that larger context, but they can
                    only become <soCalled>eventful</soCalled> when they come into contact with the
                    experience of the individual. The operationalisation of the Birdoswald section
                    of the Wall in <ref target="#table02">table 2</ref> reflects this </p>
                <table xml:id="table02">
                    <head>Narrative events around Hadrian’s Wall.</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Event</cell>
                        <cell>Wall constructed</cell>
                        <cell>Birdoswald constructed</cell>
                        <cell>Camden describes the Wall</cell>
                        <cell>Life of St Oswald (gives fort its modern name)</cell>
                        <cell>Warburton visits Birdoswald fort</cell>
                        <cell>Warburton describes Camden’s mistaken description of the
                            topography</cell>
                        <cell>English Heritage assumes responsibility for the Fort</cell>
                        <cell>Individual visitor visits Birdoswald</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Narrative Representation</cell>
                        <cell>Officially documented by historians</cell>
                        <cell>Officially documented by historians</cell>
                        <cell>Personal narration</cell>
                        <cell>Officially documented by historians</cell>
                        <cell>Personal narration delivered by historians</cell>
                        <cell>Personal narration delivered by historians</cell>
                        <cell>Officially documented by historians</cell>
                        <cell>Personal narration</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Relevance</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Script-Violation</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Irreversibility</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Effect</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Unpredictability</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Non-iterativity</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Personal Significance</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Interpersonal Significance</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Spatial outreach</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Temporal Relation</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>0</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Value</cell>
                        <cell>24</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <p>Whereas <title rend="quotes">Der Fall Pinzner</title> showed us that in one
                    single authored narrative there may be a multiple and multivocal set of events
                    which tell the story altogether, in this case study we went the other way around
                    and chose some events connected to the Birdoswald Fort in order to compare them
                    by eventfulness and tellability. First of all we have to clarify that these
                    events are historic events rather than narrative events because they are not
                    necessarily narrated. In opposition to the events of the first case study, they
                    may be seen as raw events and yet it has been proven possible to evaluate them
                    with narratological categories.</p>
                <p>Contrary to the events that constructed the narratives about Pinzner, these
                    events are relatively in the value of eventfulness/tellability despite the fact
                    that they are very heterogeneous when it comes to their historic time, or their
                    status as events that are <soCalled>told</soCalled> by official or unofficial
                    sources. What is striking about the events when represented in this way is that
                    individual visits of the wall have a slightly higher eventfulness/tellability
                    than most of the officially delivered events: <figure xml:id="figure06">
                        <head>Events connected to Birdoswald in value (x-axis = size) and way of
                            deliverance (colour)</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                    </figure></p>
                <p>Overall, this suggests that where spatial entity, such as Hadrian’s Wall, is the
                    dominant feature in its landscape, it normalises the narrative complexity of
                    events which are connected with it. The eventfulness and tellability might vary
                    with the kind of event, and the <soCalled>official</soCalled> or
                        <soCalled>unofficial</soCalled> nature of the narrator, but essentially they
                    share the fact that they are all differing interpretations of a common dominant
                    feature. This is in contrast to an area such as the Reeperbahn, which contains
                    and informs, but does not dominate, the narrative of the Pinzer events.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Conclusions</head>
                <p>This analysis has shown that representations of events in traditional media are
                    not as unilinear and univocal as they first appear, and that representing
                    subjective instances of them in a machine-readable way is potentially possible.
                    Secondly we can state that individually experienced, or
                        <soCalled>instanced</soCalled> events, to use the terminology of <ptr
                        target="#mostern2008"/>, events are of equal value as culturally delivered
                    events. This comparative analysis across a specific narrative in Hamburg, and an
                    abstract one in Northern England, shows events can be conceived in a
                    gazetteer-like way, without the reductionist limitations that a gazetteer based
                    purely on Cartesian space contains.</p>
                <p>In terms of methods we have demonstrated that an approach to events which
                    included multiple factors of eventfulness and tellability is fruitful for the
                    analysis of single events in the context of all the others, and may bring us
                    closer to the materiality of humanities discourse as evidence-based
                    storytelling. It has also been shown that narrated or mediated events and
                    historic events may be analysed with the same parameters (if these include the
                    ideas of multiplicity and multivocality). The structured data we processed in
                    our case studies showed that the storage of events in a database gives us the
                    possibility to evaluate those, along different parameters derived from
                    narratological theory.</p>
                <p>The DH workflow including several tools was fruitful but nevertheless found to be
                    inconvenient for studies focusing on larger corpora. In terms of finding
                    effective ways of automated event extraction this attempt therefore must be seen
                    more or less as failed. Nevertheless the basic ideas of quantification and
                    (semi-) automated extraction of data taken from Digital Humanities research led
                    to first insights into general narrative techniques related to the
                    representation of events. Aspects of storyline and event density could be
                    discussed and related to different narrative genres. These very first hints on
                    technical aspects of storytelling could lead to further (DH) research on plot
                    structures combining the computational with the narratological perspective. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sellar1930" label="Sellar and Yeatman 1930">Sellar, W. C. and Julian
                    Yeatman, R. J. 1066 and All That. Folio Society: London, 1999. (first published
                    by Methuen, 1930). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cuno2008" label="Cuno 2008">Cuno, J. Who Owns Antiquity? Museums and
                    the Battle over Our Ancient Heritage.Princeton University Press, Princeton
                    (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="breeze2009" label="Breeze 2009">Breeze, D. J. <title rend="quotes">Did
                        Hadrian design Hadrian’s Wall?</title> <title rend="italic">Archaeologia
                        Aeliana</title> 38 (2009): 87-103.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="taylor2005" label="Taylor and Caquard 2005">Taylor, D. R. and Caquard,
                    S. <title rend="quotes">Cybercartography: Maps and Mapping in the Information
                        Era</title>. Cartographica 41(1): 1-5. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="caquard2011" label="Caquard 2011"><title rend="quotes">Cartography I:
                        Mapping narrative cartography</title>. <title rend="italic">Progress in
                        Human Geography</title> 37(1) (2011): 135-144.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="azaryahu2008" label="Azaryahu and Foote 2008">Azaryahu, M. and Foote,
                    K. E. <title rend="quotes">Historical space as narrative medium: on the
                        configuration of spatial narratives of time at historical sites.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">GeoJournal</title>, 73.3 (2008): 179-194.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hodder1993" label="Hodder 1993">Hodder, I. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Narrative and Rhetoric of Material Culture Sequences.</title> World
                    Archaeology 25(2), Conceptions of Time and Ancient Society (1993):
                    268-282.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pluciennik1999" label="Pluciennik 1999">Pluciennik, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Archaeological narratives and other ways of telling.</title>
                    Current Anthropology: 653-678.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan2007" label="Ryan 2007">Ryan, M-L. <title rend="quotes">Towards a
                        definition of Narrative.</title> In David Herman (ed.). The Cambridge
                    Companion to Narrative. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge: 22-38.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="phelan2007" label="Phelan 2007">Phelan, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Rhetoric/ethics.</title> In David Herman (ed.). The Cambridge Companion to
                    Narrative. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge: 203-216.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="martinez2009" label="Martinez and Scheffel 2009">Martinez, M. and
                    Scheffel, M. Einführung in die Erzähltheorie. C.H. Beck, Munich. (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ochs2001" label="Ochs and Capps 2001">Ochs, E. and Capps, L. Living
                    Narrative: Creating Lives in Everyday Storytelling. Harvard University Press,
                    Cambridge, Mass (2001). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="meister2013" label="Meister 2013">Meister, J. C. Computing Action.
                    deGruyter, Berlin (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan2015" label="Ryan 2015"><title rend="quotes">Space</title>. In:
                    Peter Hühn et al. (eds.): The living handbook of narratology. Hamburg
                    University, Hamburg. <title rend="italic">Time</title>, 21 Feb 2015. <ref
                        target="http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/space"
                        >http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/space</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bonheim1982" label="Bonheim 1982">Bonheim, H. The Narrative Modes:
                    Techniques of the Short Story. Brewer, Cambridge (1982). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan1991" label="Ryan 1991">Ryan, M-L. Possible Worlds, Artificial
                    Intelligence and Narrative Theory. Indiana University Press, Indianapolis
                    (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schmid2008" label="Schmid 2008">Schmid, W. Elemente der Narratologie.
                    deGruyter, Berlin (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hühn2008" label="Hühn 2008">Hühn, P. <title rend="quotes">Functions
                        and Forms of Eventfulness in Narrative Fiction.</title> In: John Pier and
                    José Àngel García Landa (eds.): Theorizing Narrativity. de Gruyter, Berlin
                    (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="luhmann1997" label="Luhmann 1997">Luhmann, N. Die Gesellschaft der
                    Gesellschaft. Suhrkamp, Frankfurt (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="baroni2014" label="Baroni 2014">Baroni, R. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Tellability</title>. In: Peter Hühn et al. (eds.): The living handbook of
                    narratology. Hamburg University, Hamburg. <hi rend="italic">Time,</hi> 25 Nov
                    2014. <ref target="http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/tellability"
                        >http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/tellability</ref> (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fludernik2003" label="Fludernik 2003">Fludernik, M. <title
                        rend="quotes">Natural Narratology and Cognitive Parameters.</title> In: D.
                    Herman (ed.): Narrative Theory and the Cognitive Sciences. CSLI, Stanford
                    (2003). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fludernik1996" label="Fludernik 1996">Fludernik, M. <title
                        rend="italic">Towards a Natural Narratology</title>. Routledge, London
                    (1996). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hühn2014" label="Hühn 2014">Hühn, P. <title rend="quotes">Event and
                        Eventfulness</title>. In: P. Hühn et al. (ed.): The living handbook of
                    narratology. Hamburg University, Hamburg. <title rend="italic">Time</title>, 25
                    Nov 2014. <ref
                        target="http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/event-and-eventfulness"
                        >http://www.lhn.uni-hamburg.de/article/event-and-eventfulness</ref>
                    (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="norrick2000" label="Norrick 2000">Norrick, N. R. Conversational
                    Narrative: Storytelling in everyday talk. John Benjamins Publishing, Amsterdam
                    (2000). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ryan2005" label="Ryan 2005">Ryan, M-L. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Tellability.</title> In D. Herman et al. (ed.) Routledge Encyclopedia of
                    Narrative Theory. Routledge, London (2005): 589–91.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bamberg2008" label="Bamberg and Georgakopoulou 2008">Bamberg, M. and
                    Georgakopoulou, A. <title rend="quotes">Small Stories as a new Perspective in
                        Narrative and Identity Analysis</title>. Text &amp; Talk, 28/3 (2008):
                    377-396.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mostern2008" label="Mostern and Johnson 2008">Mostern, R. and Johnson,
                    I. <title rend="quotes">From named place to naming event: creating gazetteers
                        for history</title>. International Journal of Geographical Information
                    Science, 22.10 (2008): 1091-1108.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lützeler1992" label="Lützeler 1992"><title rend="quotes">Fictionality
                        in Historiography and the Novel</title>. In: A. Clark F. I. Hoesterey and M.
                    Tatar (eds.): Neverending Stories. Towards a Critical Narratology. Princeton
                    University Press, Princeton (1992): 29-44. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pavel1992" label="Pavel 1992">Pavel, T. <title rend="quotes">Between
                        History and Fiction: On Dorit Cohn’s Poetics of Prose.</title> In: A. Clark
                    F. I. Hoesterey and M. Tatar (eds.): Neverending Stories. Towards a Critical
                    Narratology. Princeton University Press, Princeton (1992): 17-28. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tilley1994" label="Tilley 1994">Tilley, C. A Phenomenology of
                    Landscape: Places, Paths and Monuments. Berg, Michigan (1994). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brück2005" label="Brück 2005">Brück, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Experiencing the past? The development of a phenomenological archaeology in
                        British prehistory</title>. Archaeological Dialogues 12.1. (2005):
                    45-72.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barrett2009" label="Barrett and Ko 2009">Barrett, J. and Ko, I. <title
                        rend="quotes">A phenomenology of landscape: A crisis in British landscape
                        archaeology?</title> Journal of Social Archaeology 9.3 (2009):
                    275-294.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohn1989" label="Cohn 1989">Cohn, D. <title rend="quotes">Fictional
                        versus Historical Lives: Borderlines and Borderline Cases.</title> Journal
                    of Narrative Technique 19.1 (1989): 3-24. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="heise2014" label="Heise 2014">Heise, D. Event Structure Analysis: A
                    short Ethno Tutorial. Time, 1 Dec 2014. <ref
                        target="http://www.indiana.edu/~socpsy/ESA/Tutorial.html"
                        >http://www.indiana.edu/~socpsy/ESA/Tutorial.html</ref>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="moretti2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, F. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Operationalizing: or, the function of measurement in modern literary
                        theory.</title> In <title rend="quotes">Pamphlets of the Stanford Literary
                        Lab</title> (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="göhre2011" label="Göhre 2011">Göhre, F. Die Kiez-Trilogie. Pendragon,
                    Bielefeld. (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lindlau1992" label="Lindlau 1992">Lindlau, D. Der Lohnkiller.
                    Drömer/Knaur, Munich (1992).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hofman1995" label="Hofman 1995">Hofman, N. Der große Abgang. SWR,
                    Baden-Baden (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="harrich-zandberg2002" label="Harrich-Zandberg 2002">Danuta
                    Harrich-Zandberg, D. <title rend="quotes">Der St. Pauli Killer.</title> In:
                    TV-Documentation: Die großen Kriminalfälle. NDR, Hamburg (2002). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="strötgen2014" label="Strötgen et al. 2014">Strötgen, J., Gertz, M.,
                    and Popov, P. <title rend="quotes">Extraction and Exploration of Spatio-Temporal
                        Information in Documents.</title> In: Proceeding GIR '10: Proceedings of the
                    6th Workshop on Geographic Information Retrieval. Time, 26 (2014): <ref
                        target="http://dbs.ifi.uni-heidelberg.de/fileadmin/Team/jannik/publications/authors_version_gir10.pdf"
                        >http://dbs.ifi.uni-heidelberg.de/fileadmin/Team/jannik/publications/authors_version_gir10.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shrestha2014" label="Shrestha et al. 2014">Shrestha, A., Miller, B.,
                    Zhu, Y. and Zhao, Y. <title rend="quotes">Storygraph: Extracting patterns from
                        spatio-temporal data.</title> In: Proceeding<ref
                        target="http://www.geo.unizh.ch/%7Ersp/gir10/">GIR '13: Proceedings of the
                        7th Workshop on Geographic Information Retrieval</ref>. Time, 26 (2014):
                        <ref target="http://poloclub.gatech.edu/idea2013/papers/p96-shrestha.pdf"
                        >http://poloclub.gatech.edu/idea2013/papers/p96-shrestha.pdf</ref>.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wang2013" label="Wang and Steward 2013">Wang, W. and Steward, K.
                        <title rend="quotes">Extracting Spatiotemporal and Semantic Events from
                        Documents.</title> In: Proceeding<ref
                        target="http://www.geo.unizh.ch/%7Ersp/gir10/">IDEA '13</ref>: Proceedings
                    of the ACM SIGKDD Workshop on Interactive Data Exploration and Analytics (2013):
                    95-103. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kuhn2011" label="Kuhn 2011">Kuhn, Markus <title rend="italic"
                        >Filmnarratology</title>. De Gruyter, Berlin (2011). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nesbitt2009" label="Nesbitt and Tolia-Kelly 2009">Nesbitt, C. and
                    Tolia-Kelly, D. Hadrian’s Wall: Embodied Archaeologies of the Linear Monument.
                        <title rend="italic">Journal of Social Archaeology</title> 9 (2009):
                    368-390.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dobson2000" label="Dobson and Breeze 2000">Dobson, B. and Breeze, D.
                    Hadrian’s Wall. Penguin: UK (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hingley2010" label="Hingley 2010">Hingley, R. <title rend="quotes">The
                        most ancient Boundary between England and Scotland’ Genealogies of the Roman
                        Wall(s)</title>. Classical Reception Journal 2.1. (2010): 25-43.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bodenhamer2010" label="Bodenhamer et al. 2010">Bodenhamer, D.,
                    Corrigan, J. J. and Harris, T. M. <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title>.
                    InD. J. Bodenhamer, J. J. Corrigan, and T. M. Harris (eds), The Spatial
                    Humanities: GIS and the Future of Humanities Scholarship. Indiana University
                    Press, Indiana (2010). .</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="warburton1753" label="Warburton 1753">Warburton, J. <title
                        rend="quotes">Vallum Romanum: or the history of the Roman Wall, commonly
                        called the Picts' wall, in Cumberland and Northumberland, built by Hadrian
                        and Severus, etc</title>. London (1753).</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
