<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>e-Science for Medievalists: Options, Challenges, Solutions and
               Opportunities</title>
            <author>Peter Ainsworth</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Peter <dhq:family>Ainsworth</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Dept of French and Humanities Research Institute, University of
                  Sheffield</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>p.f.ainsworth@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Peter Ainsworth is Professor of French at the University of Sheffield and
                     Principal Investigator on the AHRC <ref
                        target="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/onlinefroissart/overview.html">
                        <title rend="quotes">Online Froissart</title>
                     </ref> project (Humanities Research Institute). His team of 6 scholars from
                     Sheffield and Liverpool is completing an electronic edition (with facsimile,
                     collation of manuscript witnesses and partial translation into modern English)
                     of Books I-III of Jean Froissart’s <title rend="italic">Chronicles</title>
                     (c.1350-1392). An exhibition at the Royal Armouries (Dec 2007 to Apr 2008) on
                        <title rend="italic">The Hundred Years’ War in Chronicles, Arms and
                        Armour</title> featured interactive software designed by Peter with Mike
                     Meredith (Tribal and University of Sheffield). Recent publications include:
                        <title rend="quotes">Technologies nouvelles, manuscrits virtuels. La guerre
                        de Cent Ans à travers les Chroniques de Jean Froissart</title> in <title
                        rend="italic">Medieval Historical Discourses. Essays in Honour of Professor
                        Peter S. Noble</title>, ed. Marianne J. Ailes, Anne Lawrence-Mathers,
                     Françoise H.M. Le Saux, <title rend="italic">Reading Medieval Studies</title>
                     vol XXXIV (Reading, 2008), pp. 21-34 ; and <title rend="italic">Patrons,
                        Authors and Workshops</title>. <title rend="italic">Medieval Manuscript
                        Illumination and Production in Paris circa 1400</title>, ed. Peter Ainsworth
                     and Godfried Croenen, Peeters, <title rend="quotes">Synthema</title> (Leuven,
                     2006). 508 p. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <author>Michael Meredith</author>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Michael <dhq:family>Meredith</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Humanities Research Institute, University of
                  Sheffield</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>m.meredith@sheffield.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr Michael Meredith is a research associate based in the Humanities Research
                     Institute at the University of Sheffield, UK. His early research focused on 3D
                     computer character animation, virtual reality, mechanics and biomechanics,
                     which resulted in a PhD thesis titled <title rend="italic">Adapting and
                        Reconfiguring Human Figure Motion Capture Data through the Application of
                        Inverse Kinematics and Biomechanics-Based Optimisation.</title> After this
                     work he was given the opportunity to work on the e-Science project Virtual
                     Vellum under the PI Professor Peter Ainsworth of the French department at the
                     university. This initiated a very fruitful inter-disciplinary relationship that
                     has continued through into the Kiosque (DTI funded), Online Froissart (AHRC
                     funded) and Pegasus (EPSRC funded) projects. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000071</idno>
            <idno type="volume">003</idno>
            <idno type="issue">4</idno>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <date when="2010-03-20">20 March 2010</date>
            <availability>
               <cc:License xmlns="http://digitalhumanities.org/DHQ/namespace"
                  rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Authored for DHQ; migrated from original DHQauthor format</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available in the <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">DHQ keyword
                     taxonomy</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en"/>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>Encoded document</change>
         <change when="2009-08-11" who="Alyssa">updated publication statement, added to SVN</change>
         <change when="2009-10-26" who="Alyssa">updated with corrections, teaser, email,
            etc.</change>
         <change when="2013-06-20" who="Tassie Gniady">Changed "dhq:caption" to "head."</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Medievalists typically resort to parchment for primary research and when editing
               their sources. Not always accurately catalogued, manuscripts copied onto animal skins
               may have started life in the same workshop but over the centuries have become
               dispersed, coming to rest in libraries all over the world; bringing these together
               entails travel, microfilm purchases and reassembly and collation of the data within
               reach of a microfilm reader. These unwieldy machines afford only moderate scope for
               exploring single manuscripts at close quarters. High-resolution digitisation yields
               not just better surrogates in full colour; it allows for the development of
               additional research tools using image compression and manipulation, and new modes of
               representation, e.g. juxtaposed display of several related witnesses. This paper
               outlines research questions underpinning the development of an electronic tool for
               viewing, transcribing and manipulating manuscripts; it moves on to show how the
               viewer can be adapted for access from remote sites, to compare and annotation one or
               more witnesses (interactively and in real time), and for use as an integral part of
               an online edition. Finally, it explores how it can be deployed for use on projects
               taking knowledge outside the academy: in museums, galleries and other public
               spaces.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>Virtual Vellum: Working Online with Manuscripts</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>e-Science for Medievalists: Options, Challenges, Solutions and Opportunities</head>

         <p>Medievalists typically resort to parchment and vellum for their primary research. Housed
            in libraries across the world, the rolls, books and scraps bearing their precious
            written record are usually (though not always) reliably catalogued. Accessing
            manuscripts for study presents some fascinating problems. Whilst vellum is a durable
            support for the preservation of writing, the pigments used by the artists responsible
            for the miniatures and border decoration are susceptible to cumulative damage from
            abrasion or exposure to daylight. Some libraries direct scholars away from the originals
            and towards black-and-white microfilm stock of variable quality. Manuscript originals
            can sometimes be withdrawn for months at a time and at short notice for unavoidable
            conservation purposes. Yet another challenge familiar to scholars of medieval texts
            arises when one’s target <q>collection</q> or family of manuscripts is scattered across
            the world in libraries each of which has its own access, <q>rights of reproduction</q>
            and copyright policies. Printed facsimiles exist, of course, but tend to be restricted
            to luxury manuscripts. Moreover they are discrete objects, whereas medievalists
            typically want to look (comparatively) at multiple witnesses of a text, at fragments and
            at ostensibly unappealing exemplars devoid of so much as a single miniature or
            illuminated letter. Microfilms are handy, but microfilm readers are not; the machines
            typically occupy a large footprint in any library and limit the scholar to work done on
            site.</p>
         <p>Outlined below is a research trajectory starting with the scholar’s need for
            high-quality facsimiles, for transcription and editing; we move on to consider how these
            might best be developed <q>beyond microfilm,</q> or even CD or DVD, through recourse to
            the combined resources of high-resolution digital photography, image compression and
            other techniques derived from computer science. The outcome — a new electronic tool for
            viewing manuscripts — is described in some detail, with particular reference to a
            forthcoming electronic edition; we then explore how the same tool can be used by
            scholars from different institutions collaborating at a distance from one other over a
            shared Data Grid. The essay concludes with an exploration of how this and other
            e-Science tools can be deployed on projects which aspire to take knowledge outside the
            academy, to museums, galleries and other public spaces.</p>

         <div>
            <head>Microfilm and Beyond</head>
            <p>Black-and-white microfilms produced in the 1940s are still considered to have
               achieved a peak of perfection in terms of image quality and sharpness of definition;
               even so the benefits they have afforded to generations of scholars have to a large
               extent been eclipsed — however unjustly — by the advent of high-resolution color
               photography. Offering considerable benefits in terms of precision, consistency and
               sheer quality, digital photography is still most frequently undertaken by research
               libraries not so much to satisfy the needs of the scholarly community as to protect
               original materials from repeated abrasions and exposure to light. Though medievalists
               will always seek access to original manuscripts, the better to evaluate their
               codicology and sheer physical presence, high-quality digital surrogates offer an
               increasingly viable alternative (for part of the work to be done, at least). One of
               the strangest paradoxes in the digital age is the absence to date of any new,
               custom-built or standardised electronic tools to take over the role of the microfilm
               reader. Digital copies have a potential value far beyond that of serving as a
               microfilm substitute, however. Digitisation surely comes into its own when harnessed
               to technologies able to exploit the full potential of file compression, and to set
               the surrogate free to perform tasks hitherto not asked of it.</p>
            <p>Perhaps because medievalists are by their very training (and often by inclination)
               interdisciplinary, it is scarcely surprising that they have often been in the
               vanguard when novel partnerships have been formed with scholars from disciplines such
               as computer sciences. A prime example would be the pioneering electronic approach to
               the study of the British Library’s comprehensively incinerated <title rend="italic"
                  >Beowulf</title> manuscript, undertaken by Kevin Kiernan and his collaborators a
               full decade ago; this was to lead in turn to the creation of a range of e-Tools
               (known as <title rend="italic">Archway</title>) for scholars working with medieval
               texts and manuscripts <ptr target="#kiernan1997"/>.<note>See also <ptr
                     target="#shillingsburg2006" loc="203"/> and <ptr target="#lesk2004" loc="330"
                  />.</note> One might also refer to large-scale lexicological and lexicographical
               projects such as the ongoing <ref target="http://atilf.atilf.fr/dmf.htm">
                  <title rend="italic">ATILF Dictionnaire du Moyen Français</title>
               </ref> or indeed the print and now online versions of the <ref
                  target="http://www.anglo-norman.net/">
                  <title rend="italic">Anglo-Norman Dictionary</title>
               </ref> under development at Aberystwyth and Swansea. Medievalists continue to ask
               pertinent questions of computer scientists prepared to listen. Attention has shifted
               most recently towards high-resolution digitisation and e-Science. Eclectic yet
               significant collaborations are bringing together scholars, digital photographers,
               imaging specialists and computer programmers (but also, as we shall see below,
               librarians and museum curators). Scholars and programmers are beginning to ask one
               another how some of the most vexing research questions that preoccupy medievalists
               might benefit from digitisation and applications derived from it via e-Science and
               its particular agendas.</p>
            <p>Novel technological solutions are thus being devised by teams coming together for new
               kinds of partnership, sometimes on an ad hoc basis, but also for more sustained
               programmes of collaboration fostered by grand challenge calls going out from the
               research councils. The forging of such partnerships can act as a catalyst for the
               emergence of radically rethought tools for scholarly praxis. Whilst the needs of the
               scholar remain paramount, the advent of e-Science is fostering kinds of dialogue, we
               would argue, in which researcher and programmer can jointly develop new ways of
               thinking around and through their respective areas of practice.<note>Not the least
                  appealing aspect of such work is its collaborative basis. The new opportunities
                  for interdisciplinary collaboration described here deserve to be celebrated and
                  promoted in so far as they can be shown to contribute significantly to the
                  enrichment and even the transformation of disciplines which might, otherwise, risk
                  stagnation.)</note>
            </p>
            <p>Three instances of e-Science are showcased in this paper: starting with a tool for
               viewing, transcribing and manipulating (virtual) manuscripts, we move on to show how
               this resource is being integrated within a major online editorial programme; we then
               explore how it can be adapted for access by scholars at geographically remote sites
               for side-by-side comparison and discussion (interactively, collaboratively, and in
               real time). The paper concludes with a discussion of how the tool can be deployed for
               use on projects beyond the academy, in museums, galleries and other public
               spaces.</p>
            <p>As is well known, much of the most intellectually challenging scholarship in the Arts
               and Humanities is delivered by lone scholars working in research libraries on
               original primary and secondary source material. This continues to be the mainstay of
               research in the UK and in most other developed countries and should never be decried;
               but research councils and other funding bodies have sought in recent years to
               encourage interdisciplinary and collaborative work wherever it looks set to open up
               opportunities that might not otherwise be feasible or thought conceivable. Beyond
                  <q>complementarity of expertise, synergy, cross-disciplinary insights</q> and
               other fashionable buzzwords, the Arts and Humanities Research Council and the
               Engineering and Physical Science Research Council in particular have taken the lead
               in seeking to stimulate fruitful cross-disciplinary research. Two particularly
               exciting initiatives come to mind. The most recent is their joint Science and
               Heritage programme which in 2007 funded a raft of interdisciplinary studentships, and
               which in 2008 launched a new programme to encourage research clusters expected to
               bring together curators, scientists and humanities scholars around collections of
               material culture and their real or potential audiences. The other joint initiative
               was a programme pursued in 2006, this time with support from the AHRC’s own ICT
               Methods Network and the HEFCE-funded Joint Information Systems Committee (JISC); it
               funded just three e-Science <q>demonstrator</q> projects, one of which — described in
               this essay — focused on digitisation and <ref
                  target="http://www.ahessc.ac.uk/ongoing-projects">data grids</ref>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Virtual Vellum: An Online Viewing Environment</head>
            <p>The first objective of this six-month project was to take a prototype manuscript
               viewer originally developed in Flash by digital photography consultant Colin Dunn of
                  <ref target="http://www.scriptura.co.uk/">Scriptura Ltd</ref>, and to convert it
               into a more flexible, open access tool for use by the wider scientific and scholarly
               community. The resulting tool was named <ref
                  target="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/virtualvellum.html">
                  <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title>
               </ref> to reflect our desire to use high-quality digitisation to take people as close
               as possible to the materiality and detail of the medieval artefacts under
               consideration. The project aimed to explore the potential of high-resolution digital
               surrogate <q>manuscripts</q> from the standpoint not so much of the curating partner
               libraries involved (though their active support and involvement were key to success)
               as of the scholar-researcher and his or her particular needs.</p>
            <p>Research questions to be addressed included the critical issue of how best to
               prepare, configure and mount high-resolution image datasets within an electronic
               viewing framework calculated to respond flexibly to the precise requirements of
               medievalists, rather than to those of multi-million pound software houses with
               generic products to sell at high volume. Design options and desiderata were in our
               case to be arrived at via conversations with practising medievalists, editors and art
               historians. Display and processing features would be evolved to respond to scholarly
               need or ambition rather than to the lowest common (or commercial) denominator. Whilst
               recognizing that such first-rate proprietory products as Microsoft’s PowerPoint were
               more than fit for the very broad range of purposes to which they could be put and
               were designed for, the <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> team sought above
               all to concern itself with ways in which a medievalist or art historian might wish to
               access, display, process, manipulate and marshal images on their PC or laptop screen.
               Use of the plural <q>images</q> is in itself significant; art historians delivering
               public or faculty lectures typically use a pair of 35mm slide projectors (with all
               the attendant advantages, risks and drawbacks).</p>
            <p>Medievalists similarly wish to view multiple images, for a whole range of scientific
               reasons. These include the requirement to compare in fine detail two or more sections
               of text, or two or more folios from the same codex or from several related codices,
               the better to establish the objective differences between, say, the realisation of a
               given bookhand by Scribe A, Scribe C and Scribe J. Scholars have always been able to
               do this more or less intuitively by comparing the respective <emph>ductus</emph> of a
               given letter as executed by this or that copyist. The facility to move electronic
                  <q>fragments</q> right up against one another and to zoom in on them independently
               of each other, was a further, entailed desideratum. Other functionalities to be
               incorporated arose from the scholar’s desire to move quickly through a manuscript, to
               locate a particular folio in seconds, to measure the respective sizes of illuminated
               letters across a virtual <q>collection</q> of related digital manuscripts whose
               originals are now scattered across the globe, or (in the case of our art historian
               collaborators from Urbana-Champaign, Illinois) to measure the width of a king’s mouth
               or the dimensions of his crown. More recently, users have asked us to incorporate a
                  <q>last stage reached</q> button, permitting a user to resume work left off at a
               previous session and to set the screen to the precise display parameters last
               used.</p>
            <p>The viewing pane was also to be susceptible of replication: scholars should be able
               to access two, three or even four image panes within the same screen space, each of
               which would have its own autonomous panning and zooming tools. It should be possible
               for users to add still more panes if so desired, and to tile them vertically or
               horizontally on their PC or laptop screen.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Zooming and panning</q> evokes one of the most controversial issues encountered
               during the project. Librarians have to date been notoriously reluctant to allow
               high-resolution images of their manuscripts to feature on web pages, essentially and
               understandably for fear of unauthorised downloads leading in turn to copyright
               violation. They might, on the other hand, be prepared to sanction use of images as
               high as 500dpi on a commercially available DVD. The usual approved maximum, however,
               is 300dpi. From the programmer’s and scholar’s point of view this is a sorry state of
               affairs: high-specification digitising camera scans can capture images at higher
               rates than this, and the results are visually stunning as well as optically more
               faithful to the original. However, a drawback of using higher resolution 500dpi
               images had to do, as we commenced the project, with the potential limitations, this
               time, of users’ PCs and laptops. Not all of our users could be guaranteed to have
               machines with large amounts of RAM, super-performing graphics cards or gargantuan
               hard drives on which to store the rather hefty image files.</p>
            <p>Just one scan of an A3-sized manuscript folio at 500dpi typically results in image
               sizes around 150MB. The raw files are captured as TIFFs and archived as such. To the
               uninitiated the raw TIFFs captured during a scanning operation can appear
               disappointing: dull, lifeless, even dark, they are hardly ever seen in this
               pre-processed state, but have to be catalogued using industry-standard metadata
               descriptors. For this and similar projects, the processed files are saved as JPEGs,
                  <q>tweaked</q> to bring the colours to life once again. Even so, processed JPEGs
               can still be high-volume files. A second, major research question for the team to
               address was therefore how to <q>treat</q> or render the processed JPEGs in such a way
               as to reduce their volume and the time required to download them. In other words, to
               identify steps that would need to be taken to enhance the storage, retrieval, display
               and manipulation in real time of very high-resolution images (typically in excess of
               8k x 6k pixels).</p>
            <p>From Colin Dunn’s original prototype using Flash, the project researcher moved to a
               solution involving what was then the new <ref target="http://www.jpeg.org/jpeg2000"
                  >JPEG2000 standard</ref>. This was in part a response to issues arising from
               potential use of the viewer as an internet tool delivering image files over the web
               or via a Data Grid (a topic addressed in more detail below) and entailing the need
               for the efficient and prompt retrieval over such networks of what were, after all,
               still quite large images. But JPEG2000 also obviated the need for <q>tiling</q> or
                  <q>file smash-ups</q>. Instead, one file generated both a thumbnail and the
               principal image (the former to be displayed at the top of the screen with all the
               others in a kind of strapline format, the latter occupying most of the screen-space
                  <q>theatre</q> immediately below). File compression enabled us to reduce the image
               file size to around 10MB, a very considerable economy.</p>
            <p>A key element in taking the project forward proved to be the cordial relationships we
               were careful to establish with each of our partner libraries. Unlike many other
               institutions they were prepared not only to allow us to use our own photographer
               (which in turn meant that the project could maintain common and consistent standards
               from one institution to the next); they were ready also to let us use and reproduce
               the captured images at 500dpi, and to experiment with modes of delivery both locally
               on a PC or laptop, and over an internet connection. Once again, speed of delivery and
               manipulation were an issue: our potential users might not have access to
               sophisticated home broadband; even if they did, there was a likelihood that the
               images would still take an unconscionably long time to download.</p>
            <p>The requirement somehow to square this circle, allowing us — potentially — to use the
               highest resolution images we possessed without slowing down processing speed to the
               point at which use of <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> (online or offline)
               would become self-defeatingly fastidious, presented us with one of the most
               formidable challenges of the entire project. It was eventually resolved through
               implementation of a series of mathematical algorithms to optimise memory usage and
               processing power, combined with exploitation of <emph>threads</emph>.<note>This
                  allows the software to make use of modern multi-core processors to decode regions
                  of an image simultaneously and thus display it to the user much more
                  rapidly.</note> By the conclusion of the project we had produced an online viewing
               tool specifically designed for day-to-day use by researchers whose projects typically
               involved close scrutiny and manipulation of high-resolution image files: not just
               medievalists but art historians and scholars from other disciplines working with
               large corpora of digital photographs, all of whom might wish to use the tool for
               research purposes, but also for more public deployment, during a lecture or workshop
               perhaps.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> emerged from the processes described
               above as a fully-fledged and versatile viewing tool for the manipulation of
               high-resolution images. The AHRC-JISC-EPSRC e-Science project allowed the team at
               Sheffield to devise a highly flexible viewing environment equipped with a range of
               associated tools, all compatible with Windows, Mac and Linux. <title rend="italic"
                  >Virtual Vellum</title> allows scholars to present research papers with confidence
               whilst manipulating their high-resolution image files at speed, efficiently and
               flexibly. It has the additional benefit of encouraging scholars to use datasets that
               might otherwise remain dormant due to their prohibitively large file-size volume. An
               open access and open source product, it is henceforward available to scholars
               entirely free of charge. Downloadable from the project website complete with user
               manual in plain English; all that it needs to show its paces is a set of
               high-resolution images. From the very outset the tool was designed to appeal to any
               researcher involved in the regular use of such datasets. Fields envisaged included,
               to mention just a few of the more obvious, manuscript studies, art history,
               iconography, theatre and film studies, museum and gallery studies. We were less
               prepared for the interest shown in <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> by
               researchers working in the natural, physical and social sciences, described
               below.</p>
            <p>The core features of <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> are illustrated
               below by a short series of figures using sample images from our datasets. Whilst
               these obviously showcase manuscript material, it is worth mentioning at this juncture
               the interest shown in our viewing tool, used online via a data connection, by
               programmers at the Humboldt University in Berlin busy developing software for
               entomologists working in the field for Germany’s Natural History Museum. A scholar
               coming across a new species of beetle in the Amazonian rain forest might well find it
               useful to be able to take a digital photograph and port it back to Berlin, or compare
               it to all similar genus categories on their own laptop-driven database connected via
               satellite, so we are told.</p>
            <p>Figure 1 below illustrates the quality of the digitised (virtual) manuscripts used on
               the Sheffield project, the image on the left providing a preview of the complete
               image, whilst the image on the right is shown magnified to 100%. Figure 2 illustrates
               how frontispiece pages from four different but cognate manuscripts can be viewed side
               by side; the originals of the four manuscripts are located in three physically
               different locations (eastern France, Lancashire and Brussels); prior to the project
               they had never before been shown <q>together.</q>
            </p>
            <figure xml:id="figure01">
               <head>Illustrates image quality; each image can be viewed at any level of
                  magnification, and in real-time. The left-hand image shows the folio scaled so
                  that it can be viewed in its entirety, while the image on the right is displayed
                  with a 100% magnification ratio. Images are © Bibliothèque Royale Albert 1er,
                  Brussels, and Scriptura Ltd.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of virtual manuscripts including more detailed inset of
                  manuscript illustration.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure02">
               <head>Compares the frontispieces from four different manuscripts located at three
                  different physical locations (magnification is at only 30% of the originals).
                  Images are © Bibliothèque Royale Albert 1er, Brussels (left- and extreme
                  right-hand images), Stonyhurst College, Lancashire (second from left),
                  Bibliothèque d’Etude et de Conservation, Besançon (second from right), and
                  Scriptura Ltd. (digitiser of all the manuscript images shown).</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of four manuscript pages side-by-side.</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>e-Science and Data Grids</head>
            <p>Scholars presenting papers live at conferences or delivering seminars online and
               wishing to feature visual data, typically in the guise of side-by-side comparisons,
               have hitherto (as noted earlier) been dependent on PowerPoint or twin 35mm
               colour-slide projectors. Good as these are, they were never designed by, or for use
               by, scholars working in these various fields, as <title rend="italic">Virtual
                  Vellum</title> was. Envisaged in part for stand-alone or seminar use, for personal
               or for collaborative research, <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> was also
               conceived for deployment over a robust and secure internet connection, or better
               still over a supercomputing grid network. This topic is addressed in the next section
               of this essay.</p>
            <p>An invitation to present <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> at the UK
               e-Science <ref target="http://www.allhands.org.uk">All Hands Meeting</ref> in
               September 2006 brought the project team into direct contact with a fresh wave of
               potential collaborators. These included the team at the University of San
                  Diego<note>A co-member with the University of Sheffield of the Worldwide
                  Universities Network, a key factor in the successful development of our project
                  ambitions.</note> responsible for development of <ref
                  target="http://www.sdsc.edu/srb/index.php/main_page">SRB (Storage Resource Broker)
                  middleware</ref>. Using this file management system over a Data Grid would in
               theory allow us to set up a cluster of grid nodes or networked sites affording shared
               access on the part of researchers separated by oceans or continents but linked via a
               robust Grid, to the whole of our high-resolution image datasets, totalling at that
               point almost a terabyte of data. The straightforward premise behind this conviction
               was and remains that scholars working on international collaborative projects
               involving image collections held on local or distributed databases may wish to
               consult one another, the better to explore (together) questions of mutual interest
               such as aspects of iconography, art history, image content, or comparison of similar
               or related images (or specimens!). The Access and Data Grids afforded the ideal
               framework and necessary computing power for the rapid and efficient deployment of
               securely stored, IP-protected collections of this kind, plus high processing speed
               and efficient file handling.</p>
            <p>Ideally, a viewing environment involving scholars talking live to each other about
               their common <q>quarry</q> would offer scope for real-time, close-up scrutiny of
               single or multiple (juxtaposed) images, with independent zooming controls and other
               functions including hotspotting (zoning and highlighting), a facility for
               collaborative annotation, and a sophisticated blogging tool.</p>

            <p>The <q>testbed</q> dataset for <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> was
               provided by a corpus of six complete (virtual) surrogate manuscripts specially
               photographed thanks to funding provided by Yorkshire Universities Gift Aid, the
               University of Sheffield and the Leverhulme Trust. They were all captured on site by
               Colin Dunn, at each of four partner libraries, over a period of three years: Besançon
               and Toulouse Municipal Libraries, Stonyhurst College Library, and the Bibliothèque
               Royale de Belgique in Brussels. Approximately one terabyte’s worth of raw archive
               image TIFFs were securely archived on a server at the University of Sheffield. The
               processed files, converted to the <title rend="italic">JPEG2000</title> standard
               (each no more than 10MB in volume) are kept on a server at Sheffield’s Humanities
               Research Institute, federated to the White Rose and WUN Data Grids, ready for sharing
               and distribution. SRB is the middleware which does all the gophering, fetching and
               carrying.</p>
            <p>As mentioned above, one of the prime uses envisaged for <title rend="italic">Virtual
                  Vellum</title> involved live online seminars involving scholars logged on from
               several remote but affiliated sites, connected as a Grid and therefore supported by
               networked supercomputers. The idea was that the viewing environment should typically
               allow scholars to <q>bring together</q> and display within a single environment for
               purposes of comparative research, several manuscript witnesses (i.e. successive or
               alternative scribal copies or versions) of the <q>same</q> text, whose originals were
               housed, however, in libraries scattered across the globe. This objective has been
               achieved; scholars using <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> can retrieve the
               data files they wish to look at either from a local hard drive or over the internet,
               or better still via a robust Data Grid (which affords greater security and
               confidentiality).</p>
            <p>Written entirely in Java, <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> can be run
               either as an applet or as a desktop application. Java version 1.2 was chosen because
               most web browsers (minimally) have support for this version of the Java run-time
               environment; people who have not yet got access to the later versions of Java are
               thus not excluded from use of <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title>. The
               software package offered to users includes a <title rend="italic">JPEG2000</title>
               Image Decoder and a <q>multiple-pane</q> user interface designed to work from within
               a memory-limited system (less than 65MB, typically the maximum amount of memory used
               for the deployment of Java applets). It also takes full advantage of modern hardware
               developments such as multiple processor cores. Open source access is provided because
               the product has been designed for total computer platform independence. Support is
               included for single, double or multiple views, for comparison of two, three or more
               different images. <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> has already been used
               successfully during several live AHRC-funded collaborative <ref
                  target="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/accessgrid.html"
                  >Access Grid workshops</ref>, in the context of stand-alone conference
               presentations, and at events such as <ref target="http://www.allhands.org.uk">UK
                  All_Hands</ref> and Digital Resources for the Humanities and Arts. An associated
               tool called <title rend="italic">Collator</title> has since been developed to allow
               rapid and easy conversion of small or large numbers of image files (including TIFFs,
               BMPs and JPEGs) to the <title rend="italic">JPEG2000</title> file standard.</p>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> has been adopted for use by Stonyhurst
               College in the UK and by the Ceccano Library in Avignon. At the time of writing it is
               being evaluated by the Department of Manuscripts at the Bibliothèque nationale de
               France (Paris), who in July 2008 confirmed their invitation to the project PI to
               undertake a sustained programme of digitisation around the BnF’s extensive collection
               of Froissart manuscripts. A collaborative endeavour of this kind, and on such a
               scale, is not possible without a very significant degree of mutual trust, respect and
               recognition of (equally mutual) benefit, involving the scholar, photographer and of
               course the directors and curators of each of the research libraries with whom the
                  <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> team has always sought to nurture good
               working relationships.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> and the <title rend="italic">Online
                  Froissart</title>
            </head>
            <p>Digital surrogates derived from Besançon Public Library mss 864-865 are currently
               seeing service in the context of an <ref
                  target="http://www.ahrb.ac.uk/apply/research/resource_enhancement.asp">AHRC
                  Resource Enhancement award</ref> made to the author in association with Godfried
               Croenen of the University of Liverpool for an online edition of Froissart’s <title
                  rend="italic">Chroniques</title>. The <ref
                  target="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/onlinefroissart/overview.html">
                  <title rend="italic">Online Froissart</title>
               </ref> is scheduled to complete by March 2010. With an interface and search engine
               designed by the University of Sheffield’s Humanities Research Institute, and
               incorporating the <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> viewer, the online
               resource will deliver complete texts for Books I, II and III of Froissart’s
               Chronicles. The base texts will be collated against transcriptions of other witnesses
               prepared by the project team, managed with the aid of Peter Robinson’s <ref
                  target="http://www.itsee.bham.ac.uk/software/collate/">
                  <title rend="italic">Collate</title> software</ref>. Historical, political and
               cultural annotation will be supplied together with new translations into modern
               English. A concordance, glossary and index will also be provided. The <title
                  rend="italic">Online Froissart</title> is part of an international consortium
               which includes the University of Edinburgh’s <title rend="italic">Christine de Pizan
                  Queen’s Manuscript</title> project (Professor James Laidlaw and team) and the
               University of Nancy’s ATILF (<title rend="italic">Dictionnaire du Moyen
                  Français</title>) project; the consortium enjoys joint support from the British
               Academy and Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique. Users of the <title
                  rend="italic">Online Froissart</title> will have access to complete full-colour
               reproductions of the base manuscripts and of several cognate witnesses collated
               against these. Our colleagues on the Edinburgh project have contributed to ongoing
               development of <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> and have adopted it for
               their own purposes.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the most obvious contribution brought to the development of <title
                  rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> by the <title rend="italic">Online
                  Froissart</title> is a feature whereby the lines of each column of text in the
               surrogate’s electronic folios have been associated electronically with their
               equivalent lines in the edited transcription (this is achieved automatically by
               analysing each image for lines of text and matching these with the transcription
               markup files). Panning and resizing of the image entails linked, proportionate
               positioning and resizing of the transcription, and vice-versa, as illustrated below
               in Figure 3.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure03a">
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03a.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>First screenshoot of original and transcribed manuscripts.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure03b">
               <head>Screenshot juxtaposing a page of transcribed text from Besançon Public Library
                  ms 865 and the original folio image, which are synchronised while panning and
                  zooming.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure03b.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Second screenshoot of original and transcribed manuscripts.</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>e-Science, e-Learning</head>
            <p>
               <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> was recently adapted for yet another
               purpose, this time under the name <title rend="italic">Kiosque</title> and for
               service as an exhibition enhancement tool. The aim in this case was to provide
               visitors to an exhibition in Leeds with interactive digitised material accessed
               through touch screens. The manuscript viewer therefore found itself at the core of a
               four-month exhibition mounted at the Royal Armouries Museum between 08 December 2007
               and 06 April 2008, entitled <title rend="italic">The Chronicles of Froissart: from
                  conflict to cooperation</title>. Covering the Hundred Years’ War as recounted in
               the Chronicles, the exhibition focused on the craftsmanship underpinning the source
               manuscripts and the arms and armour featured in the miniatures. On display was the
               (real) Stonyhurst College manuscript, shown alongside five other virtual manuscripts
               represented as interactive surrogates, and against the background of items specially
               selected from the Museum’s internationally celebrated collection of contemporary arms
               and armour. These were displayed against the backdrop of miniatures reproduced from
               all of our digital surrogates showing the same items in use.</p>
            <p>The purpose of the <title rend="italic">Kiosque</title> software, developed jointly
               with e-Learning specialists Tribal (Sheffield) with support from the Department of
               Trade and Industry’s Knowledge Transfer Partnership scheme and incorporating a
               version of <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> adapted for touch screens was
               to provide a fully configurable e-Learning tool that could reach out to wider and
               more variegated audiences than that comprising professional medievalists and art
               historians. Visitors could explore image content at varying levels according to their
               particular interests. In addition to its presence on the touch screens, the
               manuscript viewer was used to support real-time transcription of sections of the
               Stonyhurst manuscript by Sara Mack, an experienced calligrapher. <title rend="italic"
                  >Kiosque</title> is illustrated below in Figure 4. Similar though smaller-scale
               French-language versions of the software were on display throughout the Leeds
               exhibition, at three libraries in the south of France: the Alcazar at Marseilles, the
               Cité du Livre-Méjanes in Aix-en-Provence and Avignon’s Ceccano Library. At time of
               writing there are plans to mount a French version of the exhibition at the Musée de
               l’Armée in Paris (Hôtel des Invalides), with support from the Department of
               Manuscripts at the Bibliothèque nationale de France.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure04">
               <head>
                  <title rend="italic">Kiosque</title> — telling the story of Jean Froissart’s
                  Chronicles using the digitised images as a learning resource.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of digitised image and explanation.</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Pegasus</head>
            <p>In the early months of 2007 the UK’s Engineering and Physical Sciences Research
               Council launched a programme of experimental collaboration with the US National
               Science Foundation under the latter’s <title rend="italic">TeraGrid</title>
               initiative. EPSRC funding was secured by the author to undertake a further
               demonstrator project incorporating <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> and
               baptised <ref
                  target="http://www.sheffield.ac.uk/hri/projects/projectpages/pegasus/overview.html">
                  <title rend="italic">Pegasus</title>
               </ref>. The project takes the manuscript viewing tool deeper into the realm of
               e-Science via a new partnership established with the State University of Illinois at
               Urbana-Champaign, and the National Center for Supercomputing Applications based on
               the campus there. The project aims to establish a grid-supported infrastructure for
               intercontinental research based on high-volume image and text datasets. The <title
                  rend="italic">Online Froissart</title> project once again supplies the initial
               dataset, namely its full-colour, high-resolution digital surrogates of
               closely-related manuscripts of the <title rend="italic">Chroniques</title> housed in
               libraries located in three different countries.</p>
            <p>By July 2008 <title rend="italic">Pegasus</title> was set to take off under the joint
               auspices of the EPSRC, NSF and <title rend="italic">TeraGrid</title> initiatives,
               with the full support of the Universities of Sheffield and Illinois. Additional
               financial and cyber-infrastructural support was provided by a generous grant from the
               Worldwide Universities Network, whose Executive Director Dr David Pilsbury also
               ensured that the Sheffield team were able to obtain digital surrogates from both the
               Bibliothèque Royale Albert 1er and the Bibliothèque nationale de France. The support
               of WUN Grid, involving technical expertise provided by the Universities of Bergen and
               York, is supplemented by equally robust computing support via White Rose Grid,
               underpinned by the Universities of Sheffield, York and Leeds. An early event in the
               joint programme was the attendance of programmer and project research associate
               Michael Meredith at a Supercomputing 08 workshop run at Urbana-Champaign in late July
               2008 by our NCSA partners. This allowed him to present and facilitate a hands-on
               workshop surrounding <title rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title> to a much wider
               audience, including the <title rend="italic">Abraham Lincoln Papers</title> project
               team, and to scope with art historians and programmers at Urbana-Champaign a series
               of initiatives around pattern recognition algorithms.</p>
            <figure xml:id="figure05">
               <head>Using colour channel histograms and their gradient changes to automatically
                  detect manuscript lines, folio characteristics (such as rubrics) and miniature
                  locations.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of manuscript with gradient lines.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="figure06">
               <head>The result of registration of two illustration sub-areas. The result is
                  presented as a sequence of two image overlays with variable transparency (0, 25,
                  50, 75 and 100% transparency of the right image on the left image) as indicated by
                  the slider bar on the bottom of each window (top row and the bottom left and
                  middle figures). The user driven change of transparency parameter allows not only
                  exploring the visual differences in the crown and the colour pattern of the cloth
                  but also quantifying the scaling offset of the mouth by each artist (bottom right
                  figure obtained by subtracting the registered images. Image composed by Professor
                  Peter Bajcsy of the National Center for Supercomputing Applications, University of
                  Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.</head>
               <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
               <figDesc>Screenshot of six test images of the same manuscript illustration with
                  variable transparency.</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Whilst the <title rend="italic">Online Froissart</title> virtual manuscripts serve
               once again as the pilot dataset for <title rend="italic">Pegasus</title>, partners at
               Illinois, Ottawa and at other WUN member institutions have initiated discussions with
               a view to securing the resource needed to make available for research an entirely
               different manuscript, the British Library miscellany (Royal 15 E.VI) more familiarly
               known as the Talbot Shrewsbury Book. This lavishly illuminated compilation volume
               encapsulates the full range of writings then suitable for a warrior prince or
               aristocrat, combining the literature of chivalric romances and <foreign xml:lang="fr">
                  <hi rend="italic">chansons de geste</hi>
               </foreign> with the historical accounts provided by chronicles, and with practical
               treatises and manuals of kingship, warfare and chivalry. The extraordinary range of
               texts and illuminations included in this manuscript means that it can only properly
               be understood by a team of experts, interpreting the artefact from a range of
               different but complementary intellectual and disciplinary perspectives. Under the
               auspices of the Worldwide Universities Network, an international team of scholars
               proposes to use a high-quality digital reproduction of the Shrewsbury Book in order
               to investigate numerous research questions such as how it was read and used, its
               influence in reshaping the cultures of chivalry and warfare in England at the end of
               the Hundred Years’ War (1336-1453), where and by whom the manuscript was created and
               how it compares to other collections. A detailed codicological examination of the
               manuscript via the high-resolution images of the digital reproduction, via <title
                  rend="italic">Virtual Vellum</title>, is expected to shed further light on these
               questions, in particular by extending scholars’ knowledge of the marginalia and other
               forms of notation on the manuscript, but also of its programme of illustration, and
               the different scribal hands and artists who worked on the manuscript. Initial
               scientific work towards achieving this objective was undertaken in Urbana in July
               2008 by Michael Meredith, Peter Bajcsy and Professors Anne D Hedeman and Karen
               Fresco.</p>
            <p>Scholars provided with access to the resource would be able to explore annotations
               and interpretive essays on the model of the Christine de Pizan Queen’s Manuscript,
               British Library MS Harley 4431, <ref target="http://www.pizan.lib.ed.ac.uk/"
                  >http://www.pizan.lib.ed.ac.uk/</ref>. Users would be able to contact team members
               via a blog or wiki and explore the manuscript material at their leisure using the
               e-Science framework and tools that have already been and continue to be developed. In
               sum the project bids fair to be of great interest to all those interested in
               chivalry, ideology of the political classes in France and England, the Hundred Years’
               War, patronage, canon formation, heraldry, and the iconography of the miniature.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>In Conclusion</head>
            <p>Using the combined resources of the Access and Data Grids, and of the <title
                  rend="italic">Online Froissart</title> project dataset, <title rend="italic"
                  >Virtual Vellum</title>, <title rend="italic">Kiosque</title> and <title
                  rend="italic">Pegasus</title> aspire together to establish an exemplar platform
               for collaborative project development based on large-volume, high-resolution image
               datasets, involving curators, photographers, imaging and grid technicians,
               programmers, and, most importantly, specialists in medieval textual, historical and
               art-historical scholarship. The <title rend="italic">Shrewsbury Book</title>
               consortium offers a similar approach. It is through partnerships such as those
               outlined above that genuinely useful collaborative tools will be forged to allow
               scholars in medieval studies and other, cognate areas to benefit from the
               technological advances currently being made in e-Science for the Arts and
               Humanities.</p>
            <p>Whilst there is never an adequate substitute for handling and viewing the real
               artefacts of our material culture, the ability to have at one’s disposal
               high-resolution digital surrogates that one can <q>handle</q> and inspect virtually,
               at greater leisure than is usually possible during necessarily brief visits to
               research libraries, has proven to be a more than satisfactory alternative. The
               advantages already described are further complemented by the ability to bring
               together, for instant comparison and in real time, materials that are geographically
               remote from each other, all the while respecting local IP rights. It may perhaps be
               some time before such technologies are taken up by the mainstream, but it is now that
               they need to be developed and trialled in order to ensure their availability and
               usefulness to scholars when that day eventually arrives, as it surely will.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>We are grateful to Professors Anne D Hedeman and Karen Fresco, College of Liberal
               Arts, State University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Dr Craig Taylor, Senior
               Lecturer in History, Centre for Medieval Studies, University of York, and Dr Andrew
               Taylor of the University of Ottawa, for kind permission to use material reproduced
               here.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ainsworth2010" label="Ainsworth 2010" key="ainsworth2010b">Ainsworth,
               Peter. <title rend="quotes">Editing, E-Science and Exhibitions</title>, in <title
                  rend="italic">Essays in Later Medieval French Literature. The Legacy of Jane H.M.
                  Taylor</title>, ed. Rebecca Dixon, Durham Modern Language Series 1, Manchester
               University Press, forthcoming.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="kiernan1997" label="Kiernan 1997" key="kiernan1997"> Kiernan, K. S. <title
                  rend="italic">Beowulf and the Beowulf Manuscript</title>, Ann Arbor: University of
               Michigan Press, 1997.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lesk2004" label="Lesk 2004">Lesk, M. <title rend="italic">Understanding
                  Digital Libraries</title>, Language, Arts and Disciplines. New York: Peter Lang,
               2004.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="shillingsburg2006" key="shillingsburg2006" label="Shillingsburg 2006"
               >Shillingsburg, Peter L. <title rend="italic">From Gutenberg to Google: electronic
                  Representations of Literary Texts</title>. Language, Arts and Disciplines. New
               York: Peter Lang, 2006.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
