<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Using word vector models to trace conceptual change
               over time and space in historical newspapers, 1840–1914</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jaap <dhq:family>Verheul</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Utrecht University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>j.verheul@uu.nl</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Jaap Verheul is associate professor of Cultural History at Utrecht
                     University and honorary professor of Transatlantic Relations at Radboud
                     University Nijmegen. He teaches transatlantic, transnational, and cultural
                     history. His DH interest is in applying mixed-methods approaches to examine
                     cross-cultural perceptions and influences in digitized historical newspapers
                     and other large serial textual corpora. He coordinated and participated in a
                     number of international DH consortia (e.g. (NOW) Translantis, (HERA-4) AsymEnc,
                     (Marie-Curie ITN) CHEurope, and (Digging into Data) Oceanic Exchanges),
                     co-developed analytical tools based on word vector models and machine learning
                     (e.g. Texcavator, ShiCo, GeoNewsMiner), and currently participates in two
                     consortia funded by the Netherlands National Research Agenda: Constructing the
                     Limes (c-limes.nl) and Re-Presenting Europe.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Hannu <dhq:family>Salmi</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Turku</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>hansalmi@utu.fi</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Hannu Salmi is Professor of Cultural History at the University of Turku in
                     Finland. His research interests include digital history, history of the
                     nineteenth century, and media history.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Martin <dhq:family>Riedl</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Stuttgart</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>riedl.ma@gmail.com</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Martin Riedl is a data scientist at Diamant Software GmbH. At the time he wrote
                     this publication, he was working as a postdoctoral researcher at the Institut
                     für Maschinelle Sprachverarbeitung (IMS) at the Unversität Stuttgart. He did
                     his PhD at the Language Technology group at the Technische Universität
                     Darmstadt in computational linguistics. His research was focused on
                     unsupervised methods for natural language processing. In addition, he worked on
                     lexical semantics as well as various NLP tasks such as Named Entity Recognition
                     or Complex Word Identification. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Asko <dhq:family>Nivala</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Turku</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>aeniva@utu.fi</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr. Asko Nivala is an Adjunct Professor (Docent) of Cultural History at the
                     University of Turku. He is a digital humanist who studies the spatiality of
                     literature, nineteenth-century Romanticism, and the history of AI before
                     computers. In 2022–2025 Nivala is working as a Collegium Fellow at Turku
                     Institute for Advaced Studies (TIAS). He is also the Principal Investigator of
                     "Atlas of Finnish Literature 1870–1940” – a major cultural project funded by
                     the Alfred Kordelin Foundation in 2022–2024.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Lorella <dhq:family>Viola</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Luxembourg</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>lorella.viola@uni.lu</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Dr Lorella Viola is Research Associate at the Centre for Contemporary and
                     Digital History, University of Luxembourg where she is currently co-Principal
                     Investigator in the Luxembourg National Research Fund project DHARPA (Digital
                     History Advanced Research Project Accelerator). She was previously Research
                     Associate at Utrecht University where she was Work Package Leader in the
                     Transatlantic research project <title rend="italic">Oceanic Exchanges</title>.
                     Her research focusses on how power, latent assumptions and implicit ideologies
                     are manifested through language and circulated in media and society. She also
                     researches the impact of the digital transformation on knowledge creation
                     theory and practice and develops critical, data-driven methodologies for
                     humanities and heritage research.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Jana <dhq:family>Keck</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>German Historical Institute Washington</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>keck@ghi-dc.org</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jana Keck is research fellow in Digital History at the German Historical
                     Institute Washington. She studied English and American studies and linguistics
                     at the University of Stuttgart. Before joining the GHI in 2020, she was working
                     in <title rend="quotes">Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks
                        in Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840-1914</title> (DFG), a research
                     project that boasted a team of scholars from seven countries in Europe and the
                     Americas to study transnational news circulation in C19 newspapers. She
                     coordinates the GHI’s research area Digital History and the institute’s project
                        <title rend="quotes">Migrant Connections,</title> a digital research
                     infrastructure for German-American History.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Emily <dhq:family>Bell</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>University of Leeds</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>E.J.L.Bell@leeds.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Emily Bell is a Lecturer in Digital Humanities in the School of English at the
                     University of Leeds, UK. She is Editor of <title rend="italic">The
                        Dickensian</title>, Co-Editor of the <title rend="italic">Curran Index to
                        Nineteenth-Century Periodicals</title>, and Co-Editor of <title
                        rend="italic">Dickens Search</title>. She is also a Fellow of the Software
                     Sustainability Institute.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000550</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
            <date when="2022-05-18">5/18/2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref
               target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000550/000550.xml"
               >GitHub </ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>Linking large digitized newspaper corpora in different languages that have become
               available in national and state libraries opens up new possibilities for the
               computational analysis of patterns of information flow across national and linguistic
               boundaries. The significant contribution this article presents is to demonstrate how
               word vector models can be used to explore the way concepts have shifted in meaning
               over time, as they migrated across space, by comparing newspapers from different
               countries published between 1840 and 1914. We define a concept, rather pragmatically,
               as a key term or core idea that has been used in historical discourse: an abstraction
               or mental representation that has served as a building block for thoughts and
               beliefs. We use historical newspapers in English, Finnish, German and Swedish from
               collections in the UK, US, Germany, and Finland, as well as the Europeana collection.
               As use cases, we analyze how the different conceptual constructs of “nation” and
               “illness” emerged and changed between 1840 and 1920. Conceptual change over time is
               simulated by creating a series of overlapping word vector models, each spanning ten
               years. Historical vocabularies are retrieved on the basis of vector space proximity.
               Conceptual change across space is simulated by comparing the historical change of
               vocabularies in newspaper collections from different nations in several languages.
               This computational approach to conceptual history opens up new ways to identify
               patterns in public discourse over longer periods of time and across borders.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>this article demonstrates how word vector models can be used to explore the way
               concepts have shifted in meaning over time, as they migrated across space, by
               comparing newspapers from different countries published between 1840 and 1914.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>1. Introduction</head>
            <p>Big data opens a window onto the global dimensions of our cultural heritage and
               history <ptr target="#eijnatten2014"/>. The availability of large datasets of
               digitized newspapers offers unprecedented opportunities to explore the transnational
               and intercultural connections of the western world. This article explores the ways in
               which word vector models can be used to analyse how the exchange of knowledge, ideas,
               and concepts across borders and languages is reflected in newspapers. It focuses on
               the period of globalization between the middle of the nineteenth century and the
               return to isolationism and nationalism in the wake of the First World War. </p>
            <p>This publication is based on a strand of the international research project <title
                  rend="quotes">Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global Information Networks in Historical
                  Newspaper Repositories, 1840–1914</title> (OcEx). OcEx has brought together an
               international and interdisciplinary research consortium to examine patterns of
               information flow across national and linguistic boundaries in nineteenth-century
               newspapers by linking digitized newspaper corpora currently siloed in national
               collections. Funded by the Trans-Atlantic Platform for the Social Science and
               Humanities’ <title rend="quotes">Digging Into Data Challenge,</title> this effort
               builds on the recent rediscovery of global and world history to overcome the national
               perspectives of the past.<note><title rend="quotes">Oceanic Exchanges: Tracing Global
                     Information Networks In Historical Newspaper Repositories, 1840–1914.</title>
                  DOI 10.17605/OSF.IO/WA94S. Available at: <ref target="https://osf.io/wa94s"
                     >osf.io/wa94s</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The larger academic research question this article addresses is how we can trace the
               migration of concepts over time and across space. Specifically, this article
               discusses two sets of very different concepts which changed during the second half of
               the nineteenth century and the early twentieth century. The first is the set of
               concepts that denotes the most public aspects of human existence: the collective
               identity that is framed in terms of <q>nation,</q>
               <q>state,</q>
               <q>people,</q> and <q>national identity.</q> The analysis of this category of
               concepts also allows comparison with traditional approaches to conceptual history, as
               discussed below. The second, in contrast, deals with the ultimate personal experience
               reflected in discourses about <q>illness</q> and <q>health.</q> Although belonging to
               a different domain than national identity, illness and health likewise reflect
               fundamental experiences in human life which can reach collective dimensions, as in
               the case of epidemics and pandemics. More importantly, the concepts that people in
               different nations and cultures have employed to understand and respond to these
               circumstances of well-being or illness are conditioned, or mediated, by shared ideas
               about the human condition which have changed over time. Both national identity and
               health, then, are cultural constructions which should be understood in their
               historical and geographical context. These conceptual sets are interesting use cases
               because there is already a rich body of academic literature that suggests important
               changes in the understanding of both <q>nation</q> and <q>illness</q> as labels for
               abstract ideas and knowledge domains took place during this period <ptr
                  target="#hobsbawm2012"/>
               <ptr target="#gellner2007"/>
               <ptr target="#anderson2006"/>. </p>
            <p>How can we use computational word vector models to identify the changing vocabulary
               in which concepts are expressed? While many definitions of concepts circulate in
               various academic disciplines such as linguistics, philosophy, and psychology, no
               consensus has emerged <ptr target="#margolis2005"/>
               <ptr target="#margolis1999"/>. Within this article, we define a concept rather
               pragmatically as a key term or core idea that has been used in historical discourse,
               and as an abstraction or mental representation that has served as a building block
               for thoughts and beliefs. We approach historical concepts not as analytical research
               tools constructed by historians to understand the past, but rather as the mental
               constructions of actual historical actors as they are expressed in formal and
               informal public discourse, political tracts, fiction, or life writing. We focus on
               historical newspapers as a serial and coherently structured source to demonstrate how
               such concepts are articulated <ptr target="#broersma2018"/>
               <ptr target="#douglas1999"/>
               <ptr target="#ginneken1998"/>
               <ptr target="#kunczik1997"/>
               <ptr target="#moran1978"/>. </p>
            <p>The significant contribution this article presents is to demonstrate how word vector
               models can be used on different newspaper collections in different languages to
               explore the way concepts have shifted in meaning, as they migrated, between 1840 and
               1914. Rather than attempting a comprehensive overview of conceptual history in this
               period, the aim of this article is to demonstrate the viability of this methodology
               and the significance of newspapers as representatives of the public sphere <ptr
                  target="#habermas1991" loc="181–95"/>. This computational approach to conceptual
               history opens up new ways to identify patterns in public discourse over longer
               periods of time and across borders. We also contribute to the discussion about the
               relationship between concepts and natural language in the larger process of knowledge
               discovery <ptr target="#jackson2007"/>
               <ptr target="#harras2000"/>
               <ptr target="#weitz1988"/>. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>2. Conceptual change and word vector models</head>
            <p>Historical concepts are essential to our understanding of the past <ptr
                  target="#weitz1988"/>. Concepts such as citizenship, democracy, migration,
               liberty, security, trust, and health constitute the continuous foundation of changing
               historical debates and have been compared to the <quote rend="inline"
                  >unit-ideas</quote> that form the building blocks of human discourse, similar to
               the elements that form chemical compounds <ptr target="#lovejoy1933" loc="4"/>.
               Tracing the change, continuity, and replacement of these concepts is vital for
               historians and other humanities scholars, since concepts are the lenses through which
               people in the past understood the world. </p>
            <p>Our approach builds on the tradition of conceptual history (<term xml:lang="de"
                  >Begriffsgeschichte</term>), as established by the Bielefeld school of Reinhart
               Koselleck and the Cambridge School associated with J. G. A. Pocock and Quentin
               Skinner. Koselleck argues key terms such as nation, citizenship, and family reflected
               fundamental changes in the social and political structures of European societies
               which took place from the mid-eighteenth century onwards. The magnum opus of eight
               volumes, which he edited together with Otto Brunner and Werner Conze, traces the
               shifting meaning of one hundred and thirty of these leading concepts (<term
                  xml:lang="de">Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe</term>). These concepts reflect
               modernity, and social and political change <ptr target="#brunner1972"/>. The
               methodological question this article addresses is whether computational methods can
               identify the fundamental changes in vocabulary that demonstrate the kind of
               conceptual change Koselleck’s group describes <ptr target="#koselleck2002"/>
               <ptr target="#koselleck2004"/>. </p>
            <p>The Bielefeld group is often contrasted with the conceptual history tradition
               established in the United Kingdom. The Cambridge School of Intellectual History
               established by Pocock and Skinner is interested in the inherent historical
               contextuality of conceptual change. Their work contributed to a shift from a history
               of ideas to a history of concepts, and pushes against any sense of keyword
                  <q>definitions</q>
               <ptr target="#skinner1969"/>. Skinner’s work on concepts such as the <q>state</q> and
                  <q>liberty</q> has been key to the development of conceptual history as a field.
               Pocock’s study of the key ideas of <quote rend="inline">Machiavellian
                  thought,</quote> which moved from Renaissance Italy to Civil War Britain and then
               crossed the Atlantic to inform the American Revolution, suggests an
               interconnectedness of concepts across linguistic and geographical boundaries <ptr
                  target="#pocock2016"/>
               <ptr target="#skinner2012"/>
               <ptr target="#skinner1978"/>.</p>
            <p>Building on these German and British research initiatives, and related projects in
               Scandinavia, the Netherlands and elsewhere, conceptual history became an established
               – if undertheorized – field in the 1970s, producing a number of monumental studies
               that have been described as a true <quote rend="inline">pyramid of the mind</quote>
               <ptr target="#steinmetz2016"/>
               <ptr target="#muller2016"/>. Conceptual drift – the historical shift in the meaning
               of concepts and the words that articulate them – has mainly been analyzed
               chronologically in the context of a single language <ptr target="#betti2014"/>
               <ptr target="#kuukkanen2008"/>. De Bolla demonstrates how keyword search methods can
               be used to trace how the concept of human rights developed during the era of the
               American Revolution <ptr target="#gavin2015"/>
               <ptr target="#debolla2013"/>. </p>
            <p>Little has been done to study the way in which concepts change if they are translated
               into different languages and cultural contexts. Studying <quote rend="inline">what
                  happens when concepts move between different kinds of modernities and their
                  associated temporalities</quote>
               <ptr target="#muller2014" loc="88"/> remains one of the unsolved challenges in the
               history of concepts, and is thus key to the methodology of this article. A better
               understanding of conceptual migration is essential if we want to know how news,
               knowledge, ideas and ideologies circulated in the globalizing world that emerged at
               the end of the nineteenth century, how nations emerged as imagined communities around
               common newspaper readership, or how people in various parts of the world learned
               about and gave meaning to pandemics diseases and disasters. </p>
            <p>In recent years, word vector models have been used to represent concepts in text
               corpora. Rather than relating words to objects or events in the real world, word
               vectors represent a multidimensional network of relations between words in a large
               textual corpus. Word vectors are representations based on the distributional
               hypothesis, which assumes that words tend to be similar if they occur in a similar
               context. The meaning of words is represented by the relative positions of their
               vectors in that semantic space. The effectiveness of this associative approach to
               identifying concepts has been demonstrated <ptr target="#landauer1997"/>
               <ptr target="#lund1996"/> and applied to the scientific discourse of the seventeenth
               century; <ref target="#pumfrey2012">Pumfrey, Rayson and Mariani (2012)</ref> have
               conducted significant work that compares a manual approach to a digital humanities
               methodology using corpus linguistics tools. </p>
            <p>Related approaches have also been proposed in the computational linguistic community.
               However, most approaches target a change of word senses, i.e. the different meanings
               a word can have, rather than concepts. In distributional semantic models (based on
               the distributional hypothesis by Harris) a word is defined by the context in which it
               appears <ptr target="#harris1954"/>. This notion became popularized as the idea that
                  <quote rend="inline">You shall know a word by the company it keeps!</quote>
               <ptr target="#firth1957" loc="11"/>. Such representations are used to show that word
               senses change over time. Distributional thesauri have been used, for instance, to
               compute word similarities for different time points in Google Books data <ptr
                  target="#mitra2015"/>. Computing different embedding representations for several
               time spans can show how word sense changes over time <ptr target="#hamilton2016"/>.
               This unsupervised computational methodology demonstrates how new senses are born,
               disappear, or remain consistent. By aligning the embeddings of different time spans
               in the same vector space, it has been possible to demonstrate how terms change
               position over time in the vector space. </p>
            <p>The use of word vectors models received a boost by the word2vec algorithm developed
               by Google. Using a large corpus of text as input, this algorithm offers an efficient
               and reliable method to produce a multi-dimensional vector space, in which words that
               share common contexts in the corpus are located close to each other <ptr
                  target="#mikolov2013a"/>
               <ptr target="#mikolov2013b"/>. As Word2vec can place words from a large text corpus
               such as books, web pages or newspaper articles in a vector space that represents
               semantic similarity it can indicate, or <quote rend="inline">predict,</quote>
               semantic relations between words <ptr target="#baroni2014"/>. Yet most corpus-based
               distributional semantic methods use a bag-of-words approach that lumps words together
               without taking their temporal order or historical origin into account, assuming that
               the meaning of words remains stable over time. As such, the challenge remains finding
               a computational approach that accounts for both the historicity of changing word
               meanings and also conceptual change. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>3. Computational methodology </head>
            <p>In this article, concepts are hypothesized as semantic spaces within a vector space
               in which vocabularies can be identified that express core ideas, abstractions or
               mental representations. We operationalize this by following conceptual change in
               different regions of the western world, tested computationally by comparing the
               changing vocabularies in word vector spaces of a number of concepts with a global
               presence, and then interpreting them with specific domain knowledge. </p>
            <p>A methodology has recently been developed to use word vector models, created with the
               word2vec algorithm, to interrogate historical changes in vocabularies linked to
               concepts. The digital history team at Utrecht University, in collaboration with the
               Netherlands eScience Center, has developed the tool ShiCo (Mining Shifting Concepts
               through Time) which enables researchers to test this methodology on collections of
               digitized newspapers <ptr target="#martinez-ortiz2016"/>
               <ptr target="#kenter2015"/>
               <ptr target="#kenter2013"/>. This tool creates word vector models of ten years each,
               with an overlap of two years, e.g. 1840–49, 1842–51, 1844–53. When users enter one or
               more search terms (or <q>seed words</q>), the algorithm will return the vocabularies
               found in the surrounding vector space for each model. This offers an overview of
               gradual changes over time in vocabularies associated with the concepts <ptr
                  target="#wevers2020"/>
               <ptr target="#viola2020"/>. </p>
            <p>We use ShiCo as a backend to access the embeddings of all corpora used in this study.
                  <note>For querying similar terms, we use the following ShiCo parameters:
                  non-adaptive search, maximal terms: 15, related terms: 20 and minimum similarity:
                  0.1. The other parameters were left on their default settings: word boost = 1,
                  boost method = sum similarity, words per year = 5, weighing function = gaussian,
                  etc. Documentation of these parameters and the ShiCo software is available at <ref
                     target="https://github.com/NLeSC/ShiCo"
                  >https://github.com/NLeSC/ShiCo</ref>.</note> In <q>adaptive mode</q> ShiCo is
               able to use the vocabularies that are found in a vector model as seed words for the
               next model, as a way to trace gradual concept shift. We used the <q>non-adaptive</q>
               mode to trace the changing vocabularies associated with the same seed words over
               time, in order to create a more stable baseline from which to compare vocabularies
               from different language corpora in the same time period. For the generation of the
               word embeddings, we deploy gensim and compute CBOW models, with 100 dimensions, a
               window size of five, a minimum word count of five, and with five negative samples.
                  <note> Software and scripts developed for this project are available on <ref
                     target="https://github.com/OceanicExchanges/wp5"
                     >https://github.com/OceanicExchanges/wp5</ref>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In our study, we compute similarities for a term for each window of time as set in
               the interface, using the same seed words. Since the windows of time overlap, most of
               the semantic relations between words remain stable, resulting in gradual changes over
               the years. We argue that this method offers a way to understand gradually-changing
               words that are used to articulate the same topic, concept, or idea. One can debate to
               what extent these semantic spaces in a word vector model represent historical
               concepts <ptr target="#recchia2017"/>. This article tests this hypothesis by
               employing ShiCo on several different digitized newspaper collections. </p>
            <p>Due to OCR issues with historical newspapers, particularly issues arising from the
               similarity of some characters, our corpora have large amounts of words with erroneous
               variations. Furthermore, the fraktur font is used in historical German-language
               newspapers, and the OCR models deployed to convert German-language newspapers are not
               trained on such a font. For example, the term <term xml:lang="de">Krankheit</term>
               (illness) is also similar to the writing variations <term xml:lang="de"
                  >Krankbeit</term>, <term xml:lang="de">Krankhcit</term>, <term xml:lang="de"
                  >Kraiikheit</term>, <term xml:lang="de">Kraukheit.</term> To solve this issue, we
               merge variations with manual correction lists (e.g. <term xml:lang="de"
                  >Krankheit</term>: <term xml:lang="de">Krankbeit</term>, <term xml:lang="de"
                  >Krankhcit</term>, <term xml:lang="de">Kaiikheit</term>, <term xml:lang="de"
                  >Kaukheit</term>) and use the mean of all similarity scores as the similarity
               score.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>4. A multilingual dataset of digital newspaper corpora</head>
            <p>We deploy parallel instances of the ShiCo software to create word vector models for
               the newspaper corpora we use as datasets (<ref
                  target="https://oceanicexchanges.org/news/"
                  >https://oceanicexchanges.org/news/</ref>). We use eight different corpora
               including four different languages, namely English, German, Finnish and Swedish
               (Table 1). These corpora were selected because they represent large national
               newspapers collections which can be compared to gain an understanding of the
               transnational and cross-cultural circulation of knowledge and ideas, as was the
               starting point of the <title rend="quotes">Oceanic Exchanges</title> project, and on
               the basis of their availability in digitized form with sufficient OCR reliability
                  <ptr target="#beals2020"/>. The date range 1840–1914 was selected to capture a the
               period of rapidly expanding cross-Atlantic trade, traffic, migration, and cultural
               exchange which can be understood as the first wave of globalization. This period was
               also the heyday of newspapers as the first big data for a mass audience <ptr
                  target="#orourke1999"/>
               <ptr target="#osterhammel2014"/>
               <ptr target="#nolan2012"/>. </p>
            <p><title rend="italic">The Times Digital Archive</title> (TDA) was the first online
               digitized newspaper collection of British newspapers. Currently, it contains material
               up to 2010 comprising over 1.6 million pages from 70,000 issues of <title
                  rend="italic">The Times of London</title>, sub-divided or zoned into 11.8 million
               articles, catalogued by category, including advertising, editorial and commentary,
               news, business, news, people and photojournalism. The data for the digitized
               newspapers comes in two forms: a scanned image of each newspaper page at 300 DPI,
               zoned and sub-divided at article level, and an XML file containing the text (OCR) and
               metadata for each article. The machine-readable text appears within the XML file,
               surrounded by metadata that describes various features about the article, including
               the title, issue, date, section, and page number. The collection is available in many
               state and institutional libraries throughout the world through a commercial licencing
               arrangement with Gale. The underlying text and metadata can be accessed by request,
               with a cost recovery fee. <note>For the TDA corpus models were created for the period
                  1840–1920 for reasons of repurposability</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Finnish newspaper corpus has been provided by the National Library of Finland and
               is downloadable as a data dump via the Language Bank of Finland. The collection
               includes all published issues from the birth of newspaper publishing in the country
               in 1771 up to 1920. Since the Finnish press has mainly been published in two
               languages, Swedish (SE-NLF) and Finnish (FI-NLF), we compute two models on newspapers
               from 1840 to 1914. Within this timeframe 369 different titles were published,
               totalling 3.6 million pages: 26% in Swedish, 74% in Finnish. In the corpus, the
               amount of data in Finnish is especially thin in the 1840s and 1850s as the
               Finnish-language press only expanded towards the end of the century. By 1890, 47% of
               all published newspaper pages were still in Swedish. The Finnish-language press was
               furthermore printed mostly with Gothic typeset, which results in a substantial amount
               of OCR noise. </p>
            <p>To investigate the shift of concepts in German-language newspapers, we compute
               embeddings for three different corpora: the German parts of the <title rend="italic"
                  >Europeana</title> (DE-EU) corpus, the German-language newspapers from <title
                  rend="italic">Chronicling America </title>(DE-CA) and the <title rend="italic"
                  >Berlin State Library</title> (DE-SBB) corpus.</p>
            <p>The <title rend="italic">Europeana</title> corpus<note><ref
                     target="https://www.europeana.eu/portal/en"
                     >https://www.europeana.eu/portal/en</ref></note> is a collection of 50 million
               digitized items such as books, newspapers, music and artworks that have been
               published in Europe. From these items, there are 876,724 newspapers available which
               have been digitized and OCRed. The majority of pages written in German are from
               Austria (1,184,091), followed by Germany (822,085), Italy (683,062), Estonia (39,540)
               and Lithuania (27,030). This corpus comprises 129 different newspapers from 1840 to
               1913, 6,272.3 million tokens, and around 494.8 million words. The number of tokens
               indicates the words in a corpus regardless of how often they are repeated, while the
               word count reflects the number of distinct word types. </p>
            <p><title rend="italic">Chronicling America</title> is a web-based platform that gives
               access to newspapers published in the United States from 1789 to 1963, with
               descriptive information about the newspapers and digitization of historic
                     pages.<note><ref target="https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/"
                     >https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/</ref></note> The majority of newspapers
               fall within the range 1850–1922. In addition to American titles published in English,
               it also includes newspapers of twenty ethnicities such as, for instance, Native
               American, Czech, Swedish, Icelandic, Danish, Finnish, French, German, or Italian. We
               use newspapers that were published in German (DE-CA) between 1840 and 1913. This
               collection consists of 57 newspaper magazines, resulting in a corpus of 929.8 million
               tokens and 49.5 million words.</p>
            <p>The newspaper corpus from the Berlin State Library (DE-SBB) is a collection of
               historical newspapers published in the German states. We selected newspapers from
               1872 to 1913, which is a corpus of 3,111.6 million tokens and 119.8 million words.
               Compared to the previous two corpora, this corpus is very specific according to its
               locations, as it contains only articles from three newspaper publishing houses in
               Berlin. </p>
            <table>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>Name</cell>
                  <cell>Repository</cell>
                  <cell>Language</cell>
                  <cell>Origin</cell>
                  <cell>Timespan</cell>
                  <cell>No. of words (million)</cell>
                  <cell>No. of tokens<lb/>(million)</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>TDA</cell>
                  <cell>Times Digital Archive (Gale Cengage)</cell>
                  <cell>English</cell>
                  <cell>UK</cell>
                  <cell>1840-1920</cell>
                  <cell> 221.5</cell>
                  <cell>3,544.5</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>FI-NLF</cell>
                  <cell>National Library of Finland</cell>
                  <cell>Finnish</cell>
                  <cell>Finland</cell>
                  <cell>1840-1914</cell>
                  <cell>225.8</cell>
                  <cell>2,966.4</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>DE-CA</cell>
                  <cell>Chronicling America</cell>
                  <cell>German</cell>
                  <cell>USA</cell>
                  <cell>1840-1910</cell>
                  <cell>49.5</cell>
                  <cell>929.8</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>DE-EU</cell>
                  <cell>Europeana</cell>
                  <cell>German</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <p>Austria, Germany, Estonia,</p>
                     <p>Lithuania</p>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1840-1912</cell>
                  <cell>494.8</cell>
                  <cell>6,272.3</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>DE-SBB</cell>
                  <cell>Berlin State Library </cell>
                  <cell>German</cell>
                  <cell>Germany</cell>
                  <cell>1872-1912</cell>
                  <cell>119.8</cell>
                  <cell>3,111.6</cell>
               </row>
               <row role="data">
                  <cell>SE-NLF</cell>
                  <cell>National Library of Finland</cell>
                  <cell>Swedish</cell>
                  <cell>Finland</cell>
                  <cell>1840-1914</cell>
                  <cell>80.9</cell>
                  <cell>2,321.0</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Table 1: Newspaper datasets</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>5. Case study I: Nations and national identity</head>
            <p>The nineteenth century was, in many respects, the age of nationalism and national
               identity. Although new nation states produced long genealogies of invented history
               that suggested perennial antecedents in tradition, common language, and ethnic
               affiliation, those were relatively new constructs cobbled together out of the
               regional and tribal identities of the <foreign xml:lang="fr">ancien régime</foreign>.
               Modern nation states were very much the product of modernization and
               industrialization, processes which required unification of time, language, education,
               and collective behaviour, political emancipation and mobilization of the middle
               classes, and the integration of the new urban masses. Rather than emerging from
               natural, perennial, or <quote rend="inline">primordial</quote> identities, nations
               were deliberately based on <quote rend="inline">constructed</quote> ideas of national
               identity <ptr target="#gellner1997"/>
               <ptr target="#gellner2007"/>
               <ptr target="#hobsbawm2010"/>
               <ptr target="#hobsbawm2012"/>.</p>
            <p>Several authors have indicated the importance of newspapers and other mass media in
               the formation of these new national identities <ptr target="#andrews2014"/>
               <ptr target="#rosie2004"/>
               <ptr target="#billig1995"/>. If the nineteenth century was the age of national
               identity, it was also the age of newspapers, magazines, journals, and the book
               industry. As the many local newspapers fostered urban and regional identities, the
               new national newspapers connected and informed the rapidly emerging readership of
               wealthy middle-class citizens. Anderson demonstrates that modern mass media played a
               vital role in the formation of these <quote rend="inline">imagined
                  communities,</quote> as they created collective illusions of shared experience,
               group solidarity, and common fate <ptr target="#anderson2006"/>. National identity
               and the emergence of capitalist media appear, therefore, to be interconnected. At the
               same time, the growing global information networks of the nineteenth century
               increasingly allowed national newspapers to inform their readers about developments
               in the world. These newspapers not only provided factual news about government
               decisions, political upheavals, military expeditions, trade opportunities, or new
               inventions, but also constructed political ideologies and movements. </p>
            <p>Conceptual history has produced impressive studies to trace the emergence of the new
               concepts of nation, nationalism, and the people. A large section of <title
                  rend="italic">Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe</title> (<title rend="italic"
                  >GGB</title>, 1972–97) is dedicated to the emergence of the related concepts
                  <quote rend="inline">Volk, Nation, Nationalismus, Masse</quote> in German
               discourse <ptr target="#brunner1972"/>. Although this <title rend="italic"
                  >GGB</title> chapter traces the concept from antiquity to the end of the Cold War,
               the main conceptual turning point can be traced to the period from the second half of
               the nineteenth century to the early twentieth century, when the nation became the
               focus of political mobilization. Conservative, liberal, Catholic, and socialist
               movements developed their own political and social lexicons to express their ideas
               about national identity. The concept of ”nation” thus became a synonym for social
               integration. As Koselleck hypothesizes, the German word <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Volk</foreign> (people) remained a concept (<term xml:lang="de">Begriff</term>)
               with a mainly state-centred and political meaning, whereas the loanword <foreign
                  xml:lang="de">Nation</foreign> (nation) was largely apolitical. With the rise of
               the working-class movement during the second half of the century, the concept of the
               nation became gradually connected with the democratic participation of the masses
               reflected in references to terms such as proletariat, masses, and mob (<foreign
                  xml:lang="fr">Proletariat</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fr">Masse</foreign>, and
                  <foreign xml:lang="fr">Menge</foreign>) <ptr target="#koselleck1992a"/>
               <ptr target="#koselleck1992b"/>.</p>
            <p>This case study aims to trace such conceptual changes in large datasets of digitized
               newspapers repositories, to explore how the development of national discourse
               unfolded in different European countries and across the Atlantic. The objective is to
               address the question of whether the emergence of national discourse can be seen as a
               universal and uniform phenomenon in the western world, or rather whether national
               traditions can be discerned as they are reflected in the vocabulary used to express
               the concept of the nation. In other words, by using word vector models, the analysis
               will shed light on the way in which newspapers <q>invented</q> national communities
               and created shared national experiences. What conceptual changes emerge in the public
               debates in the different countries around this discursive topic? </p>
            <p>In this experiment, we compare the changing vocabulary around the concept of nation
               by implementing word vector modelling on national newspaper corpora in different
               languages in the period 1840–1914. Word vector models were used for newspapers
               published in English, Swedish, Finnish, and German, as published in the UK, Finland,
               Germany, and the US. </p>
            <p>As entry points into the semantic vector space (seed words), we use different
               synonyms for the term <q>nation</q> derived from the <title rend="italic">GGB</title>
               and the secondary literature, to which we add the terms that resulted from the word
               vector modelling.<note>The search terms were: citizenship, civilisation,
                  civilization, country, democracy, destiny, empire (realm), fatherland, masses,
                  mob, nation, nationalism, nationality, people(s), rabble, spirit of nation,
                  state.</note> To compare the changing vocabulary and improve readability, we use
               the (modern) English translations of these terms as anchor points. </p>
            <div>
               <head>A. The transnational migration of national identity </head>
               <p>The term <q>nation</q> derives from the Latin word <foreign xml:lang="la"
                     >nationem</foreign> for birth, origin, or tribe. The geographical concept of
                  the nation is thus firmly established, and is still evident in the 1840–1914.
                  Ironically, the conceptual stability of nation in public discourse seems more
                  stable than the geopolitical realities of the time. Within the word vector space
                  of TDA, the search term <q>England,</q> for example, produced a stable set of
                  names of other nations; <q>England</q> shares a semantic space with
                     <q>Scotland,</q>
                  <q>Ireland,</q>
                  <q>France,</q> and <q>Belgium,</q> and also with <q>America.</q> Perhaps more
                  remarkably, the term <q>Europe</q> is also part of that stable presence.
                     <q>Germany</q> and <q>Spain</q> are mentioned in 1848, as the political
                  revolutions in both countries inject them into public discourse, and ensure they
                  persist after (see Table 2 below).</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in TDA related to
                        <q>England,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>france</cell>
                     <cell>ireland</cell>
                     <cell>scotland</cell>
                     <cell>america</cell>
                     <cell>germany</cell>
                     <cell>europe</cell>
                     <cell>england</cell>
                     <cell>principality</cell>
                     <cell>spain</cell>
                     <cell>italy</cell>
                     <cell>belgium</cell>
                     <cell>wales</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>0.25</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                     <cell>0.4</cell>
                     <cell>0.26</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.13</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.38</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.53</cell>
                     <cell>0.27</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.13</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.63</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.26</cell>
                     <cell>0.36</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.63</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.35</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.23</cell>
                     <cell>0.11</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.12</cell>
                     <cell>0.11</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1910s</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.56</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.56</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>In the German newspaper corpus (DE-SBB), the conceptual neighbours of
                     <q>Deutschland</q> are also its geographical neighbours France,
                  Austria-Hungary, England, Russia, Belgium and Italy, more or less in that order,
                  along with Europe. </p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-SBB related to
                        <q>Deutschland,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>deutschland</cell>
                     <cell>frankreich</cell>
                     <cell>england</cell>
                     <cell>europa</cell>
                     <cell>rußland</cell>
                     <cell>oesterreich-ungarn</cell>
                     <cell>oesterreich</cell>
                     <cell>belgien</cell>
                     <cell>spanien</cell>
                     <cell>italien</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The Finnish dataset FI-NLF shows a sense of Nordic insularity, as all the proper
                  names of nation states are from Nordic countries: Finland, Sweden, Norway, Denmark
                     (<foreign xml:lang="fi">Suomi</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >Ruotsi</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fi">Norja</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="fi">Tanska</foreign>). In Finnish there is a distinction between
                     <foreign xml:lang="fi">Suomi</foreign> (Finland) and <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >suomi</foreign> (Finnish language), but it is lost here because the word
                  embeddings are not case sensitive. Therefore, many word vectors are also related
                  to the Finnish language (like <foreign xml:lang="fi">suomenkieli</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="fi">opetuskielenä</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >kieli</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="fi">suomenkielinen</foreign>). <foreign
                     xml:lang="fi">Historia</foreign> (history) and <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >Pohjanmaa</foreign> (Ostrobothnia, a region in Finland) are also included, but
                  references to other European nations or to the concept of Europe are remarkably
                  absent in the Finnish word vector space of Nordic countries.</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in FI FNL related to
                        <q>suomi,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>suomi</cell>
                     <cell>ruotsi</cell>
                     <cell>suomenmaa</cell>
                     <cell>norja</cell>
                     <cell>suomenkieli</cell>
                     <cell>opetuskielenä</cell>
                     <cell>kieli</cell>
                     <cell>historia</cell>
                     <cell>tanska</cell>
                     <cell>pohjanmaa</cell>
                     <cell>finlands</cell>
                     <cell>suomenkielinen</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.28</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.0</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.06</cell>
                     <cell>0.35</cell>
                     <cell>0.19</cell>
                     <cell>0.06</cell>
                     <cell>0.21</cell>
                     <cell>0.25</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.07</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.05</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.05</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                     <cell>0.11</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.24</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>This semantic stability may be seen as an illustration of the fact that the nation
                  states are defined in relation to each other, as Koselleck observes <ptr
                     target="#koselleck1992a" loc="145–6"/>. The relative stability in the word
                  vector models stands in sharp contrast to the geopolitical upheavals of this
                  period. The First World War, for instance, is virtually invisible in the long-term
                  representation of the word vector models. </p>
               <p>The shifting vocabularies in which the concept of the nation is expressed in
                  public discourse, have changed over time considerably. Although references to the
                  nation appear in all European countries during the nineteenth and early twentieth
                  century, the semantic associations reflect the different contexts in which this
                  concept functions. In TDA, the semantic connection between the term <q>nation</q>
                  and <q>monarchy,</q> which is initially very strong, disappears after 1884. The
                  nation is consistently associated with <q>people</q> over the full period under
                  review, reflecting the broad meaning of the word in which national identity is
                  based on the notion of a people sharing similar language and ethnic origins.
                  Unsurprisingly, nation is also associated with the term <q>empire</q> in England,
                  although this connection weakens after 1908 (see Table 5). </p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in TDA related to
                        <q>nation,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>people</cell>
                     <cell>empire</cell>
                     <cell>patriotism</cell>
                     <cell>independence</cell>
                     <cell>community</cell>
                     <cell>mankind</cell>
                     <cell>monarchy</cell>
                     <cell>democracy</cell>
                     <cell>nations</cell>
                     <cell>fatherland</cell>
                     <cell>nationality</cell>
                     <cell>rulers</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.6</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1910s</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>A narrower political interpretation of national identity appears only in the 1860s
                  in TDA, when nationalism became associated with conservatism, but also with the
                  competing political affiliations of liberalism, democracy, and Toryism. The
                  growing political awareness and polarization in the 1870s is reflected by the
                  connection between <q>nationalism</q> and the term <q>radicalism</q> within the
                  same word vector space. That nationalism is also placed in a religious context is
                  suggested by the emergence of religious terms such as <q>protestantism,</q>
                  <q>clericalism,</q> and <q>ultramontane</q> (the latter reflecting the political
                  ambitions of the pope). The role of the state is difficult to assess on the basis
                  of the word vector models because the word <q>state</q> possesses several meanings
                  in English. Yet the term <q>state</q> seems associated with the more
                  administrative terms <q>to govern,</q>
                  <q>government,</q> and <q>administration</q> from the 1840s on, and the more
                  negative term <q>disorganisation</q> from the mid-1850s on, hinting at a tendency
                  perhaps, to describe the state, rather than the nation, in utilitarian terms.</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in TDA related to
                        <q>nationalism,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>conservatism</cell>
                     <cell>liberalism</cell>
                     <cell>democracy</cell>
                     <cell>radicalism</cell>
                     <cell>toryism</cell>
                     <cell>republicanism</cell>
                     <cell>imperialism</cell>
                     <cell>protestantism</cell>
                     <cell>separatist</cell>
                     <cell>clericalism</cell>
                     <cell>puritanism</cell>
                     <cell>exclusiveness</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.13</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.56</cell>
                     <cell>0.56</cell>
                     <cell>0.26</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.55</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.54</cell>
                     <cell>0.41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1910s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>After German unification in 1871, the newspapers reflected the strong cultural
                  origins of the German sense of national identity. The term <q>nation</q> is
                  strongly associated with <q>christianity</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Christenheit</foreign>) in the 1870s, the period marked by Bismarck’s cultural
                  war (<foreign xml:lang="de">Kulturkampf</foreign>) against Catholicism. Although
                  the Iron Chancellor faced defeat in the political arena, the emergence of the
                  secular alternative <q>civilization</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Zivilization</foreign>) in the 1880s suggests that he won in public discourse.
                  This seems to confirm Koselleck’s conclusion that the German sense of nation is
                  primarily a cultural construct (<foreign xml:lang="de">Kulturbegriff</foreign>).
                  Nevertheless, the word vector models also show the connection with power. The
                  emergence of geopolitical and military terms such as <q>sea power,</q>
                  <q>great power,</q> and <q>world power</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Seemacht</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Großmacht</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Weltmacht</foreign>) in the vocabulary around the term
                     <q>nation</q> reflects Germany’s global geopolitical ambitions, which were
                  translated into colonial expansion and maritime muscle-flexing at that time. A
                  similar German sense of superiority and the civilizing mission is reflected in the
                  close relation emerging between the term <q>civilization</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Civilisation</foreign>) and geopolitical markers such as <q>sea
                     power</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Seemacht</foreign>) and <q>world politics</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="de">Weltpolitik</foreign>) at the end of the nineteenth
                  century. </p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-SBB related to
                        <q>nation,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>dynastie</cell>
                     <cell>nation</cell>
                     <cell>civilisation</cell>
                     <cell>einheit</cell>
                     <cell>republik</cell>
                     <cell>zivilisation</cell>
                     <cell>diplomatie</cell>
                     <cell>demokratie</cell>
                     <cell>volksvertretung</cell>
                     <cell>seemacht</cell>
                     <cell>politik</cell>
                     <cell>colonialpolitik</cell>
                     <cell>weltmacht</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.57</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.19</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.37</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.36</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-EU related to
                        <q>nation,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>nation</cell>
                     <cell>dynastie</cell>
                     <cell>monarchie</cell>
                     <cell>volksvertretung</cell>
                     <cell>demokratie</cell>
                     <cell>diplomatie</cell>
                     <cell>einheit</cell>
                     <cell>nationalität</cell>
                     <cell>großmacht</cell>
                     <cell>unabhängigkeit</cell>
                     <cell>rationalität</cell>
                     <cell>aristokratie</cell>
                     <cell>völker</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.63</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.63</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.63</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.47</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.63</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The political interpretation of national identity within Germany is expressed by
                  the term <q>nationalism,</q> which can be understood as a developing term first
                  associated with foreign influences from the West and East (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Bonapartismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Polenklubs</foreign>) and the
                  indigenous national spirit (<foreign xml:lang="de">Nationalgeistes</foreign>)
                  propagated to counter France’s national ambitions. Interestingly, similarly to the
                  UK, the German term <q>nationalism</q> becomes contested at the end of the
                  century, as is evinced by its semantic association with pejorative terms with the
                  suffix -ismus such as <q>clericalism,</q>
                  <q>imperialism,</q>
                  <q>absolutism,</q>
                  <q>radicalism,</q>
                  <q>chauvinism,</q> and <q>fanaticism</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Klerikalismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Imperialismus</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Absolutismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Radikalismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Chauvinismus</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Fanatismus</foreign>). In German discourse, the term
                     <q>state</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Staat</foreign>) does not make inroads, as
                  the associated vocabulary suggests competition between governmental intervention
                  and private initiatives, such as <q>compulsory insurance</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Versicherungszwang</foreign>), <q>private firm</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Privatbetrieb</foreign>), <q>artisans</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Handwerkerstand</foreign>), and, at the end of the century, <q>taxation</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="de">Steuerbezahler</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Fiscus</foreign>). The Hegelian conception of national identity, lastly, is
                  reflected in the frequent use of the term <q>spirit of the nation</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Nationalgeist</foreign>) in connection with the German
                     <q>nation.</q> In the 1870s, this term is associated with terms such as
                     <q>idealism,</q>
                  <q>spirit,</q>
                  <q>patriotism</q> and <q>national identity</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Idealismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Geist</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Patriotismus</foreign>), which may reflect an essentialist, or
                  Hegelian, interpretation of national identity. In the 1880s, terms such as
                     <q>idealism,</q>
                  <q>altruism,</q>
                  <q>fatalism,</q>
                  <q>naturalism,</q> and <q>national character</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Idealismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Altruismus</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Fatalismus</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Volkscharacter</foreign>) dominate, perhaps suggesting a conceptual change
                  towards a more moral and personal interpretation of national identity. </p>
               <table>
                  <head>The similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-SBB related
                     to <q>nationalismus,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>despotismus</cell>
                     <cell>radikalismus</cell>
                     <cell>klerikalismus</cell>
                     <cell>absolutismus</cell>
                     <cell>imperialismus</cell>
                     <cell>individualismus</cell>
                     <cell>socialismus</cell>
                     <cell>ultramontanismus</cell>
                     <cell>parlamentarismus</cell>
                     <cell>chauvinismus</cell>
                     <cell>sozialismus</cell>
                     <cell>materialismus</cell>
                     <cell>dogmas</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.19</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.19</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.34</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.17</cell>
                     <cell>0.34</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.9</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>The similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-EU related to
                        <q>nationalismus,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>sozialismus</cell>
                     <cell>radicalismus</cell>
                     <cell>rationalismus</cell>
                     <cell>radikalismus</cell>
                     <cell>klerikalismus</cell>
                     <cell>ultramontanismus</cell>
                     <cell>chauvinismus</cell>
                     <cell>sozialismus</cell>
                     <cell>liberalismus</cell>
                     <cell>antisemitismus</cell>
                     <cell>konservatismus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.17</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.17</cell>
                     <cell>0.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.90</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.91</cell>
                     <cell>0.90</cell>
                     <cell>0.53</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.89</cell>
                     <cell>0.89</cell>
                     <cell>0.90</cell>
                     <cell>0.52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.90</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.92</cell>
                     <cell>0.91</cell>
                     <cell>0.89</cell>
                     <cell>0.91</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>In the German-language newspapers that were published in the United States
                  (DE-CA), the concept of the nation is used in a radically different political
                  context. Across the Atlantic, the nation became immediately connected with
                     <q>justice,</q>
                  <q>politics</q>, <q>party,</q>
                  <q>government,</q> and <q>principles</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Nation</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Gerechtigkeit</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Politik</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Partei</foreign>, <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Regierung</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Grundsätze</foreign>), which illustrates how readily German migrants absorbed the
                  constitutional context of their adopted nation. That adaptation may also explain
                  the emergence of the term <q>republic</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Republik</foreign>) in the 1850s, and <q>race</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Rasse</foreign>) during the last years of the nineteenth century, in the
                  discourse of nation. Similarly, the term <q>democracy</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Demokratie</foreign>) became associated with heated party politics in the
                  post-Jackson years of the 1840s, resulting in terms such as <q>slave owner</q> and
                     <q>slavery question</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Sklavenhalter</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Sklavenfrage</foreign>) in the late 1840s, and
                     <q>Republican</q> in the 1850s. The occurrence of references to silver and
                  prohibition (<foreign xml:lang="de">Silberfrage</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Silberleute</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Prohibition</foreign> and
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Prohibitionisten</foreign>) in the vocabulary around
                  democracy during the last decades of the century illustrates that German
                  immigrants absorbed the key concerns of political populism, such as alcohol
                  prohibition and resentment against the silver standard, which divided the rest of
                  the United States <ptr target="#wells2015"/>
                  <ptr target="#kazin2007"/>. For German immigrants in the United States, the term
                     <q>folk</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Volk</foreign>) is associated with
                     <q>germanness</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Deutschthum</foreign>) from the late
                  1850s and <q>fatherland</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Vaterland</foreign>) from the
                  1880s. During the 1860s, references to <q>civil rights</q> and <q>citizenship</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="de">Bürgerrecht</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Bürgerthum</foreign>) are associated with people (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Volk</foreign>), and with <q>workers</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Proletariat</foreign>) from the 1890s, which may be a reflection of the
                  emerging radicalism in the United States of socialist and anarchist groups,
                  inspired by European movements <ptr target="#kazin2012"/>
                  <ptr target="#foner2014"/>.</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-CA related to
                        <q>nation,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>partei</cell>
                     <cell>republik</cell>
                     <cell>politik</cell>
                     <cell>monarchie</cell>
                     <cell>einheit</cell>
                     <cell>demokratie</cell>
                     <cell>regierungsform</cell>
                     <cell>unabhängigkeit</cell>
                     <cell>dynastie</cell>
                     <cell>regierung</cell>
                     <cell>administration</cell>
                     <cell>civilisation</cell>
                     <cell>parle</cell>
                     <cell>menschheit</cell>
                     <cell>aristokrati</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.45</cell>
                     <cell>0.31</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.60</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.30</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.57</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in DE-SBB related to
                        <q>demokratie,</q> grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>bourgeoisie</cell>
                     <cell>partei</cell>
                     <cell>sozialdemokratie</cell>
                     <cell>Orthodoxie</cell>
                     <cell>socialdemokratie</cell>
                     <cell>demagogie</cell>
                     <cell>reaktion</cell>
                     <cell>wählerschaft</cell>
                     <cell>liberalismus</cell>
                     <cell>nation</cell>
                     <cell>fortschrittspartei</cell>
                     <cell>gewerkschaftsbewegung</cell>
                     <cell>kratie</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.41</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.20</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.41</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.40</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.02</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.84</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.65</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.16</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.83</cell>
                     <cell>0.85</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.49</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.48</cell>
                     <cell>0.33</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The case of Finland provides an interesting point of comparison with English and
                  German datasets. Finland was originally a region of the Swedish Kingdom, annexed
                  by the Russian Empire during the Napoleonic Wars. The Grand Duchy of Finland
                  (1809–1917) was an autonomous part of Russia and can be considered as a
                  predecessor of the Republic of Finland, founded in 1917. The fact that Finland is
                  a bilingual country had consequences for Finnish nationalism. In the beginning of
                  the nineteenth century, Finnish intellectuals and civil servants understood only
                  Swedish, whereas the common people tended to use Finnish in their communication.
                  This led to a situation where the early promoters of Finnish nationalism typically
                  published in Swedish, and could not understand Finnish. However, towards the end
                  of the nineteenth century, the Finnish language slowly replaced Swedish as the
                  main language of the press, and during the peak of Finnish nationalism
                  (Fennomania) , many Swedish-speaking families changed their first language to
                     Finnish.<note>During the 1860s language strife in Finland, advocates of the
                     Finnish language were called the Fennomans, and they founded the Finnish Party.
                     A significant number of the Fennomans originated in the mostly Swedish-speaking
                     upper classes who Finnicized their Swedish family names and promoted Finnish
                     culture and language. </note>
               </p>
               <p>Academic scholarship has emphasized the role of the German example in the early
                  development of Finnish nationalism. In the beginning of the nineteenth century,
                  folk (<foreign xml:lang="sv">folk</foreign> in Swedish or <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >kansa</foreign> in Finnish) was a term used in the idealized context of
                  national Romanticism. Johann Gottfried von Herder and German Romanticism were
                  important models for early Finnish nationalists like Adolf Ivar Arwidsson
                  (1791–1858), active in the 1810s and 1820s. From the beginning, the press was the
                  most important forum for Arwidsson’s nationalist activity. He founded the radical
                  journal <title rend="italic">Åbo Morgonblad</title>, which was suppressed by the
                  Russian Tsar in 1821. After the short period of Finnish Romanticism in Turku, the
                  intellectual center moved to Helsinki where the Hegelian philosophy became
                  popular. When writing about the conceptual history of folk (<foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >kansa</foreign>), <ref target="#liikanen2003">Liikanen (2003)</ref> emphasizes
                  the importance of the Fennomans and their Hegelian understanding of national
                  spirit (<foreign xml:lang="fi">kansallishenki</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >nationalanda</foreign> from German <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Volksgeist</foreign>). Inspired by Hegelian philosophy, the Finnish philosopher
                  Johann Vilhelm Snellman (1806–81) introduced the concept of <q>spirit</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="de">Geist</foreign> in German, <foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >anda</foreign> in Swedish, and <foreign xml:lang="fi">henki</foreign> in
                  Finnish) into the Finnish nationalist discourse. Although our word vector models
                  start from the 1840s, the Hegelian tradition is reflected in these German and
                  Swedish word vector models. Both German and Swedish word vector models associated
                  the Hegelian concept of <q>spirit</q> with <q>patriotism.</q>
                  <foreign xml:lang="sv">Fosterlandskärlek</foreign> (<q>love for country</q>) is
                  also strongly linked with the concept of <q>spirit</q> in Swedish results.
                  Finally, the concept of <q>national spirit</q> (<foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >kansallishenki</foreign>) is also associated with a mixture of nationalist
                  terms and Hegelian technical terminology in the Finnish results (see Table
                  12).</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in FI-NLF related to
                        <q>kansallishenki</q> (national spirit), grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>kansallistunto</cell>
                     <cell>kansallistunne</cell>
                     <cell>siwistys</cell>
                     <cell>kansallisuus</cell>
                     <cell>isänmaanrakkaus</cell>
                     <cell>itsetietoisuus</cell>
                     <cell>kansallinen</cell>
                     <cell>kulttuuri</cell>
                     <cell>yhteishenki</cell>
                     <cell>itsetunto</cell>
                     <cell>itsetajunta</cell>
                     <cell>ruotsalaisuus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.23</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.07</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.07</cell>
                     <cell>0.07</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.35</cell>
                     <cell>0.51</cell>
                     <cell>0.07</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.22</cell>
                     <cell>0.37</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.07</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.46</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.88</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>B. The ethnic roots of national identity</head>
               <p>It has been customary to make a distinction between cultural and ethnic
                  nationalism <ptr target="#leerssen2018"/>
                  <ptr target="#smith2008"/>
                  <ptr target="#alter1994"/>. For example, the late eighteenth-century philosopher
                  Johann Gottfried von Herder is considered an important early theoretician of
                  nationalism, although he in fact objected to the biological race theories of his
                  time. When Herder emphasized the importance of local national cultures, his
                  intention was to defend small states against the imperialism of the multinational
                  empires of the time <ptr target="#nisbet1999"/>Nisbet 1999). However, after the
                  development of positivism, scientism, and Darwinism, late nineteenth-century
                  nationalism became more based on ideas of ethnicity, race, and the shared
                  biological descent of national populations. This is also reflected in our results.
                  In the Fenno-Swedish corpus, <q>nationality</q> (<foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >nationalitet</foreign>) is associated with descent and origins. It seems that
                     <q>nationality</q> and <q>ancestry</q> (<foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >härkomst</foreign>) are also associated with <q>religious confession</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="sv">trosbekännelse</foreign>). In contrast to these Swedish
                  results, German word vector models for the concept of nationality (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Nationalität</foreign>) indicate a clear association between
                     <q>race</q> and <q>ancestry.</q> Finally, the Finnish model is very different
                  to the Fenno-Swedish and German results. The concepts in the word vector space
                  linked with <q>nationality</q> (<foreign xml:lang="fi">kansallisuus</foreign>)
                  refer to <foreign xml:lang="fir">siwistys</foreign> (cultivation, cf., <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Bildung</foreign>), <foreign xml:lang="fi">kulttuuri</foreign>
                  (culture), <foreign xml:lang="fi">kirjallisuus</foreign> (literature), <foreign
                     xml:lang="fi">sanomakirjallisuus</foreign> (press), <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >kieli</foreign> (language), and <foreign xml:lang="fi">aate</foreign> (idea),
                  which are related more to cultural nationalism than ethnic nationalism (see Table
                  13).</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the most frequent word vectors in FI-NLF related to
                        <q>kansallisuus</q> (nationality), grouped by decade.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>siwistys</cell>
                     <cell>kansallinen</cell>
                     <cell>kansallishenki</cell>
                     <cell>kansallistunne</cell>
                     <cell>kulttuuri</cell>
                     <cell>kansallistunto</cell>
                     <cell>aate</cell>
                     <cell>kirjallisuus</cell>
                     <cell>kieli</cell>
                     <cell>edistyminen</cell>
                     <cell>sanomakirjallisuus</cell>
                     <cell>isänmaallisuus</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.41</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.39</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.32</cell>
                     <cell>0.64</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.22</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.36</cell>
                     <cell>0.6</cell>
                     <cell>0.15</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.56</cell>
                     <cell>0.21</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.50</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.43</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.14</cell>
                     <cell>0.44</cell>
                     <cell>0.5</cell>
                     <cell>0.86</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.42</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>In German newspapers (DE-SBB) of the same period, the ethnic roots of national
                  identity are reflected by the close association between the term <q>folk</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="de">Volk</foreign>), <q>christianity</q> ( <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Christentum</foreign>) and <q>army</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Heer</foreign>). In similar fashion, the term <q>nationality</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Nationalität</foreign>) is used in the context of words that
                  strongly suggest heritage, such as <q>descent</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Abkunft</foreign>), <q>heredity</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Abstammung</foreign>), <q>religion</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Konfession</foreign>, Religion, Christian, Mission), and <q>language,</q> both
                     <q>spoken</q> and <q>written,</q>
                  <q>local</q> and <q>national</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Schriftsprache</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Landessprache</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Muttersprache</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Volkssprache</foreign>). The
                  term <q>nation</q> is also closely related to <q>civilization</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Civilisation</foreign>) and <q>mores</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Gesittung</foreign>).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>C. Citizens, peoples, and masses</head>
               <p>As discussed, Koselleck emphasizes that the politicization of nation and folk in
                  Germany towards the end of the nineteenth century was connected with the
                  development of the labour movement and concepts related to anonymous multitudes of
                  people, like mass or mob <ptr target="#koselleck1992b" loc="389"/>. In other
                  words, the politicization of <q>folk</q> did not only happen against other
                  nations, but also in relation to the inner power structures of each country. This
                  temporal process, where the connotations of <q>folk</q> change substantially, is
                  reflected very clearly in all of the national newspaper corpora analysed here. For
                  example, in FI-NLF the term <q>the poor</q> (<foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >köyhälistö</foreign>) becomes associated with <q>folk</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="fi">kansa</foreign>) only from the 1890s onwards. In SE-NLF,
                     <q>social class</q> (<foreign xml:lang="sv">samhällsklass</foreign>) appears in
                  association with <q>folk</q> from the 1870s (Figure 1). In DE-SBB, references to
                     <q>popular representation</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Volksvertretung</foreign>) appear in the word vector space around <q>nation</q>
                  in the 1870s and 1880s, and <q>workers</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Arbeiter</foreign>) appears mainly in the 1880s. Similarly, terms such as
                     <q>mob</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Janhagel</foreign>) and <q>rabble</q>
                     (<foreign xml:lang="de">Pöbel</foreign>) appear in the vocabulary around
                     <q>nation</q> with connotations such as <q>riot,</q>
                  <q>fright,</q>
                  <q>alarm,</q> and <q>rebellion</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Aufruhr</foreign>,
                     <foreign xml:lang="de">Schrecken</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Allarm</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="de">Aufstand</foreign>). The term
                     <q>folk</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Volk</foreign>) becomes semantically linked
                  to <q>workers</q> (<foreign xml:lang="de">Proletariat</foreign>) in the 1890s
                  (Figure 1).</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The rise of terms <q>köyhälistö</q> (the poor) and <q>samhällsklass</q>
                     (social class) in FI-NLF in association with <q>kansa</q> (nation).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>Whereas the labour movement sympathized with the poor and the proletariat, the
                  political conservatives often made a distinction between <q>folk</q> – the ideal
                  common people – and the disobedient <q>rabble.</q> In SE-NLF it seems that when
                     <q>common people</q> are idealized and well-behaving, they are
                     <emph>folk</emph>, but when they rebel, they become an anonymous rabble. In the
                  DE-CA corpus, for instance, the concept of <foreign xml:lang="de">Volk</foreign>
                  (folk) is associated with <foreign xml:lang="de">Schicksal</foreign> (destiny) in
                  the beginning of the nineteenth century, whereas the association with Proletariat
                  rises towards the end of the century (Figure 2). However, the etymological
                  connections between Germanic languages can be misleading in this case. For
                  example, English <q>people</q> is relatively neutral, whereas its German and
                  Swedish homonyms <foreign xml:lang="de">Pöbel</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >pöbeln</foreign> refer to a pejorative political concept meaning <q>mob</q> or
                     <q>rabble,</q> i.e. a disorderly crowd of people <ptr target="#koselleck1992b"
                     loc="143"/>. The division between idealized folk and dangerous rabble is
                  reflected in Fenno-Swedish word vector models as well: the concept of
                     <q>rabble</q> (<foreign xml:lang="sv">pöbeln</foreign>) is associated with
                     <q>rebels</q> (<foreign xml:lang="sv">rebellerna</foreign>). In Finnish,
                     <foreign xml:lang="fi">rahvas</foreign> (or <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                     >rahwas</foreign>) was first used as a neutral term to refer to <q>common
                     people,</q> but acquired the pejorative meaning of <q>rabble</q> (<foreign
                     xml:lang="fi">roskajoukko</foreign>) towards the end of the nineteenth
                  century.</p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Frequency of “proletariat” and “schicksal” in DE-CA. The concept of <hi
                        rend="italic">Volk</hi> (folk) is associated with <hi rend="italic"
                        >Schicksal</hi> (destiny) in the beginning of the nineteenth century,
                     whereas the association with <hi rend="italic">Proletariat</hi> rises towards
                     the end of the century.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>In TDA, too, the term <q>nation</q> becomes associated with the concept of
                     <q>democracy</q> from the 1860s on, and the concept similarity score gradually
                  increases until 1900 A contested aspect of national unity within the United
                  Kingdom is suggested by the terms which appear in the context of the
                     <q>people,</q> where a consistently strong association with <q>countrymen</q>
                  and <q>peasantry,</q> as well as with <q>Englishmen</q> and <q>Irishmen,</q>
                  reflects the growing tensions around industrialization, urbanization, and home
                  rule. References to Ireland typically evoke subaltern terms such as
                     <q>oppressed,</q>
                  <q>colonists,</q> and <q>loyalists</q> in the word vector space. The proximity
                  between <q>people</q> and the term <q>agitators</q> in the models of the last
                  decades of the century may reflect the rise of trade unions in the UK. </p>
               <p>An interesting transatlantic context is presented by the words surrounding the
                  concept of citizenship within the UK, as the term <q>inalienable</q> remains
                  dominant until the first decade of the twentieth century. This seems a clear
                  reference to the <q>inalienable rights</q> that were promised in the American
                  Declaration of Independence, which may have informed the British debate about
                  citizenship and national identity. The proximity of terms such as
                     <q>privileges,</q>
                  <q>birthright,</q> and <q>heritage</q> also illustrates the British dissension
                  about the concept of nation and the right to be a citizen. If we superimpose the
                  timeseries of <q>independence</q> and <q>citizenship</q> from the word vector
                  model based on the query of <q>nationality</q> on the same plot, we can see that,
                  during the beginning of the nineteenth century, <q>independence</q> is more
                  frequently used in association with <q>nationality,</q> whereas <q>citizenship</q>
                  dominates at the end of the nineteenth century (Figure 3). </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The time series of <q>independence</q> and <q>citizenship,</q> plotted from
                     the <q>nationality</q> vector space model, built on the dataset from
                     TDA.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
               </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>D. Comparing nations, linking vocabularies</head>
               <p>The word vector models illustrate that the concept of <q>nation,</q> in spite of
                  its common origin, is expressed in divergent semantic contexts in the European
                  countries examined here. The Finnish connotations of <q>nation</q> lean towards a
                  cultural interpretation, suggested by terms like spirit and idea, culture,
                  literature and language. German discourse points at a shared heritage that also
                  suggests a cultural interpretation, as is visible in words such as Christianity
                  and civilization. Although the English-language word vector models of TDA were not
                  as clear, the British concept of <q>nation</q> seems to emphasize historical
                  continuity as the basis of national identity, apparent in terms such as destiny
                  and fatherland. British and German word vectors demonstrate a conceptual shift
                  from a public to a more personal understanding of <q>nation,</q> in which state
                  and government are seen as intruders of the private sphere, suggested by
                  references to disorganization, taxation and private enterprises. Germany and
                  Finland share a tendency to understand the nation in essentialist and spiritual
                  terms, where the term <q>folk</q> embodies the body politic. At the same time, all
                  language sets show that the <q>people</q> evoked negative connotations by the
                  vicinity of alarming terms such as <q>rabble,</q>
                  <q>mob,</q> and <q>revolt</q>. The transatlantic connections, lastly, were visible
                  in the British corpus (especially in the references to independence, citizenship
                  and inalienable rights), but virtually absent in the German and Finnish
                  newspapers. Although the word vector models of the German newspapers printed in
                  the United States were not as conclusive, they suggested an interesting avenue of
                  transnational comparison for future research, particularly with respect to the way
                  the nation is understood in different geographical and historical contexts.</p>
               <p>If, on the one hand, word vectors lack the precision of a thorough conceptual
                  analysis such as the one conducted by <title rend="italic">GGB</title>, on the
                  other, they offer the advantage of extending the analysis on much larger datasets
                  that, it can be argued, reflect the public discourse of a larger readership. The
                     <foreign xml:lang="fr">longue durée</foreign> has shown, for instance, the
                  relative instability of the connection between nation and monarchy in the UK. Due
                  to the limitations of having to work with small datasets, these are subtle changes
                  that the <title rend="italic">GGB</title>, which is based on a limited set of key
                  texts, could not have noticed. </p>
               <p>More importantly, the parallel presentation of word vector models from newspapers
                  in different languages opens up a multilingual comparison of public debates around
                  common concepts. Although our methodology has had to rely on modern translations
                  of seed words, detailed comparisons of domain knowledge still allow for a thorough
                  interpretation of the research results. This offers many interesting heuristic
                  possibilities to discover changes in newspaper discourse that may result from
                  conceptual change. The current methodology does not allow us to track cross-border
                  migration of concepts, but it does demonstrate commonalities and contrasts that
                  can direct future research.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>6. Case study II: Illness and disease </head>
            <p>Compared to the concepts of <q>nation</q> and <q>nationhood,</q>
               <q>illness</q> and <q>disease</q> are different in nature: in all languages studied
               in this experiment, <q>illness</q> is not a migratory concept produced by
               modernization, but has profound local cultural roots that are based on older
               migratory ties. For example, the Finnish word <foreign xml:lang="fi"
                  >sairaus</foreign> (illness) derives from <foreign xml:lang="fi">sairas</foreign>
               (ill), which originates from the Germanic word <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >sairaz</foreign> which means sore or painful. The German word for ill, <foreign
                  xml:lang="fr">krank</foreign>, also has proto-Germanic roots; it derives from
                  <foreign xml:lang="de">krangaz</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >krankaz</foreign>, which means crooked or weak <ptr target="#kluge1891"/>.
               Despite the regional etymological rootedness of the concept of illness, our
               experiment shows that, increasingly, new conceptual linkages and influences emerged
               during the nineteenth century. </p>
            <p>In general, the word embeddings in Finnish, Swedish, German, and English refer to
               different horizons of meaning from three frames of reference. The vocabularies list
               words that 1. refer to symptoms or signs of being ill such as, for instance, fever or
               weakness; 2. identify particular diseases that raged in the nineteenth century, from
               isolated cases of the common cold to influenza and cholera pandemics; and 3. Show the
               consequences of becoming ill, like passing away, or becoming disabled through injury.
               Thus, the models retrieve vocabularies that conceptualize <q>illness</q> from
               distinct perspectives, ranging from symptoms and specific diseases to their
               consequences for human beings. Our experiment shows that illness cannot be traced to
               one stable ontological category, because these aspects are affected by shifting
               social and cultural contexts that result from specific economic, political, and
               social histories. </p>
            <div>
               <head>A. Towards the transnational semantics of <q>illness</q></head>
               <p>In the first experiment, we search for the 15 most related terms for the concept
                  term “illness” in the word embeddings of all corpora for the different time spans.
                  For all different corpora, we encounter spelling variations that have resulted
                  from OCR problems. For example, for the German word <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Krankheit</foreign> (illness) we also retrieve terms like <foreign
                     xml:lang="de">Kraukheit</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="de"
                  >Krankhett</foreign>, and the Swedish word <foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >sjukdom</foreign> (illness) was retrieved as <foreign xml:lang="sv"
                     >fjukdom</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="sv">fjuldom</foreign>. To enable a
                  better view of the results, we merge these spelling variations for all terms and
                  compute their average similarity score. </p>
               <figure>
                  <head>Combined similarity scores for synonyms of <q>illness/disease</q> in all
                     datasets.</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
               </figure>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores for the term illness/disease for all datasets. A
                     similarity score of 0.00 indicates that the term is not similar or cannot be
                     found in the corpus. A <q>-</q> indicates that the corpus does not cover these
                     years, and thus a model could not be computed.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>DE-CA</cell>
                     <cell>DE-CA</cell>
                     <cell>DE-EU</cell>
                     <cell>DE-EU</cell>
                     <cell>DE-SBB</cell>
                     <cell>DE-SBB</cell>
                     <cell>TDA </cell>
                     <cell>FI-NLF</cell>
                     <cell>SW-FNL</cell>
                     <cell>SW-NLF</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>krankheit</cell>
                     <cell>erkrankung</cell>
                     <cell>krankheit</cell>
                     <cell>erkrankung</cell>
                     <cell>krankheit</cell>
                     <cell>erkrankung</cell>
                     <cell>disease</cell>
                     <cell>tauti</cell>
                     <cell>sjukdom</cell>
                     <cell>ohälsa</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840s</cell>
                     <cell>0.59</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850s</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860s</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870s</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880s</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.5154</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890s</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.82</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900s</cell>
                     <cell>0.7863</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.79</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.78</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.87</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>In addition, we retrieve synonyms of the term illness such as sickness and
                  disease, which validate the reliability of the semantic models. We focus on the
                  most similar terms that appear in at least four of the different models with a
                  continuous time span, confirming their significance in the corpora. This enables
                  us to identify discrepancies across the different languages and corpora. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>B. The conceptualization of pandemics</head>
               <p>The modern era has been characterized by pandemics <ptr target="#caduff2015"/>.
                  The word pandemic itself is a Greek loanword that refers to diseases that affect
                  all (<hi rend="italic">pan</hi>) people (<hi rend="italic">demos</hi>). In the
                  nineteenth century, new forms of transport and mobility enabled the rapid spread
                  of diseases. Cholera and influenza in particular raged on a global scale <ptr
                     target="#hamlin2009"/>
                  <ptr target="#honigsbaum2014"/>. This effect of globalization is visible in our
                  results. Since the corpora cover slightly different timespans, they do not offer
                  any comprehensive picture of how pandemics emerged and developed conceptually.
                  However, the results refer to different regional perceptions of pandemics. In
                  themselves, <q>epidemic</q> and <q>pandemic</q> are ancient words that have been
                  used in many European languages since at least the seventeenth century <ptr
                     target="#oed2019"/>. In SE-NLF, the Swedish word <q>epidemi</q> appears eleven
                  times from 1858–68 onwards. At the same time, it also shows up in DE-CA, first as
                     <q>Seuche,</q> which was retrieved as similar to <q>Krankheit,</q> 16 times.
                  The loanword <q>Epidemie</q> appears in the results slightly later, in 1864–74. In
                  DE-CA, the term <q>cholera</q> is retrieved in 1858–68, obviously as a result of
                  the so-called third cholera pandemic of 1846–60. In Europe, cholera raged
                  particularly violently during the Crimean War of the 1850s, but the pandemic soon
                  reached the Americas in the late 1850s, which accounts for discussions in the
                  German immigrant press that label cholera <emph>the</emph> disease. While the
                  closeness of real pandemics to their conceptual reflections is obvious, the word
                  embeddings indicate that pandemics also caused conceptual changes. </p>
               <p>In addition to cholera, influenza constitutes a further interesting example that
                  gained weight in the nineteenth century. The so-called <q>Russian flu</q> pandemic
                  was particularly lethal in 1889–90. In the Swedish corpus, too, <q>influenza</q>
                  appears in 1888–98. In FI-NLF <q>influenza</q> appears for the first time as
                     <q>influentsa</q> in 1884–94, not as a synonym for <q>sairaus</q> (see above)
                  but for <q>tauti,</q> another Finnish term for illness. As a concept,
                     <q>influenza</q> went almost as viral as the disease itself. There were, of
                  course, references to influenza before the 1880s, but the international loanword
                  (and its variations) was not used, according to our empirical data. Semantically,
                  influenza hides behind different words, such as flu, or breast or lung
                  disease.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>C. Nervous diseases and the social boundaries of illness</head>
               <p>At the beginning of the nineteenth century, the understanding of the mechanisms of
                  nervous diseases was mostly pathological. However, in the course of the century,
                  modern psychology developed a more internal view of the human mind <ptr
                     target="#schultz2012"/>. In the newspaper corpora, nervous diseases appear
                  increasingly towards the end of the nineteenth century. At the turn of the
                  twentieth century there were particularly vivid discussions about neurasthenia.
                  This term for weakness of the nerves was coined in the 1820s, but became popular
                  from the 1860s onwards, especially after the publication of George Miller Baird’s
                  article <title rend="quotes">Neurasthenia, or nervous exhaustion,</title> in
                     <title rend="italic">The Boston Medical and Surgical Journal</title> in 1869
                     <ptr target="#beard1869" loc="217–21"/>. Neurasthenia was often seen as a
                  disease caused by the accelerating rhythms of modern culture <ptr
                     target="#uimonen2000"/>
                  <ptr target="#salmi2013"/>. Nervous diseases start to appear in our models in the
                  1860s, and remain an essential conceptual aspect of illness going forward. </p>
               <table>
                  <head>Similarity scores between <q>illness</q> and the terms <q>mental disease</q>
                     and <q>nervous disease.</q> While we observe <q>mental disease</q> in DE-EU,
                     DE-SBB and SE-NLF, we retrieve <q>nerve disease</q> only in DE-SBB and
                     SE-NLF.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>Mental illness</cell>
                     <cell>neuropathy</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>DE-CA</cell>
                     <cell>DE-SBB</cell>
                     <cell>SW</cell>
                     <cell>DE-SBB</cell>
                     <cell>SW</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>decade</cell>
                     <cell>geistesstörung</cell>
                     <cell>geisteskrankheit</cell>
                     <cell>sinnessjukdom</cell>
                     <cell>nervenkrankheit</cell>
                     <cell>nervsjukdom</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1840-1850</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1842-1852</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1844-1854</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1846-1856</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1848-1858</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1850-1860</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1852-1862</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1854-1864</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1856-1866</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1858-1868</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1860-1870</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1862-1872</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.58</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1864-1874</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.62</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1866-1876</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1868-1878</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1870-1880</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1872-1882</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.61</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1874-1884</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1876-1886</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1878-1888</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.69</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1880-1890</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1882-1892</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.75</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1884-1894</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1886-1896</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1888-1898</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.67</cell>
                     <cell>0.74</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1890-1900</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1892-1902</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.80</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1894-1904</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.81</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1896-1906</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.73</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.77</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1898-1908</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1900-1910</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.71</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.76</cell>
                     <cell>0.68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1902-1912</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                     <cell>0.66</cell>
                     <cell>0.72</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1904-1914</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.70</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>0.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>1908-1918</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                     <cell>-</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>The same observation applies to mental diseases. <foreign xml:lang="de"
                     >Nervenkrankheit</foreign> (nervous disease) is retrieved in DE-SBB first in
                  1882–892, and four times thereafter. In the DE-EU, it comes up in 1888–98, in
                  total eight times during the whole timespan, and in the SE-NLF in 1898–1908 three
                  times in total as <foreign xml:lang="sv">nervsjukdom.</foreign> Mental health
                  issues also appeared through a plethora of similar words: in Swedish as <foreign
                     xml:lang="sv">sinnessjukdom</foreign> (mental disease), as many as forty times
                  after 1862–72; in DE-EU as <foreign xml:lang="de">Geisteskrankheit</foreign> ten
                  times after 1872–82; and in the DE-SBB four times during the same period. This is
                  not to argue that nervous or mental problems had not been diagnosed before, but
                  conceptually they became more eminent as defining principles for illness. </p>
               <p>There are clear differences between the corpora, however. The examples from the
                  Swedish and German material refer to different timescales in the discourses and
                  articulations on nervous and mental issues. It also appears that <title
                     rend="italic">Nervenkrankheit</title> is not being retrieved in DE-CA or in
                  FI-NLF. Although the models do not make the reasons for this absence clear, these
                  results may be explained by the different audiences of the Finnish-language and
                  German immigrant press. The former was addressing a rural population, whereas
                  neurasthenia was mainly discussed in a middle-class context. This is also
                  supported by the fact that the Finnish-language models yielded many words that
                  refer to animal and plant diseases, which were important for the rural readership
                  of the Finnish-language press. These findings support the conclusion that
                     <q>illness</q> fuelled conceptual migrations across borders, while at the same
                  time reflecting social boundaries for the conceptualization of diseases. However,
                  the word vector models do not allow for further exploration of the context of
                  these concepts, which means that the semantic interaction between human and
                  natural domains in a period when Darwinian evolution theory was debated worldwide
                  would require more research <ptr target="#hawkins1997"/>
                  <ptr target="#bowler2003" loc="224–324"/></p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>D. Debating causes, symptoms, and consequences</head>
               <p>The etiological standpoint, coined by Robert Koch in the 1870s, refers to the
                  assumption that diseases are best controlled and understood by means of their
                  causes. Since this theory has dominated medical discourse for the past two
                  centuries, much of contemporary medical practice concentrates on identifying
                  specific causes of disease. A disease, however, is regularly defined by specifying
                  its nature. To study the representation of illness at community-level in the
                  nineteenth century, our results show that this identity can be expressed by more
                  than causes. Our word embeddings reflect this by showing vocabularies which
                  conceptualize illness from different perspectives such as symptoms, their
                  consequences, synonymous terms, and treatment. By breaking up illness into
                  categories (e.g. treatment, consequences, and symptoms) we can demonstrate its
                  multimodal nature as a concept without fixed entities. Moreover, the word
                     <q>illness</q> is used in different senses or meanings. The aim of this use
                  case is to investigate whether the dominant sense of illness changed over time.
                  The findings support the claim that <quote rend="inline">there is no single way of
                     defining, interpreting, experiencing or managing disease</quote>
                  <ptr target="#jackson2017" loc="6"/>. Our results show that, in contrast to
                  medical discourse, the nineteenth-century press did not concentrate on causes and
                  aetiology of diseases, but rather focused on their human consequences.</p>
               <p>To investigate the change in word sense, we first translate all similar terms for
                     <q>illness</q> into nineteenth-century English. Then, two annotators assign
                  categories to each term. After a close reading of the vocabulary, we define the
                  subcategories listed in Table 16:</p>
               <table>
                  <head>Subdivided categories of <q>illness,</q> their abbreviation, and textual
                     examples.</head>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>Category</cell>
                     <cell>Abbreviation</cell>
                     <cell>Example</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>treatment</cell>
                     <cell>T</cell>
                     <cell>surgery</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>consequences</cell>
                     <cell>C</cell>
                     <cell>death</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>synonymy</cell>
                     <cell>M</cell>
                     <cell>disease</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>symptoms</cell>
                     <cell>S</cell>
                     <cell>pain</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>specific disease </cell>
                     <cell>D</cell>
                     <cell>cholera</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>other</cell>
                     <cell>?</cell>
                     <cell>Words of other categories and words of other part-of-speech </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <figure>
                  <head>The consequences of diseases. The shifting temporal and corpus-specific
                     patterns in all datasets of <q>disease,</q> in terms of its retrieved
                     vocabulary referring to consequences of diseases. This is based on our
                     categorization of <q>illness,</q> category C (see Table 16).</head>
                  <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
               </figure>
               <p>We assigned words such as <q>death,</q>
                  <q>crisis,</q> or <q>incurable</q> to the consequences category, <q>sore
                     throat,</q>
                  <q>tiredness,</q> or <q>vomiting</q> to the symptoms category, <q>ill,</q> or
                     <q>sickness</q> to the synonymy category, <q>cholera,</q>
                  <q>influenza,</q> or <q>mental disease</q> to a category for specific diseases,
                     <q>surgery,</q> or <q>inoculation</q> to treatment, and words that were not
                  context-related to the other category. </p>
               <p>The annotation and comparison of the different subcategories highlights that the
                  majority of generated words are synonyms and consequences of diseases. These
                  categories are dominant in all six corpora. As Figure 5 illustrates, analysis of
                  word embeddings in diverse newspaper corpora suggests the discussion of
                  consequences of diseases rarely respects local, regional, or national borders.
                  This leads to the conclusion that the press constructed illness as a concept with
                  an emphasis on its consequences. This emphasis is supported by mainly negative
                  characteristics such as, for instance, <q>epidemic,</q>
                  <q>poverty,</q> “died”, and <q>suffering.</q> Thus, diseases are represented as
                  agents of suffering, misery, and death, which have a strong negative impact on
                  human lives. </p>
               <p>However, shifting temporal and corpus-specific patterns can be observed, as
                  illustrated by Figure 5. Whereas DE-SBB only textualizes consequences from 1870
                  onwards, no words categorized as consequences seem to occur in DE-EU after 1878.
                  Moreover, words that refer to consequences are widely discussed in FI-NLF and
                  SE-NLF throughout the entire time span.</p>
               <p>Analysing the different categories in which the concept illness is discussed in
                  newspapers allows us to trace the fluctuating meanings of disease and illness as a
                  superordinate category. The overview of subcategories also helps us to consider
                  the role of the press in defining diseases. The fact that there was a strong
                  emphasis on the consequences of illness may be explained by the dual nature of
                  newspaper discourse. On the one hand, the press constructed fear of diseases by
                  describing the disastrous consequences of illness, becoming a platform for
                  emotional expression. On the other, the press expressed social observations and
                  shared them with a wider audience. Pandemics such as influenza and cholera were
                  strongly present in the nineteenth-century public sphere, and papers informed
                  their readers of their impact on the life of an individual as well as on
                  society.</p>
               <p>The combination of synchronic and diachronic analysis of word vector models allows
                  us to trace the development of an abstract concept such as illness over time in
                  newspaper corpora in different languages. We can discover how specific diseases
                  emerged in public discourse in Europe and the United States at different times in
                  history, such as the epidemics of cholera and influenza that affected these parts
                  of the world. More interestingly, word vectors are an effective instrument to
                  trace the vocabularies with which national publics discussed – and constructed –
                  diseases, and their supposed causes and consequences. Our study shows the
                  influence of public discourse, newspaper publishing in particular, on definitions
                  of illness and the multidimensional network of relations between symptoms,
                  specific diseases, and their consequences to construct the concept of illness.
                  Although this case study was limited to newspaper collections from a small number
                  of nations, the differences and silences in discourse, and the changing
                  vocabularies that emerge from the word vector models, offer interesting heuristic
                  starting points for a close reading of these corpora within their proper
                  historical context.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>7. Discussion</head>
            <p>Although the two use cases demonstrate the ways in which word embeddings can be used
               for the transnational comparison of concepts and vocabularies over time, this
               experiment also illustrates the following methodological and technological challenges
               in using multilingual historical newspaper datasets for the construction of word
               vector models.</p>
            <list type="simple">
               <item>
                  <label>OCR issues:</label> One of the major issues we face with historic newspaper
                  data is the OCR quality. Some newspaper pages simply cannot be converted due to
                  low scan quality, and further issues arise with spelling variations. For example,
                  the German word <foreign xml:lang="de">Volk</foreign> appears also as <q>Bolk</q>
                  and <q>Volt.</q> To solve this issue, we merged variations and used their average
                  similarity in our study. </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Different language properties:</label> For the computation of the models,
                  we perform the same pre-processing by using standard tokenization methods.
                  However, because we are using tokenization that mostly splits words by white
                  spaces, multiword expressions composed of two words separated by white space are
                  also split. While this is not an issue for the Germanic languages, where multiword
                  expressions are often close compounds, we lose these terms for the English corpus.
                  This was particularly evident for the illness case study, where specific diseases
                  are often represented as multiword units, leading to entirely different results.
                  In this article, however, we cannot address the task of computing paraphrase
                  embeddings or detecting multiword expressions, and will leave this to future work. </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Corpus differences:</label> We use dense vector space models to compare the
                  shift of concepts across different languages and corpora. However, besides
                  language differences, the corpora we use to compute the models are very diverse in
                  size and composition, and represented different time periods. Comparisons between
                  concepts across corpora is only possible for overlapping time periods. While we
                  have the entire time span of newspapers in TDA, we have no, or only few,
                  newspapers from 1840 to 1855 for most other corpora. Models for semantic
                  similarity tend to be more stable if the size of the corpora used for the
                  computations is large <ptr target="#riedl2013"/>
                  <ptr target="#altszyler2017"/>. We observe the general trend that the number of
                  newspapers increased with time. For the first decades of the nineteenth century,
                  we often have only a few texts, making the models less reliable. In addition, the
                  individual newspaper datasets differ from one another. While TDA only contains
                  newspaper issues from a single source, we use German-language newspapers of
                  several European countries in the German Europeana corpus. In addition, newspapers
                  are always targeted to a specific audience. The Finnish corpus is mostly comprised
                  of newspapers from rural regions, and thus represents specific concerns (e.g.
                  about farming) and mostly does not cover urban trends. </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Parameters of word embeddings:</label> The embeddings depend on the
                  parameters used for the computation, as well as the number of similar terms that
                  are extracted. For the computation of the embeddings, we relied on standard
                  parameters as provided by the ShiCo tool (see footnote 2).</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Conceptual dissimilarities:</label> This article studied conceptual change
                  in two different sets of concepts, those of collective nationhood, and those of
                  the personal circumstances of health and illness. As we have argued, both are
                  cultural constructions that change over time, and both are embedded in their
                  specific cultural context. Koselleck et al also draw attention to the frequent use
                  of metaphors of illness, health, and the body to express concerns about the state
                  of the nation as body politic <ptr target="#koselleck2006" loc="163–4, 205"/>.
                  However, the word vector models shows no overlap between the two semantic domains
                  within the corpora that were used. The connection between the two conceptual sets
                  can only be established on the basis of historical domain knowledge which takes
                  the specific historical context into account. </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>8. Conclusion</head>
            <p>Historical newspapers allow us to study how everyday concepts have been used in
               public discourse. This article discusses how word vector models can help us to trace
               how such concepts were articulated in shifting vocabularies as they moved over time
               and space. This addresses the methodological question: how can computational methods
               be applied to broaden the scope of conceptual history? In order to test the usability
               of word vector models, we address two urgent academic questions within the field of
               conceptual history. The first is to what extent concepts are stable entities that are
               expressed in changing vocabularies over large periods of time, as <ref
                  target="#lovejoy1933">Lovejoy (1933)</ref> famously suggested, or whether changing
               vocabularies should be understood as an indication of conceptual change, as other
               practitioners of conceptual history argue. We test this by concentrating on a
               historical time frame, the period between 1840 and 1914, in which the western world
               experienced the rapid changes of modernization and globalization and became
               interconnected through the new mass media of newspapers. The second, perhaps more
               complex, question is how we can use this computational methodology to trace how
               concepts change as they migrate over geographical and linguistic borders. For our
               dataset, we use digitized historical newspaper corpora in five different languages.
               As use cases, we select two radically different concepts that have a global presence,
               the collective identity of the <q>nation</q> and the deeply personal experience of
                  <q>illness.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This international and interdisciplinary research project, in which researchers from
               four academic institutions in Europe collaborate, illustrates the possibilities and
               challenges of using computational methods to analyse conceptual change over longer
               periods of time in different cultural and national contexts. We can formulate a
               number of promising findings:</p>
            <list type="simple">
               <item><label>Newspaper corpora.</label> The computational tool ShiCo, which has been
                  developed to trace shifting concepts over time by constructing series of
                  overlapping word vector models, can effectively be applied to historical newspaper
                  repositories of different provenance, metadata structure, and OCR quality, and,
                  most interestingly of all, written in different languages. The resulting
                  vocabularies were consistent enough to allow meaningful scholarly interpretation.
                  Even if newspapers are commercial and professional media enterprises with their
                  own ideological agendas, they can only survive if they reflect ongoing debates in
                  society. The outcomes of this research project confirm that these combined
                  newspapers collections are rich and promising sources for a computational approach
                  to conceptual history, and may offer us a novel entry point into the historical
                  public sphere.</item>
               <item><label>Digital conceptual history.</label> Our computational approach to
                  conceptual history validates the application of a quantitative and big data method
                  to this discipline. In comparison to traditional approaches to conceptual history,
                  which tend to use limited textual corpora mostly produced by scholarly
                  communities, this computational approach enables us to draw on the big data
                  repositories of historical newspapers which reflect a much broader public
                  discourse.</item>
               <item><label>Time.</label> Word vector models prove to be a convincing and promising
                  tool to show how different vocabularies share the same semantic space over time.
                  Although we define the term <q>concept</q> rather pragmatically, the word models
                  show a consistent configuration that changed over time, sometimes gradually,
                  sometimes rapidly, introducing new words or terms as a result of historical
                  changes. The domain knowledge of the authors enables us to offer meaningful
                  interpretations of these semantic changes. This offers a new way to trace how
                  collective concepts such a nation, national identity, the people, and the more
                  personal discussions of causes, symptoms and results of illness were articulated
                  over a longer period of time, even spanning eight decades.</item>
               <item><label>Space.</label> The comparison of the word models created by applying the
                  ShiCo software to separate newspaper repositories in different languages allows
                  researchers to test the promise of comparative and transcultural conceptual
                  history. Even if this method relies on translation of key terms and vocabularies
                  in English, and on manual comparison based on historical domain knowledge, the
                  results are significant and allow us to situate concepts such as nation and
                  illness in its historical contexts. </item>
               <item><label>Distant reading.</label> As Moretti quipped, <quote rend="inline"
                     >ambition is now directly proportional to the distance from the text: the more
                     ambitious the project, the greater must the distance be</quote>
                  <ptr target="#moretti2013" loc="48"/>. Indeed, word vector models seem to allow
                  for an extreme form of distant reading of textual corpora which takes researchers
                  far from the contextual content of the newspapers. But even as the text itself
                  disappears out of sight, larger patterns emerge that carry heuristic value. By
                  identifying trends and discontinuities in the way concepts are articulated in
                  shifting vocabularies as they move over time and space, this form of distant
                  reading can help us to understand how concepts are discussed in newspapers in
                  various languages. Comparing word vector models based on newspapers from different
                  national collections offers us a glimpse at the circulation of knowledge in the
                  western world.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The outcomes of this article also suggest a number of avenues for future
               research:</p>
            <list type="ordered">
               <item>Although word vectors models offer quantitative data about the words that
                  appear in the semantic space around search queries or seed words, the comparison
                  between different language corpora still relies on qualitative interpretation. A
                  more robust method may be found in cross-mapping word vector models to represent
                  the translation of concepts and terms <ptr target="#jansen2017"/>
                  <ptr target="#luong2015"/>
                  <ptr target="#mikolov2013b"/>. The structure of the data and models currently does
                  not allow for such computational application of translation vectors. </item>
               <item>It would be valuable to divide the national newspaper corpora into different
                  sub-collections of newspapers according to their political, religious or regional
                  affiliation. Such segmentation would allow for comparisons of, for instance,
                  Catholic or socialist newspapers from different linguistic and national
                  backgrounds, or could offer indications of the audiences that are receptive to
                  international influences or ideological affiliation. Segmentation would require
                  server space and computer power that was not available for this project.</item>
               <item>Another approach would be to develop a robust computational method to determine
                  in which specific discursive contexts certain vocabularies and concepts were used
                  (e.g. in which sections of the newspapers can references to national identity be
                  found in newspapers from a particular period, and where were issues of health and
                  illness discussed? Can the discursive context of these references be
                  established?). This would necessitate combining the creation of word vectors of
                  sufficient volume with automated segmentation of newspapers in departments,
                  genres, or other sections that semantically belong to each other. </item>
               <item>A more ambitious way to trace cross-national migration of ideas would be to
                  implement algorithms that identify text reuse. Although this has been successfully
                  attempted in monolingual corpora <ptr target="#smithetal2015"/>
                  <ptr target="#cordell2015"/>, text reuse in multilingual corpora is still in
                  development. If combined with the heuristic potential of word vector models, text
                  reuse could bring us closer to the scalable, zoomable and explorative readings
                  that are the meeting ground between the big-data ambitions of distant reading and
                  the semantic precision of close reading. </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>We would like to thank prof. Marc Priewe of the University of Stuttgart for hosting
               the project conference from which this publication originated and for his feedback on
               the concept version</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alter1994" label="Alter 1994">Alter, Peter. 1994. <title rend="italic"
                  >Nationalism</title>. 2nd ed. New York: Edward Arnold.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="altszyler2017" label="Altszyler et al. 2017">Altszyler, Edgar, Sidarta
               Ribeiro, Mariano Sigman, and Diego Fernández Slezak. 2017. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Interpretation of Dream Meaning: Resolving Ambiguity Using Latent Semantic
                  Analysis in a Small Corpus of Text.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Consciousness and Cognition</title> 56 (November): 178–87. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.concog.2017.09.004"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.concog.2017.09.004</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anderson2006" label="Anderson 2006">Anderson, Benedict R. O’G. 2006.
                  <title rend="italic">Imagined Communities: Reflections on the Origin and Spread of
                  Nationalism</title>. Rev. ed. London: Verso.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andrews2014" label="Andrews 2014">Andrews, Ann. 2014. <title rend="italic"
                  >Newspapers and Newsmakers: The Dublin Nationalist Press in the Mid-Nineteenth
                  Century</title>. Liverpool: Liverpool University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="baroni2014" label="Baroni et al. 2014">Baroni, Marco, Dinu Georginana, and
               Germán Kruszewski. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Don’t Count, Predict! A Systematic
                  Comparison of Context-Counting vs. Context-Predicting Semantic Vectors.</title>
               In: Proceedings of ACL:171–81. East Stroudsburg PA. <ref
                  target="http://anthology.aclweb.org/P/P14/P14-1023.xhtml"
                  >http://anthology.aclweb.org/P/P14/P14-1023.xhtml</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="beals2020" label="Beals and Bell 2020">Beals, Melodee, and Emily Bell.
               2020. <title rend="quotes">The Atlas of Digitised Newspapers and Metadata: Reports
                  from Oceanic Exchanges,</title> Figshare, 19 january 2020. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.6084/M9.FIGSHARE.11560059"
                  >https://doi.org/10.6084/M9.FIGSHARE.11560059</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="beard1869" label="Beard 1869"> Beard, George Miller. 1869. <title
                  rend="quotes">Neurasthenia, or Nervous Exhaustion.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Boston Medical and Surgical Journal</title> (April):
               217–21.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="betti2014" label="Betti and van den Berg 2014">Betti, Arianna, and Hein
               van den Berg. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Modelling the History of Ideas.</title>
               <title rend="italic">British Journal for the History of Philosophy</title> 22 (4):
               812–35. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/09608788.2014.949217"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/09608788.2014.949217</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="billig1995" label="Billig 1995">Billig, Michael. 1995. <title
                  rend="italic">Banal Nationalism</title>. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bowler2003" label="Bowler 2003">Bowler, Peter J. 2003. <title
                  rend="italic">Evolution: The History of an Idea</title>. 3rd ed. Berkeley:
               University of California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="broersma2018" label="Broersma and Harbers 2018">Broersma, Marcel, and
               Frank Harbers. 2018. <title rend="quotes">Exploring Machine Learning to Study the
                  Long-Term Transformation of News.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Digital Journalism</title> 6 (9): 1150–64. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/21670811.2018.1513337"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/21670811.2018.1513337</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brunner1972" label="Brunner et al. 1972">Brunner, Otto, Werner Conze, and
               Reinhart Koselleck, eds. 1972. <title rend="italic">Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe:
                  Historisches Lexikon Zur Politisch-Sozialen Sprache in Deutschland</title>. 8
               vols. Stuttgart: E. Klett.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="caduff2015" label="Caduff 2015">Caduff, Carlo. 2015. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Pandemic Perhaps: Dramatic Events in a Public Culture of Danger</title>.
               Oakland, CA: University of California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="cordell2015" label="Cordell 2015">Cordell, Ryan. (2015) <title
                  rend="quotes">Reprinting, Circulation, and the Network Author in Antebellum
                  Newspapers.</title>
               <title rend="italic">American Literary History</title>, 27(3), pp. 417-445.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="debolla2013" label="De Bolla 2013">De Bolla, Peter. 2013. <title
                  rend="italic">The Architecture of Concepts: The Historical Formation of Human
                  Rights</title>. New York: Fordham University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="douglas1999" label="Douglas 1999">Douglas, George H. 1999. <title
                  rend="italic">The Golden Age of the Newspaper</title>. Westport, CT.: Greenwood
               Press. <ref target="http://public.eblib.com/choice/publicfullrecord.aspx?p=497022"
                  >http://public.eblib.com/choice/publicfullrecord.aspx?p=497022</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eijnatten2014" label="Eijnatten et al. 2014">Eijnatten, Joris van, Toine
               Pieters, and Jaap Verheul. 2014. <title rend="quotes">Big Data for Global History:
                  The Transformative Promise of Digital Humanities.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Low Countries Historical Review</title> 128 (4): 55–77.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="firth1957" label="Firth 1957">Firth, John Rupert, ed. 1957. <title
                  rend="italic">Studies in Linguistic Analysis</title>. Oxford: Blackwell.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="foner2014" label="Foner 2014">Foner, Eric. 2014. <title rend="italic">Give
                  Me Liberty!: An American History</title>. Fourth edition. New York: W.W. Norton
               &amp; Company.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gavin2015" label="Gavin 2015">Gavin, Michael. 2015. <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Arithmetic of Concepts: A Response to Peter de Bolla,</title> in: <title
                  rend="italic">Modelling Literary History</title> (blog). <ref
                  target="modelingliteraryhistory.org/2015/09/18/the-arithmetic-of-concepts-a-response-to-peter-de-bolla"
                  >modelingliteraryhistory.org/2015/09/18/the-arithmetic-of-concepts-a-response-to-peter-de-bolla</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gellner1997" label="Gellner 1997">Gellner, Ernest. 1997. <title
                  rend="italic">Nationalism</title>. New York University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gellner2007" label="Gellner 2007">— — — . 2007. <title rend="italic"
                  >Nations and Nationalism</title>. 2. ed., Malden, MA: Blackwell Publ.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ginneken1998" label="Ginneken 1998">Ginneken, Jaap van. 1998. <title
                  rend="italic">Understanding Global News: A Critical Introduction</title>. Thousand
               Oaks, CA: Sage.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="habermas1991" label="Habermas 1991">Habermas, Jürgen. 1991. <title
                  rend="italic">The Structural Transformation of the Public Sphere: An Inquiry into
                  a Category of Bourgeois Society</title>. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hamilton2016" label="Hamilton et al. 2016">Hamilton, William L., Jure
               Leskovec, and Dan Jurafsky. 2016. <title rend="quotes">Diachronic Word Embeddings
                  Reveal Statistical Laws of Semantic Change.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the 54th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational
                  Linguistics (Volume 1: Long Papers)</title>, 1489–1501. Berlin, Germany:
               Association for Computational Linguistics. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/P16-1141"
                  >https://doi.org/10.18653/v1/P16-1141</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hamlin2009" label="Hamlin 2009">Hamlin, Christopher. 2009. <title
                  rend="italic">Cholera: The Biography</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harras2000" label="Harras 2000">Harras, Gisela. 2000. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Concepts in Linguistics – Concepts in Natural Language.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Conceptual Structures: Logical, Linguistic, and Computational
                  Issues</title>, edited by Bernhard Ganter and Guy W. Mineau, 1867:13–26. Berlin:
               Springer. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/10722280_2"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/10722280_2</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harris1954" label="Harris 1954">Harris, Zellig S. 1954. <title
                  rend="quotes">Distributional Structure.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Word</title> 10 (2–3): 146–62. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/00437956.1954.11659520"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/00437956.1954.11659520</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hawkins1997" label="Hawkins1997">Hawkins, Mike. 1997. <title rend="italic"
                  >Social Darwinism in European and American Thought, 1860-1945: Nature as Model and
                  Nature as Threat</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hobsbawm2012" label="Hobsbawm 2012">Hobsbawm, Eric J. 2012. <title
                  rend="italic">Nations and Nationalism since 1780: Programme, Myth,
               Reality</title>. Second edition. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hobsbawm2010" label="Hobsbawm and Ranger 2010">Hobsbawm, Eric J., and
               Terence O. Ranger, eds. 2010. <title rend="italic">The Invention of
               Tradition</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="honigsbaum2014" label="Honigsbaum 2014">Honigsbaum, Mark. 2014. <title
                  rend="italic">A History of the Great Influenza Pandemics: Death, Panic and
                  Hysteria, 1830–1920</title>. New York: I.B. Tauris.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jackson2017" label="Jackson 2017">Jackson, Mark, ed. 2017. <title
                  rend="italic">The Routledge History of Disease</title>. London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jackson2007" label="Jackson and Moulinier 2007">Jackson, Peter, and
               Isabelle Moulinier Moulinier. 2007. <title rend="italic">Natural Language Processing
                  for Online Applications: Text Retrieval, Extraction and Categorization</title>. nd
               revised ed. Amsterdam: John Benjamins. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jansen2017" label="Jansen 2017">Jansen, Stefan. 2017. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Word and Phrase Translation with Word2vec.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1705.03127 [Cs]</title>, May. <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03127"
               >http://arxiv.org/abs/1705.03127</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kazin2007" label="Kazin 2007">Kazin, Michael. 2007. <title rend="italic">A
                  Godly Hero: The Life of William Jennings Bryan</title>. New York: Anchor
               Books.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kazin2012" label="Kazin 2012">— — — . 2012. <title rend="italic">American
                  Dreamers: How the Left Changed a Nation</title>. New York: Vintage Books.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kenter2013" label="Kenter 2013">Kenter, Tom. 2013. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Filtering Documents over Time for Evolving Topics.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the Twenty-Second Text REtrieval Conference (TREC
                  2013)</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kenter2015" label="Kenter et al. 2015">Kenter, Tom, Melvin Wevers, Pim
               Huijnen, and Maarten de Rijke. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Ad Hoc Monitoring of
                  Vocabulary Shifts over Time.</title> In: <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the
                  24th ACM International on Conference on Information and Knowledge
                  Management</title> - CIKM ’15, 1191–1200. Melbourne, Australia: ACM Press. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1145/2806416.2806474"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1145/2806416.2806474</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kluge1891" label="Kluge 1891">Kluge, Friedrich. 1891. <title rend="italic"
                  >Etymological Dictionary of the German Language.</title> London: George Bell &amp;
               Sons.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koselleck1992a" label="Koselleck 1992a">Koselleck, Reinhart. 1992a. <title
                  rend="quotes">Einleitung: Volk, Nation, Nationalismus, Masse.</title> In: <title
                  rend="italic">Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe: Historisches Lexikon Zur
                  Politisch-Sozialen Sprache in Deutschland</title>, edited by Otto Brunner, Werner
               Conze, and Reinhart Koselleck, 7:141–51. Stuttgart: E. Klett.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koselleck1992b" label="Koselleck 1992b">— — — . 1992b. <title
                  rend="quotes">Lexikalischer Rückblick.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >Geschichtliche Grundbegriffe: Historisches Lexikon zur Politisch-Sozialen Sprache
                  in Deutschland</title>, edited by Otto Brunner, Werner Conze, and Reinhart
               Koselleck, 7:380–89. Stuttgart: Klett-Cotta.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koselleck2002" label="Koselleck 2002">— — — . 2002. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Practice of Conceptual History: Timing History, Spacing Concepts</title>.
               Translated by Todd Samuel Presner. Stanford, CA: Stanford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koselleck2004" label="Koselleck 2004">— — — . 2004. <title rend="italic"
                  >Futures Past: On the Semantics of Historical Time</title>. New York: Columbia
               University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="koselleck2006" label="Koselleck et al. 2006">Koselleck, Reinhart, Ulrike
               Spree, Willibald Steinmetz, and Carsten Dutt. 2006. <title rend="italic"
                  >Begriffsgeschichten: Studien zur Semantik und Pragmatik der politischen und
                  sozialen Sprache</title>. Frankfurt am Main: Suhrkamp Verlag.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kunczik1997" label="Kunczik 1997">Kunczik, Michael. 1997. <title
                  rend="italic">Images of Nations and International Public Relations</title>. LEA’s
               Communication Series. Mahwah, N.J: Erlbaum.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kuukkanen2008" label="Kuukanen 2008">Kuukkanen, Jouni-Matti. 2008. <title
                  rend="quotes">Making Sense of Conceptual Change.</title>
               <title rend="italic">History and Theory</title> 47 (3): 351–72. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-2303.2008.00459.x"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1468-2303.2008.00459.x</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="landauer1997" label="Landauer et al. 1997">Landauer, Thomas K., and Susan
               T. Dumais. 1997. <title rend="quotes">A Solution to Plato’s Problem: The Latent
                  Semantic Analysis Theory of Acquisition, Induction, and Representation of
                  Knowledge.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Psychological Review</title> 104 (2): 211–40. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.104.2.211"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1037/0033-295X.104.2.211</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="leerssen2018" label="Leerssen 2018">Leerssen, Joep. 2018. <title
                  rend="italic">National Thought in Europe: A Cultural History</title>. Amsterdam:
               Amsterdam University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lenci2018" label="Lenci 2018">Lenci, Alessandro. 2018. <title
                  rend="quotes">Distributional Models of Word Meaning.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Annual Review of Linguistics</title> 4 (1): 151–71. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-linguistics-030514-125254"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-linguistics-030514-125254</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lovejoy1933" label="Lovejoy 1933">Lovejoy, Arthur O. 1933. <title
                  rend="italic">The Great Chain of Being: A Study of the History of an Idea</title>.
               Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press. <ref
                  target="http://site.ebrary.com/id/10314249"
                  >http://site.ebrary.com/id/10314249</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="lund1996" label="Lund and Burgess 1996">Lund, Kevin, and Curt Burgess.
               1996. <title rend="quotes">Producing High-Dimensional Semantic Spaces from Lexical
                  Co-Occurrence.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Behavior Research Methods, Instruments, &amp; Computers</title>
               28 (2): 203–8. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3758/BF03204766"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3758/BF03204766</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="luong2015" label="Luong et al. 2015">Luong, Minh-Thang, Hieu Pham, and
               Christopher D. Manning. 2015. <title rend="quotes">Bilingual Word Representations
                  with Monolingual Quality in Mind.</title>
               <title rend="italic">NAACL Workshop on Vector Space Modeling for NLP</title>,
               151–59.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="margolis1999" label="Margolis and Laurence 1999">Margolis, Eric, and
               Stephen Laurence, eds. 1999. <title rend="italic">Concepts: Core Readings</title>.
               Cambridge, MA: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="margolis2005" label="Margolis and Laurence 2005">— — — . 2005. <title
                  rend="quotes">Concepts.</title> In <title rend="italic">The Stanford Encyclopedia
                  of Philosophy</title>, edited by Edward N. Zalta. Stanford University. <ref
                  target="https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2014/entries/concepts/#Aca"
                  >https://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2014/entries/concepts/#Aca</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="martinez-ortiz2016" label="Martinez-Ortiz 2016">Martinez-Ortiz, Carlos,
               Tom Kenter, Melvin Wevers, Pim Huijnen, Jaap Verheul, and Joris van Eijnatten. 2016.
                  <title rend="quotes">Design and Implementation of ShiCo: Visualising Shifting
                  Concepts over Time.</title> Edited by Marten Duering, Adam Jatowt, Antal van den
               Bosch, and Johannes Preiser-Kappeller. <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 3th
                  Histoinformatics Conference, Krakow, July 11 2016</title>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mikolov2013a" label="Mikolov et al. 2013a">Mikolov, Tomas, Kai Chen, Greg
               Corrado, and Jeffrey Dean. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Efficient Estimation of Word
                  Representations in Vector Space.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1301.3781 [Cs]</title>, January. <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1301.3781"
               >http://arxiv.org/abs/1301.3781</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mikolov2013b" label="Mikolov et al. 2013b">Mikolov, Tomas, Quoc V. Le, and
               Ilya Sutskever. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Exploiting Similarities among Languages
                  for Machine Translation.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1309.4168 [Cs]</title>, September. <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1309.4168"
               >http://arxiv.org/abs/1309.4168</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mikolov2013c" label="Mikolov et al. 2013c">Mikolov, Tomas, Ilya Sutskever,
               Kai Chen, Greg Corrado, and Jeffrey Dean. 2013. <title rend="quotes">Distributed
                  Representations of Words and Phrases and Their Compositionality.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1310.4546 [Cs, Stat]</title>, October. <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.4546"
               >http://arxiv.org/abs/1310.4546</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mitra2015" label="Mitra et al. 2015">Mitra, Sunny, Ritwik Mitra, Suman
               Kalyan Maity, Martin Riedl, Chris Biemann, Pawan Goyal, and Animesh Mukherjee. 2015.
                  <title rend="quotes">An Automatic Approach to Identify Word Sense Changes in Text
                  Media across Timescales.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Natural Language Engineering</title> 21 (5): 773–98. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S135132491500011X"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/S135132491500011X</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moran1978" label="Moran 1978">Moran, James. 1978. <title rend="italic"
                  >Printing Presses: History and Development from the Fifteenth Century to Modern
                  Times</title>. Berkeley: University of California Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moretti2013" label="Moretti 2013">Moretti, Franco. 2013. <title
                  rend="italic">Distant Reading</title>. London: Verso.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="muller2016" label="Müller and Schmieder 2016">Müller, Ernst, and Falko
               Schmieder. 2016. <title rend="italic">Begriffsgeschichte Und Historische Semantik:
                  Ein Kritisches Kompendium</title>. Berlin: Suhrkamp.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="muller2014" label="Müller 2014">Müller, Jan-Werner. 2014. <title
                  rend="quotes">On Conceptual History.</title> In: <title rend="italic">Rethinking
                  Modern European Intellectual History</title>, edited by Darrin M. McMahon and
               Samuel Moyn, 74–93. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nisbet1999" label="Nisbet 1999">Nisbet, H.B. 1999. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Herder: The Nation.</title> In <title rend="italic">Approaches to the Writing of
                  National History in the North-East Baltic Region</title>, edited by Michael
               Branch, 78–96. Helsinki: Finnish Literature Society.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="nolan2012" label="Nolan 2012">Nolan, Mary. 2012. <title rend="italic">The
                  Transatlantic Century: Europe and America, 1890–2010</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge
               University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="orourke1999" label="O’Rourke 1999">O’Rourke, Kevin H. 1999. <title
                  rend="italic">Globalization and History: The Evolution of a Nineteenth-Century
                  Atlantic Economy</title>. Cambridge, Mass: MIT Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="osterhammel2014" label="Osterhammel 2014">Osterhammel, Jürgen. 2014.
                  <title rend="italic">The Transformation of the World: A Global History of the
                  Nineteenth Century</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="oed2019" label="OED 2019">
               <title rend="italic">Oxford Dictionary of English</title>. 2019. Oxford University
               Press. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1093/acref/9780199571123.001.0001"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1093/acref/9780199571123.001.0001</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pocock2016" label="Pocock 2016">Pocock, J. G. A. 2016. <title
                  rend="italic">The Machiavellian Moment: Florentine Political Thought and the
                  Atlantic Republican Tradition</title>. Princeton: Princeton University
               Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pumfrey2012" label="Pumfrey et al. 2012">Pumfrey, Stephen, Paul Rayson,
               and John Mariani. 2012. <title rend="quotes">Experiments in 17th Century English:
                  Manual versus Automatic Conceptual History.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Literary and Linguistic Computing</title> 27 (4):
               395–408.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="recchia2017" label="Recchia et al. 2017">Recchia, Gabriel, Ewan Jones,
               Paul Nulty, John Regan, and Peter de Bolla. 2017. <title rend="quotes">Tracing
                  Shifting Conceptual Vocabularies Through Time.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >Knowledge Engineering and Knowledge Management</title>, edited by Paolo
               Ciancarini, Francesco Poggi, Matthew Horridge, Jun Zhao, Tudor Groza, Mari Carmen
               Suarez-Figueroa, Mathieu d’Aquin, and Valentina Presutti, 10180:19–28. Cham: Springer
               International Publishing. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-58694-6_2"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-58694-6_2</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="riedl2013" label="Riedl and Bieman 2013">Riedl, Martin, and Chris Bieman.
               2013. <title rend="quotes">Scaling to Large3 Data: An Efficient and Effective Method
                  to Compute Distributional Thesauri.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Proceedings of the 2013 Conference on Empirical Methods in
                  Natural Language Processing</title>, no. October: 884–890.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rosie2004" label="Rosie et al. 2004">Rosie, Michael, John MacInnes, Pille
               Petersoo, Susan Condor, James Kennedy, M.J. Rosie, J. MacInnes, P. Petersoo, S.
               Condor, and J. Kennedy. 2004. <title rend="quotes">Nation Speaking Unto Nation?
                  Newspapers and National Identity in the Devolved UK.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Sociological Review</title> 52 (4): 437–58. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-954X.2004.00490.x"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1467-954X.2004.00490.x</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="salmi2013" label="Salmi 2013">Salmi, Hannu. 2013. <title rend="italic"
                  >Nineteenth-Century Europe: A Cultural History</title>. Cambridge, Mass.:
               Polity.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schultz2012" label="SChultz and Schultz 2012">Schultz, Duane P., and
               Sydney Ellen Schultz. 2012. <title rend="italic">A History of Modern
                  Psychology</title>. 10th ed. Belmont, CA: Wadsworth.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="skinner1969" label="Skinner 1969">Skinner, Quentin. 1969. <title
                  rend="quotes">Meaning and Understanding in the History of Ideas.</title>
               <title rend="italic">History and Theory</title> 8 (1): 3. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.2307/2504188"
               >https://doi.org/10.2307/2504188</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="skinner1978" label="Skinner 1978">— — — . 1978. <title rend="italic">The
                  Foundations of Modern Political Thought</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University
               Press.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="skinner2012" label="Skinner 2012">— — — . 2012. <title rend="italic"
                  >Liberty Before Liberalism</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139197175"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781139197175</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smith2008" label="Smith 2008">Smith, Anthony D. 2008. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Ethnic Origins of Nations</title>. Malden, MA: Blackwell. </bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="smithetal2015" label="Smith et al. 2015">Smith, David A., Ryan Cordell,
               and Abby Mullen. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Computational Methods for Uncovering
                  Reprinted Texts in Antebellum Newspapers.</title>
               <title rend="italic">American Literary History</title>, 27(3), pp. E1-E15.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="steinmetz2016" label="Steinmetz 2016">Steinmetz, Willibald. 2016. <title
                  rend="quotes">Forty Years of Conceptual History: The State of the Art.</title> In:
                  <title rend="italic">Global Conceptual History: A Reader</title>, edited by
               Margrit Pernau and Dominic Sachsenmaier, 339–66. London ; New York: Bloomsbury
               Academic.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="uimonen2000" label="Uimonen 2000">Uimonen, Minna. 2000. <title
                  rend="italic">Hermostumisen Aikakausi: Neuroosit 1800- Ja 1900-Lukujen Vaihteen
                  Suomalaisessa Lääketieteessä</title>. Helsinki: Finnish Literature Society.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="viola2020" label="Viola and Verheul 2020">Viola, Lorella, and Jaap
               Verheul. 2020. <title rend="quotes">One Hundred Years of Migration Discourse in The
                  Times: A Discourse-Historical Word Vector Space Approach to the Construction of
                  Meaning.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Frontiers in Artificial Intelligence</title> 3 (September): 64.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.3389/frai.2020.00064"
                  >https://doi.org/10.3389/frai.2020.00064</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="weitz1988" label="Weitz 1988">Weitz, Morris. 1988. <title rend="italic"
                  >Theories of Concepts: A History of the Major Philosophical Tradition</title>.
               London: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wells2015" label="Wells 2015">Wells, Wyatt. 2015. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Rhetoric of the Standards: The Debate over Gold and Silver in the 1890s.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Journal of the Gilded Age and Progressive Era</title> 14
               (1): 49–68. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S153778141400053X"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/S153778141400053X</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="wevers2020" label="Wevers and Koolen 2020">Wevers, Melvin, and Marijn
               Koolen. 2020. <title rend="quotes">Digital Begriffsgeschichte: Tracing Semantic
                  Change Using Word Embeddings.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Historical Methods: A Journal of Quantitative and
                  Interdisciplinary History</title>, May, 1–18. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01615440.2020.1760157"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/01615440.2020.1760157</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
