<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:array="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/array"
     xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
     xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
     xmlns:map="http://www.w3.org/2005/xpath-functions/map"
     xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
     xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt><!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English--></title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo><!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>first name(s) <dhq:family>family name</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000--></idno>
               <dhq:affiliation/>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110--></idno>
            <idno type="volume"><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND"><!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="project_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ project registry; full list available at <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml">http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/projects.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords"><!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors--><!--Enter keywords below preceeded by a "#". Create a new term element for each-->
               <term corresp=""/>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords"><!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#project_keywords">
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc><!-- Replace "NNNNNN" in the @target of ref below with the appropriate DHQarticle-id value. -->
         <change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target="https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/main/articles/NNNNNN/NNNNNN.xml">GitHub
        	   </ref>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract><!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser><!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="Title">Visualizing a Series: Aggregate Compositional Analysis of Botticelli’s Commedia</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
         </titlePage>
         <p>Nathaniel Corley, Amherst College</p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Abstract</head>
            <p>Applying digital methods as inputs to an interpretive process, I expose
                    compositional motifs within Sandro Botticelli’s momentous
                    <hi rend="italic">Divina Commedia </hi>codex that depart
                    from canonical manuscript illustrations. I then situate these visual findings
                    within Quattrocento literary and artistic theory, arguing that Botticelli
                    manipulated his compositional structures to harmonize with the humanist
                    Cristoforo Landino’s interpretation of the
                    <hi rend="italic">Commedia </hi>as an allegory for the
                    soul’s ascension from “disorder” to “order.” By leafing through the pages of
                    Botticelli’s manuscript and perceiving the striking structure and style of the
                    illustrations, the observer could experience the incremental progress of Dante
                    the Pilgrim’s soul — and perhaps the viewer’s own — through the different stages of
                    hell to paradise. Ultimately, I reflect on the implications of digital
                    methodologies within art history, and how these techniques may enrich or even
                    challenge traditional modes of “seeing” works of art.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Sandro Botticelli’s fifteenth-century drawings of Dante Alighieri’s <hi rend="italic">Divina Commedia</hi> are an art-historical puzzle. Throughout
                    a lavish codex, the artist widely varies his mode of representation while
                    chronicling Dante the Pilgrim’s epic journey through the afterlife’s three
                    realms — <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and
                        <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>. Although Botticelli doubtless illustrated
                    all one hundred cantos (narrative units best understood as “little songs”) of
                    Dante’s epic, only ninety-two folios from the series are extant.<note> Medieval writers
                            regularly employed the vernacular locution “canto,” from the Latin <hi rend="italic">cantus</hi>, to reference songs and lyrical
                            composition. However, Dante endows the term with a new sense — as each of
                            the one hundred narrative units that compose his <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>. Dante presents one introductory canto followed by
                            three large narrative subsections, labeled “canticles,” of thirty-three
                            cantos each (<hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>). The
                            overarching structure of the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>, then,
                            follows the organization: 1 + 33 + 33 + 33 = 100 cantos
                            <ptr target="#" loc="139"/>(Lansing
                            2010, 139). Of Botticelli’s surviving illustrations, seven reside in
                            the<hi rend="italic"> Biblioteca Apostolica Vaticana</hi>,
                            while the remaining eighty-five vellum sheets entered Berlin’s
                            Kupferstichkabinett in 1882 from the Duke of Hamilton’s
                        collection.</note> Nevertheless, the surviving drawings confound. Each
                    canticle of Botticelli’s series (to use Dante’s poetic unit for a realm of hell,
                    comprising thirty-three cantos) seemingly derives from distinct compositional
                    principles that depart from centuries of manuscript illustration. </p>
            <p>Somehow, the unusual and innovative characteristics of Botticelli’s codex must be
                    indebted to Florence’s swirling discourse around Dante’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>. Botticelli, as an early favorite of the Medici family, was
                    raised within the cradle of Florentine humanism. Together with the learned
                    academics Marsilio Ficino, Politian, and Cristoforo Landino, the artist
                    participated in the late Quattrocento explosion of vernacular culture and
                    discourse. Indeed, as will be discussed later, Botticelli often reinterpreted
                    textual sources through his compositions and iconography. Given this context,
                    Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> series must not plainly illustrate
                    a narrative but instead, with tremendous originality and subtlety, give artistic
                    expression to a poetic invention. However, what precisely this invention
                    entails, and which humanist thinkers Botticelli called upon, remains to be
                    treated.</p>
            <p>Most scholars, while acknowledging the codex’s unusual deviations from canonical
                        <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> manuscripts and Botticelli’s close ties to
                    literary circles, have refrained from identifying cohesive compositional
                    patterns across the many drawings.<note> Hein-Thomas Schulze Altcappenberg, in his
                            exhibition catalogue on the series, stresses Botticelli’s enigmatic use
                            of “an apparently outmoded narrative technique” coupled with “widely
                            differing modes of representation” that depart from canonical Dante
                            illustration (Schulze Altcappenberg 2000, 35). Or, as Friedrich Lippmann
                            describes: “[I]n Inferno and Purgatorio the compositions contain a great
                            variety of small figures, whereas in Paradiso the scale is larger, and
                            in many of the drawings, Dante and Beatrice appear alone”
                            (<ptr target="#" loc="18"/>Lippmann
                            1896, 18).</note> Indeed, traditional visual analysis alone — long a
                    cornerstone of the art historian’s toolkit — struggles to address such a multitude
                    of images. As a result, researchers have largely demurred from addressing the
                    work’s totality, opting instead to focus on specific images or canticles alone.
                    Yet novel observations on the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> must arise not
                    from a biased selection of cantos, but rather from the entirety of Botticelli’s
                    ambitious project. To fully understand Botticelli’s work and artistic intent, we
                    must develop a new way of viewing that can decipher patterns and relationships
                    across the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>’s breadth, not just its individual
                    parts.</p>
            <p>Recent literature reinforces the need to treat the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> series as a whole object. Sharifa Turab Lookman demonstrates,
                    for example, that Botticelli did not execute the illustrations in the order
                    suggested by Dante’s narrative, as had long been accepted
                    <ptr target="#"/>(Lookman
                        2017).<note>
                            Lippman first proposed that “Botticelli’s designs were produced in the
                            order suggested by the poem,” a claim that was largely uncontested until
                            recently
                            (<ptr target="#" loc="19"/>Lippmann
                            1896, 19). </note> By piecing together ink marks and compass traces,
                    Lookman discerned several “sets” of folios that Botticelli worked
                    simultaneously. Each of the sets of related folios that Lookman identified
                    concentrated not on a single canticle, but instead involved sheets from <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>. Therefore, Lookman persuasively argues,
                    Botticelli conceived of the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> as a unified whole,
                    not as single folios or even clusters of drawings. Conclusions must then be
                    drawn not merely across <hi rend="italic">cantos</hi>, but also across <hi rend="italic">canticles</hi>.<note> The close relationship between text and image
                            within Botticelli’s series further reinforces the utility of a digital
                            art history approach. As medievalist Sonja Drimmer warned in an
                            interview, we must resist the temptation to subordinate image to text by
                            asking “how does the image reflect the author’s text,” and instead
                            inquire “how does the author’s text illuminate what we observe first in
                            the image?” (Drimmer 2019). Making use of computational techniques helps
                            alleviate the risk of imposing textual interpretations onto the
                            drawings, as we first derive insights from the series as a whole, and
                            then look to the historical sources to add vital context (Drimmer
                            2019)..</note>
            </p>
            <p>This paper proposes a methodological innovation in the field of art history by
                    applying digital techniques to elucidate the compositional complexities within
                    Botticelli's <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>. By correlating these stylistic
                    choices with Quattrocento literary theory, the current study not only provides a
                    novel interpretation of Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> but also
                    sets forth a procedure for digital visualization as a tool to analyze large
                    corpora of works.</p>
            <p>Supported with observations and visualizations drawn from all ninety-two extant
                    folios, I argue that the manuscript’s varying modes of representation can be
                    understood as a pictorial expansion of the humanist Cristoforo Landino’s
                    prestigious 1481 Dante commentary. According to Landino, Dante the Pilgrim’s
                    soul experiences cacophonous disorder within <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>,
                    incremental organization within <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and sublime
                    unity within <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>. In kind, Botticelli adjusts his
                    organizational schema for each canticle so that it appears to harmonize with
                    Landino’s corresponding allegory — figures are strewn across the page in <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, organized by some centripetal force in <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and condensed into an ethereal whole in <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>.<note> My proposal — that Botticelli adjusts his mode of
                            representation to suit the canticle — finds literary precedent in Dante’s
                            notion of <hi rend="italic">contrapasso</hi>; literally, Italian for
                            “counter-suffering” (not to be confused with the ubiquitous
                            art-historical term <hi rend="italic">contrapposto</hi>). Within the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>, <hi rend="italic">contrapasso</hi>
                            refers to the balancing of the sin and the punishment. That is, the
                            retribution reflects the crime; or, more precisely, the <hi rend="italic">contrapasso</hi> exposes the sin’s horror through a
                            grotesque perversion. <hi rend="italic">Inferno XX</hi> provides a
                            quintessential example. The sorcerers, astrologers, and misleading
                            prophets must wander across the tundra with heads “twisted — their faces
                            looked down on their backs; / they had to move ahead by moving
                            backwards; / they never saw what was ahead of them”
                            (<hi rend="italic">Inf. </hi>20.13–15). Fittingly,
                            Dante condemns those who in life falsely claimed prescience to
                            perpetually look backward at their ill-conceived crimes, not forward to
                            the future. I suggest that Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>
                            program is an artistic elaboration of Dante’s literary <hi rend="italic">contrapasso</hi>: just as Dante matches the punishment to the sin,
                            so too does Botticelli match the composition to the rules and aesthetics
                            of the corresponding canticle. For the translation of <hi rend="italic">Inferno XX</hi>, see Mark Musa’s 1996 edition
                            (<ptr target="#"/>Alighieri
                            1996).</note> By leafing through the pages and perceiving the
                    striking structure and style of the illustrations, the observer could experience
                    the incremental progress of Dante the Pilgrim’s soul — and perhaps his own — through
                    the different stages of hell to paradise.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Digital Visualization Techniques as an Input to an Interpretive Process</head>
            <p>One of my central claims is that Botticelli, unlike earlier <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> illustrators, altered his mode of representation to
                    correspond with the central themes of each canticle. More specifically, I posit
                    that the series exhibits a deliberate compositional arc — from disorder to
                    unity — that was unprecedented within the canon of <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>
                    illustrations. To augment traditional visual interpretation, I adopt a two-part
                    digital approach: first, I use digital visualization of the canticles on the
                    aggregate to expose recurring patterns; and second, I employ descriptive
                    statistics to make concrete how Botticelli’s compositions differed from
                    preceding editions.<note> Recent scholars have fruitfully employed similar
                            digital methods to illuminate patterns across large collections of
                            works. For instance, Alexander Brey recorded the features of an
                            extensive Quran manuscript within a digital database, and conducted
                            principal component analysis (PCA) on the resultant data set, revealing
                            subtle trends in the complex and varied sura heading decoration
                            (<ptr target="#"/>Brey
                            2017). </note> These computational methodologies offer an innovative
                    lens for “seeing,” bringing into sharp focus patterns across the work’s breadth.
                    Then, I marry the scientific and the qualitative by drawing upon historical
                    sources and suggest an explanation for the phenomena surfaced in the data. </p>
            <p>Paging through the manuscript, Botticelli’s viewers intuitively experience the
                    differing modes of representation. Within <hi rend="italic">Inferno XXXIII</hi>,
                    for instance, scientific perspective and chronological narrative are cast aside
                    for a tumult of episodes and vanishing points (Figure 1). Dante’s sinners
                    sequester themselves into distinct paratactic spaces, and all attempts to glean
                    the logic of the patchwork quilt of flesh and agony leave the viewer frustrated
                    and unsatisfied. </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image1.jpeg"/>
               </figure>Figure
                    1. Botticelli, Inferno XXXIII, c. 1481-90. Ink and metal point on parchment, Kupferstichakbinett, Berlin.</p>
            <p>Yet a few cantos later, the cacophonous discord of <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>
                    gives way to cohesion and consonance within <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>.
                    Take <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio XIII: </hi>assembled in
                    symmetric groups of two and three, Botticelli’s penitents huddle together for
                    comfort and warmth (Figure 2). Each pyramidal cluster emanates stability and
                    solidarity rather than disarray. </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image3.jpeg"/>
               </figure>Figure
                    2. Botticelli, Purgatorio XIII. Ink and metal point on parchment. Kupferstichakbinett, Berlin.</p>
            <p>At last, Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi> arrives with the reduction
                    of structural principles to an ineffable simplicity characteristic of Dante’s
                    Earthly Paradise, as evident within <hi rend="italic">Paradiso IX</hi>. Only two
                    elegant figures — Dante and Beatrice — grace the page, at once distinct yet
                    harmonious, engaged in an intricate dance about the central axis. Botticelli
                    presents not only concord but also a simultaneous expression of intangibility,
                    where either figure threatens to dissolve into the vellum’s vast expanse (Figure
                    3). </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image5.jpeg"/>
               </figure>Figure 3.
                    Botticelli, Paradiso IX, c. 1481–90. Ink and metal
                        point on parchment. Kupferstichkabinett, Berlin.</p>
            <p>But a single illustration from each canticle cannot adequately represent
                    Botticelli’s momentous series, nor can three hand-picked examples mitigate
                    confirmation bias.<note> Within psychology, confirmation bias (colloquially “cherry picking”)
                            refers to the tendency of researchers to search for and include only the
                            examples that support their existing hypothesis. In the context of the
                                <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>, that would involve authors’
                            selection, conscious or unconscious, of only the cantos that bolster
                            their previously determined argument.</note> Such limitations are
                    inescapable when analyzing three canticles with thirty-three illustrations each. </p>
            <p>Within textual disciplines, scholars have embraced computational analysis tools
                    that measure word frequency patterns to overcome similar challenges,
                    facilitating a new way to read large text bodies. These software packages serve
                    as an adjunct to traditional close reading, illuminating intricate patterns –
                    such as word usage, psychological tendencies, and language choices – that might
                    otherwise evade human detection.<note> A treatment of computation techniques within
                            textual sources is given in
                            <ptr target="#"/>Argamon
                            and Olsen, 2009.</note> Borrowing from this methodology, although we
                    cannot directly compare so many drawings, we can make sense of a much smaller
                    selection of visualizations that aggregate the compositional structure of the
                    larger group, supporting a qualitatively different kind of insight. A challenge,
                    though, remains: How to represent the arrangement of forms within each
                    canticle’s thirty-three drawings <hi rend="italic">at once</hi>, effectively
                    creating a visual equivalent of a word frequency map? </p>
            <p>Statistics offers one possible interpretative technique: heat maps. At their
                    simplest, heat maps elucidate the spatial clustering of phenomena, rendering
                    once inscrutable data sets comprehensible at a glance. The term “heat” refers
                    not to physical temperature, but instead to the density of the entity under
                    consideration, where “red” typically indicates greatest concentration. Since
                    heat maps convert longitudinal point data into a single interpolated surface,
                    they wield tremendous — as yet unrealized — potential as compositional visualization
                    tools for art history. Namely, in the case of a <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>
                    manuscript, by labeling the <hi rend="italic">x</hi>, <hi rend="italic">y</hi>
                    coordinates of all figures (sinners, devils, penitents, etc.) throughout a given
                    canticle, we can construct a single heat map that reveals patterns in how
                    Botticelli tended to construct his compositions. </p>
            <p>To expedite the tedious procedure of labeling figure locations (as there are more
                    than one thousand across Botticelli’s series alone, to say nothing of the
                    comparative materials that must be considered as well), I designed a web
                    application. In essence, this application recorded the coordinates of any point
                    clicked with the mouse, allowing for the rapid and accurate collection of figure
                    locations. I conducted this procedure not only for Botticelli’s codex, but also
                    for two Tuscan codices that were in all likelihood familiar to Botticelli, and
                    which he drew upon for inspiration: the Bodleian Libraries’ Trecento manuscript
                    MS Holkham Misc. 48 and the British Library’s Quattrocento manuscript MS Yates
                    Thompson 36.<note>
                            According to a 1495–96 inventory, the Medici library alone boasted at
                            least six sumptuously bound manuscripts of Dante’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>—all of which Botticelli would have had unrestricted
                            access to, given his elevated position within the Medici circle. As
                            such, Botticelli would have been eminently familiar with most extant
                            Tuscan editions, and perhaps with several other models now lost. For the
                            original inventory, see
                            <ptr target="#"/>Piccolomini
                            1874. Scholars have also identified consistencies between Botticelli’s
                            codex and preceding models, further confirming the influence of
                            canonical manuscripts. For an instructive treatment on the pictorial
                            tradition of the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> and the illuminator’s
                            tradition of copyists, look to
                            <ptr target="#" loc="140"/>Alexander
                            1992, 140.</note> If heat map analysis of Botticelli’s manuscript,
                    but not these two canonical works (which typify the preceding illumination
                    practice), demonstrate differing modes of representation across the series, I
                    could then support my compositional argument with some confidence.<note> In general,
                            Botticelli may have been exposed to three roughly chronological idioms
                            of <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> manuscripts. The categories are:
                            first, those with miniatures interspersed among the text and numerous
                            illustrations per canto; second, those with more extensive so-called
                            marginal vignettes; and third, those with larger, full-width scenes
                            executed above or below the text, including a more complete treatment of
                            events. The second and third styles are typified in the current study
                            with MS Holkham Misc. 48 and MS Yates Thompson 36, respectively, while
                            the first style exhibits such minimal compositional variation that
                            statistical analysis is unnecessary.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The heat map analysis revealed no structural differences between the compositions
                    illustrating the canticles in either MS Holkham Misc. 48 or MS Yates Thompson 36
                    (Figure 4, Figure 5). From the visualizations, the spread of figures is
                    relatively similar, as are the centralized regions of focus. While some
                    variation persists — due in part to Dante the Pilgrim’s dynamic environment — a
                    single compositional paradigm of linear organization prevails. No hierarchy of
                    form emerges, as all figures appear equal. </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image7.png"/>
               </figure>Figure
                        4. Density maps of the figures throughout each canticle for MS Holkham Misc.
                    48. Darker red indicates greater figural density.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image9.png"/>
               </figure>Figure
                        5. Density maps of the figures throughout each canticle for Yates Thompson MS
                    36. Darker red indicates great figure density. </p>
            <p>Analysis of the heat maps of Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>
                    illustrations, in contrast, expose how each canticle adheres to a distinct mode
                    of representation (Figure 6). Take for example the <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> compositions: the figures are spread across the page, with
                    many banished to the fringes — a fitting locale for those souls who in life
                    strayed from the righteous path. Returning to Botticelli’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Inferno XXXIII, </hi>we find figures are
                    juxtaposed without subordination; no social hierarchy or formal relationships
                    arise from the diffuse chaos (Figure 1). Sinners are literally hewn in two at
                    the edges of the parchment. The viewer’s eye, desperate for an aesthetic focus,
                    wanders across the page. The
                    <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio </hi>heatmap, meanwhile,
                    reveals an underlying centripetal organization that is consistent with the
                    introduction of compositional principles visible within <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio XIII</hi> (Figure 2). No longer are figures clustered near the
                    edges in isolation and distress. Instead, the central locations become the most
                    prominent, radiating balance and harmony. And finally, the <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi> heatmap illustrates the reduction of chaotic structure to a
                    simple unity, as seen in <hi rend="italic">Paradiso IX</hi> (Figure 3). Dante
                    and Beatrice float untethered through the ocean of parchment as if engaged in a
                    cosmic waltz; unconcerned with <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image11.png"/>
               </figure>Figure
                        6. Density maps of the figures throughout each canticle for Botticelli’s Commedia drawings. Darker red indicates great figure
                    density.earthly troubles, they ascend towards the Empyrean. </p>
            <p>The use of such heatmaps within art historical analysis, however, has
                    limitations. First, a single heavily populated folio could exercise outsized
                    influence on the final, aggregated visualization. The resultant chart would then
                    not necessarily represent an “average” composition, but instead a “weighted”
                    one. Second, heat maps require arbitrary input parameters, like the raster cell
                    size, which refers to the extent of the area to group together into a single
                    color. At one extreme, every point in a composition could be contained within
                    the same cell, obscuring any patterns. At the other extreme, the visualization
                    could dissolve into an unintelligible mass of points that exhibit few trends.
                    Third, the comparison of heat maps is inherently qualitative. In other words, we
                    can subjectively examine the three visuals and proclaim that they exhibit stark
                    differences, but how can we be certain such irregularities did not arise by
                    chance? </p>
            <p>While heat maps give obvious visual clues to patterns across the series, to move
                    from general observation to quantification, we must incorporate statistical
                    tests as well. Scholars from related fields have successfully used similar
                    techniques to tackle “humanistic” research questions. For instance,
                    archaeologists applied hypothesis tests to evaluate whether social status or sex
                    influenced burial types within the Parthian Empire, ultimately concluding that
                    no statistically significant existed
                    <ptr target="#"/>(Eghdami
                    et al. 2023). Drawing a parallel again to Botticelli’s drawings, we must find a
                    way to <hi rend="italic">quantify</hi> each canticle’s thematic variations, and
                    then can conduct hypothesis tests to uncover and examine any trends. </p>
            <p>How, indeed, can we measure Botticelli’s differing modes of representation? No
                    doubt, convolutional and non-parametric methods offer potential solutions.
                    Weinstein et al. raise one possibility with their algorithmic treatment of Paul
                    Cézanne’s <hi rend="italic">Bathers</hi>
               <ptr target="#"/>(Weinstein,
                    Voss, and Soll 2019). By repurposing a dendrology computer application to
                    identify axial symmetry and golden ratios within Cézanne’s
                    <hi rend="italic">Bathers </hi>series, the authors
                    discovered that the works’ compositions — previously characterized as “awkward” — in
                    fact conform to harmonious mathematical proportions. However, such an algorithm
                    would prove less fruitful when applied to
                    Botticelli’s<hi rend="italic"> Commedia</hi>, as the <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi> illustrations most often exhibit only two
                    figures, and the diffuse confusion within <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> resists
                    structural analysis.<note> A version of Weinstein et al.’s algorithm modified
                            to detect and quantify violations of proportion rather than adherence to
                            golden ratios, however, might allow novel insights into Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> drawings. </note> The authors’
                    adapted dendrology technique, while adept at locating compositional <hi rend="italic">harmony</hi>, fails when confronted with unmoored figures and
                    assiduously devised <hi rend="italic">disharmony</hi>. A more parsimonious
                    approach would capture within a statistic the spread of the figures from the
                    center. As the Dante scholar Rachel Jacoff remarks, “For Dante, sin is a
                    violation of community”
                    <ptr target="#"/>(Jacoff
                    2018). Indeed, the presence of a cohesive community most distinguishes
                    Botticelli’s three canticles; accordingly, the physical (and therefore
                    emotional) distance between figures suffices as an adequate measure.</p>
            <p>And so, to analyze the Commedia illustrations through these methods, I took the
                    centroid — the geometric center of a shape — as the “middle” of a composition
                    (Supplemental Figure 1). To quantify the spread of the forms within a given
                    canto, I computed the mean distance from the topological centroid to each figure
                    (overarching procedure illustrated in Supplemental Figure 2; means for each
                    canticle found in Supplemental Table 1). Next, to evaluate whether the mean
                    spread of figures differed significantly by canticle, I performed a one-way
                    ANOVA (Analysis of Variance), a standard test for statistical significance when
                    comparing three or more groups (see Appendix for discussion of statistical
                        techniques).<note> I am indebted to Amherst College’s Professor of Statistics and Data
                            Science Nick Horton for his advice regarding these statistical
                            calculations.</note> In all cases, statistics validated the trends
                    first observed in the heat maps: for both MS Holkham Misc. 48 and MS Yates
                    Thompson 36, the analysis revealed no significant compositional variations
                    across canticles (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0.751 and <hi rend="italic">p</hi>
                    = 0.279, respectively),<note> The large <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-values found
                            from the ANOVA analysis (<hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0.751 and <hi rend="italic">p</hi> = 0.279, respectively) did not allow rejection
                            of the null hypothesis that any discrepancies between canticles could be
                            attributed to random noise (Supplemental Table 2).</note> while for
                    Botticelli’s manuscript, the results indicated that the canticles are
                    compositionally distinct (<hi rend="italic">p </hi>= 2.2 *
                        10-16).<note> More formally, the small p-value allowed
                            rejection of the null and conclusion of the alternative hypothesis. One
                            complication remains, however. Although the ANOVA confirms the presence
                            of a statistical difference between the three groups, it does not
                            identify which group(s) are different. I therefore conducted a post-hoc
                            Fukey HST (Honestly Significant Test), which compared all three options
                            (<hi rend="italic">Purgatorio </hi>vs.<hi rend="italic"> Inferno, Paradiso </hi>vs.<hi rend="italic"> Inferno, Paradiso </hi>vs.
                                <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>) and reported which differ
                            significantly. For Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>
                            drawings, the post-hoc Fukey HST indicated that, indeed, all three
                            combinations are significant to a high degree, and that each canticle
                            thus operates within distinct compositional principles (Supplemental
                            Figure 3).</note>
            </p>
            <p>What is more, close study of the series (conducted both on the drawings in the
                    flesh and through high-quality visual reproductions) reveals that Botticelli
                    adjusted more than his mode of representation: his drawing style exhibits
                    stunning variation by canticle as well. Within <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>,
                    the artist sketched frantic, heavy lines in dark ink, evoking the chaotic energy
                    endemic to Dante’s hell. Consider the depiction of Dante the Pilgrim’s figure
                    within <hi rend="italic">Inferno XXXIII</hi> (Figure 7).<note> For the drawing style of <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, and later for the other two canticles, I
                            supply a single example to illustrate the stylistic trend. Of course, as
                            discussed, a single folio from a set of thirty-three is not convincing
                            evidence across the canticle. Further digital art history scholarship
                            (perhaps employing image manipulation to isolate disconnected lines and
                            heavy strokes, for example) is needed to explore how the trend holds
                            across the work’s totality.</note> Gestural lines start, stutter,
                    and cease, conveying form but not volume. The strokes’ weight lends Dante’s
                    figure material presence, yet their angularity insists that he exists outside of
                    the human world. Botticelli’s representation of the two wayfarers in <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio XIII</hi>, meanwhile, typifies the greater sense of
                    naturalism present within the second canticle’s drawings (Figure 7). Sketched in
                    a mixture of light and dark ink with significant metal point underdrawings,
                    Botticelli’s strokes are confident, deliberate, and measured. We here witness
                    the series at its most tangible: the figures of Dante and Virgil threaten to
                    wander off the page and into the profane world. The pen strokes of <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>, on the other hand, are thin and hesitant, with
                    no signs of the dark ink that suffused the earlier canticles. As a
                    demonstration, follow the line suggesting the outer fold of Beatrice’s
                    diaphanous drapery within <hi rend="italic">Paradiso IX</hi> (circled in red in
                    Figure 7). The stroke slopes gently downward, swerves abruptly, and terminates
                    just short of Beatrice’s sleeve. A second mark overlaps the first’s lower
                    section, but also ceases inexplicably. This is not an anomaly — Beatrice’s whole
                    ensemble consists not of continuous strokes, but instead a precarious assemblage
                    of disembodied lines, each drifting unmoored from its neighbors. The artist’s
                    drawing mode thus mimics the evanescent nature of his subject. The wayfarers are
                    both present and absent, flitting between the ordinary and the
                        transcendental.<note> In <hi rend="italic">Paradiso I</hi>, Dante
                            admits, “I could not look for long, but my eyes saw / the sun enclosed
                            in blazing sparks of light like molten iron as it pours from the fire”
                            (<hi rend="italic">Par. </hi>1.58-1.60). Of course,
                            how could Botticelli render in permanent, dark ink what Dante
                            experienced as if squinting into the blinding sun?</note>
            </p>
            <p>�<note>unable to handle picture of Windows format
                            media/image13.emf</note>Figure
                    7. Details of Botticelli’s differing drawing style within Inferno XXXIII, Purgatorio XIII, and Paradiso IX.</p>
            <p>Such a process — first clarifying a pattern through digital art-history methods,
                    and then augmenting that discovery through close visual analysis — illustrates the
                    symbiotic relationship between the scientific and the visual. Even so, the
                    utility of computational techniques within art history remains limited. As
                    Pamela Fletcher explains, digital tools function as “machines for thinking with,
                    rather than replacements for thinking”
                    <ptr target="#"/>(Fletcher
                    2015). All too often, researchers indiscriminately apply scientific approaches
                    to art history and publish their interpretations of the results, unconsciously
                    presupposing an unchangeable context of seeing. In other words, the original way
                    a work was viewed — what the art historian Michael Baxandall refers to as the
                    “period eye,” cultivated through exhaustive analysis of historical sources — can
                    differ dramatically from modern perspectives and so must be considered alongside
                    the data.<note> The
                            perils of scientific approaches to art history without proper period
                            context are perhaps most obviously manifest within recent studies of
                            portraiture, as discussed by Yael Rice and Sonja Drimmer. As an example,
                            Rice and Drimmer highlight a recent study on the Habsburg jaw. After an
                            analysis of sixty-six Habsburg family portraits, the study’s authors
                            conclude that the consistent presence of large jaws evidences
                            inbreeding. Yet, as Rice and Drimmer astutely note, within dynastic
                            portraiture, portrayal of the sitter with a feature distinctive to one
                            of the family’s ancestors helps reinforce the royal lineage. Indeed, the
                            painter’s aim was to legitimize, not accurately depict (although as Rice
                            and Drimmer emphasize the notion of “accuracy” itself varies across time
                            periods and geographies), his subject. By assuming that likeness
                            reflects reality, the study’s authors failed to incorporate their genres
                            context, thereby introducing critical bias into their research
                            (<ptr target="#"/>Rice
                            and Drimmer 2020).</note> Thus, although digital technologies make a
                    formidable addition to the modern art historian’s methodological toolset, they
                    merely complement, and cannot substitute for, deep knowledge and scholarly
                    investigation. Applying these considerations to the current study, while
                    heatmaps and statistical analysis make clear that Botticelli varied his mode of
                    representation by canticle, movement from observation to interpretation
                    necessitates the introduction of Quattrocento literary and artistic theory.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Interpreting Botticelli’s Thematic Patterns within a Quattrocento
                    Context</head>
            <p>Earlier <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> illuminators were bound by a textual
                    primacy that restricted and overshadowed their illustrations. Scribes would
                    leave gaps in the verse, and often provide written instructions to the
                    illuminator as well, thereby dictating the decision of <hi rend="italic">where</hi> and often even <hi rend="italic">how</hi> an artist could
                        work.<note> See
                            especially
                            <ptr target="#" loc="39-42"/>Alexander
                            1992, 39–42</note> But after Nicholas Jenson’s 1470 Roman font fixed
                    humanist handwriting in type of an unmatchable beauty and regularity, attention
                    shifted to pictorial interpretation of the text, as with illustration the
                    craftsman could still far exceed the printer.<note> Look to
                            <ptr target="#" loc="48"/>Davies
                            1996, 48</note> Botticelli’s codex, as an explosion of the book,
                    accentuates this cultural inversion: he banished the text to the rough <hi rend="italic">verso</hi>, and instead privileged the images on the smooth
                        <hi rend="italic">recto</hi>.<note> In codicology (the study of manuscripts), each
                            folio of parchment has two sides: the <hi rend="italic">verso</hi>
                            (back) and the
                            <hi rend="italic">recto </hi>(front). For vellum,
                            the <hi rend="italic">verso </hi>is the rough side
                            of the parchment leaf, while the
                            <hi rend="italic">recto </hi>is smooth and more
                            suited for detailed illustration. Indeed, the term <hi rend="italic">recto</hi> derives from the Latin <hi rend="italic">rectum</hi>
                            meaning “right” or “proper.” Look to
                            <ptr target="#" loc="21"/>(Lyons
                            2011, 21) It must be noted as well, however, that Botticelli’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Inferno I </hi>is sketched on the
                                <hi rend="italic">verso</hi>, since the famous <hi rend="italic">Chart of Hell</hi> occupies the <hi rend="italic">recto</hi>. For a
                            discussion of Botticelli’s format, see
                            <ptr target="#" loc="18"/>(Schulze
                            Altcappenberg 2000, 18)</note> If oriented horizontally, and bound
                    in a deluxe codex, the viewer would first encounter the drawings, and then the
                    text. To be sure, Botticelli incorporated elements of previous Dante manuscripts
                    into his designs. But of course, Botticelli was also well acquainted with
                    monumental panel painting, and inspired by the Renaissance spirit of
                    experimentation. Indeed, Botticelli models his topography of <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi> after Domenico di Michelino’s c. 1465 massive panel painting
                        <hi rend="italic">Dante Reading from the Divine Comedy</hi> in the north
                    aisle of the Florence Cathedral, where readings from the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> had been held since at least 1432.<note>
                  <ptr target="#"/>Rowlands
                            2003. For a study of the topography of Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, refer to
                            <ptr target="#"/>(Watts
                            1995)</note> Significantly, the aspect ratio (the ratio between the
                    width and the height) of Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> codex is
                    almost identical to that of his <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Birth of Venus</hi> panel paintings.<note> The aspect ratio of
                            Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> is 1.5:1, the same as that
                            of the <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi> (1.5:1), and very close to that
                            of the <hi rend="italic">Birth of Venus</hi> (1.6:1). Canonical
                            illuminated manuscripts, by contrast, have aspect ratios in the
                            neighborhood of 0.6:1. </note> Hence, while translating between
                    media, Botticelli suffused his work with remnants of his storied Florentine
                    panels to emancipate image from text and inflect his drawings with Renaissance
                        innovations.<note> Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> can further be understood
                            within the context of Florence’s posthumous reclamation of Dante.
                            Despite exiling the poet a mere century earlier, fifteenth-century
                            Florentine aristocrats clamored for the reunification of Dante’s body
                            and his birthplace. In 1430, the humanist and statesman Leonardo Bruni
                            petitioned for the return of Dante’s remains from Ravenna (where he died
                            in exile) to Florence. “This man’s glory is such that he undoubtedly
                            adds to the splendor and renown of our city,” Bruni writes.
                            <ptr target="#"/>(Cachey
                            1995)</note>
            </p>
            <p>Further, following the Renaissance ethos that “a painting is indeed nothing else
                    but a wordless poem,” scholarship on Botticelli’s panel paintings demonstrates
                    how the artist’s compositions and iconography innovatively reinterpret classical
                        sources.<note>
                            The Italian humanist Bartolomeo Fazio then continues, in his
                            Quattrocento treatise <hi rend="italic">De pictoribus</hi>: “For truly
                            almost equal attention is given by both to the invention and the
                            arrangement of their work.” Translation from
                            <ptr target="#" loc="98"/>(Baxandall
                            1964, 98) More broadly, Horace’s famous dictum — “Ut pictura poesis”;
                            literally, “a picture is like a poem” — anchored much of the Renaissance’s
                            revived interest in rhetoric’s visual manifestations (<hi rend="italic">Ars Poetica</hi>, Line 361). For the given translation, see
                            <ptr target="#" loc="480"/>(Horace
                            1926, 480)</note> Stanly Meltzoff, for instance, proposes that
                    Politian was the rhetor (or architect) for Botticelli’s c. 1494-95 panel
                    painting <hi rend="italic">Calumny of Apelles</hi>, advising the artist on which
                    moralizing vignettes to include, and how they ought to be represented, based on
                    precedent from classical sources (Figure 8;
                    <ptr target="#"/>Meltzoff
                    1987). The sixty-four visible
                    <hi rend="italic">rilievo schiacciato </hi>reliefs,
                    Meltzoff maintains, weave an intricate moral argument for the necessity of
                    beauty and eloquence within the liberal arts.<note> Such a statement, Meltzoff continues, was
                            needed given the ascetic friar Savonarola’s sermons advocating that even
                            Christian poetry and eloquence were mere pig swill, fit only for animal
                            natures
                            (<ptr target="#" loc="86"/>Meltzoff
                            1987, 86). <hi rend="italic">Rilievo schiacciato</hi> is a sculpting
                            technique that allows for flattened reliefs to represent convincing
                            spatial recession through optical illusion. </note> Ernst Gombrich
                    similarly relates Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi> (c. 1477–1482)
                    to the philosopher Ficino’s Neoplatonism, suggesting that the artist intended
                    the work to impart a didactic lesson to its rebellious patron, Lorenzo di
                    Pierfrancesco de’ Medici (Figure 9;
                    <ptr target="#"/>Gombrich
                    1945). Charles Dempsey expands on Gombrich’s thesis, arguing that in the <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi>, we witness the two great cultures of
                    Italy — ancient Latin and vernacular Tuscan — brought together in indissoluble
                    union. “Botticelli’s painting,” Dempsey writes, “is informed by such a fine
                    poetic instinct, combined with philological rigor and tact so exquisitely
                    deployed, that it produces its own aesthetic response”
                    <ptr target="#" loc="30"/>(Dempsey
                    1992, 30). </p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image15.jpeg"/>
               </figure>Figure
                    8. Sandro Botticelli, Calumny of Apelles, 1494-95. Tempera on panel. Florence, Uffizi.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head/>
                  <graphic url="media/image17.jpeg"/>
               </figure>Figure 9. Sandro Botticelli, <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi>, 1477–1482. Tempera on panel. Florence, Uffizi.</p>
            <p>It is reasonable to speculate, then, that Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> series also manifests contemporary poetic and literary
                    discourse. Taking Dante as his theme, Botticelli suffuses his <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> manuscript with the new Florentine culture birthed from
                    Lorenzo de’ Medici and amplified by the latter’s coterie of poets and
                    philosophers. If Politian was the architect of Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Calumny of Apelles</hi>, and Ficino instrumental for the <hi rend="italic">Primavera</hi>, might we hypothesize a rhetor for the <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> series?</p>
            <p>The likely candidate here is the humanist Cristoforo Landino, whose influential
                    Dante commentary and text, <hi rend="italic">Comento sopra la Comedia</hi>, was
                    printed in Florence in 1481.<note> For the full argument, summarized here, look to
                            <ptr target="#"/>Corley
                            2020. </note> Botticelli apparently pored over the <hi rend="italic">Comento</hi> with great attention. The artist’s own <hi rend="italic">Calumny</hi> composition derives from an ekphrasis found within Landino’s
                    text, and the edition was even published alongside preliminary engravings of
                    Botticelli’s series.<note> And yet, scholars have largely neglected Landino’s
                            commentary. As two thousand pages of Renaissance Tuscan, still
                            untranslated into modern Italian or English, Landino’s
                            <hi rend="italic">Comento </hi>is a formidable
                            tome. Moreover, the most comprehensive secondary source on Landino’s <hi rend="italic">Comento</hi>, Bruce McNair’s <hi rend="italic">Cristoforo Landino: His Work and Thought</hi>, was published in
                            2019, and hence previously unavailable
                            <ptr target="#"/>(McNair
                            2019). Botticelli’s adaption of Landino’s <hi rend="italic">Calumny</hi>
                            ekphrasis is first advanced in
                            <ptr target="#"/>Dressen
                            2017.</note> Therefore, Landino’s commentary presents a contextually
                    relevant parallel to Botticelli’s drawings that can augment computational
                        findings.<note>
                            Implicit in my argument is that the target audience for Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> drawings would be familiar with a whole
                            host of humanist texts, including Landino’s Florentine commentary.
                            Typically, this assumption of such a privileged viewer would not stand.
                            Margaret Miles, for example, emphasizes the need to “not focus on the
                            associations and interpretation of a viewer who was culturally or
                            educationally privileged in relation to most people in his culture”
                            (<ptr target="#" loc="28"/>Miles
                            1992, 28). Undeniably, I am suggesting just that! But, because we know
                            that the erudite aristocrat Lorenzo di Pierfrancesco de’ Medici
                            commissioned Botticelli’s drawings for, at least initially, his personal
                            collection, such an assumption holds. For a summary of the scholarship
                            on the drawings’ patronage, look to
                            <ptr target="#" loc="21"/>Schulze
                            Altcappenberg 2000, 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Study of the <hi rend="italic">Comento</hi> alongside the
                    <hi rend="italic">Commedia </hi>illustrations reveals how
                    Botticelli develops a pictorial expansion of Landino’s work that is every bit as
                    innovative and nuanced as its printed counterpart. According to Landino, Dante’s
                        <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> presents a nuanced allegory for the soul’s
                    ascension from sinful “disorder” to divine “order.” Gradually, Dante the Pilgrim
                    purges himself of vice and elevates his spirit from profane temptation
                    (“disorder”) to sacred grace (“order”). Misalignment of body and soul reigns in
                        <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, Landino maintains, while divine governance
                    facilitates penance
                    in<hi rend="italic"> Purgatorio </hi>(the most human of
                    domains), and all mundane structure dissolves under the ineffable radiance of
                        <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>.<note> Summarized from original primary-source study of
                            Landino’s text alongside Bruce McNair’s instructive monograph
                            <ptr target="#"/>(McNair
                            2019). </note> Landino’s incremental organization of the soul
                    relates strikingly to Botticelli’s calculated variation of his style and mode of
                    representation in his <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi>. Indeed, the heat maps and
                    statistical analysis suggest a familiar story: diffuse cacophony within <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, where members sequester themselves into discrete
                    paratactic spaces; meticulous harmony within <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>,
                    where social organization and divine forces guide both Botticelli’s compositions
                    and Dante’s penitents; and unity within <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>, where
                    earthly principles of structure and verse give way to a sublime simplicity. But
                    to say that Botticelli simply adapts Landino’s interpretations is to
                    dramatically understate the innovative and effective properties of the images.
                    While Botticelli finds inspiration in Landino’s allegorical treatment of Dante,
                    his ensuing explosion of the illuminated manuscript tradition is entirely novel
                    and unprecedented.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Conclusion</head>
            <p>Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commedia </hi>series, at once
                    literary exegesis and synoptic illustration, occupies an unmatched position
                    within Dante’s illuminated tradition. Later cycles, including those of Salvador
                    Dalí, William Blake, and Gustave Doré, adapt Dante’s text with their own unique
                    interpretations; however, they all build from Botticelli’s model by elevating
                    image over verse and departing from faithful representation to find visual
                    equivalents of the human phenomena that Dante the Pilgrim experiences.</p>
            <p>This paper applied an interdisciplinary approach involving both traditional
                    visual analysis and novel statistical methods to demonstrate that Botticelli
                    deviated from canonical manuscripts by adjusting his mode of representation to
                    the canticle at hand. Botticelli’s varying compositions, I propose, can be
                    understood through study of the series alongside Landino’s <hi rend="italic">Comento</hi>, presenting Botticelli’s manuscript as a pictorial expansion
                    of Landino’s exhaustive commentary. Digital tools thus enrich formal visual
                    analysis, providing a materially distinct way of “seeing” a work of art. We can
                    react to the emotive depth of Botticelli’s drawings, marvel at the master’s
                    treatment of line and form, and then, empowered by digital methodologies,
                    discuss cross-series compositional trends. </p>
            <p>However, the possible applications of digital techniques to art history, and even
                    to Botticelli’s <hi rend="italic">Commento</hi>, extend far beyond compositional
                    analysis. Future investigations could, for example, quantify Botticelli’s
                    handling of strokes, applying edge detection or morphological operators as
                    interpretive tools to describe and measure the line’s comparative weight,
                    curvature, and decisiveness. With recent advancements in machine learning,
                    scholars could even apply digital techniques to reinforce the connection between
                    Landino’s <hi rend="italic">Comento</hi> and Botticelli’s series. We’ve used
                    descriptive statistics to quantify <hi rend="italic">visual</hi> parataxis
                    (disharmony) within the drawings; we could similarly apply Large Language Models
                    to measure <hi rend="italic">textual</hi> parataxis within Landino’s work and
                    relate the two. Indeed, with the increasing number of digital tools available to
                    scholars, similar analyses will no doubt unearth previously unseen patterns
                    across all disciplines of the humanities, inviting careful qualitative research
                    and expert interpretation.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            <p>This paper derives from the 2020 Amherst College Honors Thesis, <hi rend="italic">The 'Art of Visible Speech': Illustration as Exegesis in Botticelli's
                        Commedia</hi>, which was awarded the Moseley Prize for best dissertation on
                    the subject of religion and the Anna Baker Heap prize for best essay in the
                    field of ‘Art’. In addition, this project benefited from the generous support of
                    Amherst College's Alpha Delta Phi fund, which allowed me to study the drawings
                    in the flesh in November 2019 at the Vatican Library in Rome and the
                    Kupferstichkabinett in Berlin. I am also indebted to the kind input and support
                    throughout this process from Nicola Courtright, Amherst College William McCall
                    Vickery 1957 Professor of the History of Art, and Yael Rice, Amherst College
                    Professor of Art &amp; the History of Art.</p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Appendix</head>
            <div>
               <head>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <graphic url="media/image19.png"/>
                  </figure>
               </head>
               <div>
                  <head>�<note>unable to handle picture of Windows format
                                    media/image20.emf</note>Supplemental Figure 1. Illustration of the geometric centroid
                                (labeled “G”) for the triangle ABC. Mathematically, the centroid is
                                the point where the medians intersect; or, equivalently, the
                                arithmetic mean position of all points within a figure.
                        </head>
                  <p>�<note>unable to handle picture here, no embed or
                                    link</note>Supplemental Figure
                            2. Flowchart for statistical analysis of illuminated manuscript illustrations. Describes the step-by-step process that each manuscript underwent in order to determine whether the compositions within Inferno, Purgatorio, and Paradiso differed statistically.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <head/>
                     <graphic url="media/image21.png"/>
                  </figure>
                  <p>Supplemental Figure 3. Graphical
                            representation of the post-hoc Tukey HSD test performed on Botticelli’s
                                <hi rend="italic">Commedia</hi> series. The boundaries indicate 95%
                            confidence intervals — tellingly, none of them cover zero. The p-values
                            for the combinations were all extremely small, allowing for rejection of
                            the null hypothesis. Thus, the mean distance to the centroid differed
                            significantly for all possible combinations. </p>
                  <p>Mean and Standard
                                Deviation for Each Manuscript Series</p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Inferno <hi rend="italic">(cm)</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Purgatorio <hi rend="italic">(cm)</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell>Paradiso <hi rend="italic">(cm)</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Holkham Misc. 48</cell>
                        <cell>4.55 (1.16) </cell>
                        <cell>4.30 (1.20)</cell>
                        <cell>4.88 (1.95)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Yates Thompson 36</cell>
                        <cell>7.42 (0.70)</cell>
                        <cell>7.41 (0.99)</cell>
                        <cell>7.02 (1.31)</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Botticelli</cell>
                        <cell>12.4 (1.67)</cell>
                        <cell>10.1 (1.54)</cell>
                        <cell>4.03 (2.64)</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>Supplemental Table 1. Data table of the mean
                            distance to the centroid (standard deviation in parenthesis) for each
                            canticle of the three manuscripts analyzed. Botticelli’s manuscript, the
                            data suggests, is the only one where the mean varies substantially. </p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <p>One-way ANOVA Analysis
                                for Each Manuscript Series</p>
                  <table>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell/>
                        <cell>Degrees of Freedom</cell>
                        <cell>F value</cell>
                        <cell>P value</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Holkham Misc. 48</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>0.2869</cell>
                        <cell> 0.751</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Yates Thompson 36</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>1.297</cell>
                        <cell>0.279</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row role="data">
                        <cell>Botticelli</cell>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>129.3</cell>
                        <cell>2.20 • 10–16</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
                  <p>Supplemental Table 2. One-way ANOVA output
                            analyzing the impact of the categorical variable canticle on the mean
                            distance to the centroid. A significant effect was observed only for
                            Botticelli’s manuscript, whereas no others were significant at any
                            level. </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Statistical Techniques</head>
            <p>One-way ANOVA: One-way ANOVA is a statistical test
                    used to determine whether there are any statistically significant differences
                    between the means of three or more independent groups. In our study, these
                    groups are represented by Botticelli's three canticles: <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi>. In this case, the null hypothesis is that there is no
                    significant difference between the means of the canticles, suggesting that
                    Botticelli's compositional approach is consistent across the series. If the <hi rend="italic">p</hi>-value is less than a predefined significance level
                    (usually 0.05), we reject the null hypothesis in favor of the alternative: the
                    canticles are compositionally distinct. One key limitation of ANOVA is that
                    while it can detect differences between groups, it does not specify which groups
                    are different. Another consideration is the assumption of normality and equal
                    variances in the data, which if not met, may lead to erroneous conclusions.</p>
            <p>Post-hoc Fukey HST: To address the limitations of
                    ANOVA, the post-hoc Fukey Honestly Significant Test (HST) was applied as well.
                    This test is designed to compare all possible pairs of means to ascertain which
                    specific groups differ significantly. In our study, we compare <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi> vs. <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi> vs. <hi rend="italic">Inferno</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">Paradiso</hi> vs. <hi rend="italic">Purgatorio</hi>. If a significant
                    difference is found, it suggests that the mode of representation is
                    significantly different between those canticles. The strength of the Fukey HST
                    is that it controls the experiment-wide error rate, reducing the chance of
                    making Type I errors (false positives). It's important to note that post-hoc
                    tests, including Fukey HST, rely on the initial ANOVA to indicate that
                    differences exist among groups. If the ANOVA is not significant, performing
                    post-hoc tests is statistically inadvisable.</p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Works Cited</head>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/A6WR5BTM">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Medieval illuminators and their methods of work</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>J. J. G.</forename>
                        <surname>Alexander</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-0-300-05689-1</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>New Haven, CT</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1992">1992</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>Alighieri, D. (1996) <title rend="italic">The divine
                    comedy</title>. Translated and edited by M. Musa. Indiana Masterpiece Edition.
                    Bloomington, IN: Indiana University Press.</bibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/AYDL6QDR">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Words, Patterns and Documents: Experiments in Machine Learning and Text Analysis</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Shlomo</forename>
                        <surname>Argamon</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mark</forename>
                        <surname>Olsen</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">003</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                     <date when="2009-6-18">2009-6-18</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/SRRMNSSW">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Bartholomaeus Facius on Painting: A Fifteenth-Century Manuscript of the De Viris Illustribus</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Baxandall</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.2307/750513</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">90-107</biblScope>
                     <date when="1964">1964</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>Brey, A. (2017) 'Quantifying the Quran', in Muhanna, E. (ed.)
                        <title rend="italic">The digital humanities and Islamic &amp; Middle East
                        studies</title>. Berlin: De Gruyter, pp. 151-174.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cachey, T. J. (1995) <title rend="italic">Renaissance Dante in
                        print (1472–1629)</title>. Notre Dame, IN: University of Notre Dame
                    Library.</bibl>
            <bibl>Corley, N. (2020)
                    <title rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">The ‘art of visible speech’: Illustration as exegesis in </title>Botticelli’s
                        Commedia<title rend="italic">.</title> Honors thesis. Amherst College.</bibl>
            <bibl>Davies, M. (1996) 'Humanism in script and print in the
                    fifteenth century', in Kraye, J. (ed.) <title rend="italic">The Cambridge companion
                        to Renaissance humanism</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, pp.
                    47–62.</bibl>
            <bibl>Dempsey, C. (1992) <title rend="italic">The portrayal of love:
                        Botticelli’s primavera and humanist culture at the time of Lorenzo the
                        Magnificent</title>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press.</bibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/CS9U3KV7">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" xml:lang="de; en">From Dante to Landino: Botticelli's Calumny of Apelles and its Sources</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Angela</forename>
                        <surname>Dressen</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" xml:lang="de; en">Mitteilungen des Kunsthistorischen Institutes in Florenz</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">324-339</biblScope>
                     <date when="2017">2017</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>Drimmer, S. (2019) Conversation with Nathaniel Corley, 25
                    September.</bibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/9UJILSJ5">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Excavations of Parthian Human Bone Remains at Liyarsangbon Cemetery, Amlash District, Guilan Province, Iran: with Special Reference to Sexed Patterns of Burial and Gender Discrimination</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mohammad Reza</forename>
                        <surname>Eghdami</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Vali</forename>
                        <surname>Jahani</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Majid Gholamzadeh</forename>
                        <surname>Roudbordeh</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Seyed Hashem</forename>
                        <surname>Mousavi</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Near Eastern Archaeology</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.1086/724787</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">122-131</biblScope>
                     <date when="2023-6">2023-6</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>Fletcher, P. (2015) 'Reflections on digital art history', <title rend="italic">College Art Association Reviews</title>, 18 June.
                    http://doi.org/10.3202/caa.reviews.2015.73.</bibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/ZI6TJ4ZM">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Botticelli's Mythologies: A Study in the Neoplatonic Symbolism of His Circle</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>E. H.</forename>
                        <surname>Gombrich</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.2307/750165</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">7-60</biblScope>
                     <date when="1945">1945</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/9UNYVUW8">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Ars Poetica</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename/>
                        <surname>Horace</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1926">1926</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Loeb Classical Library 194</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>Jacoff, R. (2018) 'Rachel Jacoff: Hell is other people in
                    Dante’s <title rend="italic">Inferno', Los Angeles Review of Books</title>, 18
                    February. Available at:
                    https://lareviewofbooks.org/entitled-opinions/rachel-jacoff-hell-people-dantes-inferno/.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lansing, R. (2010) <title rend="italic">The Dante
                        encyclopedia</title>. New York: Routledge.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lippmann, F. (1896)
                    <title rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Drawings by Sandro Botticelli for Dante’s </title>Divine
                    Comedy. London: Lawrence and Bullen.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lookman, S. T. (2017) <title rend="italic">Reconsidering the
                        Dante series: Botticelli’s artistic process as a deconstruction of Vasarian
                        linearity</title>. Honors thesis. Wesleyan University.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lyons, M. (2011) <title rend="italic">Books: A living
                        history</title>. Los Angeles: J. Paul Getty Museum.</bibl>
            <bibl>McNair, B. (2019) <title rend="italic">Cristoforo Landino: His
                        works and thought</title>. Medieval and Renaissance Authors and Texts. Leiden,
                    Netherlands: Brill.</bibl>
            <bibl>Meltzoff, S. (1987) <title rend="italic">Botticelli, Signorelli
                        and Savonarola: Theologia poetica and painting from Boccaccio to
                        Poliziano</title>. Biblioteca di “Lettere italiane” 33. Florence: L.S.
                    Olschki.</bibl>
            <bibl>Miles, M. R. (1992) 'The virgin’s one bare breast', in N.
                    Broude and M.D. Garrard (eds.) <title rend="italic">The expanding discourse:
                        Feminism and art history</title>. 1st edn. New York: Icon Editions.</bibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/WHC8UYJL">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" xml:lang="it">Delle condizioni e delle vicende della Libreria Medicea privata dal 1494 al 1508</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Enea</forename>
                        <surname>Piccolomini</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" xml:lang="it">Archivio Storico Italiano</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">79</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">101-129</biblScope>
                     <date when="1874">1874</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/EY7HDCWP">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Facing Facts: How Scientists Use and Abuse Portraiture</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Yael</forename>
                        <surname>Rice</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Sonja</forename>
                        <surname>Drimmer</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Hyperallergic</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2020">2020</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/YNN7XB28">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Domenico di Michelino</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Eliot W.</forename>
                        <surname>Rowlands</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Oxford Art Online</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.1093/gao/9781884446054.article.T023183</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2003">2003</date>
                     <note type="url">https://www.oxfordartonline.com/groveart/view/10.1093/gao/9781884446054.001.0001/oao-9781884446054-e-7000023183</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <bibl>Schulze Altcappenberg, H. T.. (2000) '"Per essere persona
                    sofistica": Botticelli’s drawings for the <title rend="italic">Divine Comedy</title>',
                    in In
                    <title rend="italic" xml:space="preserve">Sandro Botticelli: The drawings for Dante’s </title>Divine
                    Comedy. London: Royal Academy Publications.</bibl>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/4T2BC4QA">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Sandro Botticelli's Drawings for Dante's "Inferno": Narrative Structure, Topography, and Manuscript Design</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Barbara J.</forename>
                        <surname>Watts</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Artibus et Historiae</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.2307/1483567</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">32</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">163-201</biblScope>
                     <date when="1995">1995</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/XB4GVUHG">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Dendrography and Art History: a computer-assisted analysis of Cézanne’s Bathers.</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Melinda</forename>
                        <surname>Weinstein</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Edward</forename>
                        <surname>Voss</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>David</forename>
                        <surname>Soll</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">013</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                     <date when="2019-10-14">2019-10-14</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <!-- Entries below were cited but could not be matched to Zotero's bibliography -->
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/ZG72V2KN">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The Dante Encyclopedia</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Richard</forename>
                        <surname>Lansing</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-1-136-84972-5</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Routledge</publisher>
                     <date when="2010">2010</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/AVMJV4P3">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" xml:lang="it; en">Botticelli, Signorelli and Savonarola: Theologia Poetica and Painting from Boccaccio to Poliziano</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Stanley</forename>
                        <surname>Meltzoff</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-88-222-3494-0</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>L.S. Olschki</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Florence, Italy</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1987">1987</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Biblioteca di "Lettere italiane"</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/9MAWHLGQ">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Books: a living history</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Martyn</forename>
                        <surname>Lyons</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-1-60606-083-4</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>J. Paul Getty Museum</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Los Angeles, CA</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2011">2011</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/QNS3DK94">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The portrayal of love: Botticelli's Primavera and humanist culture at the time of Lorenzo the Magnificent</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Charles</forename>
                        <surname>Dempsey</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-0-691-03207-8</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Princeton University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Princeton, NJ</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1992">1992</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/CS9U3KV7">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" xml:lang="de; en">From Dante to Landino: Botticelli's Calumny of Apelles and its Sources</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Angela</forename>
                        <surname>Dressen</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" xml:lang="de; en">Mitteilungen des Kunsthistorischen Institutes in Florenz</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">59</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">324-339</biblScope>
                     <date when="2017">2017</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/AYDL6QDR">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Words, Patterns and Documents: Experiments in Machine Learning and Text Analysis</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Shlomo</forename>
                        <surname>Argamon</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mark</forename>
                        <surname>Olsen</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">003</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                     <date when="2009-6-18">2009-6-18</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/A86MHC8R">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Drawings by Sandro Botticelli for Dante's Divine Comedy</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Friedrich</forename>
                        <surname>Lippmann</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Lawrence and Bullen</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London, England and New York, NY</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1896">1896</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/BLKXIC6F">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Cristoforo Landino: his works and thought</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Bruce</forename>
                        <surname>McNair</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-90-04-38952-6</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Brill</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Leiden, The Netherlands and Boston, MA</pubPlace>
                     <date when="2019">2019</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Medieval and Renaissance authors and texts</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="thesis"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/LCMTY69H">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Reconsidering the Dante Series: Botticelli's Artistic Process as a Deconstruction of Vasarian Linearity</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Sharifa Turab</forename>
                        <surname>Lookman</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Wesleyan University</publisher>
                     <date when="2017">2017</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/A6WR5BTM">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Medieval illuminators and their methods of work</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>J. J. G.</forename>
                        <surname>Alexander</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-0-300-05689-1</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Yale University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>New Haven, CT</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1992">1992</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="chapter"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/SEB3JW6B">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Humanism in script and print in the fifteenth century</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Martin</forename>
                        <surname>Davies</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The Cambridge Companion to Renaissance Humanism</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Jill</forename>
                        <surname>Kraye</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-0-521-43624-3</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="page">47-62</biblScope>
                     <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, England</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1996">1996</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Cambridge Companions to Literature</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/9UJILSJ5">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Excavations of Parthian Human Bone Remains at Liyarsangbon Cemetery, Amlash District, Guilan Province, Iran: with Special Reference to Sexed Patterns of Burial and Gender Discrimination</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mohammad Reza</forename>
                        <surname>Eghdami</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Vali</forename>
                        <surname>Jahani</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Majid Gholamzadeh</forename>
                        <surname>Roudbordeh</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Seyed Hashem</forename>
                        <surname>Mousavi</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Near Eastern Archaeology</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.1086/724787</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">86</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">122-131</biblScope>
                     <date when="2023-6">2023-6</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/ZI6TJ4ZM">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Botticelli's Mythologies: A Study in the Neoplatonic Symbolism of His Circle</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>E. H.</forename>
                        <surname>Gombrich</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.2307/750165</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">7-60</biblScope>
                     <date when="1945">1945</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/YNN7XB28">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Domenico di Michelino</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Eliot W.</forename>
                        <surname>Rowlands</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Oxford Art Online</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.1093/gao/9781884446054.article.T023183</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2003">2003</date>
                     <note type="url">https://www.oxfordartonline.com/groveart/view/10.1093/gao/9781884446054.001.0001/oao-9781884446054-e-7000023183</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/EG5J3ZAH">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" xml:lang="engita">The Divine Comedy</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename/>
                        <surname>Dante Alighieri</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mark</forename>
                        <surname>Musa</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <idno type="ISBN">978-0-253-32968-4</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
                     <publisher>Indiana University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Bloomington, IN</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1996">1996</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Indiana Masterpiece Editions</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/4T2BC4QA">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Sandro Botticelli's Drawings for Dante's "Inferno": Narrative Structure, Topography, and Manuscript Design</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Barbara J.</forename>
                        <surname>Watts</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Artibus et Historiae</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.2307/1483567</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">32</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">163-201</biblScope>
                     <date when="1995">1995</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="chapter"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/QCCLKYFN">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">The Virgin's One Bare Breast</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Margaret R.</forename>
                        <surname>Miles</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The Expanding Discourse: Feminism and Art History</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Norma</forename>
                        <surname>Broude</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Mary D.</forename>
                        <surname>Garrard</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Icon Editions</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>New York, NY</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1992">1992</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/9UNYVUW8">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Ars Poetica</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename/>
                        <surname>Horace</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1926">1926</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Loeb Classical Library 194</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="book"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/MK56CJNN">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Renaissance Dante in Print (1472–1629)</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Theodore J.</forename>
                        <surname>Cachey</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>University of Notre Dame Library</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>Notre Dame, IN</pubPlace>
                     <date when="1995">1995</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/TZFKXRQG">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Quantifying the Quran</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Alex</forename>
                        <surname>Brey</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The Digital Humanities and Islamic &amp; Middle East Studies</title>
                  <editor>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Elias</forename>
                        <surname>Muhanna</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2017">2017</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="song"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/76Z99HZT">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Rachel Jacoff: Hell is Other People in Dante’s Inferno</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Rachel</forename>
                        <surname>Jacoff</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Los Angeles Review of Books</publisher>
                     <date when="2018">2018</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Entitled Opinions</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/I9DVBKJ3">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Reflections on Digital Art History</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Pamela</forename>
                        <surname>Fletcher</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">College Art Association</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">doi.org/10.3202/caa.reviews.2015.73</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2015-6-18">2015-6-18</date>
                     <note type="url">http://www.caareviews.org/reviews/2726</note>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Field Editors’ Reflections</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/XB4GVUHG">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Dendrography and Art History: a computer-assisted analysis of Cézanne’s Bathers.</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Melinda</forename>
                        <surname>Weinstein</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Edward</forename>
                        <surname>Voss</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>David</forename>
                        <surname>Soll</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">013</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
                     <date when="2019-10-14">2019-10-14</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="chapter"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/CRZXQWAL">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">&lt;span class="nocase"&gt;'Per essere persona sofistica':&lt;/span&gt; Botticelli's Drawings for the &lt;i&gt;Divine Comedy&lt;/i&gt;</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Hein-Thomas</forename>
                        <surname>Schulze Altcappenberg</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Sandro Botticelli: The Drawings for Dante's Divine Comedy</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2000">2000</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/WHC8UYJL">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a" xml:lang="it">Delle condizioni e delle vicende della Libreria Medicea privata dal 1494 al 1508</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Enea</forename>
                        <surname>Piccolomini</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m" xml:lang="it">Archivio Storico Italiano</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">19</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="issue">79</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">101-129</biblScope>
                     <date when="1874">1874</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/SRRMNSSW">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Bartholomaeus Facius on Painting: A Fifteenth-Century Manuscript of the De Viris Illustribus</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Michael</forename>
                        <surname>Baxandall</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Journal of the Warburg and Courtauld Institutes</title>
                  <idno type="DOI">10.2307/750513</idno>
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">27</biblScope>
                     <biblScope unit="page">90-107</biblScope>
                     <date when="1964">1964</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="thesis"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/UD2YQ2W6">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">The 'Art of Visible Speech': Illustration as Exegesis in Botticelli's &lt;i&gt;Commedia&lt;/i&gt;</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Nathaniel</forename>
                        <surname>Corley</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <imprint>
                     <publisher>Amherst College honors thesis</publisher>
                     <date when="2020">2020</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id=""
                        type="articleJournal"
                        corresp="http://zotero.org/users/5916578/items/EY7HDCWP">
               <analytic>
                  <title level="a">Facing Facts: How Scientists Use and Abuse Portraiture</title>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Yael</forename>
                        <surname>Rice</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
                  <author>
                     <persName>
                        <forename>Sonja</forename>
                        <surname>Drimmer</surname>
                     </persName>
                  </author>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title level="m">Hyperallergic</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <date when="2020">2020</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
