<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en"><!--article title in English-->Lessons from the
               Library: Extreme Minimalist Scaling at Pirate Ebook Platforms</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <dhq:author_name>Martin Paul <dhq:family>Eve</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID"
                  ><!--if the author has an ORCID ID, include the full URI, e.g. https://orcid.org/0000-0000-0000-0000-->https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5589-8511</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Birkbeck College, University of London</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>martin.eve@bbk.ac.uk</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Martin Paul Eve is the Professor of Literature of Literature, Technology, and Publishing at the University of London's Birkbeck College. He is also a founder of the Open Library of Humanities. </p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000587</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->2</idno>
         	<date when="2022-06-25">25 June 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
      	<change>The version history for this file can be found on <ref target=
      		"https://github.com/Digital-Humanities-Quarterly/dhq-journal/commits/master/articles/000587/000587.xml">GitHub
      	</ref></change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>At 33TB of data in its main collection, the highly illegal Library Genesis project is
               one of the largest repositories of copyright-violating educational ebooks ever
               created. Established over a decade ago in 2008, the goal of Library Genesis is nothing
               short of a modern Library of Alexandria, albeit without anyone’s legal sanction. As
               one of its administrators wrote: <quote rend="inline">within decades, generations of
                  people everywhere in the world will grow up with access to the best scientific
                  texts of all time. [...] [T]he quality and accessibility of education to the poor
                  will grow dramatically too. Frankly, I see this as the only way to naturally
                  improve mankind: we need to make all the information available to them at any
                  time</quote>
               <ptr target="#bodo2018b"/>. Rooted in its homeland’s Russian communist principles and
               particularly the Soviet isolationist copyright policies of the twentieth century,
               Library Genesis is a formidable resource and threat to conventional academic publishers.</p>
            <p>The Library Genesis database had just short of 1.2m records (books) in 2014 <ptr
                  target="#bodo2018a"/>. As of January 2020, this capacity has doubled to 2.5m
               books. In this article, I examine the minimal computational design choices taken
               by this maximal-in-intent, illicit archive of epistemological dissent and how such
               decisions have shaped the scalability and growth of the platform. This includes
               Library Genesis’s numerical subdivision of record identifiers into <q>buckets</q> to work around
               directory file limitations in the GNU/Linux operating system; its use of md5 hashing
               of filenames within directories capped at 1,000 files to avoid future hashing
               collisions while allowing for on-disk integrity checking; and its use of the MySQL
               socket/network server as opposed to SQLite or similar disk-based database.</p>
            <p>Beyond these computational details, though, the theoretical tension that this article
               highlights is the path dependencies that are set in (illegal) computational projects
               that have goals of absolute abundance and maximalist capacity, and the minimalist
               design principles that they must instigate at the outset to ensure a degree of
               scalability. I also query the ways in which the project’s contested mission
               statements target an economic (geographic) audience demographic with only minimalist
               access to high-capacity computing resources. I finally examine the limits on
               scalability of the distribution of the Library Genesis through its torrent archive
               and other distributed networking technologies such as IPFS, which despite their
               promise of peer-to-peer redundancy fall down on an archive of this size.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p>This article examines the limits on scalability of the distribution of the Library
               Genesis through its torrent archive and other distributed networking technologies
               such as IFS, which despite their promise of peer-to-peer redundancy fall down on an
               archive of this size.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <p>Minimalist computing principles in scholarly communications focus on the moderation
               of digital resource consumption and global social equity <ptr target="#sayers2016"
                  />.<note> I would like to extend my thanks in this article to the anonymous
                  readers at <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> who prompted me to rethink the scope
                  and scale of this work, as well as to the editors of the special issue. Work on
                  this article was funded by a Philip Leverhulme Prize from the Leverhulme
                  Trust.</note> Such an application of minimalist principles to computing is
               designed both to make the global flow of digital information accessible<emph>
                  to</emph> the widest audiences and to allow the broadest set of people to
               participate in the creation <emph>of</emph> such resources. By minimizing the
               resource constraints required to run computational architectures, minimalist
               computing principles work to ensure that the world is not falsely separated into a
               Global <q>expert</q> North and a Global <q>apprentice</q> South, in which those with
               resources merely export digital expertise outwards from a claimed center to the
               supposed margins <ptr target="#gil2016" loc="29, 23"/>. Minimalist computational
               principles are designed for inclusivity.</p>
            <p> By contrast, contemporary models of scholarly communication — the composite systems
               through which academics and other intellectuals disseminate their findings for global
               consumption — appear to be the opposite of minimalist. They cover a full and
               ever-expanding disciplinary range, from natural scientific outputs, to humanistic
               arguments, to social scientific research. Their social processes and techniques are
               vast, involving peer review systems, citations, references, and footnotes <ptr
                  target="#grafton1999"/>
               <ptr target="#fyfe2015"/>
               <ptr target="#moxham2018"/>. The technical elements of such systems also tend to
               proliferate, including platforms, persistent identifiers, XML standards, digital
               preservation systems, and manuscript management technologies <ptr target="#gray2020"/>
               <ptr target="#andrews2020"/>. </p>
            <p>The costs involved in these dissemination systems are also maximal. Since the 1980s,
               rising in line with the expansion of higher education, the cost of subscribing to
               academic serials has outpaced inflation by approximately 6% every year <ptr
                  target="#bosch2018"/>, while library budgets have faced cuts or remained flat <ptr
                  target="#jurchen2020" loc="161"/>. Over forty years, this amounts to a
               several-hundredfold price increase. A discourse of maximalism and growth seems
               omnipresent in scholarly communications.</p>
            <p> These maximalist principles in scholarly communications have resulted in well-known
               damaging consequences and inequalities. For instance, Thomas Mboa Nkoudou notes the
               spread of an <soCalled>epistemic alienation</soCalled> when researchers at the
                  <q>margins</q> of the Global North’s publication systems must conform to external
               pressures and norms <ptr target="#mboa2020"/>. As another example, peer review is
               supposed to be a system that distinguishes work based solely on merit rather than any
               identity characteristic of the author. However, critics of this system note that
               pre-publication peer review favors those for whom English is their first language
                  <ptr target="#moore2017"/>
               <ptr target="#eve2021"/>. Further evidence of biases from peer review includes the
               extraordinary fact that just 1.5% of economics articles in highly ranked journals
               were about countries other than the United States <ptr target="#das2013" loc="112"/>
               <ptr target="#roh2020" loc="43"/>. </p>
            <p> The spiraling, maximalist costs of the for-profit subscription scholarly publication
               ecosystem also price out much of the world’s population <ptr target="#kapczynski2010"/>
               <ptr target="#androcec2017"/>
               <ptr target="#boudry2019"/>. It is in part this inequality that has spurred the open
               access movement (OA) for research, which seeks to abolish paywalls <ptr
                  target="#chan2002"/>
               <ptr target="#berlin2003"/>
               <ptr target="#suber2003"/>
               <ptr target="#fitzpatrick2011"/>
               <ptr target="#suber2012"/>
               <ptr target="#eve2014"/>. Yet even this movement has come under fire. Built on the
               premise that nobody, worldwide, should be excluded from access to the scholarly
               record by their (in)ability to pay and that the benefits of re-use should be broadly
               extended to third parties using Creative Commons licenses, the road to OA was paved
               with noble intentions. As Ulrich Herb notes, open access was originally <quote
                  rend="inline">embedded in a conceptual ensemble of participation, democratisation,
                  digital commons and equality</quote>
               <ptr target="#herb2018" loc="69"/>. However, parts of this vision have died over
               time. <quote rend="inline">Nowadays,</quote> Herb writes, <quote rend="inline">Open
                  access seems to be exclusive: to the extent that commercial players have
                  discovered it as a business model and article fees have become a defining feature
                  of gold open access, open access has increasingly transformed into a
                  distinguishing feature and an exclusive element</quote>
               <ptr target="#herb2018" loc="69"/>.</p>
            <p> Thus, the contemporary scholarly communications environment has many defects that
               pertain to inequality and that intersect with its maximalist characteristics. Given
               the goals of minimalist computing, rooted in equity and diversity, might it be
               possible for our scholarly communications to learn from such principles? Is there a
               way in which ideas of <quote rend="inline">scaling small</quote>
               <ptr target="#adema2021"/> might help these systems to contend, as Roopika Risam puts
               it, <quote rend="inline">Not only with the colonial hangovers from the cultural
                  record, but also with forces that are actively constructing the medium of the
                  digital cultural record — the Internet — as a hostile environment</quote>
               <ptr target="#risam2018" loc="6"/>?</p>
            <p> In the remainder of this article I turn to a specific illicit scholarly
               communications practice that has emerged in recent years: the idea of the
                  <soCalled>pirate</soCalled> shadow library. These archives, which violate
               copyright, work around paywalls and provide access to all comers. Although frequently
               on the wrong side of the law, shadow library operators conceive of their sites in
               ethical terms. Framing their banditry in terms of a Robin Hood-esque outfit, such
               sites believe they are robbing from the rich to give to the scholarly poor <ptr
                  target="#faust2016"/> (see also <ptr target="#hobsbawm1981"/>). Importantly for
               the themes of this special issue, I believe that such archives can also be understood
               in certain terms of computational minimalism. As I will go on to detail, various
               technical design principles of these archives lower social barriers to participation.
               This article thus sets out a fresh theoretical terrain for understanding what I call
                  <q>minimal-maximal tensions</q> in computational architectures and projects. While
               this discourse is rooted in older information technology debates about microkernels
               versus macrokernels <ptr target="#tanenbaum2008"/>, through my case study of Library
               Genesis — the shadow library that is the main focus of this article — I seek to
               unpack a new framework for thinking about the relationships between minimal
               components and maximal outcomes. While Library Genesis seeks to <q>shadow</q> an
               enormous archive, the constraints under which it operates lead to a series of
               unexpected minimalist design principles.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The Growth and Emergence of Shadow Libraries</head>
            <p>Shadow libraries — pirate archives of copyrighted scholarly publications — emerged in
               response to a frustration at the slow growth of open access <ptr target="#green2017"/>
               <ptr target="#brembs2020"/>. Nonetheless, open-access advocates remain divided as to
               whether these <soCalled>guerilla</soCalled> libraries are a solution to, or merely a
               symptom of, the ills of scholarly communication <ptr target="#swartz2015"/>
               <ptr target="#hockenberry2013"/>
               <ptr target="#faust2016"/>
               <ptr target="#machinmastromatteo2016"/>. The two most famous (and interlinked) of
               these systems for illicit access to pirate scholarship as of 2022 are Sci-Hub and
               Library Genesis.</p>
            <p> The former, Sci-Hub, is a credential-proxying site that bypasses publisher paywalls,
               primarily for journal articles. Founded by Alexandra Elbakyan in 2011, the site has
               grown to provide access to at least 68.9% of the 81.6 million scholarly articles
               registered with Crossref and to 85.1% of all articles published in subscription
               journals <ptr target="#himmelstein2018"/>. The site is based in Kazakhstan, which
               introduces complex jurisdictional legal issues. It works by collecting credentials
               from academic institutions, possibly by conducting phishing attacks <ptr
                  target="#russell2017"/>. These credentials are then used to fetch any article
               requested by an end-user. In order to reduce the number of requests to publishers’
               sites — and thereby evade detection and a ban on its credentials — Sci-Hub caches
               fetched journal articles in an archive called Library Genesis. Sci-Hub has faced and
               lost several court cases, particularly in the U.S. where the publisher Elsevier has
               been awarded millions of dollars in damages <ptr target="#schiermeier2017"/>. Because
               the site sits outside of U.S. jurisdiction and because Elbakyan has no means of
               paying such damages, it is unlikely that publishers will see any financial return
               from these lawsuits. Nonetheless, for much of 2021, Elbakyan paused the ingestion of
               new articles while awaiting the results of a court case in India, which could rule in
               Sci-Hub’s favor <ptr target="#reddy2021"/>.</p>
            <p> Library Genesis, by contrast, is the largest and oldest shadow archive on the
               Internet. With over thirty-three terabytes of data in its primary book collection
               (and more than sixty terabytes in its pool of scientific journal articles powered by
               its aforementioned sister project, Sci-Hub), the project is one of the largest
               repositories of copyright-violating educational ebooks ever created <ptr
                  target="#bodo2020c"/>. Established in 2008, the goal of Library Genesis is nothing
               short of a totalizing modern Library of Alexandria, albeit without legal sanction. As
               one of its administrators wrote, emphasizing its extralegal, yet claimed moral and
               ethical, status: <quote rend="inline">Within decades, generations of people
                  everywhere in the world will grow up with access to the best scientific texts of
                  all time.... [T]he quality and accessibility of education to the poor will grow
                  dramatically too. Frankly, I see this as the only way to naturally improve
                  mankind: we need to make all the information available to them at any time</quote>
               <ptr target="#bodo2018b" loc="25"/>.<note> It is worth noting that some of the
                  secondary accounts of Library Genesis can tip over into hagiographic commentary,
                  an angle that I seek to avoid here.</note> Philosophically rooted in the communist
               principles of its homeland, Russia, and particularly in the Soviet isolationist
               copyright policies of the 20th century <ptr target="#bodo2018b"/>, Library
               Genesis is a formidable resource and a large-scale threat to conventional academic
               publishers <ptr target="#green2017"/>.</p>
            <p> Shadow libraries differ in their models, usage patterns, and effects. The Z-library
               system, for instance, charges for specific formats, such as Amazon Kindle conversion
                  <ptr target="#dulong2021"/>. Other pirate libraries such as Library Genesis have
               no charges at all and their funding mechanisms are unknown, leading to accusations of
               state subterfuge, although they do use advertising <ptr target="#harris2019"/>. While
               the total percentage of the market eaten by piracy is unknown, in the general ebook
               space some studies have shown that as many as 35.1% of books are downloaded illegally
                  <ptr target="#camarero2014"/>. What is clear from existing studies of Library
               Genesis is that it is used by participants worldwide, including in wealthier regions
               of the Global North <ptr target="#bohannon2016"/>
               <ptr target="#till2019"/>. Various studies have also shown a citation advantage to
               papers that appear in Sci-Hub <ptr target="#correa2021"/>. However, considering the
               prevalence of material in this archive, this effect could simply be due to the
               difficulty of obtaining the original papers.</p>
            <p> Given that Sci-Hub and Library Genesis are <emph>shadows</emph> of the formalised
               academic publication system, we might expect them to share the maximalist tendencies
               of mainstream scholarly communications systems. These libraries are, indeed,
               enormous. Yet what it means to be a <q>shadow</q> has changed over time. It was not
               until the 18th century that the shadow became defined as the colorless inverse image
               of the object itself. Before this point, shadows were represented, in art and
               heraldry, as a partial transparency and outline. In heraldic terms, shadows represent
               an outlined shape that reveals a hidden part of the family tree, not a mirror of it
                  <ptr target="#pastoureau2003" loc="26–7"/>. That is, shadows can be seen as a
               shameful family link, rather than a precise formal reflection, and such a history
               reminds us, as Nanna Bonde Thylstrup puts it, of the <quote rend="inline">inherently
                  unstable form of shadow libraries as a cultural construct</quote>
               <ptr target="#thylstrup2018" loc="98"/>. In this light, there are several
               characteristics of shadow libraries that present minimalist design principles and
               that we can take as refractive and instructive lenses for understanding mainstream
               practices.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Minimalist Shadows</head>
            <p>Just what, then, is minimalist about these shadow libraries? Certainly, they are
               minimalist in terms of the <q>minimal barriers</q> that they present to their
               readership for access to scholarly publications. In eliminating paywalls and
               presenting only a flat search box, with no authentication mechanisms, Sci-Hub and
               Library Genesis are far simpler than the systems used by formal publishers. By
               contrast, these archives are <emph>not</emph> minimal in terms of the
                  <soCalled>minimal space</soCalled> that they consume <ptr target="#sayers2016"/>.
               Nonetheless, I will argue that we can understand shadow libraries in minimal terms
               along a number of axes: minimalist surface exposure, minimalist metadata design
               principles, and minimalist distributional principles. I will cover each of these in
               turn, primarily with respect to Library Genesis.</p>
            <p> To begin with the minimal surface exposure of the site, as a highly illegal,
               copyright-violating initiative that also wants to achieve worldwide transformation of
               educational potential, Library Genesis finds itself in a minimal-maximal double bind.
               On one hand, it must remain difficult to access, hidden, and must lie low to evade
               law enforcement. It must be a resource with a minimal surface. On the other hand, to
               achieve its stated goals, this resource must be accessible and known to as many
               people as possible. This double bind is not unique to these libraries. Similar
               minimal-maximal tensions exist within legal digital social justice projects that seek
               to criticize powerful governmental norms, such as the Global Detention Project. Such
               platforms are not illegal like Library Genesis, but they seek to criticize
               often-hostile regimes for a broad audience while avoiding tyrannical government
               crackdowns. </p>
            <p> Nonetheless, Library Genesis has several technical hurdles to overcome in its quest
               to retain its minimal surface presence on the Internet. Two of these are the use of
               the Domain Name System (DNS) and the threat of (distributed) denial of service (DDOS)
               attacks. On the first of these fronts, to provide a memorable location for the
               archive, Library Genesis uses DNS <ptr target="#mockapetris1987"/>. This is the
               system that translates an address such as gen.lib.rus.ec into an Internet Protocol
               (IP) address (198.167.223.167, for example). This is a useful system because IP
               addresses are not easily memorable for humans. However, DNS addresses are subject to
               takedowns and blocking by Internet Service Providers (ISP). That is, if an allegedly
               infringed party can persuade a court of law or an ISP that a site’s sole purpose is
               copyright infringement, the domain name (or IP address) can be blocked for large
               swathes of users <ptr target="#bambauer2012"/>. It is, of course, possible to
               circumvent such blocks by a variety of techniques, such as the use of a Virtual
               Private Network (VPN) that routes traffic through a different ISP in a friendlier
               jurisdiction. Systems such as The Onion Router (Tor) are another way of evading these
               blocks <ptr target="#farnan2019"/>.</p>
            <p> Library Genesis plays the games of whack-a-mole and hide-and-seek with DNS <ptr
                  target="#schiermeier2015"/>. Its mirrors rapidly switch between addresses in an
               attempt to avoid takedowns <ptr target="#sar2015"/>. Given international jurisdictional challenges,
               it is very hard for countries that <emph>do</emph> care about copyright infringement
               to shut down Library Genesis permanently. The distributed nature of DNS acts in the
               interests of projects such as Library Genesis as it is simply impossible, at present,
               to garner the level of international legal compliance that would be necessary to shut
               down its DNS records permanently. Advances in DNS privacy and encryption are only
               likely to make this problem more difficult to combat (see, for instance, <ptr
                  target="#schmitt2018"/>.) That said, Library Genesis also has a communication
               problem with respect to DNS. If the goal of DNS is to provide memorable addresses for
               sites on the Internet then changing these addresses within a narrow time window
               frustrates the ultimate purpose of the system. Sites such as Reddit — a contemporary
               bulletin board system — spread news of new DNS mirrors, but, of course, once these
               addresses are public, the takedown process can begin anew. It is a war of attrition
               and, thus far, Library Genesis is winning the war through its guerilla tactics.</p>
            <p> The small visible central surface of sites such as Library Genesis, only accessible
               through circumvention technologies such as VPNs, reflects a phenomenon seen in
               Alternate Reality Games (ARGs). Such hiddenness is characteristic of ARGs, which
               often have obscure entry points, conventionally referred to as <q>rabbit holes</q>:
               points of ingress that lure in new users searching for clues <ptr
                  target="#szulborski2005" loc="49"/>. For Garcia and Niemeyer, <quote rend="inline"
                  >a ‘good’ rabbit hole is one that, for those not looking for clues, blends into
                  the background and noise of the world</quote>
               <ptr target="#garcia2017" loc="15"/>. An example of how Library Genesis seeds such a
               trail, rather than blatantly advertising itself, can be seen in its metadata.
               Searching for <q>Library Genesis</q> on Google yields a link but its description only
               reads, <quote rend="inline">No information is available for this page.</quote>
               Additionally, the site does not feature in the top results of <quote rend="inline"
                  >download scientific books for free.</quote> Instead, one needs to be told about
               the site and then visit it directly.</p>
            <p> This minimal surface principle is also clear in the site’s upload procedures, which
               intersect with its minimal metadata implementations. Although Library Genesis has a
               prominent upload link on its homepage, it requires a password to proceed. This gives
               the impression that uploading is a private activity, conducted only by an elite cadre
               of individuals who know the magic word.<note> For more on passwords, see <ptr target="#eve2016"/>.</note> In reality, though, users who follow the <q>rabbit hole</q> into the
                  <q>forum</q> on the site and then register can readily find the requisite username
               and password to begin uploading.</p>
            <p> There are several reasons why Library Genesis presents such a minimal surface.
               While, surely, the core reason for Library Genesis’ minimal surface is its
               illegality, this feature also lowers the potential for rights-holders to flood the
               site with false metadata and uploads. Indeed, the gravest threat to Library Genesis’s
               operation would be contamination of its records with inaccurate files, which could
               cause a denial-of-service attack against the archive. While the simple reason is that
               all uploads must be vetted, it would also be surprising if the use of the password
               seriously deters a concerted effort to pollute the library. As we will also see,
               though, the minimalist metadata principles of Library Genesis actively
                  <emph>encourage</emph> participation.</p>
            <p> In terms of minimal metadata, it is worth first considering the scale of Library
               Genesis. The main Library Genesis database collection had just short of 1.2 million
               records (books) in 2014 <ptr target="#bodo2018a" loc="53"/>. As of January 2020, this
               capacity had more than doubled to 2.5 million books. Clearly, a database of
               epistemological dissent at this size and with this scale of growth requires a
               lightweight — or, as we might say, <q><emph>minimal</emph></q> metadata scheme if it
               is not to collapse under the strain of its size. Although the ext2 and ext3
               filesystems that were commonly used on Linux systems at the time of the database’s
               inception have a sizable upper limit of 1.3×1020 files per directory, there are known
               performance issues in handling more than 10,000 <ptr target="#poirier2001"/>. There
               are also issues of integrity monitoring at this scale. When dealing with 2.5 million
               records, how can one ensure that physical media degradation — <soCalled>bit
                  rot</soCalled> — does not lead to corrupted files on the disk that may not come to
               light for substantial periods? That said, the scale of Library Genesis pales in
               comparison to formal archives. For instance, a report from 2009 noted that there are
               over 9,000 missing volumes in the British Library’s main collection, illustrating
               that this problem exists in both the legal and illegal spaces <ptr
                  target="#dawar2009"/>. The British Library is also substantially larger than
               Library Genesis, with a main collection of approximately 170 million items total and
               13.5 million books, with a digital collection that is over a petabyte in size <ptr
                  target="#britishlibrary2021"/>.</p>
            <p> Library Genesis is an enormous archive in terms of total size (maximal), but it is
               composed of files that are relatively small (minimal). The average (mean) file size
               in the database is 13.90MB, with a significant portion of these files being less than
               5MB. The file size distribution varies for the different file types within the
               database. Despite the accessibility challenges of the format — the Portable Document
               Format (PDF) is not the best format for screen readers, for instance — PDFs dominate
               the archive. For PDFs (n=1,697,927), for instance, the tail is longer to trail off
               and the average file size is higher at 16.49MB. By contrast, EPUB (n=179,926;
               average: 7.32 MB) and Mobi (n=23,947; average: 4.33MB) bring the mean file sizes down
               as they can jettison the formatting information inherent in PDF files. Nonetheless,
               with this volume of small files, addressability is a core performance concern.</p>
            <p> The solution that Library Genesis devised for handling such a vast, proliferating
               archive composed of relatively small files is based on minimalist principles of
               metadata, distribution, and hashing. Files are <emph>distributed</emph> over multiple
               directories (called <q>buckets</q>) while being referenced within a database that
               includes metadata about the file, as well as a message-digest algorithm v5 (MD5) hash
               of the file, which serves as a filename. There are 47 metadata fields within the
               database for each entry, which can be subdivided into categories of file and record
               information, file and record properties, and external identifiers.<note> The metadata
                  fields are ID, Title, VolumeInfo, Series, Periodical, Author, Year, Edition,
                  Publisher, City, Pages, PagesInFile, Language, Topic, Library, Issue, Identifier,
                  ISSN, ASIN, UDC, LBC, DDC, LCC, Doi, Googlebookid, OpenLibraryID, Commentary, DPI,
                  Color, Cleaned, Orientation, Paginated, Scanned, Bookmarked, Searchable, Filesize,
                  Extension, MD5, Generic, Visible, Locator, Local, TimeAdded, TimeLastModified,
                  Coverurl, Tags, IdentifierWODash.</note> Importantly, though, very few of these
               fields are <emph>required</emph>. The subset that are absolutely necessary are kept
               to a minimum.</p>
            <p> The first of these categories — file and record information — pertains to local
               lookup of the file. For instance, to retrieve a local file for a record, one simply
               divides the ID field by 1,000 to get the bucket directory, then retrieves the object
               with the specified MD5 record from that directory (e.g.,
                  <q>243000/9e107d9d372bb6826bd81d3542a419d6</q>). To specify the content type, a
               user can append the <q>Extension</q> field (e.g., <q>pdf</q> or <q>epub</q>) to the
               delivered file (and could also infer the multipurpose Internet mail extensions or
               MIME type if necessary). In addition to using the <q>Filesize</q> field to check a
               download, it is also possible to verify that the contents of the file have not been
               corrupted at any time. This verification is achieved by computing the file’s MD5 hash
               and then comparing this to the database/filename. Although MD5 is a very old (and
               possibly even <q>broken</q>) hashing algorithm, it has a 1.47x10-29 chance of a
               random collision (that is, of two files sharing the same hash) <ptr
                  target="#ramirez2015"/>. There are no two records within the Library Genesis
               database that share an MD5 hash as of March 1, 2020.<note> This was verified by the
                  MySQL query: <q>SELECT MD5, COUNT(MD5) FROM updated GROUP BY MD5 HAVING
                     COUNT(MD5) &gt; 1;</q>.</note> Nonetheless, the subdivision into <q>bucket</q>
               directories of 1,000 files makes the on-disk likelihood of two files sharing a
               hash/filename extremely unlikely and further reduces this risk. The verification
               algorithm means that the detection of corrupt files can be handled automatically
               rather than on a reporting basis from users (although computing all MD5 hashes in the
               database is a computationally demanding task given the scale). These field and record
               information fields are the bare minimum required to retrieve a file from the
               filestore.</p>
            <p> The second category of metadata field — file and record properties — gives specific
               metadata for a record, such as the work’s title and authors. Interestingly, for the
               principles of minimal computational design, the database does not store authors in a
               structured and linked form, but rather as free-text. Traditionally, if one were
               designing a relational database where an author could be ascribed to more than one
               book, one would create a separate database table called <q>author</q> that had
               properties such as <q>first name,</q>
               <q>last name,</q> and <q>ORCID ID,</q> and then, in the <q>books</q> table, link to
               the author. This would create a mechanism to query an author called, say, <q>Joe
                  Bloggs,</q> and to retrieve all books written by that specific Joe Bloggs. Such a
               schema would provide high-quality structured data. This is not what Library Genesis
               does. Instead, it simply stores author names as <q>plaintext.</q> Sometimes this
               means that authors and editors are listed in a long string, and it is not clear
               whether authors of the same name are the same person.</p>
            <p> Such an approach comes with several minimalist computational advantages. The
               clearest of these are: (1) there is no need to maintain the structural integrity of
               the database between tables, and (2) the overhead for entering metadata is greatly
               simplified by flattening the input. In this way, Library Genesis lowers both the
               computational requirements for maintenance and the barriers for entry/participation
               by allowing freeform textual input. Given the size of the database, and the fact that
               a free-text search can take a long time, the single-field, free-text approach to
               “author” rather than a linked record also allows interested parties to create their
               own indexes of the database with relative ease.</p>
            <p> The third and final metadata field type (external identifiers) — also entirely
               optional — demonstrates further minimalist design principles. Instead of storing all
               metadata locally, the database points to offsite management of such data, allowing
               for others, likely specialists, to focus entirely on metadata curation, collection,
               and provision. While this carries some initial lookup overhead for the pirate
               entering the data, the labor of maintaining this metadata is then outsourced and can
               be resolved on demand. This all points towards a minimalist labor approach and an
               awareness that by lowering the threshold for participating to the minimum, the
               maximalist goals of the project are more likely to be achieved.</p>
            <p> If Library Genesis encodes many of its minimalist functions in its metadata design
               principles, its distributional characteristics are also emblematic of such
               operations. The distributional minimalism principle can be seen in discussions about
               the preservation of the archive and the future of sites such as Library Genesis. On
               the first front of digital preservation, the challenge is that this archive is
               maximal, not minimal. A reasonable cost estimate for simply the hard disks to mirror
               the entire 33TB archive as of March 2020 is $1,200. This does not include either
               redundancy in terms of drive failure or the server hardware in which the hard drives
               would be housed. In terms of minimal cost scaling, the sheer size of the archive
               makes for a difficult environment if the local copy is to be complete and usable.</p>
            <p> That said, full preservation in every replica may not be the aim of distribution,
               and it is of course possible for partial replicas of the database to exist worldwide
                  <ptr target="#menasche2013"/>
               <ptr target="#neglia2007"/>. Clients such as aria2 also make it possible to download
               a single file from a torrent swarm, which in theory makes single books within the
               Library Genesis archive addressable and retrievable in distributed form. However, the
               torrent swarm is not ideal for Library Genesis’s use case. Anybody seeding on the
               network will have an exposed IP address, and it will be clear that they are
               participating, with legal risk. For this reason it is likely that many users in the
               swarm will be connecting using VPNs or so-called seedboxes (remote high-bandwidth
               servers) in order not only to protect their identity, but also to ensure the
               efficient, high-speed distribution of the material.</p>
            <p> Indeed, in late 2019, coordinating around a pirate archiving initiative known as
                  <q>The Eye,</q> a group of individuals took it upon themselves to ensure the full
               torrent availability of the Library Genesis filestore. Under this initiative, <quote
                  rend="inline">swarm peers increased from 3,000 seeders to 30,000 seeders,</quote>
               and <quote rend="inline">speeds increased from about 60KB/s on most torrents to over
                  100MB/s</quote>
               <ptr target="#ushrine2020"/>. The users who undertook this illegal initiative viewed
               their work as <q>charitable,</q> presumably under the rubric of <q>educational
                  advancement,</q> which has long held eleemosynary status in many jurisdictions.
               The amateur <q>archivists</q> who seeded Library Genesis believe that the <quote
                  rend="inline">initiative fulfils United Nations/UNESCO world development goals
                  that mandate the removal of restrictions on access to science</quote> and that
                  <quote rend="inline">[l]imiting and delaying humanity’s access to science isn’t a
                  business, it’s a crime, one with an untold number of victims and preventable
                  deaths</quote>
               <ptr target="#ushrine2020"/>. Somewhat boldly, two seedbox companies — Seedbox.io and
               UltraSeedbox.com — offered their servers for this avowedly illegal project, thereby
               providing the bandwidth to achieve the aforementioned speeds <ptr
                  target="#maxwell2019"/>. That said, the torrent archive is not viewed as a
               long-term viable mechanism for distribution, according to these individuals: <quote
                  rend="inline">It obviously isn't sane to store 33TB long-term, we just want to
                  push this out to archivers</quote>
               <ptr target="#ushrine2019"/>.</p>
            <p> A potentially more viable distribution, storage, and retrieval mechanism proposed
               for Library Genesis could be the InterPlanetary File System (IPFS) protocol <ptr
                  target="#rahalkar2020"/>. IPFS presents an addressable, distributed system in
               which objects are assigned a hash: </p>
            <cit>
               <quote rend="block">IPFS provides a high throughput content-addressed block storage
                  model, with content addressed hyper links [sic]. This forms a generalized Merkle
                  DAG, a data structure upon which one can build versioned file systems,
                  blockchains, and even a Permanent Web. IPFS combines a distributed hashtable
                  [sic], an incentivized block exchange, and a self-certifying namespace. IPFS has
                  no single point of failure, and nodes do not need to trust each other.</quote> <ptr
                     target="#benet2014"/>
            </cit>
            <p>Further, IPFS has a system called <q>pinning,</q> in which objects are immutable and
               pulled down to clients, thus ensuring their permanent availability: <quote
                  rend="inline">This also makes IPFS a Web where links are permanent, and Objects
                  can ensure the survival of others they point to</quote>
               <ptr target="#benet2014"/>. </p>
            <p> IPFS does not address the anonymity of nodes that participate, meaning that it would
               still be possible to locate a serving entity by IP address, which could have legal
               implications. Such problems could, again, be mitigated by the use of anonymity
               networks such as Tor. The scalability of IPFS to 33TB of material, spread over 2.5 or
               so million unique entities of small file sizes is also unproven. An intermediate
               address lookup table would be needed to translate between the Library Genesis
               structure and any IPFS version of the platform. However, IPFS would present a
               minimalist design platform with the distributed preservation of a maximalist
               scholarly archive, in which many actors all share a small proportion of the total
               output, contributing towards a holistic totality in fragmentary participation.
               Nonetheless, once again, the fragmentary approach, in which smaller portions of the
               archive are distributed between many actors, rather than in a centralised store,
               yields a minimal approach to the function of a maximal archival.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Minimum-Maximum</head>
            <p>Throughout this Library Genesis case study, I have been proposing a framework for
               thinking about minimal-maximal tensions. It is tempting to consider minimalist
               computing paradigms as the opposite to proliferating maximal systems. In reality,
               instead, minimalist paradigms can work as fragments of a distributed whole; this is
               one of the lessons that we can learn from the pirate archive.</p>
            <p> These debates are not abstract for scholarly communications. At present, various
               research funders across the globe are embarking on the establishment of their own
               platforms to replace the journal ecosystem. Spurred by the same motivation as Library
               Genesis and Sci-Hub — the slower-than-desired growth of open access — the Open
               Research Europe, Wellcome Open Research, and Gates Open Research platforms represent
               significant centralizations of research outputs under funder control, as opposed to a
               distributed journal publishing architecture. These platforms, running on the
               for-profit F1000 platform owned by Taylor &amp; Francis, bill themselves as
                  <q>megajournals,</q> following the terminology developed by the world’s largest
               journal, <title rend="italic">PLOS ONE</title>. There are many competing interests in
               these systems. Even as such initiatives represent centralizations and maximal
               architectures, funders insist on open licenses for re-use and re-distribution. Hence,
               we have centralization efforts mandating licenses that allow for de-centralization
               and micro/minimal circulation.</p>
            <p> Library Genesis also yields various principles of participation and consumption that
               are minimal in their design, even while they yield access to a maximal resource. By
               requiring only the minimum of metadata provision, Library Genesis lowers barriers to
               participation, an aspect also bolstered by the off-shoring and distribution of its
               identifier systems. In terms of consumption, the single search box that returns all
               results for everything, ever, represents a maximal centralization. In terms of ease
               of use and accessibility, this one-stop-shop demonstrates a concision and minimalism
               that is lacking in most scholarly communications systems.</p>
            <p> Finally, Library Genesis demonstrates a minimally exposed surface, mostly due to its
               illegality. It would be churlish to pretend that there are huge implications for
               legitimate scholarly communications infrastructures or lessons to be learned from
               this. The more people have access to scholarship and research, the better. The
               minimally exposed surface of the shadow archive is precisely — and only — because it
               must remain hidden. The strait that this archive must navigate, though, is the space
               between its maximal presence and its minimal entrance, the rabbit holes of the
               alternate reality game.</p>
            <p> Nonetheless, in all, I have attempted in this article to document several features
               of Library Genesis that serve as an index of minimal-maximal infrastructures. At
               least some of these features could be adopted by mainstream scholarly communications
               providers to increase not only the resilience of, but also global equity of access
               to, our publication ecosystems. While shadows are not equal to mirrors, in these
               senses I contend that there are lessons to be learned from the (shadow) library.</p>

         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="adema2021" label="Adema and Moore 2021"> Adema, Janneke and Samuel A.
               Moore. <title rend="quotes">Scaling Small; Or How to Envision New Relationalities for
                  Knowledge Production.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Westminster Papers in Communication and Culture</title> vol. 16.1
               (2021). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.16997/wpcc.918"
                  >https://doi.org/10.16997/wpcc.918</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="andrews2020" label="Andrews 2020"> Andrews, Penny C. S. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Platformization of Open.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >Reassembling Scholarly Communications: Histories, Infrastructures, and Global
                  Politics of Open Access</title>, edited by Martin Paul Eve and Jonathan Gray, 265-276.
               Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="androcec2017" label="Andročec 2017"> Andročec, Darko. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Analysis of Sci-Hub Downloads of Computer Science Papers.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Acta Universitatis Sapientiae, Informatica</title> vol. 9.1 (2017):
               83–96. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1515/ausi-2017-0006"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1515/ausi-2017-0006</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bambauer2012" label="Bambauer 2012"> Bambauer, Derek E. <title
                  rend="quotes">Orwell’s Armchair.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The University of Chicago Law Review</title> vol. 79.3 (2012):
               863-944.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="benet2014" label="Benet 2014"> Benet, Juan. (2014). <title rend="quotes"
                  >IPFS - Content Addressed, Versioned, P2P File System.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1407.3561 [Cs]</title>, July. <ref
                  target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1407.3561"
               >https://arxiv.org/abs/1407.3561</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="berlin2003" label="Berlin Declaration 2003">
               <title rend="quotes">Berlin Declaration on Open Access to Knowledge in the Sciences
                  and Humanities.</title> October 22, 2003. <ref
                  target="https://oa.mpg.de/lang/en-uk/berlin-prozess/berliner-erklarung"
                  >https://oa.mpg.de/lang/en-uk/berlin-prozess/berliner-erklarung</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodo2018a" label="Bodó 2018a"> Bodó, Balázs. <title rend="quotes">Library
                  Genesis in Numbers: Mapping the Underground Flow of Knowledge.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Shadow Libraries: Access to Educational Materials in Global Higher
                  Education</title>, edited by Joe Karaganis, 53–78. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press,
               2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodo2018b" label="Bodó 2018b">Bodó, Balázs. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Genesis of Library Genesis: The Birth of a Global Scholarly Shadow
                  Library.</title> In <title rend="italic">Shadow Libraries: Access to Educational
                  Materials in Global Higher Education</title>, edited by Joe Karaganis, 25–52.
               Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bodo2020c" label="Bodó 2020c"> Bodó, Balázs, Dániel Antal and Zoltán
               Puha. <title rend="quotes">Can Scholarly Pirate Libraries Bridge the Knowledge Access
                  Gap? An Empirical Study on the Structural Conditions of Book Piracy in Global and
                  European Academia.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PLOS ONE</title> vol. 15.12 (2020): e0242509. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0242509"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0242509</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bohannon2016" label="Bohannon 2016"> Bohannon, John. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Who’s Downloading Pirated Papers? Everyone.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Science,</title> April 25, 2016. <ref
                  target="https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/04/whos-downloading-pirated-papers-everyone"
                  >https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/04/whos-downloading-pirated-papers-everyone</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="bosch2018" label="Bosch and Henderson 2018"> Bosch, Stephen and Kittie
               Henderson. <title rend="quotes">Predicting the Future in 3,000 Words and Charts: The
                  Library Journal Serials Pricing Article.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Serials Librarian</title> vol. 74.1–4 (2018): 224–27. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/0361526X.2018.1430442"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/0361526X.2018.1430442</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="boudry2019" label="Boudry et al. 2019"> Boudry, Christophe, Patricio
               Alvarez-Muñoz, Ricardo Arencibia-Jorge, Didier Ayena, Niels J. Brouwer, Zia
               Chaudhuri, Brenda Chawner, et al. <title rend="quotes">Worldwide Inequality in Access
                  to Full Text Scientific Articles: The Example of Ophthalmology.</title>
               <title rend="italic">PeerJ</title> 7 (2019): e7850. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7850"
                  >https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.7850</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="brembs2020" label="Brembs 2020"> Brembs, Björn. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Ultimate Open Access Timeline.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Bjoern.Brembs.Blog</title>, March 3, 2020. <ref
                  target="https://bjoern.brembs.net/2020/03/the-ultimate-open-access-timeline/"
                  >https://bjoern.brembs.net/2020/03/the-ultimate-open-access-timeline/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="camarero2014" label="Camarero et al. 2014"> Camarero, Carmen, Carmen
               Antón and Javier Rodríguez. <title rend="quotes">Technological and Ethical
                  Antecedents of E-Book Piracy and Price Acceptance: Evidence from the Spanish
                  Case.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Electronic Library</title> vol. 32.4 (2014): 542–66. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1108/EL-11-2012-0149"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1108/EL-11-2012-0149</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="chan2002" label="Chan et al. 2002"> Chan, Leslie, Darius Cuplinskas,
               Michael Eisen, Fred Friend, Yana Genova, Jean-Claude Guédon, Melissa Hagemann, et al.
                  <title rend="quotes">Budapest Open Access Initiative.</title> February 14, 2002.
                  <ref target="https://www.soros.org/openaccess/read.shtml"
                  >https://www.soros.org/openaccess/read.shtml</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="correa2021" label="Correa et al. 2021"> Correa, Juan C., Henry
               Laverde-Rojas, Julian Tejada and Fernando Marmolejo-Ramos. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Sci-Hub Effect on Papers’ Citations.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Scientometrics</title>, January 2021. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-020-03806-w"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/s11192-020-03806-w</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="das2013" label="Das et al. 2013"> Das, Jishnu, Quy-Toan Do, Karen Shaines
               and Sowmya Srikant. <title rend="quotes">U.S. and Them: The Geography of Academic
                  Research.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Journal of Development Economics</title> 105 (2013): 112–30.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jdeveco.2013.07.010"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jdeveco.2013.07.010</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dawar2009" label="Dawar and Kennedy 2009"> Dawar, Anil and Maev Kennedy.
                  <title rend="quotes">British Library Mislays 9,000 Books.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Guardian</title>, March 17, 2009. . <ref
                  target="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2009/mar/17/british-library-books-mein-kampf"
                  >https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2009/mar/17/british-library-books-mein-kampf</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="dulong2021" label="Dulong de Rosnay 2021"> Dulong de Rosnay, Melanie.
                  <title rend="quotes">Open Access Models, Pirate Libraries and Advocacy
                  Repertoires: Policy Options for Academics to Construct and Govern Knowledge
                  Commons.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Westminster Papers in Communication and Culture</title> vol. 16.1
               (2021). <ref target="https://doi.org/10.16997/wpcc.913"
                  >https://doi.org/10.16997/wpcc.913</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eve2014" label="Eve 2014"> Eve, Martin Paul. <title rend="italic">Open
                  Access and the Humanities: Contexts, Controversies and the Future</title>.
               Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2014. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781316161012"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/CBO9781316161012</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eve2016" label="Eve 2016"> Eve, Martin Paul. <title rend="italic"
                  >Password</title>. NY: Bloomsbury, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="eve2021" label="Eve 2021"> Eve, Martin Paul, Cameron Neylon, Daniel
               O’Donnell, Samuel Moore, Robert Gadie, Victoria Odeniyi and Shahina Parvin.<title
                  rend="italic">Reading Peer Review: </title>PLOS ONE<title rend="italic"> and
                  Institutional Change in Academia</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press,
               2021.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="britishlibrary2021" label="The British Library 2021">
               <title rend="quotes">Facts and Figures of the British Library.</title> <title rend="italic">The British
               Library</title>. Accessed September 23, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.bl.uk/about-us/our-story/facts-and-figures-of-the-british-library"
                  >https://www.bl.uk/about-us/our-story/facts-and-figures-of-the-british-library</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="farnan2019" label="Farnan et al. 2019"> Farnan, Oliver, Alexander Darer
               and Joss Wright. <title rend="quotes">Analysing Censorship Circumvention with VPNs
                  via DNS Cache Snooping.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1907.04023 [Cs]</title>, July 2019. <ref
                  target="https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.04023"
               >https://arxiv.org/abs/1907.04023</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="faust2016" label="Faust 2016"> Faust, Jeremy S. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Sci-Hub: A Solution to the Problem of Paywalls, or Merely a Diagnosis of a Broken
                  System?</title>
               <title rend="italic">Annals of Emergency Medicine</title> vol. 68.1 (2016): A15–17. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.annemergmed.2016.05.010"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1016/j.annemergmed.2016.05.010</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fitzpatrick2011" label="Fitzpatrick 2011"> Fitzpatrick, Kathleen. <title
                  rend="italic">Planned Obsolescence: Publishing, Technology, and the Future of the
                  Academy</title>. NY: New York University Press, 2011.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="fyfe2015" label="Fyfe 2015"> Fyfe, Aileen. <title rend="quotes">Journals,
                  Learned Societies and Money: Philosophical Transactions, ca. 1750–1900.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Notes and Records: The Royal Society Journal of the History of
                  Science</title> vol. 69.3 (2015): 277–99. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1098/rsnr.2015.0032"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1098/rsnr.2015.0032</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="garcia2017" label="Garcia and Niemeyer 2017"> Garcia, Antero and Greg
               Niemeyer. <title rend="quotes">Introduction.</title> In <title rend="italic"
                  >Alternate Reality Games and the Cusp of Digital Gameplay</title>, edited by
               Antero Garcia and Greg Niemeyer, 1–28. NY: Bloomsbury Academic,
               2017.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gil2016" label="Gil and Ortega 2016"> Gil, Alex and Élika Ortega. <title
                  rend="quotes">Global Outlooks in Digital Humanities: Multilingual Practices and
                  Minimal Computing.</title> In <title rend="italic">Doing Digital Humanities:
                  Practice, Training, Research</title>, edited by Crompton Constance, Richard J.
               Lane, and Raymond G. Siemens, 22–34. NY: Routledge, 2016.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="grafton1999" label="Grafton 1999"> Grafton, Anthony. <title rend="italic"
                  >The Footnote: A Curious History</title>. Cambridge, MA: Harvard University Press,
               1999.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="gray2020" label="Gray 2020"> Gray, Jonathan. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Infrastructural Experiments and the Politics of Open Access.</title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Reassembling Scholarly Communications: Histories, Infrastructures,
                  and Global Politics of Open Access</title>, edited by Martin Paul Eve and Jonathan
               Gray, 251–64. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="green2017" label="Green 2017"> Green, Toby. <title rend="quotes">We’ve
                  Failed: Pirate Black Open Access Is Trumping Green and Gold and We Must Change Our
                  Approach.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Learned Publishing</title> vol. 30.4 (2017) 325–29. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1002/leap.1116"
               >https://doi.org/10.1002/leap.1116</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="harris2019" label="Harris and Barrett 2019"> Harris, Shane and Devlin
               Barrett. <title rend="quotes">Justice Department Investigates Sci-Hub Founder on
                  Suspicion of Working for Russian Intelligence.</title> <title rend="italic"
                  >The Washington Post</title>, December 19, 2019. <ref
                  target="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/justice-department-investigates-sci-hub-founder-on-suspicion-of-working-for-russian-intelligence/2019/12/19/9dbcb6e6-2277-11ea-a153-dce4b94e4249_story.html"
                  >https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/justice-department-investigates-sci-hub-founder-on-suspicion-of-working-for-russian-intelligence/2019/12/19/9dbcb6e6-2277-11ea-a153-dce4b94e4249_story.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="herb2018" label="Herb 2018"> Herb, Ulrich. <title rend="quotes">Open
                  Access And Symbolic Gift Giving.</title> In <title rend="italic">Open Divide:
                  Critical Studies on Open Access</title>, edited by Joachim Schöpfel and Ulrich
               Herb, 69–81. Sacramento, CA: Library Juice Press, 2018. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1206377"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.1206377</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="himmelstein2018" label="Himmelstein et al. 2018"> Himmelstein, Daniel S,
               Ariel Rodriguez Romero, Jacob G Levernier, Thomas Anthony Munro, Stephen Reid
               McLaughlin, Bastian Greshake Tzovaras and Casey S Greene. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Sci-Hub Provides Access to Nearly All Scholarly Literature.</title> <title rend="italic">ELife</title> 7 (February 2018): e32822. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.32822"
                  >https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.32822</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hobsbawm1981" label="Hobsbawm 1981"> Hobsbawm, Eric. <title rend="italic"
                  >Bandits</title>. NY: Pantheon Books, 1981.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="hockenberry2013" label="Hockenberry 2013"> Hockenberry, Benjamin. <title
                  rend="quotes">The Guerilla Open Access Manifesto: Aaron Swartz, Open Access and
                  the Sharing Imperative.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Lavery Library Faculty/Staff Publications</title>, November
               2013, 1–7.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="jurchen2020" label="Jurchen 2020"> Jurchen, Sarah. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Open Access and the Serials Crisis: The Role of Academic Libraries.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Technical Services Quarterly</title> vol. 37.2 (2020): 160–70. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1080/07317131.2020.1728136"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/07317131.2020.1728136</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="kapczynski2010" label="Kapczynski and Krikorian 2010"> Kapczynski, Amy
               and Gaëlle Krikorian, eds. <title rend="italic">Access to Knowledge in the Age of
                  Intellectual Property</title>. NY: Zone Books, 2010.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="machinmastromatteo2016" label="Machin-Mastromatteo et al. 2016">
               Machin-Mastromatteo, Juan D, Alejandro Uribe-Tirado and Maria E Romero-Ortiz. <title
                  rend="quotes">Piracy of Scientific Papers in Latin America: An Analysis of Sci-Hub
                  Usage Data.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Information Development</title> vol. 32.5 (2016): 1806–14.
               <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1177/0266666916671080">https://doi.org/10.1177/0266666916671080</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="maxwell2019" label="Maxwell 2019"> Maxwell, Andy. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Meet the Guy Behind the Libgen Torrent Seeding Movement.</title>
               <title rend="italic">TorrentFreak,</title> December 5, 2019. <ref
                  target="https://torrentfreak.com/meet-the-guy-behind-the-libgen-torrent-seeding-movement-191205/"
                  >https://torrentfreak.com/meet-the-guy-behind-the-libgen-torrent-seeding-movement-191205/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mboa2020" label="Mboa Nkoudou 2020"> Mboa Nkoudou, Thomas Hervé.
                  <title rend="quotes">Epistemic Alienation in African Scholarly Communications:
                  Open Access as a <title rend="italic">Pharmakon.</title></title> In <title
                  rend="italic">Reassembling Scholarly Communications: Histories, Infrastructures,
                  and Global Politics of Open Access</title>, edited by Martin Paul Eve and Jonathan
               Gray, 25–40. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="menasche2013" label="Menasché et al. 2013"> Menasché, Daniel S., Antonio
               A. de A. Rocha, Bin Li, Don Towsley and Arun Venkataramani. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Content Availability and Bundling in Swarming Systems.</title>
               <title rend="italic">IEEE/ACM Transactions on Networking</title> vol. 21.2 (2013): 580–93.
                  <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/TNET.2012.2212205"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1109/TNET.2012.2212205</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="mockapetris1987" label="Mockapetris 1987"> Mockapetris, P. V. <title
                  rend="quotes">Domain Names - Concepts and Facilities.</title> <title rend="italic">Internet Engineering
               Task Force</title>. November 1987. <ref target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1034"
                  >https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1034</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moore2017" label="Moore et al. 2017"> Moore, Samuel, Cameron Neylon,
               Martin Paul Eve, Daniel O’Donnell and Damian Pattinson. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Excellence R Us: University Research and the Fetishisation of Excellence.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Palgrave Communications</title> 3 (2017). <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1057/palcomms.2016.105"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1057/palcomms.2016.105</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="moxham2018" label="Moxham and Fyfe 2018"> Moxham, Noah and Aileen Fyfe.
                  <title rend="quotes">The Royal Society and the Prehistory of Peer Review,
                  1665–1965.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Historical Journal</title> vol. 61.4 (2018): 863–89. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1017/S0018246X17000334"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1017/S0018246X17000334</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="neglia2007" label="Neglia et al. 2007"> Neglia, G., G. Reina, H. Zhang, D.
               Towsley, A. Venkataramani and J. Danaher. <title rend="quotes">Availability in
                  BitTorrent Systems.</title> In <title rend="italic">IEEE INFOCOM 2007 - 26th IEEE
                  International Conference on Computer Communications</title>, 2007, 2216–24.
               Anchorage, AK, USA: IEEE. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1109/INFCOM.2007.256"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1109/INFCOM.2007.256</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="pastoureau2003" label="Pastoureau 2003"> Pastoureau, Michel. <title
                  rend="quotes">L’incolore n’existe Pas.</title> In <title rend="italic">Points de
                  Vue: Pour Philippe Junod</title>, edited by Danielle Chaperon and Philippe Kaenel,
               21–36. Champs Visuels. Paris: L’Harmattan, 2003.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="poirier2001" label="Poirier 2001"> Poirier, Dave. <title rend="quotes">The
                  Second Extended File System.</title> Savannah. 2001. <ref
                  target="https://www.nongnu.org/ext2-doc/ext2.html"
                  >https://www.nongnu.org/ext2-doc/ext2.html</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="rahalkar2020" label="Rahalkar and Gujar 2020"> Rahalkar, Chaitanya, and
               Dhaval Gujar. <title rend="quotes">Content Addressed P2P File System for the Web with
                  Blockchain-Based Meta-Data Integrity.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1912.10298 [Cs]</title>, January 2020. <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.10298"
               >http://arxiv.org/abs/1912.10298</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ramirez2015" label="Ramirez 2015"> Ramirez, Gorka. <title rend="quotes"
                  >MD5: The Broken Algorithm.</title> <title rend="italic">Avira Blog</title>,
               July 28, 2015. <ref target="https://blog.avira.com/md5-the-broken-algorithm/"
                  >https://blog.avira.com/md5-the-broken-algorithm/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="reddy2021" label="Reddy et al. 2021"> Reddy, Hrishikesh and Shivang
               Mishra. <title rend="quotes">Sci-Hub Case: Legally Removing the Barriers in the Way
                  of Science.</title>
               <title rend="italic">NLUJ Law Review,</title> April 29, 2021. <ref
                  target="http://www.nlujlawreview.in/sci-hub-case-legally-removing-the-barriers-in-the-way-of-science/"
                  >http://www.nlujlawreview.in/sci-hub-case-legally-removing-the-barriers-in-the-way-of-science/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="risam2018" label="Risam 2018"> Risam, Roopika. <title rend="italic">New
                  Digital Worlds: Postcolonial Digital Humanities in Theory, Praxis, and
                  Pedagogy</title>. Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="roh2020" label="Roh et al. 2020"> Roh, Charlotte, Harrison W. Inefuku and
               Emily Drabinski. <title rend="quotes">Scholarly Communications and Social
                  Justice.</title> In <title rend="italic">Reassembling Scholarly Communications:
                  Histories, Infrastructures, and Global Politics of Open Access</title>, edited by
               Martin Paul Eve and Jonathan Gray, 41–52. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2020.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="russell2017" label="Russell and Sanchez 2017"> Russell, Carrie and Ed
               Sanchez. <title rend="quotes">Sci-Hub Unmasked: Piracy, Information Policy, and Your
                  Library | Russell | College &amp; Research Libraries News.</title>
               <title rend="italic">College &amp; Research Libraries News</title> vol. 77.3 (2017):
               122–25. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5860/crln.77.3.9457"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5860/crln.77.3.9457</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sar2015" label="Sar 2015"> Sar, Ernesto Van Der. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Sci-Hub, BookFi and LibGen Resurface After Being Shut Down.</title>
               <title rend="italic">TorrentFreak,</title> November 21, 2015. <ref
                  target="https://torrentfreak.com/sci-hub-and-libgen-resurface-after-being-shut-down-151121/"
                  >https://torrentfreak.com/sci-hub-and-libgen-resurface-after-being-shut-down-151121/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="sayers2016" label="Sayers 2016"> Sayers, Jentery. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Minimal Definitions.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Minimal Computing Working Group,</title> October 2, 2016. <ref
                  target="http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2016/10/02/minimal-definitions/"
                  >http://go-dh.github.io/mincomp/thoughts/2016/10/02/minimal-definitions/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schiermeier2015" label="Schiermeier 2015"> Schiermeier, Quirin. <title
                  rend="quotes">Pirate Research-Paper Sites Play Hide-and-Seek with
                  Publishers.</title>
               <title rend="italic">Nature</title>, December 2015. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature.2015.18876"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1038/nature.2015.18876</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schiermeier2017" label="Schiermeier 2017"> Schiermeier, Quirin. <title
                  rend="quotes">US Court Grants Elsevier Millions in Damages from Sci-Hub.</title>
                  <title rend="italic">Nature</title>, June 2017. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature.2017.22196"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1038/nature.2017.22196</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="schmitt2018" label="Schmitt et al. 2018"> Schmitt, Paul, Anne Edmundson,
               and Nick Feamster. <title rend="quotes">Oblivious DNS: Practical Privacy for DNS
                  Queries.</title>
               <title rend="italic">ArXiv:1806.00276 [Cs]</title>, December 2018. <ref
                  target="http://arxiv.org/abs/1806.00276"
               >http://arxiv.org/abs/1806.00276</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="suber2012" label="Suber 2012"> Suber, Peter. <title rend="italic">Open
                  Access</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2012.
                  <ref target="http://bit.ly/oa-book">http://bit.ly/oa-book</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="suber2003" label="Suber et al. 2003"> Suber, Peter, Patrick O. Brown,
               Diane Cabell, Aravinda Chakravarti, Barbara Cohen, Tony Delamothe, Michael Eisen, et
               al. <title rend="quotes">Bethesda Statement on Open Access Publishing,</title> 2013
                  <ref target="http://dash.harvard.edu/handle/1/4725199"
                  >http://dash.harvard.edu/handle/1/4725199</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="swartz2015" label="Swartz 2015"> Swartz, Aaron. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Guerilla Open Access Manifesto.</title> In <title rend="italic">The Boy Who Could
                  Change the World</title>, 26–27. London: Verso, 2015.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="szulborski2005" label="Szulborski 2005"> Szulborski, Dave. <title
                  rend="italic">This Is Not A Game: A Guide To Alternate Reality Gaming</title>.
               Macungie, PA: New-Fiction Pub, 2005.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="tanenbaum2008" label="Tanenbaum and Torvalds 2008"> Tanenbaum, Andrew S.
               and Linus Torvalds. <title rend="quotes">Appendix A: The Tanenbaum-Torvalds
                  Debate.</title> In <title rend="italic">Open Sources: Voices from the Open Source
                  Revolution</title>, edited by Chris DiBona, Sam Ockman, and Mark Stone, 221–51.
               Sebastopol: O’Reilly Media, Inc., 2008. <ref
                  target="http://public.ebookcentral.proquest.com/choice/publicfullrecord.aspx?p=443191"
                  >http://public.ebookcentral.proquest.com/choice/publicfullrecord.aspx?p=443191</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="thylstrup2018" label="Thylstrup 2018"> Thylstrup, Nanna Bonde. <title
                  rend="italic">The Politics of Mass Digitization</title>. Cambridge, MA: The MIT
               Press, 2018.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="till2019" label="Till et al. 2019"> Till, Brian M., Niclas Rudolfson,
               Saurabh Saluja, Jesudian Gnanaraj, Lubna Samad, David Ljungman and Mark Shrime.
                  <title rend="quotes">Who Is Pirating Medical Literature? A Bibliometric Review of
                  28 Million Sci-Hub Downloads.</title>
               <title rend="italic">The Lancet Global Health</title> vol. 7.1 (2019): e30–31. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30388-7"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1016/S2214-109X(18)30388-7</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ushrine2019" label="u/shrine 2019"> u/shrine. <title rend="quotes"
                  >Charitable Seeding Update: 10 Terabytes and 900,000 Scientific Books in a Week
                  with Seedbox.Io and UltraSeedbox.</title> Reddit - r/Seedboxes. Accessed
               September 28, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.reddit.com/r/seedboxes/comments/e3yl23/charitable_seeding_update_10_terabytes_and_900000/"
                  >https://www.reddit.com/r/seedboxes/comments/e3yl23/charitable_seeding_update_10_terabytes_and_900000/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="ushrine2020" label="u/shrine 2020"> u/shrine. <title rend="quotes">Library Genesis Project
               Update: 2.5 Million Books Seeded with the World, 80 Million Scientific Articles
               Next.</title> Reddit - r/DataHoarder. Accessed September 28, 2021. <ref
                  target="https://www.reddit.com/r/DataHoarder/comments/ed9byj/library_genesis_project_update_25_million_books/"
                  >https://www.reddit.com/r/DataHoarder/comments/ed9byj/library_genesis_project_update_25_million_books/</ref>.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
