<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Ghosts in the Machine: a motion-capture
                    experiment in distributed reception</title>
                <!-- Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English -->
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Helen <dhq:family>Slaney</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Roehampton</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>helen.slaney@roehampton.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Anna <dhq:family>Foka</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>DH Uppsala and Humlab Umeå</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>anna.foka@abm.uu.se</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Anna Foka is Associate Professor of Information Technology and Scientific
                            Leader and Manager of DH Uppsala, at Uppsala University. She has a
                            background Classics, Ancient History and Archaeology (MA 2006, PhD 2009,
                            University of Liverpool) as well as Media and Performance Studies (NCU
                            Athens, Greece). Anna Foka’s research interests lie in the intersection
                            of digital technology with historical disciplines. She has published on
                            classics,  ancient history and archaeology, gender and humour, classical
                            reception, game studies, augmented and virtual reality  for museums,
                            digital visualizations and geography.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Sophie <dhq:family>Bocksberger</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Oxford</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sophie.bocksberger@classics.ox.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p/>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>

                <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000395</idno>
                <idno type="volume">012</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2018-11-19">19 November 2018</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
                <!-- add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages -->
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- If a translation is added to the original article, add an enclosing <text> and <group> element -->
    <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Digital reconstructions of classical antiquity are generally ocularcentric,
                    appealing only to the sense of vision. We propose that new technologies may be
                    used to engage the other senses in the act of reception, and specifically here
                    we focus on kinaesthesia, or the sense of self-movement. This paper analyses a
                    phase of the project Ancient Dance in Modern Dancers in which participants
                    created performance pieces in a genre of Graeco-Roman dance for use in a
                    motion-capture system. It was necessary for the performers to develop a range of
                    translational strategies in order to communicate their movement to the system,
                    entailing what we term <q>distributed reception</q>, in which the ultimate
                    recipient of ancient source-material is not a human actor but rather the machine
                    with which s/he is in collaboration.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Can new technologies be used to engage senses other than sight in the act of
                    reception?</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Introduction</head>
            <p>Digital reconstructions of classical antiquity tend typically to use visualization as
                their primary sensory vehicle. As the <soCalled>sensory turn</soCalled> in
                historical scholarship moves beyond vision, however (e.g. <ptr target="#butler2013"
                />; <ptr target="#toner2014"/>; <ptr target="#betts2017"/>), the question also
                arises of how alternative sense-experiences may be re-imagined, and how this
                re-imagining might be facilitated using digital media. Different forms of sensory
                engagement generate different forms of knowledge, creating what Foka and Arvidsson
                have termed the <quote rend="inline" source="#foka2016">experiential
                analogy</quote>, whereby the ephemeral cultural practices of another era are
                translated into present-day sense experience <ptr target="#foka2016"/>. Foka and
                Arvidsson concentrate on sound, but equally crucial to knowledge-production is
                kinaesthesia, or the sense of self-movement. The vital contributions made by
                kinaesthesia to comprehending physical potentialities and spatial relationships as
                well as the abstract concepts derived from them have been widely demonstrated in the
                domain of cognitive science <ptr target="#sheets-johnstone2011"/> (see also <ptr
                    target="#gallese2005"/>, <ptr target="#gallagher2005"/>, <ptr target="#noë2004"
                />). It is our contention that kinaesthetic engagement can also contribute to
                formulating conceptions of the ancient past, and that digital technology is an ideal
                tool for fashioning this analogical relationship. Even as self-movement offers the
                impression of immersive bodily contact with antiquity, virtuality presents a
                simultaneous reminder of its otherness.</p>
            <p> Technology has opened up new ways to examine antiquity.<note> See precisely previous
                    work by <ptr target="#schreibman2004"/> and <ptr target="#forte2010"/>; for 3D
                    visualizations as emerging from popular culture see <ptr target="#foka2017"
                    />.</note> Digital technologies are used to relate detailed topographic data to
                primary sources in order to visualize place and space distant in time <ptr
                    target="#schreibman2004"/>
                <ptr target="#mahony2010" loc="1–14"/>
                <ptr target="#barker2010"/>
                <ptr target="#barker2012" loc="185–200"/>. Digital prototypes in the form of 3D
                visualisations have found prominent use within humanities research <ptr
                    target="#drucker2011"/>
                <ptr target="#frischer2006" loc="163–82"/>
                <ptr target="#forte2010"/>
                <ptr target="#nygren2014"/>
                <ptr target="#foka2017"/>
                <ptr target="#vitale2016"/>. As argued by Foka and Arvidsson, the vast majority of
                scholarly attempts to digitally reconstruct ancient urban sites for entertainment or
                otherwise indeed rely on the visual representation of (physical) materiality such as
                buildings, bridges or roads through 3D and virtual reality models. 3D models thus
                make evident how existing digital tools carry assumptions of knowledge as primarily
                visual, neglecting other sensory detail and thereby sustaining the ocularcentric
                tradition within humanities research (e.g. <ptr target="#howes2005" loc="14"/>; <ptr
                    target="#classen1997" loc="401–12"/>), as well as idealised representations of
                antiquity. Western intellectual traditions have indeed shown a marked preference for
                vision as the figure of knowledge <ptr target="#evens2005" loc="ix"/>. The excuse is
                often that elements of intangible cultural heritage such as dance and motion (see
                definition by <ref
                    target="https://ich.unesco.org/en/what-is-intangible-heritage-00003)"
                    >UNESCO</ref>) leave no traces or evidence, so we cannot represent them in their
                entirety. This lack of direct experiential evidence is in fact present in any
                historical research, sensory or not. </p>
            <p>Kinaesthesia, however, is becoming increasingly important to reconstructive
                interfaces. Digital visualizations, prototypes and reconstructions provide
                historical insights into aspects of urban development and facilitate critical
                discussions of the application of digital tools within the context of museology or
                narratives of digital cultural heritage <ptr target="#giaccardi2012"/>. With the
                development of immersive technology, the recent trend is to move beyond static 3D
                models and to enable interaction with users navigating in virtual environments <ptr
                    target="#westin2012"/>. Contemporary technologies such as Virtual Reality (VR)
                and Motion Tracking (MT) engines enable participation, observation and
                user-interaction; these in turn afford sensory engagements with space (environment,
                architecture) and artifacts of the past <ptr target="#forte2010"/>. Materials and
                environments are further digitally reconstructed as 3D Models (for a review see <ptr
                    target="#forte2010"/>, <ptr target="#vitale2016"/>). These are currently
                implemented beyond databases, and within gaming <ptr target="#chapman2016"/>
                <ptr target="#chapman2017"/>, or Augmented Reality environments <ptr
                    target="#astic2011"/>
                <ptr target="#westin2018"/> as well as, less frequently, within Virtual or Mixed
                Reality environments. The rarity of VR or MR is an issue attributed to the
                complexities of local infrastructure <ptr target="#foka2017"/> as well as emerging
                upgrades and sustainability. Our knowledge about the intangible elements of the
                ancient world, such as movement, image, and sound, may be currently recreated in
                immersive laboratory environments.<note> Many universities have programs that
                    research and develop immersive technology. Examples are Stanford's Virtual Human
                    Interaction Lab, USC's Computer Graphics and Immersive Technologies Lab, Iowa
                    State Virtual Reality Applications Center, University of Buffalo's VR Lab, and
                    Teesside University's Intelligent Virtual Environments Lab, Humlab at Umeå
                    University and <ref target="http://immersiveeducation.org"
                        >http://immersiveeducation.org</ref>.</note> However, beyond archaeology
                proper, research of ancient performance within immersive environments has not been
                conducted until recently.<note> With the exception of Bozia <title rend="quotes"
                        >Reviving Classical Drama: Virtual Reality and Experiential Learning in a
                        Traditional Classroom</title> in this special issue.</note> Specifically,
                the creation of immersive interactive and multimodal environments for historical
                performance has been underexplored.</p>
            <div>
                <head>1.</head>
                <p>The practice-led research collaboration Ancient Dance in Modern Dancers (ADMD)
                    was set up in 2013 with the aim of translating the verbal and iconographic
                    evidence for Graeco-Roman dance back into movement. Our initial hypothesis was
                    that applying this evidence in the formulation of physical performances would
                    provide an alternative mechanism for understanding dance from the performer’s
                    standpoint, as a kinaesthetic process, rather than its usual treatment as
                    spectacle or ocularcentric product. By drawing on the expertise of
                    professionally-trained dancers, we have been able to produce a range of
                    conjectures for the representation of selected scenarios, and at the same time
                    to extrapolate a number of key principles for the art-form.</p>
                <p> The dance genre we have concentrated on is <foreign xml:lang="la">tragoedia
                        saltata</foreign>, otherwise known as Graeco-Roman tragic pantomime, or
                    simply <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign>. This was a form of solo
                    storytelling through dance and gesture popular between the first and fifth
                    centuries CE across the Roman empire, especially in the Greek East. Much
                    excellent scholarship over the last decade or so has established the attributes
                    of <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign>, which is now recognised as a
                    sophisticated cultural discourse and an important vehicle for the late antique
                    transmission of tragedy <ptr target="#lada-richards2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#hallwyles2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#webb2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#macintosh2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#garelli2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#zanobi2013"/>. <foreign xml:lang="gr">Orchēsis</foreign> scenarios
                    could be comic or tragic, erotic or philosophical; a single masked dancer, the
                        <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign>, played multiple roles,
                    indicating character, setting and plot through a combination of hand gestures,
                    choreograpic sequences, and iconic poses. He (usually he, although some female
                        <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstes</foreign> are also known)<note> See e.g.
                        epigraphic inscriptions such as <hi rend="italic">IG</hi> XIV 2342 (= <hi
                            rend="italic">GV</hi> 675); epigrams such as <title rend="italic">Greek
                            Anthology</title> 16.284, 16.286 &amp; 16.287; Apuleius <title
                            rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title> 10.29. For discussion of the
                        evidence for female pantomime artists, see <ptr target="#starks2008"
                        />.</note> wore a flowing robe and cape, and was accompanied by musicians
                    and a singer or singers who performed a libretto alongside.</p>
                <p> No extant libretti have been definitively identified,<note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="la">pace</foreign>
                        <ptr target="#hall2008"/>. In the literature these are referred to as
                            <foreign xml:lang="la">fabulae salticae</foreign>. Famous poets such as
                        Lucan and Statius are recorded as having composed them, but they do not
                        survive.</note> but one very probable Latin source is Ovid’s poetic
                    compendium of myth, the <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title>
                    <ptr target="#ingleheart2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#lada-richards2013"/>.<note> Greek plays were also adapted for
                        pantomime: see e.g. <title rend="italic">TrGF</title> 1, p344 ad 14a;
                        Suetonius, <title rend="italic">Gaius</title> 57.9; <title rend="italic"
                            >Greek Anthology</title> 16.289.</note> Transformation between
                    characters, or from one state to another, was one of the skills for which
                        <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstes</foreign> were celebrated;<note> Lucian,
                            <title rend="italic">On the Dance</title> 19.</note> moreover, the
                    themes of <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign> as summarised by the
                    second-century satirist Lucian, <quote rend="inline" source="#canonical">all of
                        the mythical metamorphoses (<foreign xml:lang="gr">muthikas
                            metamorphōseis</foreign>), those who have changed into trees and beasts
                        and birds… and above all, the love-affairs of [the gods], even Zeus
                        himself</quote>, closely resemble the subject matter of Ovid’s poem.<note>
                        Another inclusion in the canon of pantomime subjects is Pythagorean
                        philosophy, with its principle of reincarnation (Lucian, <title
                            rend="italic">On the Dance</title> 70; cf. Athanaeus <title
                            rend="italic">Deipnosophistai</title> 629d-e), which is also treated in
                        Ovid’s <title rend="italic">Metamorphoses</title> (Book 15).</note> For the
                    current phase of ADMD, the two passages selected as our libretti were one
                    episode in which sea-nymph Thetis attempts to evade a rapist by transforming
                    herself into multiple creatures (<title rend="italic">Met</title>. 11.229-65),
                    and one in which the impious king Pentheus is torn apart by worshippers of the
                    god Dionysus (<title rend="italic">Met.</title> 3.699-729) (click <ref
                        target="http://www.humlab.umu.se/sv/forskning-och-utveckling/avslutade-projekt/digitising-ancient-dance/"
                        >here</ref> to listen; both texts may be found in the Appendix to this
                    article).</p>
                <p> Hitherto, ADMD has experimented only with live performance. Digitization has
                    added new variables and raised a new set of questions regarding the relationship
                    between the body of the dancer in the present, ever-mutable moment and the
                    absent figure of the ancient <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign>, for
                    whom the live dancer acts as a <foreign xml:lang="gr">sēma</foreign>, a marker.
                    Live dance practice offered us insights into the vital symbiosis between the
                        <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign> and the libretto, the <foreign
                        xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign> and the musician, the <foreign
                        xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign> and costume, character, emotions, mask/s
                    and space; the additional layer of digitization placed more acute emphasis on
                    the fundamental process of embodiment. Rather than the proprioceptive (internal
                    sensorimotor) feedback which dominated the dancers’ choices in the development
                    of their live performance pieces, the activation of an external avatar required
                    ongoing interaction with this distorted mirror-image, this not-quite-self which
                    both resisted and responded to the dancers’ manipulation. In setting up this
                    experiment in motion capture, we shifted the point of reception from the human
                    body to its virtual analogue.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2.</head>
                <p>The objective of the pilot workshop run with ADMD was to examine how the dancers’
                    kinaesthetic translation of ancient data pertaining to <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >orchēsis</foreign> would be affected by the additional factor of digital
                    interaction. For this purpose we used Motion Capture in order to create 3D
                    avatars of the dancers. Once animated, the resulting videos will also enable
                    each dance piece to be analysed from any angle in the context of a virtual
                    ancient theatre environment. </p>
                <p>Over the last few decades motion capture engines have been mostly enhancing our
                    understanding of normal and pathological human movement and have been used in
                    the context of medical practice and education, gaming and cinema.<note> See <ptr
                            target="#foka2018"/>.</note> Motion capture (or motion tracking)
                    generally refers to the process of recording human actor or object movement and
                    this information is used to animate digital character models in 2D or 3D user
                    animation. Early techniques used images from multiple cameras to calculate 3D
                    positions and assemble them to reconstruct the movement but not the actor’s
                    visual appearance. Improved knowledge of locomotion drove the invention of new
                    methods of observation. Currently, the most common method for the capture of
                    three-dimensional human movement requires a laboratory environment inclusive of
                    markers, fixtures or sensors. The movement of the markers is typically used to
                    capture movement between two adjacent segments (e.g. knee joint, ankles, elbows
                    etc) with the goal of near-precisely recording the movement of the joint (<ref
                        target="#figure01">figures 1 &amp; 2</ref>). For ADMD’s purposes, the
                    crucial difference between 3D tracking and video recording is that video fixes a
                    static viewpoint and coerces prospective users into a spectatorial role, with
                    all the binary dynamics implied by this relationship.<note> See <ptr
                            target="#mcmillan2002" loc="271–91"/> and <ptr target="#dixon2007"/>
                        especially in relation to the study of interactive platforms for the study
                        of performance arts, <ptr target="#kilteni2012" loc="373–87"/> regarding
                        VR.</note> In contrast, the interactive user plays an active role in
                    determining the order in which already-generated elements are accessed. This is
                    the simplest kind of interactivity, and it allows for variability of
                    interpretations, as opposed to mere spectatorship.<note> For interactivity and
                        interactive media see <ptr target="#manovich2001"/>.</note> In order to
                    bring the user into the performance space, as it were, alongside the dancer, we
                    found the polyfocal coverage of 3D capture to afford a less restricted medium. </p>
                <p>For the purpose of recording the dancers we used the <q>Black Box</q>, an
                    isolated motion capture laboratory space in the ground floor of the Sliperiet
                    facility at Umeå University. In a space of approximately 20m<hi
                        rend="superscript">2</hi> (4x5m) we positioned a wooden flooring (3x3m), and
                    initially twelve cameras on different angles to record the dancers. The hardware
                    we used for the motion capture was an OptiTrack 13W system and the interface
                    software was Motive. On the first day, we began warming up one by one the twelve
                    motion capture cameras in by using the <q>wanding option</q> OptiTrack CW-500
                    (B= 250mm). We then tested the sensors with an OptiTrack three point sensor
                    triangle (CS 200). The 90 degree triangle was rigid but served as a testing
                    point to observe and to capture the two axes for the 3D capture. The software we
                    used (Motive) offered several different interfaces including: <list
                        type="ordered">
                        <item>Avatar, skeleton (no gender) that could be modified with default
                            models that are male or female (<ref target="#figure03">figures
                                3–4</ref>).</item>
                        <item>Motion tracking avatars with strings that display the direction and
                            the velocity of the motion capture (<ref target="#figure05">figures
                                5–7</ref>).</item>
                    </list></p>
                <p>Numerous problems were encountered while trying to set up and use the tracking
                    system. The dancers’ feet could not be <soCalled>captured</soCalled> at first
                    due to reflection from the concrete floor. The system would not pick up anything
                    lower than 15cm, so the dancers’ feet remained undetectable. While the system
                    was ready, the software was still not reading all the markers properly; it was
                    picking up all 37 out of 37 sensor points, but informing us that it required
                    more markers. This was solved by a combination of adjustments. We raised the
                    floor surface to a height of about 3cm, and used non-reflective wooden boards.
                    We also altered the angle of the cameras and moved the capture area so cameras
                    could be attached to fixed points as opposed to being placed on moveable stands. </p>
                <p>All this resulted in wasting some valuable time. By midday on the first day of
                    laboratory work we still could not capture the whole skeleton as one, and we had
                    to move on to test it with the dancers. While we got the 37 sensor points to
                    show, there were further glitches in the system. For example, we would
                    temporarily lose all movements of the arms and legs (because they had frozen or
                    disappeared), but then manage to detect all the points again after a few moves.
                    We were informed by Humlab and Sliperiet senior technician Jim Robertsson that
                    glitches of that sort may be rectified with post-production animation. Another
                    issue was the fact that we could not capture movement in detail – for example
                    hands and feet. While there was no need to capture facial expressions given that
                    historically pantomime dancers normally wore masks, there was absolutely no
                    possibility to capture the movement of fingers or hands, or small, subtle
                    movement. That put some constraints on how the dancers would perform. </p>
                <p>The first question asked by the participating dancers was whether they should
                    modify their performances in any way to compensate for these technological
                    constraints. Many movements in the <title rend="quotes">Thetis</title> piece,
                    for example, took place on the ground; but crouching, kneeling, rolling, or
                    reclining brought the dancer perilously close to the plane below which the
                    cameras could not reliably track. We instructed them not to make any initial
                    modifications, but to wait until after reviewing the footage in order to
                    identify problem areas. Feet proved troublesome, placing much of the footwork,
                    the essential <foreign xml:lang="gr">pedēmata</foreign> of <foreign
                        xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign>, out of range, creating glitches in which
                    they popped up reversed at the ankles or vanished altogether from the figure on
                    the interface. Although our dancers typically performed their pieces barefoot,
                    we found that wearing shoes under the suit’s felt slippers tightened the fabric
                    and hence improved the consistency of capture. Another common issue was the
                    concealment of bent limbs, particularly in some of these floor-level positions.
                    Rapid or complex sequences were easier to track if executed in the centre of the
                    performance area, where more of the cameras could track each marker. We added
                    more markers, taking the total suit count up to the maximum of 50. It seems that
                    for dance, and for this genre of dance in particular, more flexibility is needed
                    in the options for positioning the markers on the body. The mask eliminates any
                    need for capturing facial expressions, but the corollary is that a need for
                    greater accuracy accrues to the hands, feet, and torso. (Click <ref
                        target="http://www.humlab.umu.se/sv/forskning-och-utveckling/avslutade-projekt/digitising-ancient-dance/"
                        >here</ref> to see an extract from one of the dances and the resulting
                    avatar pre-animation).</p>
                <p>Another of the issues we encountered had to do with veils, shawls and loose
                    clothing. These costume items are integral to <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >orchēsis</foreign>
                    <ptr target="#wyles2008"/> (<ref target="#figure08">figures 8–10</ref>) but
                    could not be recorded in any possible way. We were advised to use small
                    triangular <soCalled>rigid body</soCalled> markers attached to the edges of the
                    cloth, and attached these rigid bodies onto a veil made of semi-transparent
                    gauzy fabric. The rigid bodies we used had sensory properties but also made the
                    thin veil the dancers wore significantly heavier. Moreover, they would create
                    further problems for animators in post-production as they only marked the
                    extremity of the cloth. The inability of the motion capture system to track the
                    movement of the veil, however, presented a creative opportunity as well as a
                    problem. Even if the material object could not be tracked by the sensors, its
                    presence could still be perceived in the quality of the dancers’ movements, as
                    they had to adapt to the constraints the prop imposed on them.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3.</head>
                <p>The use of masks in itself has a profound effect on the way the dancers move.
                    When facial expressions are hidden behind a mask, the dancers can only rely on
                    body language to create meaning through their movements. This also allows them
                    to embody with more ease a wider range of characters or other entities such as
                    landscapes or elemental substances, as their individual self is made less
                    visible. The dancers are aware that the focus of the audience shifts from the
                    face to the whole body, and that they have to adapt their choreography
                    accordingly. In the absence of any expression on the face to read, the effect of
                    very subtle movements, such as those of a shoulder, a finger, or an inclination
                    of the head, is magnified, thereby acquiring the potential to become very
                    powerful and highly significant. Consequently, each movement has to be very
                    precise and neat, as the smallest imprecisions are more likely to catch the
                    audience’s attention and thus to blur the dancer’s intention. Working with a
                    veil (a <foreign xml:lang="la">pallium</foreign>) equally pushes the dancers to
                    make clearer and more precise propositions. It also forces them to make more
                    ample movements when dancing with it.</p>
                <p>Working with the avatar turned out to have similar effects on the dancers’
                    choreography to those triggered by the use of the mask and of the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">pallium</foreign>, and indeed actually amplified them. On the
                    one hand, the avatar appears to become an extension of the mask, as it conceals
                    the dancers’ own identity one step further. It promotes dissociation between the
                    dancer and his performance. The body is perceived to be a kind of raw material
                    that can be shaped at will to produce the desired effects, and is thus less
                    emotionally invested. On the other hand, working with an avatar also imposes
                    constraints which resemble those created by the use of the <foreign
                        xml:lang="la">pallium</foreign>. It requires that the dancers focus more on
                    the smoothness and details of their movement, and less on their levels of energy
                    and emotions. The movements have to be bigger in order to translate on the
                    screen. Consequently, the dancers have to rely more on their technical skills as
                    well as on the visual cues provided by the avatar, and less on their inner
                    feelings. This also applies to the dancers’ energy levels. How much energy they
                    put into each movement no longer reflects their emotional state, but instead is
                    largely dependent on how much of it is needed to convey the desired effect
                    through the avatar.</p>
                <p> The performer of <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign> is already in
                    possession or occupation of dual, even multiple body-images, and the
                    introduction of the on-screen avatar further complicates this perceptual
                    relationship. Firstly, the dancer is both subject and object, skilled
                    manipulator of the instrument that is her body. She is both spectacle and
                    impresario. Second, the notorious plasticity of the <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >orchēstēs</foreign> means that by altering factors such as bearing, rhythm,
                    tension, and speed, this instrumental body becomes the vehicle for a multitude
                    of characters.<note> Lucian, <title rend="italic">On the Dance</title>
                        19.</note> The articulate body which consists of a visible, exterior
                    manifestation of motion – the shared sign-system of pantomimic gesture –
                    coexists with the subjective, kinaesthetic evolution of the moving body-schema
                    as experienced from within (on which distinction in dance more generally, see
                        <ptr target="#cohen1997"/>).</p>
                <p> In antiquity, <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstes</foreign> had no means of seeing
                    the whole of this outer body except as reflected in the movement of a trainer or
                    rival performer. Their sensory feedback was purely proprioceptive. In the
                    studio, our collaborating dancers make use of the mirror; previous ADMD research
                    has embedded the use of video footage in the development process of pieces for
                    performance. The 3D feedback of the screen extends this strategy of separating
                    the visible (exterior) from the kinaesthetic (interior) body. The screen
                    interface was available to our participants throughout, and although they did
                    not typically refer to it during the execution of their performances, it was
                    used in much the same way as a mirror when preparing. This mirror-image,
                    however, was distorted, producing an appreciable disconnect between the motion
                    of the dancer and its on-screen realisation. (A very basic example: because the
                    markers were on the backs of the hands, they remained some 5cm apart on the
                    avatar when the dancer clapped; in order for the avatar to clap, the dancer’s
                    hands must cross.)</p>
                <p> This raises the matter of translation. This has been central to ADMD from the
                    beginning, as we define the activity of participating dancers as a form of
                    intermedial translation, or translation across media:<note> Influential in this
                        respect has been the work of <ptr target="#scott2012"/>.</note> performances
                    witnessed in antiquity have been translated into the written texts and static
                    images which are our source-material, and these we then translate back into
                    movement using the kinetic discourses of twenty-first-century dance training and
                    practice. One primary challenge addressed by ADMD has been that of making
                    comprehensible a language of gesture that both references the extant data on
                        <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign> and resonates for present-day
                    spectators. In the project’s initial phase, it was sufficient that participants
                    invented an idiolect, a private language accessible to other members of the
                    group. Subsequent phases involved public performance and consequently demanded
                    expansion of the gestural vocabulary as well as refinement of its utterance:
                    elements had to be at once precise, repeatable, and recognisable. Instead of
                    addressing human spectators, on the other hand, the Umeå participants were
                    addressing their performances towards the impersonal and inorganic but no less
                    partial and interpretive gaze of the motion-capture system. As when a
                    performance is transferred from an intimate venue to a large stage – which may
                    certainly have been the case for Roman <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >orchēstes</foreign> –<note> On the range of performance venues used for
                        pantomime, see <ptr target="#webb2008"/> and <ptr target="#garelli2007"
                        />.</note> gestures suited to the studio had to be adapted in scale and
                    orientation if their effect was to be comparable.</p>
                <p> Ironically, the space in which the dancers were working (3m x 3m, as mentioned
                    above) had shrunk to a fraction of their rehearsal room. In a similar fashion to
                    the multiplication of bodies, the introduction of a screen environment added
                    another dimension to the already-complex spatial dynamics operational in
                        <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign>. As well as representing
                    character, the <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign> is responsible for
                    establishing his setting: the sea-cave where Thetis is assaulted, the
                    mountainside where Pentheus is caught spying. Without scenery or backdrop, space
                    is transformed imaginatively through the interaction of movement and libretto.
                    The musical soundscape is vital, as it fills up the space like liquid with the
                    mood which the <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign> crystallises and
                    channels. The other fictional setting, however, simultaneously being defined by
                    the movements of our participants was the on-screen grid. In one sense
                    featureless, in that it consists of nothing but the geometric axes that contain
                    the stick-figure or <q>skeleton</q>, this anonymous screen-space in fact makes a
                    powerful intervention into the conceptual location of the dance. No longer
                    constitutively identified with the live dancing body and its material context,
                    the dance is transposed into an intermediary, purgatorial zone where it is
                    perceptibly <emph>neither</emph> the actions performed by the present-day dancer
                    opposite, <emph>nor</emph> those of an ancient <foreign xml:lang="gr"
                        >orchēstēs</foreign>. A participant may be animating (dancing the role of)
                    Pentheus on Mt Cithaeron, but he is at the same time animating (dancing the role
                    of) the skeleton in the grid.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4.</head>
                <p>From Humlab’s perspective and that of Digital Humanities in general, the
                    collaboration with ADMD offered new insights. There is no comprehensive research
                    about how the collaboration between artists, technicians, and academics may
                    approach and appropriate technology as a critical tool, how technology changes
                    conditions for participation in artistic (re)creation, and what is the value of
                    technology as a medium and a reflective tool for knowledge processes within
                    academic settings. Through the process of capturing the movements of Roman
                    pantomime, we attempted to give at least partial answer to these questions. We
                    examined first and foremost how the entanglements between technology,
                    scholarship and performance art enable new knowledge production in multiple
                    dimensions. Technology acts as a lens that affects the way we conduct empirical
                    research. It brings new conditions and demands for research. </p>
                <p>While the team of researchers, technicians and dancers initially saw this as a
                    non-teleological experiment, the final implementation deliverable was to create
                    a Virtual Reality prototype of a pantomime dancing avatar within a Roman theatre
                    setting. With the aid of Humlab-based 3D artist Mattis Lindmark a simple,
                    neutral avatar was first placed within a test space without a specific theatre
                    background: (<ref
                        target="http://cultumea.com/testzone/MocapHistoryWeb/index.html"
                        >http://cultumea.com/testzone/MocapHistoryWeb/index.html</ref> last accessed
                    27.09.2017). At a later stage, the team borrowed a Virtual Reality environment
                    of the theatre at Pompeii.<note> Credit: Jeffrey Jacobson, Public VR.</note>
                        (<ref
                        target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gApcaxSGqh0&amp;feature=youtu.be"
                        >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gApcaxSGqh0&amp;feature=youtu.be</ref> last
                    accessed 27.09.2017 see also <ref target="#figure07">figure 7</ref>). The avatar
                    used was a synthesis of disparate gender and age features: a conventional female
                    face on a young/early teenager male body with an olive skin complexion and
                    African hair. The reason for the combination of these aesthetic elements was to
                    reflect that professional dance training started from a young age in antiquity
                    (Libanius, <title rend="italic">Oration</title> 64). The final virtual reality
                    prototype is intended primarily for HTC VIVE headmounts, while there are
                    currently discussions for its incorporation within higher education as a study
                    tool for the intangible cultural heritage of the Roman empire. </p>
                <p>There is an advocacy for a gradually stronger integration of technology within
                    arts and humanities research, and that is manifested in academic infrastructure,
                    recognized by scholars as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#burdicket2012">inevitable change</quote>
                        <ptr target="#burdick2012"/>
                    </cit>. In spite of being a relatively young direction, still on a stage of
                    self-determination and struggling to situate itself in a bigger context <ptr
                        target="#crane2009"/>, the digitalization of arts and humanities
                    infrastructures has become an increasingly popular topic in academic spheres.
                    Digital and computational tools promise new relationships between individuals
                    and the knowledge production processes, the collapse of the long-standing
                    opposition between the natural sciences and the humanities as well as freeing
                    the humanities from anxious attempts to advocate for their worth and relevance
                    in contemporary society <ptr target="#nygren2014"/>
                    <ptr target="#foka2016"/>. We further argue in this article that immersion
                    dictates that movement, auditory components and other forms of expression enable
                    an interactive appreciation of materiality beyond the visual, thus enabling a
                    simulation of what UNESCO defines as <q>Intangible Cultural Heritage</q>.
                    Typically intended for education or for cultural heritage purposes, virtual
                    worlds are gradually becoming popularized beyond the cultural or the creative
                    heritage industry and have become tools for research, education and
                    dissemination of the past (on mixed reality and CH see <ptr
                        target="#kolsouzoglou2006"/>). The complexity of building digital immersive
                    visualizations, as well as the power of experiencing the past emotionally and
                    physically ought to be addressed.</p>
                <p>This discourse, however, is not unproblematic. First, although recent scholarship
                    reflects the notion that humanistic study should correspond to the contemporary
                    reality of the human experience, there are no relevant discussions for
                    performance arts in relationship to its gradual reorientation toward technology.
                    Second, there are no comprehensive studies about how new technological
                    competences may critically relate historical performances to our current
                    post-human, technologically intertwined condition. As a consequence of this
                    digitization of disciplines that are (incorrectly) considered impractical and
                    valueless, new directions have arisen: the importance of practical engagement,
                    hands-on work, thinking-through-making alongside developments in digital
                    software and hardware <ptr target="#burdick2012"/>
                    <ptr target="#gold2012"/>. A third issue that arises is that these directions
                    remain equally under-studied and elusive. Against this backdrop, digital
                    infrastructure for academia, recently reiterated as the material presence of
                    technology that may bring praxis and theory together, is only discussed at the
                    level of potentials of settings <ptr target="#smithies2014"/> as a core
                    component for new, digital forms of knowledge production. The intersections of
                    art with traditional humanistic research and the role of technology as
                    infrastructure have only been studied in their theoretical potential, and not
                    necessarily addressing organizational tensions related to the installation and
                    use of digital research infrastructures <ptr target="#fokaetal2017"/>. </p>
                <p>While for ADMD technology as a medium facilitated interdisciplinary research and
                    brokered collaboration between the artists, academics and technicians, there are
                    some further, practical observations that need to be made. One issue was that
                    the system required a lot of extra calibration and time to test cameras, sensor
                    points and interface response to begin with. In the reality of academic
                    experiments as such that require specific time and resources, it is good, in the
                    future, to allow extra time so as to optimize the empirical part of the process.
                    One striking example was the recalibration early in the workshop that lasted for
                    a total of four hours. The further, practical engagement of scholars and
                    practitioners benefitted greatly from keeping a diary of events, achievements,
                    and problems.</p>
                <p>In order to optimize the process of motion capture to record movement more
                    accurately, there is not much to be done at the moment beyond post-production
                    development of the captured avatars. We suggest that developers of motion
                    capture may in the future consider how to ameliorate the issues identified
                    above: glitches between sensor points and interface response, and the lack of
                    ability to record items of clothing or motion intensity. Although early and
                    preliminary, our very engagement with artists, text, motion, and captured image
                    gave us new insights into both technological and humanistic inquiry. Humanities
                    laboratories should ideally facilitate empirical engagements with text, accessed
                    through the full range of sensory modalities, and slowly open up to recreating
                    immersive portals to conduct humanistic research through crafting, experiencing
                    and reflecting. Digitalized infrastructures for Arts and Humanities gain meaning
                    and become innovative through equality of the socio-technical components and
                    strong collaborative efforts between technology, art, and the humanities. </p>
                <p>This collaboration between practitioners, scholars, technicians, and indeed with
                    the technology itself can be defined as an instance of what we term here
                        <emph>distributed reception</emph>. According to theories of distributed
                    cognition more generally, cognitive (intellectual) activity takes place not
                    exclusively within the human brain but rather within a more extensive, networked
                    field of interactions incorporating both biological matter and inanimate objects
                    (e.g. <ptr target="#clark2008"/>, <ptr target="#damasio1999"/>, <ptr
                        target="#rowlands2010"/>, <ptr target="#shapiro2004"/>, <ptr
                        target="#noë2004"/>, <ptr target="#bennett2010"/>, <ptr
                        target="#sheets-johnstone2011"/>, <ptr target="#gallagher2005"/>). In this
                    instance, we relocated the cognitive act of processing movement from the locus
                    of a human being to a (distributed) technological recipient. In translating
                    ancient dance for a post-human world, for a cultural context in which digital
                    media have become integral to everyday activities, the human actor-interpreter
                    may not necessarily remain the sole target audience of ancient texts. Dance, it
                    could be argued, is so intrinsically embodied an activity that it occurs only
                    within the closed circuit of the human body; but we feel on the contrary that
                    the technological can be incorporated productively into the terpsichoreal. </p>
                <p>Performances, we found, had to be modified in order to convert the electrical
                    firing of muscular innervation into the electrical signals of the motion-capture
                    system and transmit a version of <foreign xml:lang="gr">orchēsis</foreign>
                    meaningful to our many-eyed nonhuman spectator. A feedback loop was created as
                    the dancers’ movements were informed in turn by the reactions of the figure on
                    the screen. Subtle movements, for example, had to be rendered in a more explicit
                    fashion if the system was to register them; hands must overlap to clap; a hidden
                    foot glitches. The dancer dances their avatar like a marionette, but the
                    marionette’s responses also affect the dancer. Agency was thus likewise
                    distributed (as in <ptr target="#bennett2010"/>). Further modification and
                    refinement of the performance could of course be deferred to post-production,
                    but another option is to develop effective translation techniques for meeting
                    the medium halfway and adapting this dance form to make it comprehensible not
                    just to human viewers but also to the alternative sensory faculties of a
                    machine. Dispensing with the unattainable goal of ever more isomorphic capture,
                    we might instead exploit the given conditions of this unique partnership,
                    creatively accommodating the demands of this obedient yet exacting
                    collaborator.</p>
                <p>In doing so, the dancer’s relationship to the antiquity s/he represents becomes
                    manifest. When the dance is live, it is possible to elide the present-day
                    performer with the absent ancient dancer, to mistake the translation for the
                    source-text and to forget its duplicity, or (less pejoratively) its doubleness;
                    but when, on screen, the skeleton simultaneously appears in all its inhuman
                    smoothness and misapprehended disjointedness, we are reminded of how these
                    performances are inescapably haunted by their predecessors. If and when the
                    avatar appears in its fully reanimated Graeco-Roman guise, the effect will be
                    even more pronounced. The figure in the grid, the imagined <foreign
                        xml:lang="gr">orchēstēs</foreign>, comes into being only as the ghostly
                    body-double of the dancer on the floor: visible as an external analogue of the
                    kinaesthetic metamorphosis experienced within, its separateness supplies an
                    imagined point of origin, a parallel text created in the act of reception.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Figures</head>
                <figure xml:id="figure01">
                    <head>The capture area.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure02">
                    <head>A dancer experiments with the suit, while watching her 3D image on
                        screen.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure03">
                    <head>The <q>skeleton</q> view.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure04">
                    <head>A more acrobatic version of the <q>skeleton</q> view.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure05">
                    <head>The <q>marionette</q> view.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure06">
                    <head>The <q>marionette</q> view in action.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpeg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure07">
                    <head>The Virtual Reality environment and avatar in 2D.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure08">
                    <head>Dancers rehearsing with mask and <foreign xml:lang="la">pallium</foreign>
                        (veil / cape).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure09">
                    <head>Dancer rehearsing with mask and <foreign xml:lang="la">pallium</foreign>
                        (veil / cape).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>
                <figure xml:id="figure10">
                    <head>Dancers rehearsing with mask and <foreign xml:lang="la">pallium</foreign>
                        (veil / cape).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.jpg"/>
                </figure>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Appendix: texts and translations</head>
                <table xml:id="table01">
                    <head>Ovid, <hi rend="italic">Metamorphoses</hi> 11.229-65</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell><l>Est sinus Haemoniae curvos falcatus in arcus:</l>
                            <l>bracchia procurrunt, ubi, si foret altior unda,</l>
                            <l>portus erat (summis inductum est aequor harenis);</l>
                            <l>litus habet solidum, quod nec vestigia servet</l>
                            <l>nec remoretur iter, nec opertum pendeat alga.</l>
                            <l>Myrtea silva subest bicoloribus obsita bacis</l>
                            <l>et specus in medio (natura factus an arte,</l>
                            <l>ambiguum, magis arte tamen), quo saepe venire</l>
                            <l>frenato delphine sedens, Theti, nuda solebas.</l>
                            <l>Illic te Peleus, ut somno vincta iacebas,</l>
                            <l>occupat: et quoniam precibus temptata repugnas,</l>
                            <l>vim parat, innectens ambobus colla lacertis.</l>
                            <l>Quod nisi venisses variatis saepe figuris</l>
                            <l>ad solitas artes, auso foret ille potitus.</l>
                            <l>Sed modo tu volucris (volucrem tamen ille tenebat),</l>
                            <l>nunc gravis arbor eras (haerebat in arbore Peleus),</l>
                            <l>tertia forma fuit maculosae tigridis: illa</l>
                            <l>territus Aeacides a corpore bracchia solvit.</l>
                            <l>Isque deos pelagi vino super aequora fuso</l>
                            <l>et pecoris fibris et fumo turis adorat,</l>
                            <l>donec Carpathius medio de gurgite vates</l>
                            <l>&quot;Aeacide,&quot; dixit, &quot;thalamis potiere petitis!</l>
                            <l>Tu modo, cum rigido sopita quiescit in antro,</l>
                            <l>ignaram laqueis vincloque innecte tenaci.</l>
                            <l>Nec te decipiat centum mentita figuras,</l>
                            <l>sed preme, quidquid erit, dum, quod fuit ante, reformet!&quot;</l>
                            <l>Dixerat haec Proteus et condidit aequore vultum</l>
                            <l>admisitque suos in verba novissima fluctus.</l>
                            <l>Pronus erat Titan inclinatoque tenebat</l>
                            <l>Hesperium temone fretum, cum pulchra relecto</l>
                            <l>Nereis ingreditur consueta cubilia saxo.</l>
                            <l>Vix bene virgineos Peleus invaserat artus,</l>
                            <l>illa novat formas, donec sua membra teneri</l>
                            <l>sentit et in partes diversas bracchia tendi.</l>
                            <l>Tum demum ingemuit, &quot;neque&quot; ait &quot;sine numine
                                vincis&quot;</l>
                            <l>exhibita estque Thetis. Confessam amplectitur heros</l>
                            <l>et potitur votis ingentique implet Achille.</l>
                        </cell>
                        <cell><l>There is a bay in Haemonia, curved like a sickle:</l>
                            <l>it extends its arms, where, if the sea were deeper,</l>
                            <l>there would be a port (the water lies flat over sand-banks);</l>
                            <l>It has a solid shore, which is neither marked by tracks</l>
                            <l>nor confined by a road, nor covered by dangling seaweed.</l>
                            <l>There is a myrtle-wood beneath mottled ivy</l>
                            <l>and in the middle, a cave (whether made by art or nature</l>
                            <l>is uncertain – more likely art), where often,</l>
                            <l>seated on your bridled dolphin, Thetis, nude, you come.</l>
                            <l>Here Peleus, as you lay overcome by sleep,</l>
                            <l>assailed you: and when you tried to resist him by pleading,</l>
                            <l>he became violent, and wrapped both arms around your neck.</l>
                            <l>And if you had not assumed many different shapes</l>
                            <l>as is your accustomed art, his audacity would have succeeded.</l>
                            <l>But first you became a bird (he still held the bird)</l>
                            <l>then an imposing tree (Peleus hung onto a branch).</l>
                            <l>Your third form was a striped tiger: and <emph>that</emph> one</l>
                            <l>made the terrified son of Aeacus loose his arms from your body. </l>
                            <l>He addressed the gods of the sea, pouring wine on the waves</l>
                            <l>and the innards of sacrificial beasts and the smoke of incense,</l>
                            <l>until the Carpathian prophet rose from the depths.</l>
                            <l>&quot;Son of Aeacus,&quot; he said, &quot;You seek to be able to bed
                                her!</l>
                            <l>Well now, when she lies quiet, asleep in her rocky cave,</l>
                            <l>tie her up while she’s unconscious and confine her in tight
                                bonds.</l>
                            <l>And don’t be deceived by her hundred deceptive forms</l>
                            <l>but hang on, whatever she becomes, until she turns back to
                                herself!&quot;</l>
                            <l>So saying, Proteus sank his face into the water</l>
                            <l>and his final words were submerged in the flowing tide.</l>
                            <l>The Sun was setting, and turning his chariot,</l>
                            <l>set a course for the west, when the beautiful sea-nymph</l>
                            <l>returned and reclined on her accustomed rocky couch.</l>
                            <l>Immediately Peleus assaulted her virgin limbs.</l>
                            <l>She assumed new forms, until she felt her body restrained</l>
                            <l>and her arms stretched in different directions.</l>
                            <l>Then at last she groaned, &quot;You have not won without divine
                                help!&quot;</l>
                            <l>and showed herself as Thetis, defeated. The hero embraced her,</l>
                            <l>achieved his desire, and fathered the invincible Achilles.</l></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
                <table xml:id="table02">
                    <head>Ovid, Metamorphoses 3.699-729</head>
                    <row>
                        <cell><l>Perstat Echionides. Nec iam iubet ire, sed ipse</l>
                            <l>vadit, ubi electus facienda ad sacra Cithaeron</l>
                            <l>cantibus et clara bacchantum voce sonabat.</l>
                            <l>Ut fremit acer equus, cum bellicus aere canoro</l>
                            <l>signa dedit tubicen, pugnaeque adsumit amorem,</l>
                            <l>Penthea sic ictus longis ululatibus aether</l>
                            <l>movit, et audito clamore recanduit ira.</l>
                            <l>Monte fere medio est, cingentibus ultima silvis,</l>
                            <l>purus ab arboribus, spectabilis undique campus.</l>
                            <l>Hic oculis illum cernentem sacra profanis</l>
                            <l>prima videt, prima est insano concita cursu,</l>
                            <l>prima suum misso violavit Penthea thyrso</l>
                            <l>mater. </l>
                            <l>&quot;Io, geminae&quot; clamavit &quot;adeste sorores!</l>
                            <l>ille aper, in nostris errat qui maximus agris,</l>
                            <l>ille mihi feriendus aper.&quot; Ruit omnis in unum</l>
                            <l>turba furens; cunctae coeunt trepidumque sequuntur,</l>
                            <l>iam trepidum, iam verba minus violenta loquentem,</l>
                            <l>iam se damnantem, iam se peccasse fatentem.</l>
                            <l>Saucius ille tamen &quot;fer opem, matertera&quot; dixit</l>
                            <l>&quot;Autonoe! moveant animos Actaeonis umbrae.&quot;</l>
                            <l>Illa, quis Actaeon, nescit dextramque precantis</l>
                            <l>abstulit: Inoo lacerata est altera raptu.</l>
                            <l>Non habet infelix quae matri bracchia tendat,</l>
                            <l>trunca sed ostendens deiectis vulnera membris</l>
                            <l>&quot;adspice, mater!&quot; ait. </l>
                            <l>Visis ululavit Agaue</l>
                            <l>collaque iactavit movitque per aera crinem</l>
                            <l>avulsumque caput digitis complexa cruentis</l>
                            <l>clamat &quot;io comites, opus haec victoria nostr’ est!&quot;</l>
                            <l>Non citius frondes autumni frigore tactas</l>
                            <l>iamque male haerentes alta rapit arbore ventus,</l>
                            <l>quam sunt membra viri manibus direpta nefandis.</l></cell>
                        <cell><l>The son of Echion persisted. He no longer ordered others to go,</l>
                            <l>but went himself to Mt Cithaeron, where the followers of the god</l>
                            <l>performed their rites and raised their voices in Bacchic singing.</l>
                            <l>Like a war-horse foams at the mouth with desire for battle </l>
                            <l>when the war-trumpet sounds the advance with its sonorous bronze, </l>
                            <l>so Pentheus was struck by the ululations that made the air
                                vibrate,</l>
                            <l>and as he heard their cries his rage burned hot again.</l>
                            <l>In the heart of the mountains, on a peak surrounded by forest</l>
                            <l>but clear of trees, visible from everywhere, is a field.</l>
                            <l>Here he came to lay profane eyes on the sacred rites.</l>
                            <l>The first to see him, the first to halt her wild running,</l>
                            <l>the first to strike Pentheus with her rod like a spear…</l>
                            <l>…was his mother.</l>
                            <l> &quot;Hey, sisters,&quot; she shouted, &quot;come here, my
                                sisters!</l>
                            <l>This huge boar, that has been causing havoc in our fields - </l>
                            <l>I have to smash him!&quot; They came running as one,</l>
                            <l>the furious crowd; they all came together and pursued him,
                                terrified,</l>
                            <l>- oh, terrified now, now speaking words less violent,</l>
                            <l>now cursing himself and admitting that he had done wrong.</l>
                            <l>Wounded, he still said, &quot;Oh, help me, Aunt</l>
                            <l>Autonoe! Be moved by the spirit of Actaeon.&quot;</l>
                            <l>She knew nothing of Actaeon, and as he held out his hand to her</l>
                            <l>she ripped it off: Ino got the other one.</l>
                            <l>The poor man had no arms left to extend to his mother,</l>
                            <l>but thrust his maimed torso at her, stripped of limbs.</l>
                            <l>&quot;Look, Mother!&quot; he said.</l>
                            <l> Agave howled exultantly at the sight </l>
                            <l>and tossed her head, and whipped her hair,</l>
                            <l>and tore off his head, gripping it in blooded fingers.</l>
                            <l>&quot;Hey, girls,&quot; she cried, &quot;This is a great victory for
                                us!&quot;</l>
                            <l>Autumn leaves, touched by the frost and unable to cling </l>
                            <l>to the tall tree, are not more quickly scattered by the wind</l>
                            <l>than the limbs of that man were dismembered by terrible
                            hands.</l></cell>
                    </row>
                </table>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="astic2011" label="Astic 2011">Astic, I., et al.: A Ubiquitous Mobile
                    Edutainment Application for Learning Science through Play. In: Museums and the
                    Web 2011, Philadelphia, PA, USA (2011)</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barker2010" label="Barker et al. 2010">Barker, E., Bouzarovski, S.;
                    Pelling, C. and Isaksen, L. 2010 <ref target="http://oro.open.ac.uk/20528"
                            ><title rend="quotes">Mapping an ancient historian in a digital age: the
                            Herodotus Encoded Space-Text-Image Archive (HESTIA)</title></ref>
                    <title rend="italic">Leeds International Classical Studies</title>, 9. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barker2012" label="Barker et al. 2012">Barker, E. Bissell, C.,
                    Hardwick, L., Jones, A., Ridge, M. and Wolffe, J. 2012. <ref
                        target="http://oro.open.ac.uk/30146">Digital technologies: help or hindrance
                        for the humanities?</ref> (2012-02) Arts and Humanities in Higher Education,
                    11(1-2) (pp. 185-200). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bennett2010" label="Bennett 2010">Bennett, J. 2010. <title
                        rend="italic">Vibrant Matter: a political ecology of things</title>. Durham:
                    Duke University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="betts2017" label="Betts 2017">Betts, E. (ed.) 2017. <title
                        rend="italic">Senses of the Empire: multisensory approaches to Roman
                        culture</title>. Farnham: Ashgate.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="burdick2012" label="Burdick et al. 2012">Burdick, A., Drucker, J.,
                    Luenfeld, P., Presner, T., &amp; Schnapp, J. (2012). <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital_Humanities</title>. New York: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="butler2013" label="Butler and Purves 2013">Butler, S. &amp; Purves, A.
                    2013. <title rend="italic">Synaesthesia and the Ancient Senses</title>. Durham:
                    Acumen.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chapman2017" label="Chapman 2017">Chapman, A. 2017. <ref
                        target="https://www.academia.edu/12633230/Digital_Games_as_History_How_Videogames_Represent_the_Past_and_Offer_Access_to_Historical_Practice"
                            ><title rend="italic">Digital Games as History: How Videogames Represent
                            the Past and Offer Access to Historical Practice</title></ref>, London:
                    Routledge. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chapman2016" label="Chapman, Foka, and Westin 2016">Chapman, A. Foka,
                    A., Westin, J. (2016) <title rend="quotes">What Is Historical Game
                        Studies?</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Rethinking History</title> vol.20:4, Taylor and
                    Francis. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="classen1997" label="Classen 1997">Classen, C. 1997. <title
                        rend="quotes">Foundations for an Anthropology of the Senses</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">International Social Science Journal</title> 49 (153): 401–12. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crane2009" label="Crane, Seales, and Terras 2009">Crane, G., Seales
                    B., and Terras, M. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Changing the center of gravity:
                        Transforming classical studies through cyberinfrastructure</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title>, 3(1). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dixon2007" label="Dixon 2007">Dixon, S. 2007. Digital performance: a
                    history of new <hi rend="bold">media</hi> in theater, dance, performance <hi
                        rend="bold">art</hi>, and installation, Cambridge, Massachussets: MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="drucker2011" label="Drucker 2011">Drucker, J. 2011. <title
                        rend="quotes">Humanities Approaches to Graphical Display</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> 5:1.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clark2008" label="Clark 2008 (1998)">Clark, A. &amp; Chalmers, D.
                    (2008) [1998] <title rend="quotes">The Extended Mind</title> in Clark, <title
                        rend="italic">Supersizing the Mind: embodiment, action, and cognitive
                        extension</title>, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen1997" label="Cohen Bull 1997">Cohen Bull, C. 1997. <title
                        rend="quotes">Sense, meaning and perception in three dance cultures</title>
                    in Desmond (ed.) <title rend="italic">Meaning in Motion: new cultural studies of
                        dance</title>. Durham: Duke University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="damasio1999" label="Damasio 1999">Damasio, A. 1999. <title
                        rend="italic">The feeling of what happens: body and emotion in the making of
                        consciousness</title>. New York: Harcourt Brace.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="evens2005" label="Evens 2005">Evens, A. 2005. <title rend="italic"
                        >Sound Ideas: Music, Machines, and Experience</title> (Minneapolis, MN:
                    University of Minnesota Press, 2005). </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="foka2016" label="Foka 2016">Foka, A. &amp; Arvidsson, V. 2016. <title
                        rend="quotes">Experiential Analogies: A Sonic Digital Ekphrasis as a Digital
                        Humanities Project</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                        Quarterly</title> 10.2.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="foka2017" label="Foka 2017">Foka A. &amp;Gelfgren, S. 2017, <title
                        rend="quotes">Visualisering som verktyg och metod för
                        historieforskning</title>. Stockholm: Daedalus.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Foka 2018" xml:id="foka2018">Foka, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">The
                        Digital Aesthetic in Atlantis: the Evidence</title> in Hobden, F. and
                    Wringley, A. <title rend="italic">Ancient Greece on British Television</title>,
                    University of Edinburgh Press. 187-202. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fokaetal2017" label="Foka et al. 2017">Foka, A., Misharina, A.,
                    Arvidsson A., and Gelfgren, S. (2017) <title rend="quotes">Digitalized
                        Infrastructures: Towards a viable socio-spatial model for Arts and
                        Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the
                        Humanities</title>: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="forte2010" label="Forte 2010">Forte, M. (ed) 2010. <title
                        rend="italic">Cyber Archaeology</title>. BAR International Series 2177,
                    Oxford: Archaeopress.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="frischer2006" label="Frischer et al. 2006">Frischer, B., Abernathy,
                    D., Giuliani, F. C., Scott, R. T., and Ziemssen, H. 2006. <title rend="quotes">A
                        New Digital Model of the Roman Forum</title>. In <title rend="italic"
                        >Imaging Ancient Rome</title> edited by Haselberger, L. and Humphrey, J.,
                    Portsmouth, RI: Journal of Roman Archaeology, 163-182. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallagher2005" label="Gallagher 2005">Gallagher, S. 2005. <title
                        rend="italic">How the body shapes the mind</title>. Oxford: Clarendon </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gallese2005" label="Gallese and Lakoff 2005">Gallese, V. &amp; Lakoff,
                    G. 2005. <title rend="quotes">The brain’s concepts: the role of the
                        sensory-motor system in conceptual knowledge</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Cognitive Neuropsychology</title> 22.3-4, 455-79.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="garelli2007" label="Garelli 2007">Garelli, M-H., 2007. <title
                        rend="italic">Danser le Mythe: la Pantomime et sa Réception dans la Culture
                        Antique</title>. Louvain: Peeters.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="giaccardi2012" label="Giaccardi et al. 2012">Giaccardi, G. et al 2012.
                        <title rend="italic">Digital Heritage and Social Media.</title> New York:
                    Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gold2012" label="Gold 2012">Gold, M. K. (ed.), <title rend="italic"
                        >Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> (2012). Minneapolis: University
                    of Minnesota Press: 490–509. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hall2008" label="Hall 2008">Hall, E., 2008. Is the <title
                        rend="quotes">Barcelona Alcestis</title> a Latin pantomime libretto? In: E.
                    Hall and R. Wyles, eds. <title rend="italic">New Directions in Ancient
                        Pantomime</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press. 258-82.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hallwyles2008" label="Hall and Wyles 2008">Hall, E. and Wyles, R.,
                    eds. 2008. <title rend="italic">New Directions in Ancient Pantomime</title>.
                    Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howes2005" label="Howes 2005">Howes, D. 2005. <title rend="italic"
                        >Empire of the Senses: the Sensual Culture Reader.</title> Oxford:
                    Berg.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ingleheart2008" label="Ingleheart 2008">Ingleheart, J., 2008.
                        &quot;<foreign xml:lang="la">Et mea sunt populo saltata poemata
                        saepe</foreign>&quot; (<title rend="italic">Tristia</title> 2.519): Ovid and
                    the pantomime. In: E. Hall and R. Wyles, eds. <title rend="italic">New
                        Directions in Ancient Pantomime</title>, Oxford: Oxford University Press.
                    198-217.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kilteni2012" label="Kilteni, Groten, and Slater 2012">Kilteni, K.,
                    Groten, R. And Slater, M. 2012 <title rend="quotes">The Sense of Embodiment in
                        Virtual Reality</title> MIT Presence. vol. 21, No. 4, Pages 373-387. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kolsouzoglou2006" label="Kolsouzoglou and Veneris 2006">Kolsouzoglou,
                    A., Veneris, Y. 2006 Studying Antikythera Mechanism in Mixed Reality. In: <title
                        rend="italic">International Conference on Decoding the Antikythera Mechanism
                        - Science and Technology in Ancient Greece</title>. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lada-richards2013" label="Lada-Richards 2013">Lada-Richards, I. 2013.
                        <title rend="quotes">Mutata corpora: Ovid’s changing forms and the
                        metamorphic bodies of pantomime dancing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Transactions of the American Philological
                        Association</title> 143.1.105−52.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lada-richards2007" label="Lada-Richards 2007">Lada-Richards, I. 2007.
                        <title rend="italic">Silent Eloquence: Lucian and Pantomime Dancing</title>.
                    London: Duckworth.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="macintosh2010" label="Macintosh 2010">Macintosh, F., ed., 2010. <title
                        rend="italic">The Ancient Dancer in the Modern World: Responses to Greek and
                        Roman dance</title>, Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mahony2010" label="Mahony and Bodard 2010">Mahony, S. and Bodard, G.
                    2010. <title rend="quotes">Introduction</title>. In <title rend="quotes">Digital
                        Research in the Study of Classical Antiquity</title>, edited by Mahony, S.
                    and Bodard, G., Surrey Ashgate: 1-14. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="manovich2001" label="Manovich 2001">Manovich, L. (2001). <title
                        rend="italic">The Language of New Media</title>, MIT Press. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mcmillan2002" label="McMillan 2002"> McMillan, S. 2002 <title
                        rend="quotes">Some cyber-places are more interactive than others : A
                        four-part model of cyber-interactivity</title>, <title rend="italic">New
                        Media and Society</title>. Vol 4(2): 271–291. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="noë2004" label="Noë 2004">Noë, A. 2004. <title rend="italic">Action in
                        Perception</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: M.I.T Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nygren2014" label="Nygren, Foka, and Buckland 2014">Nygren, T., Foka,
                    A., and Buckland, P. 2014 <title rend="quotes">Digital History in
                    Sweden</title>. H-Soz- Kult, Humbolt: Humbolt University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rowlands2010" label="Rowlands 2010">Rowlands, M. 2010. <title
                        rend="italic">The New Science of the Mind: from extended mind to embodied
                        phenomenology</title>. Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="scott2012" label="Scott 2012">Scott, C. 2012. <title rend="italic"
                        >Literary Translation and the Rediscovery of Reading</title>. Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="schreibman2004" label="Schreibman, Siemens, and Unsworth 2004"
                    >Schreibman, S., Siemens, R., Unsworth, J. 2004. <title rend="italic">A
                        Companion to Digital Humanities</title>. Oxford: Blackwell.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="shapiro2004" label="Shapiro 2004">Shapiro, L. 2004. <title
                        rend="italic">The Mind Incarnate.</title> Cambridge, Mass.: MIT
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="sheets-johnstone2011" label="Sheets-Johnstone 2011">Sheets-Johnstone,
                    M. 2011. <title rend="italic">The primacy of movement</title> (2<hi
                        rend="superscript">nd</hi> edn.). Amsterdam: John Benjamins.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="smithies2014" label="Smithies 2014">Smithies, J. 2014 <title
                        rend="quotes">Digital Humanities, Postfoundationalism, Postindustrial
                        Culture</title>
                    <title rend="italic">DHQ</title> Vol.8 n.1.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="starks2008" label="Starks 2008">Starks, J.H. 2008. <title
                        rend="quotes">Pantomime actresses in Latin inscriptions</title> in Hall
                    &amp; Wyles (eds.) <title rend="italic">New Directions in Ancient
                        Pantomime</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="toner2014" label="Toner 2014">Toner, J. 2014. <title rend="italic">A
                        Cultural History of the Senses in Antiquity</title>. London:
                    Bloomsbury.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="webb2008" label="Webb 2008">Webb, R. 2008. <title rend="italic">Demons
                        and Dancers: Performance in Late Antiquity</title>. Cambridge,
                    Massachussets: Harvard.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="westin2012" label="Westin 2012">Westin, J. 2012. <title rend="italic"
                        >Negotiating Culture, Assembling a Past: the Visual, the Non-Visual and the
                        Voice of the Silent Actant</title>. Gothenburg: University of Gothenburg
                    Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Westin, Chapman, and Foka 2018" xml:id="westin2018">Westin, J.,
                    Chapman, A. and Foka, A. (2018) <title rend="quotes">Special issue on Technology
                        and Cultural Heritage for Histories of the Oppressed,</title>
                    <title rend="italic">International Journal of Heritage Studies</title>:
                    Routledge, 24, volume 3: 283–286. </bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="witmore2006" label="Witmore 2006">Witmore, C. L. 2006. <title
                        rend="quotes">Vision, Media Noise and the Percolation of Time: Symmetrical
                        Approaches to the Mediation of the Material World</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Journal of Material Culture</title> Vol. 11(3): 267–29.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="wyles2008" label="Wyles 2008">Wyles, R. <title rend="quotes">The
                        symbolism of costume in ancient pantomime</title> in Hall &amp; Wyles (eds.)
                        <title rend="italic">New Directions in Ancient Pantomime</title>. Oxford:
                    Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zanobi2013" label="Zanobi 2013">Zanobi, A. 2013. <title rend="italic"
                        >Seneca’s Tragedies and the Aesthetics of Pantomime</title>. London:
                    Bloomsbury.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vitale2016" label="Vitale 2016"> Vitale, V. 2016, <title rend="quotes"
                        >Transparent, Multivocal, Cross-disciplinary: The Use of Linked Open Data
                        and a Community-developed RDF Ontology to Document and Enrich 3D
                        Visualisation for Cultural Heritage.</title> In: Bodard, G &amp; Romanello,
                    M (eds.) <title rend="italic">Digital Classics Outside the Echo-Chamber:
                        Teaching, Knowledge Exchange &amp; Public Engagement</title>. London:
                    Ubiquity Press 147-68. </bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
