<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">GIS and Literary History: Advancing Digital Humanities
                    research through the Spatial Analysis of historical travel writing and
                    topographical literature</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Patricia
                        <dhq:family>Murrieta-Flores</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Digital Humanities Research Centre, University of
                        Chester</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>p.murrietaflores@chester.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Patricia Murrieta-Flores is Director of the Digital Humanities Research
                            Centre at the University of Chester, UK; she is also European Research
                            Council Senior Researcher on the The Past in its Place project
                            (2014-2016) and an affiliate of the European Research Council-funded
                            project Spatial Humanities: Texts, GIS, Places (2012–2016).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Christopher
                        <dhq:family>Donaldson</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>History Department, Lancaster University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>c.e.donaldson@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Christopher Donaldson is Lecturer in Regional History at Lancaster
                            University. He is co-I on the Leverhulme Trust-funded project Geospatial
                            Innovation in the Digital Humanities (2015–2018); he is also an
                            affiliate of the European Research Council-funded project Spatial
                            Humanities: Texts, GIS, Places (2012–2016). </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Ian <dhq:family>Gregory</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>History Department, Lancaster University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>i.gregory@lancaster.ac.uk</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Ian N. Gregory is Professor of Digital Humanities at Lancaster
                            University. He is PI on both the Leverhulme Trust-funded project
                            Geospatial Innovation in the Digital Humanities (2015–2018) and the
                            European Research Council-funded project Spatial Humanities: Texts, GIS,
                            Places (2012–2016).</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000283</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">1</idno>
                <date when="2016-11-29">29 November 2016</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item>Spatial Humanities</item>
                        <item>Literary GIS</item>
                        <item>English Literature</item>
                        <item>Travel writing</item>
                        <item>English Lake District</item>
                        <item>Cost Surface Analysis</item>
                        <item>Least Cost Paths</item>
                        <item>Digital Mapping</item>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="JDF" when="2016-11-15">Created file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>Exploratory studies have demonstrated the benefits of implementing Geographic
                    Information Systems (GIS) technology in literary and cultural-historical
                    research. These studies have done much to affirm the power and flexibility of
                    GIS technology as a resource for humanities scholarship. At the same time,
                    however, these studies share a common limitation in that they tend to rely on
                    the analysis of point-based cartographic representations. Such representations
                    are suitable for modelling quantitative geographical phenomena, but they are
                    inadequate for modelling qualitative human phenomena. This inadequacy
                    constitutes a significant problem for researchers who aspire to analyse the
                    geographical experiences and spatial relationships represented in works of
                    literature, including works that contain accounts of travel. The present article
                    proposes a solution to this problem by demonstrating how advanced spatial
                    analyses within GIS such as Cost-Surface Analysis (CSA) and Least-Cost-Path
                    Analysis (LCP) can be used to facilitate more nuanced interpretations of
                    historical works of travel writing and topographical literature. Specifically,
                    the article explains how GIS, CSA and LCP can be combined to build coherent
                    spatial models of the journeys recorded in the works of three canonical
                    eighteenth-century British travellers, each of whom composed influential
                    accounts of their travels through the English Lake District: the poet Thomas
                    Gray (1716–1771), the naturalist Thomas Pennant (1726–1798) and the
                    agriculturist Arthur Young (1741–1820).</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>Demonstrates how advanced spatial analyses within GIS can be used to facilitate
                    more nuanced interpretations of historical works of travel writing and
                    topographical literature.</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>

            <div>
                <head>1. Introduction</head>
                <p>Geographic Information Systems (GIS) technology has been at the forefront of
                    research in the applied sciences since its inception during the 1960s. In the
                    Humanities, however, the use of GIS has been much more sporadic. This latter
                    trend can principally be attributed to the fact that only some Humanities
                    disciplines routinely engage with the kinds of quantitative and geographical
                    data that GIS were designed to analyse <ptr target="#pickles1995"/>
                    <ptr target="#bodenhamer2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#bodenhamer2015"/>. Thus, whereas specialists in the discipline of
                    Archaeology have been employing GIS since the early 1980s <ptr
                        target="#aldenderfer1996"/>
                    <ptr target="#fotheringham2000"/>
                    <ptr target="#wheatley2002"/>
                    <ptr target="#conolly2006"/>
                    <ptr target="#parker2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#okabe2006"/>
                    <ptr target="#goodchild2010"/>, in disciplines such as History, equivalent
                    fields of digital research have only emerged over the past two decades <ptr
                        target="#knowles2008"/>
                    <ptr target="#gregory2003"/>
                    <ptr target="#gregory2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#knowles2008"/>. Within Literary Studies, the discipline with which
                    this article is primarily concerned, the turn towards GIS has occurred even more
                    recently and has been driven both by a growing interest in the study of space,
                    place and landscape, and by the refinement of the application of quantitative
                    methods and computational approaches in literary research <ptr
                        target="#moretti1999"/>
                    <ptr target="#moretti2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#moretti2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#jockers2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#tally2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#donaldson2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#gregory2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#cooper2016"/>. </p>
                <p> These disciplinary trends in Literary Studies have been shaped by pioneering
                    interdisciplinary scholarship which has enabled literary critics, theorists and
                    historians to work with Geographic Information Scientists on projects that
                    employ GIS in collaborative research. One innovation that has occurred as a
                    result of this research is the implementation of GIS in the study of both
                    individual literary works and literary corpora composed of several works. This
                    development has variously been labelled ‘Literary GIS’ (see <ptr
                        target="#cooper2016"/>). Notably, between 2007 and 2008 the British
                    Academy-funded <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Lakes: A Literary GIS</title>
                    project at Lancaster University tested the interpretive possibilities of using
                    GIS to compare different literary accounts of the English Lake District: a
                    mountainous region in north-western England that has particularly significant
                    associations with British literature and art <ptr target="#gregory2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#cooper2011"/>. More recently, research projects at the New
                    University of Lisbon, Trinity College Dublin, ETH Zurich, the University of
                    Edinburgh, Cardiff University and Stanford University have adopted similar
                    approaches in order to explore the imaginative and affective geographies of
                    writers and readers, and to examine how these geographies intertwine with one
                    another <ptr target="#alves2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#travis2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#piatti2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#andersonloxley2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#anderson2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#heuser2016"/>. The studies undertaken by these research projects
                    have enriched our understanding both of specific geographies and of the
                    potential of geospatial technologies, including GIS, as resources for literary
                    and cultural-historical research. </p>
                <p>At the same time, however, these studies share a common limitation in that they
                    largely rely on the analysis of distribution maps and other kinds of point-based
                    cartographic representations. Point-based mapping techniques are useful for
                    plotting the position of fixed geographical features and for facilitating the
                    implementation of methodologies such as point pattern analysis; but these
                    techniques are also reductive in that they limit the real complexity of places
                    as sites of social engagement and interaction. Although we are accustomed to
                    thinking about places as being <q>static</q>, or as being defined by fixed
                    boundaries, their cultural significance is in fact defined by other factors,
                    such as the interconnected flow of experiences that converge in them and the
                    roles they play as nodes in larger spatial networks <ptr target="#ingold2009"/>.
                    Point-based maps are suitable for structuring the analysis of quantitative
                    geographical phenomena, such as proximity and scale; however, they are less
                    adequate for structuring the analysis of qualitative human phenomena, such as
                    the experience of visiting a place or of travelling from one place to another.
                    This is a significant problem for scholars who are engaged in research that
                    aspires to analyse the geographical experiences and spatial relationships
                    represented in literary works and, even more specifically, in works of travel
                    writing and topographical literature. Analysing such works requires us to
                    consider how the accounts they contain are shaped not only by the experience of
                    specific locations, but also by the experience of travelling
                        <emph>through</emph> and <emph>between</emph> those locations. We need to
                    come to grips with both of these types of experience in order to appreciate how
                    the authors of the accounts we are reading encountered and apprehended the
                    places and landmarks they describe. </p>
                <p>The present article proposes and models a GIS-based approach that can assist with
                    structuring analyses that satisfy these requirements. In what follows, we shall
                    demonstrate how advanced GIS-based spatial analysis, particularly Cost-Surface
                    Analysis (CSA) and Least-Cost-Path Analysis (LCP), can facilitate more nuanced
                    interpretations of historical works of travel writing and topographical
                    literature. Our objective in the following pages shall be to combine these
                    methodologies to perform a spatial analysis of the journeys recorded in the
                    travelogues of three canonical, eighteenth-century British travellers: the poet
                    Thomas Gray (1716–1771), the naturalist Thomas Pennant (1726–1798) and the
                    agriculturist Arthur Young (1741–1820). The travelogues of Gray, Young and
                    Pennant are diverse works, and they reflect the fact that these three writers
                    undertook their journeys for distinctive reasons. For the sake of concision, we
                    shall limit our analyses to the portions of Gray, Young and Pennant’s writings
                    that concern the English Lake District, and we shall focus on employing GIS, CSA
                    and LCP to investigate how the relative accessibility of the Lakeland landscape
                    influenced both the routes these three travellers followed and, consequently,
                    the experiences documented in their accounts.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>2. Enhancing <q>Literary GIS</q> through the spatial analysis of historical
                    travel writing and topographical literature</head>
                <div>
                    <head>2.1 <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Lakes</title></head>
                    <p>In engaging with a selection of historical works about the English Lake
                        District, this article aims to extend and refine aspects of the research
                        undertaken by the <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Lakes</title> project.
                        The chief case study completed by <title rend="quotes">Mapping the
                            Lakes</title> focused on two famous accounts of the Lake District. In
                        that study, Thomas Gray’s Lakeland travelogue (written in 1769) was assessed
                        alongside the letters and notes that a later writer, the Romantic poet
                        Samuel Taylor Coleridge (1772–1834), composed during his ramble through the
                        western fells of the Lake District in 1802. As the findings of this case
                        study demonstrated, although Gray’s and Coleridge’s texts ostensibly contain
                        accounts of the same landscape, a GIS mapping of them reveals a set of
                        radically divergent patterns (Figure 1).</p>


                    <figure>
                        <head>Maps of Gray’s (left) and Coleridge’s (right) tours through the Lake
                            District <ptr target="#gregory2009"/>; reproduced with the authors’
                            permission.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.jpg"/>
                    </figure>


                    <p>Significantly, these divergent patterns point up a number of the key
                        differences between Gray’s and Coleridge’s excursions. Gray’s tour was a
                        fifteen-day trip by coach and horseback from Brough to Lancaster via the
                        lakes of Ullswater, Derwentwater, Thirlmere and Windermere. Coleridge’s
                        tour, by contrast, was a nine-day odyssey taken on foot from his house in
                        Keswick to the coastal village of St Bees, and thence famously over Scafell
                        Pike to Eskdale and Coniston before returning homeward over Dunmail Raise.
                        These contrasting routes indicate crucial differences in touristic attitudes
                        and practices <ptr target="#cooper2011" loc="93–95"/>. Gray’s account,
                        though famously one of the earliest documents of its kind, exemplifies many
                        of the tendencies of later picturesque tourism in the Lake District. Gray
                        travelled on coach roads in a planned route that took him through densely
                        populated areas to sites of visual grandeur and beauty. Coleridge, by
                        contrast, was a resident of the Lake District at the time he set off for the
                        western fells, and his irregular route reflected his desire to avoid
                        well-trodden paths. In short, whereas Gray was rather unabashedly what we
                        would call a tourist, Coleridge regarded himself as a traveller (see <ptr
                            target="#buzard1993"/>
                        <ptr target="#cooper2012"/>). </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>2.2 Enhancing the study of historical travelogues through spatial
                        analysis</head>
                    <p>In using GIS to ground these interpretations, the study completed by the
                            <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Lakes</title> project confirmed that
                        quantitative spatial approaches can play a meaningful role in the
                        qualitative analysis of works of travel writing and topographical
                        literature. Our current research into the implementation of CSA and LCP
                        builds on these results, and it aims to enhance further the use of GIS-based
                        methodologies in literary and cultural-historical scholarship. Our
                        contention is that methods such as CSA and LCP can enable researchers to
                        move beyond merely schematic point-based mapping techniques and towards
                        spatial methodologies that are sensitive to the fact that places are
                        characterised by much more than their geographic location. </p>
                    <p>As the map displayed in Figure 1 indicates, the <title rend="quotes">Mapping
                            the Lakes</title> project used straight lines to represent the
                        itineraries of Gray’s and Coleridge’s Lake District tours. Although this
                            <q>connect-the-dots</q> strategy does portray the sequence of places
                        that Gray and Coleridge visited, the geometrical depiction it produces gives
                        us, at best, a superficial understanding of how the physical geography of
                        the Lake District shaped the experiences documented in their accounts.
                        Integrating CSA and LCP, we decided to undertake a more nuanced spatial
                        analysis of a selection of key historical Lake District travelogues. Once
                        again, we decided to focus on Gray’s account, which was composed in 1769 as
                        a series of epistles to his friend Thomas Wharton. But instead of working
                        with Coleridge’s account (which was written more than four decades later),
                        we elected to draw on the accounts of two other writers who toured the Lake
                        District at roughly the same time as Gray did. The first of these writers,
                        again, is Arthur Young, who paid a visit to the Lakes whilst completing an
                        agricultural survey of Northern England in 1768; the second is Thomas
                        Pennant, who passed through the region as part of his tours of Scotland in
                        1769 and 1772.</p>
                    <p>Our decision to focus on Gray, Young and Pennant is not, however, solely
                        based on chronology. It is, more significantly, based on the fact that they
                        were the three chief authorities cited in Thomas West’s highly influential
                            <title rend="italic">A Guide to the Lakes</title> (1778). A foundational
                        work in the history of British tourism, West’s <title rend="italic">Guide to
                            the Lakes</title> sold through an unprecedented eleven editions and was
                        still being reprinted more than forty years after its initial publication.
                        It was, accordingly, the work through which most late-eighteenth-century and
                        early-nineteenth-century Lake District tourists first encountered Gray,
                        Young and Pennant’s writings about the region. Importantly, however, West’s
                        guide only reproduces portions of each of these writer’s accounts of the
                        Lake District and thus only gives a partial glimpse of the geographies of
                        their Lakeland tours. In using LCP and CSA to investigate Gray, Young and
                        Pennant’s accounts of the Lake District, then, our aim was to achieve a
                        better understanding of the experience of Lake District travellers in the
                        era before the region was popularised by the works of writers such as West.
                        More broadly, our objectives in spatially analysing the tours of these three
                        writers were threefold: </p>
                    <list type="ordered">
                        <item>In the first place, we wanted to assess the extent to which the Lake
                            District’s topography conditioned Gray, Young and Pennant’s accounts by
                            determining the degree to which the places each writer records having
                            visited either corresponds to or deviates from the corridors formed by
                            the natural contours of the region’s terrain.</item>
                        <item>In the second place, our object was to compare Gray, Young and
                            Pennant’s accounts in order to ascertain whether they collectively or
                            individually favoured particular parts of the Lakeland region, and
                            (whenever a preference for a particular place or type of place could be
                            discerned) to assess the reason for the writers’ attraction to specific
                            locations.</item>
                        <item>Finally, our goal was to employ GIS technology to create not only more
                            accurate visualisations of the routes Gray, Young and Pennant followed,
                            but also to examine the spatial relationship between these routes and
                            the places Gray, Young and Pennant mentioned, but did not visit.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>3. Simulating and analysing Gray, Young and Pennant’s tours </head>
                <div>
                    <head>3.1 Workflow and methodology</head>
                    <p>We shall proceed to explain the use of CSA and LCP momentarily. Before we do,
                        however, we will first summarize succinctly the steps we took to meet each
                        of our three objectives. The first step in this process was to create a
                        GIS-readable version of the tours documented in Gray, Young and Pennant’s
                        accounts of the Lake District, and this itself involved several stages.
                        First of all, we had to digitise the portions of each writer’s account that
                        dealt with the Lakeland region. This gave us a set of text extracts
                        comprising <ptr target="#gray1775" loc="350–379"/>
                        <ptr target="#young1770" loc="III, 117–196"/>
                        <ptr target="#pennant1771" loc="216–220"/>
                        <ptr target="#pennant1774" loc="23–71"/>.<note>Pennant, as noted above,
                            passed through the Lakeland region twice and thus provided us with two
                            extracts.</note> Once we had prepared these extracts, we read them
                        individually to identify and to record every place-name reference each
                        extract contained. These place-names were then manually coded using XML and
                        divided into groups to distinguish the places and landmarks that the writers
                        visited from those they mentioned but did not visit. The places and
                        landmarks tagged as having been visited were then arranged sequentially in a
                        table to form an itinerary for each account. Once tagged, annotated and
                        arranged in this manner, the place-names were geo-referenced using
                        coordinate data from the Old Cumbria Gazetteer <ptr target="#norgate2014"/>.
                        The fully georeferenced dataset was then uploaded into ArcGIS. This dataset
                        represents the geographic information contained in Gray, Young and Pennant’s
                        accounts as isolated points on the Lakeland landscape; however, it also
                        provides a platform for performing more sophisticated forms of geographical
                        analysis (such as CSA and LCP) in order to explore these accounts as records
                        of movement <emph>through</emph> that landscape. </p>
                    <p>In order to achieve our first objective, we used CSA and LCP to simulate the
                        natural corridors, determining the most efficient route for travelling over
                        the terrain taking into account the relief of the Lake District’s
                        topography. We then implemented a spatial proximity test in order to assess
                        whether the places in itineraries we had extracted from Gray, Young and
                        Pennant’s accounts were closer to the natural corridors formed by the
                        region’s topography than would be expected by chance alone. Performing this
                        test allowed us to ascertain the relative accessibility of the places each
                        writer decided to visit. In order to achieve our second objective, we
                        simulated the routes most likely taken by the three writers according to the
                        places they visited. Taking the journeys of the three authors into account,
                        we then employed a Line Density Analysis (LDA) to identify the most
                        frequented routes in order to determine whether there was a preponderance of
                        attention given to any particular area or region. Finally, in order to
                        achieve our third objective, we carried out another spatial proximity test.
                        In this instance, however, we analysed the spatial relationship between the
                        simulated pathways and those places that were mentioned in Gray, Young and
                        Pennant’s accounts, but which were not actually sites these travellers
                        visited. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.2 CSA and LCP</head>
                    <p>The use of CSA and LCP is well established in the applied sciences <ptr
                            target="#collischon2000"/>
                        <ptr target="#yu2003"/>
                        <ptr target="#adriaensen2003"/>
                        <ptr target="#atkinson2005"/>
                        <ptr target="#gonzales2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#howey2007"/>
                        <ptr target="#larue2008"/>
                        <ptr target="#wang2009"/>. But this is the first time that these methods
                        have been used in Humanities research to analyse the journeys recorded in
                        historical travelogues. Admittedly, there are limitations to employing the
                        geospatial models that CSA and LCP create to study the accounts of
                        historical travellers. Methods such as CSA and LCP are ideal for measuring
                        the degree to which the routes taken by travellers correlate with the
                        contours of the terrain those travellers are traversing. CSA and LCP do not,
                        however, offer much in the way of insight about those traveller’s attitudes
                        towards the landscape through which they are moving or about the ideas they
                        form whilst moving through it. As GIS-based methods, CSA and LCP rely on
                        computational processes for which quantification is a prerequisite, and much
                        of the information contained in works of travel writing (including feelings,
                        sensations, and intuitions) is not necessarily quantifiable. Such
                        limitations notwithstanding, CSA and LCP can contribute meaningfully to our
                        understanding of historical works of travel writing and topographical
                        literature. In particular, CSA and LCP can assist us with visualising the
                        journeys such works describe, and they can alert us to geographical patterns
                        that are not otherwise readily discernible. In sum, then, these methods are
                        not a substitute for interpretation; rather, they are an aid for guiding
                        critical inquiry and facilitating research. </p>
                    <p> CSA is a spatial methodology that allows one to determine the <q>cost</q> of
                        travelling over a surface by considering not only Euclidean space, but also
                        more complicated factors, such as slope and elevation. In other words,
                        instead of limiting us to the examination of the Cartesian spatial
                        properties of the data, it allows us to consider additional factors such as
                        the contours of the terrain, as well as other variables (such as boundaries
                        and borders) which influence how one moves through the landscape <ptr
                            target="#murrietaflores2012"/>. The first step in creating a cost
                        surface model in a GIS environment involves using a Digital Elevation Model
                        (DEM), which is a raster image that represents the topography of the surface
                        of the earth. Raster images, like DEMs, are similar to digital pictures;
                        they are composed of pixels (or, more properly, cells) to which attribute
                        information has been assigned. In digital pictures, this attribute
                        information typically assigns a colour or shade to each cell. In a DEM,
                        however, the attribute information assigned to each cell relates to the
                        elevation of the portion of the earth’s surface which that cell represents
                        (Figure 2). </p>


                    <figure>
                        <head>Representation of morphometric types of the terrain in a DEM (after
                                <ptr target="#wood1996" loc="112"/>); the information in each cell
                            of the raster image assigns that cell an elevation.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>



                    <p>The second step in performing CSA is to establish the associated cost of
                        traversing the terrain and any impediments (such as rivers or bodies of
                        water) it might contain. This is accomplished by creating a <term>friction
                            surface</term>. Like DEMs, friction surfaces are raster images. In a
                        friction surface, though, the cells that comprise the image contain
                        information about the variables that influence the amount of effort it would
                        take to travel across the terrain being represented. There are several cost
                        functions that can be used to create a friction surface and to derive
                        friction values <ptr target="#herzog2013"/>. The variables used in these
                        functions can take a variety of different costs into account, such as the
                        mode of transportation being used, the type of surface being crossed and the
                        slope of the terrain <ptr target="#fairen2004"/>
                        <ptr target="#fairen2006"/>
                        <ptr target="#fiz2008"/>
                        <ptr target="#frachetti2008"/>
                        <ptr target="#wheatley2010"/>
                        <ptr target="#murrietaflores2012"/>
                        <ptr target="#yubero2015"/>. These variables can also account for values
                        based on other costs, such as the amount of weight the traveller is carrying
                        or the speed at which the traveller is moving. The values of such costs are
                        stored in each cell of the friction raster map, which is accordingly used to
                        calculate the relative cost of traversing the terrain (Figure 3).</p>




                    <figure>
                        <head>Example of slope surface reclassified into a friction surface
                            depicting a cost from 1 (easy) to 5 (difficult) for traversing the
                            terrain represented.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                    </figure>



                    <p> The third step in performing the CSA is to derive from the friction surface,
                        a final <term>cost surface</term>. This is done by calculating the cost of
                        traversing the terrain from a source cell or point of origin. This source
                        cell acts as a node from which to begin calculating the cumulative value of
                        traversing the terrain. In this process, the adjacent cell with the lowest
                        cost is searched for repeatedly until each of the cells has a cumulative
                        cost value assigned to it <ptr target="#stucky1998"/>. The result is a
                        raster image called <q>cost surface</q> that depicts the cumulative cost of
                        travelling from a source or point of origin to any other location within the
                        terrain represented (Figure 4). This step is performed multiple times to
                        calculate the cost to travel from each location to any part of the
                        landscape, which result in cost surfaces derived for each place investigated
                        in the corpus. </p>




                    <figure>
                        <head>An example of cost surface calculated in terms of the cost incurred to
                            reach any place in the Lakeland region from Delmaine; the farther one
                            travels from the node, the greater the cost incurred.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.jpg"/>
                    </figure>



                    <p>Once the cost surfaces have been established, one can then proceed with
                        completing LCP. LCP is, essentially, a subsequent set of calculations that
                        determines the path across the cost surface that will cost the traveller the
                        least. The GIS is instructed to create a path across the cost surface
                        following the adjacent cell with the lowest value assigned. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>3.3 Implementing CSA and LCP</head>
                    <p>As with the cost surface, the paths that result from performing LCP analysis
                        are dependent on the cost variables that were used to create the model. For
                        the purposes of this case study, we created two anisotropic models using
                        ArcGIS. Anisotropic models account for the direction of movement in the
                        calculation of the cost, whereas isotropic models do not. It should be noted
                        that for each of our experiments we made use of LCP, and that we created two
                        different models in order to meet our objectives. In order to avoid
                        confusion, when we discuss the results related to our first objective, we
                        shall use the expression <q>natural corridors</q> to indicate those paths
                        for which a model was designed to identify the least cost paths for the
                        whole region. When we discuss the results related to our second and third
                        objectives, we shall refer to either <q>simulated pathways</q> or
                            <q>simulated itineraries</q> in order to describe the model that was
                        designed to calculate the least cost paths for each of the authors’ tours. </p>

                    <div>
                        <head>3.3.1 Objective One: The influence of topography</head>
                        <p>In order to investigate the degree to which the Lake District’s
                            topography may have conditioned the itineraries of Gray, Young and
                            Pennant’s tours, we calculated the least cost paths between the places
                            each author visited. We accounted for three variables in these
                            calculations: 1. the slope of the region’s terrain; 2. the presence of
                            bodies of water; 3. the direction in which Gray, Young and Pennant were
                            each travelling (Figure 5). We then carried out a statistically based
                            spatial proximity test in order to assess the spatial relationship
                            between the places Gray, Young and Pennant visited and the Lake
                            District’s topography. In order to do this, we created a distance index
                            for the accounts of each writer by calculating buffers of 500m from the
                            natural corridors and then counting the number of visited places within
                            each buffer (Figure 6). We then used this data to perform a statistical
                            significance test (Kolmogorov-Smirnov). Our goal was to test whether the
                            places Gray, Young and Pennant visited were closer to the natural
                            corridors than one would expect by chance alone. The significance level
                            set to test the null hypothesis was 0.01, and in all cases it was
                            rejected. (As noted above, our goal here was to ascertain the degree to
                            which Gray, Young and Pennant were influenced by a logic of optimality
                            in their journeys: in other words, how closely they followed the natural
                            corridors of the terrain.) This finding suggests that Gray, Young and
                            Pennant did generally follow the natural corridors of the Lake District
                            in their journeys and, accordingly, either that they were able to read
                            the contours of the landscape successfully or, at least, that they were
                            well informed about the most efficient ways to move between the
                            locations through which they travelled. </p>


                        <figure>
                            <head>A map of the natural corridors of the region calculated with LCP
                                in GIS and places visited by Gray, Young and Pennant.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                        </figure>

                        <figure>
                            <head>A graph displaying the number of places visited by distance from
                                the natural corridors; the figures summarised here indicate that
                                most of the places Gray, Young and Pennant visited are located
                                either along or near the least cost paths.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.jpg"/>
                        </figure>

                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>3.3.2 Objective Two: The influence of specific places</head>
                        <p>Having thus satisfied the first of our three objectives, we then
                            proceeded to determine the extent to which Gray, Young and Pennant
                            emphasised specific portions of the Lake District in their tours. In
                            order to do this, it was necessary to construct simulations of the
                            journeys documented in their accounts. We built these simulations by
                            using each of the places in the itineraries we created for each writer
                            as nodes, and then by using cost surface analysis to calculate the least
                            cost path between these places, following the order in which they were
                            visited (Figure 7). After we calculated least cost paths for each
                            account, we then performed a LDA, which allowed us to identify those
                            parts of the landscape through which each of the writers were likely to
                            pass most frequently (Figure 8). Performing these analyses indicates
                            that, collectively, Gray, Young and Pennant spent a significant amount
                            of their time in the Lake District travelling around the lakes of
                            Windermere, Ullswater and Derwentwater. We will offer additional
                            commentary about these findings in the following section. But before
                            concluding, it is worth noting that in addition to examining the
                            locations Gray, Young and Pennant visited, we also performed an analysis
                            on the places they mentioned but did not visit.</p>



                        <figure>
                            <head>LCPs calculated from the itineraries of a) Young, b) Pennant 1771,
                                c) Gray, and d) Pennant 1774 during their tours. To the right is a
                                map displaying the road network through the Lake District in
                                    the18<hi rend="superscript">th</hi> century (after <ptr
                                    target="#hindle1998" loc="Figure 6.2"/>); reproduced with
                                permission of the author.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.jpg"/>
                        </figure>

                        <figure>
                            <head>LDA of all LCPs calculated; the key areas marked are a)
                                Derwentwater, b) Ullswater, and c) Windermere.</head>
                            <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.jpg"/>
                        </figure>
                    </div>

                    <div>
                        <head>3.3.3 Objective Three: The function of places mentioned, but not
                            visited</head>
                        <p>Our intention, in this case, was to determine the role played by these
                            unvisited places in the travel narratives presented in Gray, Young and
                            Pennant’s accounts. Accordingly, after we identified all the places in
                            the four accounts that were mentioned but not visited, we then carried
                            out another spatial proximity test. This time, the distance index for
                            each writer was calculated with buffers of 1 km created from the
                            itineraries simulated and the statistical test was also set to a
                            significance level of 0.01. Our intention was to assess the degree to
                            which the representation of the Lake District in each account was
                            influenced by the places Gray, Young and Pennant visited and the degree
                            to which it was influenced by places that they mentioned but did not
                            visit. The results of this test indicate that the places mentioned but
                            not visited in Gray and Young’s accounts, and in Pennant’s account of
                            his tour of 1772, are closer to the routes they these writers followed
                            than one would expect by chance alone. When it came to Pennant’s account
                            of his 1769 tour, however, the null hypothesis could not be rejected. As
                            we explain below, this result clues us into an important aspect of how
                            Pennant’s 1769 tour stands apart from the other texts assess in this
                            experiment.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>4. Analysis and interpretation</head>
                <p>We believe that the methods outlined above can facilitate more detailed analyses
                    of how the records of historical travellers were shaped by the contours of the
                    landscapes through which they travelled. What is more, to the degree that we
                    accept those travellers’ accounts as accurate descriptions of their journeys,
                    these methods can furnish useful insights into how their accounts were
                    conditioned by factors including the physical geography of the terrain, the
                    existence of roads and tracks, and the availability of specific kinds of
                    transportation. Our first spatial proximity analysis of the relationship between
                    the tours and the Lake District’s natural corridors demonstrates that all the
                    places Gray, Young and Pennant record visiting are nearer to these pathways than
                    would be expected by chance alone (Figure 5). In other words, although these
                    three writers certainly visited a few places that could be considered remote —
                    even adventurous — their itineraries still closely followed the natural
                    corridors of the Lake District. (Indeed, as indicated in Figure 6, most of the
                    places they visited fall within 500 metres of the region’s natural corridors.) </p>
                <p>These initial observations assist us in making some basic distinctions about the
                    tours documented by Gray, Young and Pennant. For instance, they help us to
                    discern that of the four accounts, the itinerary Pennant followed during his
                    1769 tour was the one that most closely adhered to the natural corridors of the
                    region’s topography. Comparatively, Young and Gray strayed farther from the Lake
                    District’s natural corridors. This finding makes sense, since in 1769 Pennant
                    merely travelled along the outskirts of the Lakeland region whilst on his return
                    from Scotland to his Downing estate. In his tour of 1772, Pennant visited other
                    parts of the Lake District, particularly the Cumberland coast. Here again,
                    however, the analysis shows us that, for the most part, he still followed the
                    natural contours of the region’s terrain. </p>
                <p> Beyond enabling us to draw such basic distinctions, the spatial proximity
                    analysis we conducted also helps us to perceive the correspondence between the
                    Lake District’s natural corridors and the routes that were present at the time
                    Gray, Young and Pennant paid their visits to the region. Inasmuch, this analysis
                    enables us to discern that, without exception, all three writers primarily
                    relied on local carriage roads and turnpikes in their travels. At first glance
                    this may seem a minor point, but it is of significant importance. Scholars <ptr
                        target="#andrews1989"/>
                    <ptr target="#ousby1990"/>
                    <ptr target="#powell2010"/> have long credited the accounts of early Lakeland
                    travellers, such as John Dalton and George Smith, with attracting tourists to
                    the region. At the same time, however, these scholars have generally paid less
                    attention to how the improvement of local roadways during the 1750s and 1760s
                    influenced the places to which those tourists were attracted. Brian Paul Hindle,
                    one of the few historians to devote substantial attention to the early history
                    of turnpikes in the Lake District, has observed that the influence of these
                    improvements was twofold. They not only established standard routes that
                    afforded swifter and safer access to several of the region’s main settlements
                    (including Kendal, Keswick, Carlisle, Lancaster and Penrith), but also, in doing
                    so, distinguished the places connected by, or at least visible from, these
                    routes as the sites most worthy of the tourist’s attention <ptr
                        target="#hindle1998" loc="147–177"/>
                    <ptr target="#bouch1961" loc="277–283"/>
                    <ptr target="#williams1975"/>. </p>
                <p> Accordingly, turning to Figure 8, it makes sense that the parts of the landscape
                    through which Gray, Young and Pennant passed most frequently are located in the
                    eastern half of the region (generally speaking, around the lakes of Ullswater,
                    Derwentwater and Windermere), since these were the sites around which the
                    majority of road improvements occurred. Incidentally, this also helps to explain
                    why neither Gray nor Young nor even Pennant — who travelled through much more of
                    Cumberland — set foot in the western valleys of Wasdale and Ennerdale. Although
                    turnpike acts were passed to improve access to this area in 1750 and 1762, the
                    roads in this remote part of the country remained in disrepair well into the
                    nineteenth century <ptr target="#hindle1998" loc="154"/>
                    <ptr target="#hodge1957" loc="67"/>. Indeed, whereas West, writing in 1778,
                    could confidently declare that the roads throughout the Lake District had been
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#west1778">much improved since Mr. Gray made
                        his tour in 1765 [sic], and Mr. Pennant his in 1772</quote>, as late as 1821
                    West’s guidebook (then in its eleventh edition) still cautioned tourists that
                    the roads leading to Ennerdale and Wasdale were, as yet, unimproved <ptr
                        target="#west1778" loc="2"/>
                    <ptr target="#west1821" loc="141"/>. Roads, in this way, can be seen to have
                    exerted a decided influence over the cultural construction of the Lake District
                    in the eighteenth century: they determined not only which portions of the
                    Lakeland region travellers visited, but also the perspectives those travellers
                    were afforded and, therefore, the descriptions of the region set down in their
                    accounts.</p>
                <p> So, in the first instance, Figure 7 shows us that Gray, Young and Pennant
                    chiefly went where the local carriage routes and turnpikes enabled them to go.
                    But how, we might ask, did those roadways shape their impression of the places
                    through which they passed? Cultural historians have often remarked, with due
                    amusement, that tourists in the late 1700s moved from scenic vista to scenic
                    vista, collecting sensations in much the same way that modern tourists collect
                    snapshots and souvenirs. Significantly, however, cultural histories of the Lake
                    District tend to quote passages from eighteenth-century travelogues and
                    guidebooks without commenting on the material conditions that determined the
                    writer’s point of view. Thus, whereas Gray’s panoramic description of Grasmere’s <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#gray1775">peace, rusticity, and happy
                            poverty</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gray1775" loc="365"/>
                    </cit> is regularly cited as an archetypal display of picturesque sentiment, few
                    scholars have noted that the poet’s perspective of the town was determined by
                    his having first seen it from the road over Dunmail Raise on a sunny autumn
                    afternoon. This is precisely the sort of empirical detail to which reading the
                    tours of Gray, Young and Pennant in relation to visualisations such as the one
                    displayed in Figure 9 helps to alert us. The following examples, from Young’s
                    and Pennant’s accounts of the journey over Shap Fell on the Heron Syke-Eamont
                    Bridge turnpike, help to develop this point further: <quote rend="block"
                        source="#young1770">Twelve of the fifteen miles from <hi rend="italic"
                            >Shapp</hi> to <hi rend="italic">Kendal</hi> are a continued chain of
                        mountainous <hi rend="italic">moors</hi>, totally uncultivated; one dreary
                        prospect, that makes one melancholy to behold. <ptr target="#young1770"
                            loc="III, 169"/></quote>
                    <quote rend="block" source="#pennant1771">Pass over <hi rend="italic">Shap</hi>
                        Fells, more black, dreary, and melancholy, than any of the Highland hills,
                        being not only very barren but destitute of every picturesque beauty. This
                        barren scene continued till within a small distance of Kendal[.] <ptr
                            target="#pennant1771" loc="219"/></quote>
                </p>
                <p>When read in isolation, these two passages might seem simply to reflect the
                    late-eighteenth-century vogue for sensational landscape description. When we
                    turn to the map, however, we begin to discern that they are as much shaped by
                    the aesthetic conventions of their era as they are by the situation of the
                    roadway that Young and Pennant followed. With a peak elevation of some 445m
                    above sea level, the route of the old turnpike between Shap and Kendal is
                    notorious for its isolation, exposure and poor weather <ptr target="#hindle1998"
                        loc="157"/>. (Even today the M6 at Shap, which rises to only some 315m, is
                    considered one of the highest and most treacherous stretches of road in the UK.)
                    It comes as little surprise, then, that Young and Pennant found the landscape
                    around Shap desolate and oppressive. </p>



                <figure>
                    <head>The route Gray, Young and Pennant followed over Shap Fell and the route of
                        M6.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.jpg"/>
                </figure>

                <p>This is one of the benefits of using spatial models to study historical works of
                    travel writing and topographical literature: it obliges us to examine local
                    descriptions within the broader geographic context of the traveller’s
                    experience. Rather than thinking in terms of isolated places, the models we have
                    developed emphasize that these writers were describing journeys from place to
                    place. In doing so, these models help remind us that the experience of
                    travelling in the Lake District in the late eighteenth century was not always
                    pleasurable, but that it imposed upon the body in other ways, through the jolts
                    of deep wheel ruts, the hazards of unpaved roads, the exposure to the wind and
                    the rain and the mud. The fact that Gray, Young and Pennant take the time to
                    record these details alongside the various scenes they encounter indicates the
                    importance of the <emph>experience</emph> of travel in eighteenth-century travel
                    writing and topographical literature. Young in fact goes so far as to include an
                    appendix in the final volume of his <title rend="italic">Six Months’
                        Tour</title>, recording the condition of each stretch of road he travelled —
                    often in exasperated detail. Hence, his damning account of the turnpike from
                    Preston to Wigan: <quote rend="block" source="#young1770">I know not, in the
                        whole range of language, terms sufficiently expressive to describe this
                        infernal road… let me most seriously caution all travellers, who may
                        accidentally purpose to travel this terrible country, to avoid it as they
                        would the devil; for thousand to one but they break their limbs by
                        overthrows or breakings down. They will here meet with rutts [sic] which I
                        actually measured four feet deep, and floating with mud only from a wet
                        summer; what therefore must it be [like] after a winter? … These are not
                        merely opinions, but facts, for I actually passed three carts broken down in
                        these eighteen miles of execrable memory. <ptr target="#young1770"
                            loc="IV, 180–81"/></quote>
                </p>
                <p>Carrying out a spatial analysis to obtain a more precise visualisation of the
                    routes writers like Young might have followed helps put these sorts of
                    commentaries into context. </p>
                <p> In addition, the other GIS-based methods we employed allow us to analyse the
                    role that particular places play in the geographies represented in Gray, Young
                    and Pennant’s accounts. For instance, by examining whether the places that were
                    mentioned but not visited in these accounts have a significant spatial
                    relationship with the paths simulating the itineraries of Gray, Young and
                    Pennant, we can assess how the routes they travelled might have influenced the
                    perception of the places and geographies recorded in their tours. The results of
                    the statistical significance test indicate that places mentioned but not visited
                    in Gray and Young’s account, and in Pennant’s 1769 tour, are closer to the
                    routes than one would expect as a matter of chance alone (Table 1). In the case
                    of Pennant’s 1772 tour, however, the null hypothesis could not be rejected,
                    indicating that there appears not to be a significant relationship between the
                    places mentioned but not visited in his account and the simulated pathway we
                    created from it. </p>
                <p>This result is significant because it confirms how working with quantitative
                    research techniques can clue us into the qualitative differences between
                    historical works of travel writing. Specifically, it clues us into the fact that
                    whereas Gray and Young’s account, and Pennant’s second account, are all accounts
                    of journeys <emph>into</emph> the Lake District, Pennant’s first account is
                    actually only an account of a journey that <emph>passed by</emph> the Lake
                    District. As mentioned above, in his first tour, Pennant simply travelled down
                    the turnpikes linking Carlisle, Kendal and Lancaster on his way home from the
                    Highlands. His account of the Lake District in the account he published in 1771
                    was, therefore, extremely cursory and only made reference to a few famous local
                    places, most of which lay outside his line of travel. Significantly, however,
                    Pennant returned to the region a few years later to view, as he expressed it in
                    his memoirs, <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#pennant1793">those parts of Lancashire,
                            Westmoreland, and Cumberland, which I had not before seen</quote>
                        <ptr target="#pennant1793" loc="16"/>
                    </cit>. In this second tour (which was published in 1774) Pennant travelled
                    through the Lake District in a manner similar to Gray and Young — hence, the
                    statistical similarity between these three accounts.</p>

                <table>
                    <head>Results from the Kolmogorov-Smirnov test assessing the relationship
                        between places only mentioned and the itineraries of the authors.</head>
                    <row role="label">
                        <cell>Literary Text</cell>
                        <cell>Places Mentioned</cell>
                        <cell>Critical Value</cell>
                        <cell>DMAX</cell>
                        <cell>Null Hypothesis</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Young 1770</cell>
                        <cell>29</cell>
                        <cell>0.24571</cell>
                        <cell>1.1</cell>
                        <cell>REJECTED</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Gray 1775</cell>
                        <cell>94</cell>
                        <cell>0.140273</cell>
                        <cell>0.7444</cell>
                        <cell>REJECTED</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Pennant 1776</cell>
                        <cell>23</cell>
                        <cell>0.125198</cell>
                        <cell>2.22</cell>
                        <cell>REJECTED</cell>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                        <cell>Pennant 1771</cell>
                        <cell>128</cell>
                        <cell>0.2749</cell>
                        <cell>0.029</cell>
                        <cell>NOT REJECTED</cell>
                    </row>
                </table>


                <p>Conducting this statistical test, then, enables us to draw a meaningful
                    distinction between the four works in our case study. More generally, it prompts
                    us to think critically about the role that places that were mentioned but not
                    visited plays within each tour. That each of the four works contains references
                    to such places indicates that the accounts of Gray, Young and Pennant are more
                    than mere itineraries; rather, they are descriptive records that attempt to
                    broaden the reader’s awareness of the geography of the Lake District, which was
                    still a relative <foreign xml:lang="latin">terra incognita</foreign> during the
                    late eighteenth century. The fact that each account contains references to
                    places that the writers did not actually visit suggests Gray, Young and Pennant
                    all endeavoured to give their readers a sense of the surrounding countryside. In
                    fact, when one turns back to the works themselves, one begins to see that the
                    place-names that are mentioned but not visited are often invoked in panoramic
                    descriptions. Thus, for example, Pennant’s account of the mountains visible from
                    the ramparts of Carlisle castle: <quote rend="block" source="#pennant1771">The
                        castle is ancient, but makes a good appearance at a distance: the view from
                        it is fine, of rich meadows, at this time covered with thousands of cattle,
                        it being fair-day. The <hi rend="italic">Eden</hi> here forms two branches,
                        and insulates the ground; over one is a bridge of four, over the other one
                        of nine arches. There is besides a prospect of a rich country, and a distant
                        view of <hi rend="italic">Cold-fells</hi>, <hi rend="italic"
                            >Cross-fells</hi>, <hi rend="italic">Skiddaw</hi>, and other mountains.
                            <ptr target="#pennant1771" loc="217"/></quote>
                </p>
                <p>Elsewhere, one finds that place-names that are mentioned but not visited are also
                    invoked in descriptions of trade, manufacturing and shipping. In these
                    instances, the place-names are typically used to situate the industrial centres
                    of the Lake District in relation to the economic geography of the nation. Hence,
                    Pennant’s observation <ptr target="#pennant1771" loc="217"/> that salmon from
                    the River Eden are shipped to the markets in Newcastle and London, or,
                    similarly, his later explanation of how Ulverston is connected, via Liverpool,
                    with the slave trade: <quote rend="block" source="#pennant1774"><hi
                            rend="italic">Ulverston</hi>, a town of about three thousand souls,
                        seated near the water side, and is approachable at high water by vessels of
                        a hundred and fifty tuns [sic]; has a good trade in iron ore, pig and bar
                        iron, bark, lime-stone, oats and barley, and much beans, which last are sent
                        to <hi rend="italic">Leverpool</hi> [sic], for the food of the poor enslaved
                            <hi rend="italic">negroes</hi> in the <hi rend="italic">Guinea</hi>
                        trade. Numbers of cattle are also sold out of the neighborhood, but the
                        commerce in general declines; at present there are not above sixty vessels
                        belonging to the place; formerly about a hundred and fifty mostly let out to
                        freight; but both master and sailors go now to <hi rend="italic"
                            >Leverpool</hi> for employ. <ptr target="#pennant1774" loc="29"
                        /></quote>
                </p>
                <p>Significantly, one finds similar passages in Arthur Young’s account, which was in
                    large part a survey of agricultural productivity. Consider, for example, his
                    account of the wool market in Kendal, where he uses place-names to refer to
                    specific market centres as well as to specific breeds of sheep: <quote
                        rend="block" source="#young1770">The wool they use is chiefly <hi
                            rend="italic">Leicestershire, Warwickshire</hi>, and <hi rend="italic"
                            >Durham</hi>: They generally mix <hi rend="italic">Leicestershire</hi>
                        and <hi rend="italic">Durham</hi> together. The price 8<hi rend="italic"
                            >d</hi>. 9<hi rend="italic">d</hi>. and 10<hi rend="italic">d. per
                            lb</hi>. They send all the manufacture to <hi rend="italic">London</hi>
                        by land carriage, which is said to be the longest, for broad wheel wagons,
                        of any stage in <hi rend="italic">England</hi>. <ptr target="#young1770"
                            loc="III, 171"/></quote>
                </p>
                <p>These observations, when viewed alongside the results from the second spatial
                    proximity analysis, suggest that places that are mentioned but not visited
                    played a number of important roles within the broader associative geographies of
                    each text. They are invoked not only to describe the surrounding countryside,
                    but also to document how places throughout the greater Lakeland region connect
                    geographically, socially and economically with the wider world. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>5. Conclusions</head>
                <p>Although the use of spatial analysis in Humanities disciplines such as Literary
                    Studies is still at an early stage, the application of geospatial technologies,
                    such as GIS, has already begun to have a profound influence on the way literary
                    scholars and historians approach the study of space, place and landscape. By
                    implementing the geospatial methods employed in this study, for example,
                    researchers can achieve new insights not only into the cognitive construction of
                    geographies in literary works, but also into <q>fuzzier</q> phenomena, such as
                    geographies of absence: places that are not specifically mentioned in a literary
                    work, but nonetheless form part of its implied geography. In addition, the
                    introduction of approaches such as Geographical Text Analysis <ptr
                        target="#leidner2007"/>
                    <ptr target="#martins2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#gregory2009"/>
                    <ptr target="#andogah2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#buscaldi2010"/>
                    <ptr target="#gregory2011"/>
                    <ptr target="#rupp2013"/>
                    <ptr target="#murrietaflores2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#porter2015"/>
                    <ptr target="#gregory2016"/> has resulted in significant improvements in the
                    automated extraction of geographical information from works of literature for
                    the purposes of spatial analysis. As scholars in Literary Studies continue to
                    adopt new computational methods, a growing number of researchers are also
                    embracing GIS techniques to extract, examine and explore the spatial
                    relationships embedded not only in works of non-fiction (such as those analysed
                    above), but also in works of creative fiction as well as poetry and drama <ptr
                        target="#bushell2016"/>
                    <ptr target="#murietaflores2017"/>. </p>
                <p> The application of GIS technology in literary studies represents an important
                    development. Until recently, however, little has been done to implement more
                    creative approaches to mapping a writer’s movement through space. Advancing from
                    point-based representations to the analysis of raster-based pathways is,
                    therefore, a major step forward in the application of spatial technologies for
                    studying works of travel writing and topographical literature. Such works are,
                    after all, not merely descriptive inventories of places, monuments and
                    buildings; they are narratives that offer first-hand accounts of the journeys of
                    specific individuals. In order to visualise such works adequately we must employ
                    techniques that are capable of representing the places they mention not as
                    discrete locations, but as a series of interconnected points along the line of
                    transit that constitutes the narrator’s tour. As noted at the beginning of this
                    article, is only by assessing works of travel writing as journeys that we can
                    understand how the writers of those works encountered the places and landmarks
                    they described. Thus, with respect to Gray, Young and Pennant, it is only by
                    tracing their journeys through the Lake District that we can hope to obtain
                    insights into how the topography of the region — with its valleys, peaks and
                    mountain passes — shaped the local experiences recounted in their travelogues. </p>
                <p> The implementation of these methods, however, is as yet imperfect. One
                    significant complication is that the data used to create the Digital Elevation
                    Models (DEMs) used to perform CSA and LCP comes from modern sources (Lidar
                    images and/or satellite or aerial photographs). This means that they contain the
                    elevation data of modern roads, motorways and towns. Although the routes
                    followed by eighteenth-century Lake District tourists often correspond to the
                    routes of the modern road networks in Cumbria, in many instances there are
                    significant differences between the two <ptr target="#hindle1998" loc="154–157"
                    />. The accuracy of our data could be greatly enhanced by the creation of
                    historical DEMs. This could be accomplished by modifying and integrating to DEMs
                    data from sources such as historical maps. Another important innovation would be
                    the development of spatial models capable of accounting for more variables. The
                    use of different modes of transportation and surfaces based on time instead of
                    relative cost might also furnish new insights into the empirical realities
                    underlying travel narratives. Finally, one must remember that the development of
                    CSA models still relies primarily on quantitative variables and that LCP is
                    still based on a rationale of optimality, which is not always applicable to
                    human behaviour. These are all issues that shall need to be addressed as
                    humanities scholars and Geographic Information Scientists develop, extend and
                    refine the application of geospatial technologies in humanities research.</p>
                <p> Based on the study on which we have reported in this article, and the examples
                    cited herein, we can confidently conclude that spatial analysis can facilitate
                    more nuanced interpretations of works of travel writing and topographical
                    literature. The process of creating a spatial dataset from the tours of Gray,
                    Young and Pennant alerted us to details that most previous studies have
                    overlooked. The simulations we created using this dataset have, moreover,
                    provided the foundation for our on-going research into experimental forms of
                    digital literary geography, such as using Google Earth to create interactive
                    virtual tours. We believe that studies, such as the one presented here, can be
                    productively combined with other emergent forms of geospatial technology to
                    foster innovative collaboration between researchers in the Humanities and the
                    Geographic Information Sciences.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                <p>This research was supported by the European Research Council (ERC) under the
                    European Union’s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2013) / ERC grant <title
                        rend="quotes">Spatial Humanities: Texts, GIS, places</title> (agreement
                    number 283850). Thanks are also due to the Institute for Historical Research and
                    the North East Forum in Eighteenth-Century and Romantic Studies, as well as to
                    audiences at conferences at the University of Oxford and Lancaster University.
                </p>
            </div>



        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>

                <bibl label="Adriaensen et al. 2003" xml:id="adriaensen2003">Adriaensen, F.,
                    Chardon, J.P., De Blust, G., Swinnen, E., Villalba, S., Gulinck, H., and
                    Matthysen, E. <title rend="quotes">The application of ‘least-cost’ modelling as
                        a functional landscape model</title>. <title rend="italic">Landscape and
                        Urban Planning</title>, 64 (4), (2003): 233–247.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Aldenderfer et al. 1996" xml:id="aldenderfer1996">Aldenderfer, M.S. and
                    Maschner, H.D.G., eds., <title rend="italic">Anthropology, space, and geographic
                        information systems</title>. New York: Oxford University Press
                    (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Alves and Queiroz 2013" xml:id="alves2013">Alves, D. and Queiroz, I.
                        <title rend="quotes">Studying urban space and literary representations using
                        GIS: Lisbon, Portugal, 1852-2009</title>. <title rend="italic">Social
                        Science History.</title> 37, (4) (2013): 457-481.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Anderson et al. 2016" xml:id="anderson2016">Anderson, J., Orford, S.
                    and Bohata, K. <title rend="italic">A New Literary Geography: Establishing a
                        Digital Literary Atlas of Wales and its Borderlands</title>, AHRC Research
                    Project <ref target="http://gtr.rcuk.ac.uk/projects?ref=AH/N003764/1"
                        >http://gtr.rcuk.ac.uk/projects?ref=AH/N003764/1</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Anderson and Loxley 2016" xml:id="andersonloxley2016">Anderson, M. and
                    Loxley, J. <title rend="quotes">The Digital Poetics of Place-names in Literary
                        Edinburgh</title>. In: Cooper, D., Donaldson, C., and Murrieta-Flores, P.,
                    eds. <title rend="italic">Literary Mapping in the Digital Age</title>. Abingdon,
                    UK; New York: Routledge (2016): 47–66. Digital Research in the Arts and
                    Humanities.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Andogah 2010" xml:id="andogah2010">Andogah, G. <title rend="italic"
                        >Geographically Constrained Information Retrieval.</title> PhD Thesis,
                    University of Groningen (2010).</bibl>

                <bibl label="Andrews 1989" xml:id="andrews1989">Andrews, M. <title rend="italic">The
                        Search of the Picturesque: Landscape Aesthetics and Tourism in Britain,
                        1760–1800</title>, Stanford University Press: Stanford, CA (1989)</bibl>

                <bibl label="Atkinson et al. 2005" xml:id="atkinson2005">Atkinson, D.M., Deadman,
                    P., Dudycha, D., and Traynor, S. <title rend="quotes">Multi-criteria evaluation
                        and least cost path analysis for an arctic all-weather road</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Applied Geography</title>, 25 (4), (2005): 287–307.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bodenhamer et al. 2010" xml:id="bodenhamer2010">Bodenhamer, D.J.,
                    Corrigan, J., and Harris, T.M., eds. <title rend="italic">The spatial
                        humanities: GIS and the future of humanities scholarship</title>.
                    Bloomington: Indiana University Press (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bodenhamer et al. 2013" xml:id="bodenhamer2013">Bodenhamer, D.J.,
                    Harris, T.M., and Corrigan, J. <title rend="quotes">Deep Mapping and the Spatial
                        Humanities</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities
                        and Arts Computing</title>, 7 (1-2) (2013):170–175.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bodenhamer et al. 2015" xml:id="bodenhamer2015">Bodenhamer, D.J.,
                    Corrigan, J., and Harris, T.M., eds. <title rend="italic">Deep Maps and Spatial
                        Narratives</title>. Bloomington: Indiana University Press (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bouch and Jones 1961" xml:id="bouch1961">Bouch, M. L, and Gwilym P
                    Jones. <title rend="italic">A Short Economic and Social History of the Lake
                        Counties: 1500-1830</title>. Manchester: Manchester Univ. Press
                    (1961)</bibl>

                <bibl label="Buscaldi 2010" xml:id="buscaldi2010">Buscaldi, D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Toponym Disambiguation in Information Retrieval.</title> PhD Thesis,
                    Universidad Politecnica de Valencia, (2010). </bibl>
                <bibl label="Bushell 2016" xml:id="bushell2016">Bushell, S. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Mapping Fiction: Spatialising the Literary Work</title>. In: Cooper, D.,
                    Donaldson, C., and Murrieta-Flores, P., eds. <title rend="italic">Literary
                        Mapping in the Digital Age</title>. Abingdon, UK; New York: Routledge
                    (2016): 125–46. Digital Research in the Arts and Humanities.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Buzard 1993" xml:id="buzard1993">Buzard, J. <title rend="italic">The
                        Beaten Track: European Tourism, Literature, and the Ways to Culture,
                        1800-1918</title>. Oxford, UK; New York: Oxford University Press
                    (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Collischonn and Pilar 2000" xml:id="collischon2000">Collischonn, W. and
                    Pilar, J.V. <title rend="quotes">A direction dependent least-cost-path algorithm
                        for roads and canals</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                        Geographical Information Science</title>, 14 (4), (2000): 397–406.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Conolly and Lake 2006" xml:id="conolly2006">Conolly, J. and Lake, M.
                        <title rend="italic">Geographical information systems in
                    archaeology</title>. Cambridge, UK; New York: Cambridge University Press
                    (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Cooper and Gregory 2011" xml:id="cooper2011">Cooper, D. and Gregory,
                    I.N. <title rend="quotes">Mapping the English Lake District: a literary GIS:
                        Mapping the English Lake District</title>. <title rend="italic">Transactions
                        of the Institute of British Geographers</title>, 36 (1), (2011):
                    89–108.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Cooper 2012" xml:id="cooper2012">Cooper, D. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Critical Literary Cartography: Text, Maps and a Coleridge Noebook</title>.
                    In: Roberts, L. ed. <title rend="italic">Mapping Cultures: Practices, Places,
                        Performances</title>. Houdsmills, UK: Palgrave Macmillan (2012):
                    29–52.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Cooper et al. 2016" xml:id="cooper2016">Cooper, D., Donaldson, C., and
                    Murrieta-Flores, P., eds. <title rend="italic">Literary Mapping in the Digital
                        Age</title>. Abingdon, UK; New York: Routledge (2016). <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Research in the Arts and Humanities</title>.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Donaldson and Murrieta-Flores 2015" xml:id="donaldson2015">Donaldson,
                    C., Gregory, I.N., and Murrieta-Flores, P., 2015. <title rend="quotes">Mapping
                        ‘Wordsworthshire’: A GIS Study of Literary Tourism in Victorian
                        Lakeland</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Victorian Culture</title>,
                    20 (3), (2015): 287–307.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fairén Jiménez 2004" xml:id="fairen2004">Fairén Jiménez, S. <title
                        rend="quotes">Movilidad y territorialidad. El poblamiento neolítico en las
                        comunidades centro-meridionales Valencianas</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Saguntum</title>, (36),( 2004): 23–34.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fairén Jiménez, Cruz Berrocal, López Romero, and Walid Sbeinati 2006"
                    xml:id="fairen2006">Fairén Jiménez, S., Cruz Berrocal, M., López Romero, E., and
                    Walid Sbeinati, S. <title rend="quotes">Las vías pecuarias como elementos
                        arqueológicos</title>. <title rend="italic">In</title>: I. Grau Mira, ed.
                        <title rend="italic">La aplicación de los SIG en la arqueología del
                        paisaje</title>. San Vicente del Raspeig: Universidad de Alicante
                    (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fiz Fernández and Orengo, 2008" xml:id="fiz2008">Fiz Fernández, I. and
                    Orengo, H. <title rend="quotes">Simulating communication routes in Mediterranean
                        alluvial plains</title>. In: <title rend="italic">International Conference
                        on Computer Applications and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology</title>, A.
                    Posluschny, K. Lambers, and I. Herzog, eds. <title rend="italic">Layers of
                        perception: proceedings of the 35th International Conference on Computer
                        Applications and Quantitative Methods in Archaeology (CAA); Berlin, Germany,
                        April 2-6, 2007</title>. Bonn: Habelt, (2008): 316–321.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fotheringham, Brunsdon, and Charlton 2000" xml:id="fotheringham2000">
                    Fotheringham, A.S., Brunsdon, C., and Charlton, M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Quantitative geography: perspectives on spatial data analysis</title>.
                    London; Thousand Oaks, Calif: Sage Publications (2000).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Frachetti 2008" xml:id="frachetti2008">Frachetti, M.D. <title
                        rend="quotes">Variability and dynamic landscapes of mobile pastoralism in
                        ethnography and prehistory</title>. <title rend="italic">In</title>: H.
                    Barnard and W. Wendrich, eds. <title rend="italic">The archaeology of mobility:
                        old world and new world nomadism</title>. Los Angeles: Cotsen Institute of
                    Archaeology, University Of California, (2008): 366–396.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Giraldi, Ferlan, and Romeo 1976" xml:id="giraldi1976">Giraldi, T.,
                    Ferlan, I., and Romeo, D. <title rend="quotes">Antitumor activity of
                        equinatoxin</title>. <title rend="italic">Chemico-Biological
                        Interactions</title>, 13 (3-4), (1976): 199–203.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gonzales and Gergel 2007" xml:id="gonzales2007">Gonzales, E.K. and
                    Gergel, S.E. <title rend="quotes">Testing assumptions of cost surface analysis —
                        a tool for invasive species management</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >Landscape Ecology</title>, 22 (8), (2007): 1155–1168.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Goodchild, and Janelle, 2010" xml:id="goodchild2010">Goodchild, M.F.
                    and Janelle, D.G. <title rend="quotes">Toward critical spatial thinking in the
                        social sciences and humanities</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >GeoJournal</title>, 75 (1), (2010): 3–13.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gray 1775" xml:id="gray1775">Gray, T. <title rend="italic">The Poems of
                        Mr. Gray, to Which Are Prefixed Memoirs of His Life and Writings</title>.
                    York: H. Hughs (1775).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gregory 2003" xml:id="gregory2003">Gregory, I. <title rend="italic">A
                        place in history: a guide to using GIS in historical research</title>.
                    Oxford: Oakville, CT: Oxbow; David Brown (2003).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gregory, Donaldson, Murrieta-Flores, and Rayson 2015"
                    xml:id="gregory2015">Gregory, I., Donaldson, C., Murrieta-Flores, P., and
                    Rayson, P. <title rend="quotes">Geoparsing, GIS, and Textual Analysis: Current
                        Developments in Spatial Humanities Research</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >International Journal of Humanities and Arts Computing</title>, 9 (1),
                    (2015): 1–14.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gregory and Cooper 2009" xml:id="gregory2009">Gregory, I.N. and Cooper,
                    D. <title rend="quotes">Thomas Gray, Samuel Taylor Coleridge and geographical
                        information systems: A literary GIS of two Lake District tours</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and Arts
                        Computing</title>, 3 (1-2), (2009): 61–84.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gregory and Donaldson 2016" xml:id="gregory2016">Gregory, I.N. and
                    Donaldson, C. <title rend="quotes">Geographical Text Analysis: Digital
                        Cartographies of Lake District Literature</title>. In: Cooper, D.,
                    Donaldson, C., and Murrieta-Flores, P., eds. <title rend="italic">Literary
                        Mapping in the Digital Age</title>. Abingdon, UK; New York: Routledge
                    (2016): 67–87 Digital Research in the Arts and Humanities.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gregory and Hardie 2011" xml:id="gregory2011">Gregory, I.N. and Hardie,
                    A. <title rend="quotes">Visual GISting: bringing together corpus linguistics and
                        Geographical Information Systems</title>. <title rend="italic">Literary and
                        Linguistic Computing</title>, 26 (3), (2011): 297–314.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gregory and Healey 2007" xml:id="gregory2007">Gregory, I.N. and Healey,
                    R.G. <title rend="quotes">Historical GIS: structuring, mapping and analysing
                        geographies of the past</title>. <title rend="italic">Progress in Human
                        Geography</title>, 31 (5), (2007): 638–653.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Herzog 2013" xml:id="herzog2013">Herzog, I. <title rend="quotes">Theory
                        and practice of cost functions</title>. In F. Contreras Cortés, M. Farjas,
                    and F.J. Melero, eds. <title rend="italic">CAA2010: fusion of cultures:
                        Proceedings of the 38th Annual Conference on Computer Applications and
                        Quantitative Methods in Archaeology, Granada, Spain, April 2010</title>.
                    Oxford: Archaeopress (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Heuser et al. 2016" xml:id="heuser2016">Heuser, R., Algee-Hewitt, M.,
                    Steiner, E., and Tran, V. <title rend="quotes">Mapping the Emotions of London,
                        1700-1900: A Crowdsourcing Experiment</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >In</title>: Cooper, D., Donaldson, C., and Murrieta-Flores, P., eds. <title
                        rend="italic">Literary Mapping in the Digital Age</title>. Abingdon, UK; New
                    York: Routledge (2016): 25–46. Digital Research in the Arts and
                    Humanities.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hindle 1998" xml:id="hindle1998">Hindle, B.P. <title rend="italic"
                        >Roads and tracks of the Lake District</title>. Rev. ed. Milnthorpe:
                    Cicerone (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hodge 1957" xml:id="hodge1957">Hodge, E.W. <title rend="italic"
                        >Enjoying the Lakes, from post-chaise to national park.</title> Edinburgh:
                    Oliver and Boyd (1957).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Howey 2007" xml:id="howey2007">Howey, M.C.L. <title rend="quotes">Using
                        multi-criteria cost surface analysis to explore past regional landscapes: a
                        case study of ritual activity and social interaction in Michigan, AD
                        1200–1600</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Archaeological
                        Science</title>, 34 (11), (2007): 1830–1846.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ingold 2009" xml:id="ingold2009">Ingold, T. <title rend="quotes"
                        >Against Space: Place, Movement, Knowledge</title>. <title rend="italic"
                        >In</title>: P.W. Kirby, ed. <title rend="italic">Boundless worlds: an
                        anthropological approach to movement</title>. New York: Berghahn Books,
                    (2009): 29–43.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Jockers 2013" xml:id="jockers2013">Jockers, M.L. <title rend="italic"
                        >Macroanalysis: digital methods and literary history</title>. Urbana:
                    University of Illinois Press (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Knowles 2002" xml:id="knowles2002">Knowles, A.K., ed. <title
                        rend="italic">Past time, past place: GIS for history</title>. Redlands,
                    California: ESRI Press (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Knowles and Hiller 2008" xml:id="knowles2008">Knowles, A.K. and
                    Hillier, A., eds. <title rend="italic">Placing history: how maps, spatial data,
                        and GIS are changing historical scholarship</title>. 1st ed. Redlands,
                    California: ESRI Press (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl label="LaRue and Nielsen 2008" xml:id="larue2008">LaRue, M.A. and Nielsen,
                    C.K. <title rend="quotes">Modelling potential dispersal corridors for cougars in
                        midwestern North America using least-cost path methods</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Ecological Modelling</title>, 212 (3-4), (2008):
                    372–381.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Leidner 2007" xml:id="leidner2007">Leidner, J.L. <title rend="italic"
                        >Toponym resolution in text: annotation, evaluation and applications of
                        spatial grounding of place names</title>. PhD Thesis. University of
                    Edinburgh (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Martins 2009" xml:id="martins2009">Martins, B. <title rend="italic"
                        >Geographically Aware Web Text Mining</title>. PhD Thesis. University of
                    Lisbon (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Moretti 2009" xml:id="moretti1999">Moretti, F., 1999. <title
                        rend="italic">Atlas of the European novel, 1800-1900</title>. London; New
                    York: Verso (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Moretti 2007" xml:id="moretti2007">Moretti, F. <title rend="italic"
                        >Graphs, maps, trees: abstract models for literary history</title>.
                    Paperback ed. London; New York: Verso (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Moretti 2013" xml:id="moretti2013">Moretti, F. <title rend="italic"
                        >Distant reading</title>. London; New York: Verso (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Murrieta-Flores 2012" xml:id="murrietaflores2012">Murrieta-Flores, P.
                        <title rend="quotes">Understanding human movement through spatial
                        technologies. The role of natural areas of transit in the Late Prehistory of
                        South-western Iberia</title>. <title rend="italic">Trabajos de
                        Prehistoria</title>, 69 (1), (2012): 103–122.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Murrieta-Flores et al. 2015" xml:id="murrietaflores2015">
                    Murrieta-Flores, P., Baron, A., Gregory, I., Hardie, A., and Rayson, P. <title
                        rend="quotes">Automatically Analyzing Large Texts in a GIS Environment: The
                        Registrar General’s Reports and Cholera in the 19th Century</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Transactions in GIS</title>, 19 (2), (2015): 296–320.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Murrieta-Flores and Howell 2017-Forthcoming" xml:id="murietaflores2017"
                    > Murrieta-Flores, P., and Howell, N. <title rend="quotes">Evolving the Spatial
                        Humanities through Medieval Romance: Moving into the digital analysis of
                        vague and imaginary place in historical and literary texts</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Article submitted for publication.</title></bibl>
                <bibl label="Norgate and Norgate 2014" xml:id="norgate2014">Norgate, M and Norgate,
                    J. <title rend="italic">Guides to the Lakes</title>, University of Portsmouth
                    (2014) <ref target="http://www.geog.port.ac.uk/webmap/thelakes/"
                        >http://www.geog.port.ac.uk/webmap/thelakes/</ref></bibl>
                <bibl label="Okabe 2006" xml:id="okabe2006">Okabe, A., ed. <title rend="italic"
                        >GIS-based studies in the humanities and social sciences</title>. Boca
                    Raton, FL: CRC/Taylor &amp; Francis (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ousby 1990" xml:id="ousby1990">Ousby, I. <title rend="italic">The
                        Englishman’s England: taste, travel, and the rise of tourism</title>.
                    Cambridge, Cambridge University Press (1990).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Parker and Asencio 2008" xml:id="parker2008">Parker, R.N. and Asencio,
                    E.K. <title rend="italic">GIS and spatial analysis for the social sciences:
                        coding, mapping and modeling</title>. New York: Routledge (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pennant 1771" xml:id="pennant1771">Pennant, T. <title rend="italic">A
                        Tour in Scotland, MDCCLXIX</title>. Chester: John Monk (1771).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pennant 1774" xml:id="pennant1774">Pennant, T. <title rend="italic">A
                        Tour in Scotland and Voyage to the Hebrides</title>. Chester: John Monk
                    (1774).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pennant 1793" xml:id="pennant1793">Pennant, T. <title rend="italic">The
                        Literary Life of the Late Thomas Pennant, Esq. By Himself</title>. London:
                    Benjamin and John White (1793).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Piatti 2016" xml:id="piatti2016">
                    <title rend="quotes">Mapping Fiction: The Theory, Tools and Potentials of
                        Literary Geography</title>. In: Cooper, D., Donaldson, C., and
                    Murrieta-Flores, P., eds. <title rend="italic">Literary Mapping in the Digital
                        Age</title>. Abingdon, UK; New York: Routledge (2016): 88–101. Digital
                    Research in the Arts and Humanities.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Pickles 1995" xml:id="pickles1995">Pickles, J., ed. <title
                        rend="italic">Ground truth: the social implications of geographic
                        information systems</title>. New York: Guilford Press (1995).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Porter et al. 2015" xml:id="porter2015">Porter, C., Atkinson, P.,
                    Gregory, I.N. (2015) <title rend="quotes">Geographical Text Analysis: A new
                        approach to understanding nineteenth-century mortality</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Health &amp; Place</title>, 36 (2015): 25-34. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Powel and Hebron 2010" xml:id="powell2010">Powell, C. and Hebron, S.
                        <title rend="italic">Savage grandeur and noblest thoughts: discovering the
                        Lake District 1750-1820</title>. Grasmere, Cumbria: Wordsworth Trust
                    (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rupp et al. 2013" xml:id="rupp2013">Rupp, C.J., Rayson, P., Baron, A.,
                    Donaldson, C., Gregory, I., Hardie, A., and Murrieta-Flores, P. <title
                        rend="quotes">Customising geoparsing and georeferencing for historical
                        texts</title>. IEEE, (2013): 59–62.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Stucky 1998" xml:id="stucky1998">Stucky, J.L.D. <title rend="quotes">On
                        applying viewshed analysis for determining least-cost paths on Digital
                        Elevation Models</title>. <title rend="italic">International Journal of
                        Geographical Information Science</title>, 12 (8), (1998): 891–905.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Tally 2013" xml:id="tally2013">Tally, Robert, Jr. <title rend="italic"
                        >Spatiality</title>. Abingdon, UK; New York: Routledge (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Travis 2015" xml:id="travis2015">Travis, C. <title rend="quotes">Visual
                        Geo-Literary and Historical Analysis, Tweetflickrtubing, and James Joyce’s
                            <title rend="italic">Ulysses</title></title> (1922). <title
                        rend="italic">Annals of the Association of American Geographers</title>,
                    (2015): 1–24.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wang, Savage and Bradley 2009" xml:id="wang2009">Wang, I.J., Savage,
                    W.K., and Bradley Shaffer, H. <title rend="quotes">Landscape genetics and
                        least-cost path analysis reveal unexpected dispersal routes in the
                        California tiger salamander (Ambystoma californiense)</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">Molecular Ecology</title>, 18 (7), (2009): 1365–1374.</bibl>
                <bibl label="West 1778" xml:id="west1778">West, T. <title rend="italic">A Guide to
                        the Lakes: Dedicated to the Lovers of Landscape Studies, and to All who Have
                        Visited, Or Intend to Visit the Lakes in Cumberland, Westmorland, and
                        Lancashire. By the Author of The Antiquities of Furness</title>. London:
                    Richardson and Urquhart, under the Royal Exchange, and W. Pennington, Kendal
                    (1778).</bibl>
                <bibl label="West 1821" xml:id="west1821">West, T. <title rend="italic">A Guide to
                        the Lakes, in Cumberland, Westmorland, and Lancashire</title>. 11th ed.
                    Kendal: W. Pennington (1821).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wheatley et al. 2010" xml:id="wheatley2010">Wheatley, D., García
                    Sanjuán, L., Murrieta Flores, P.A., and Marquez Perez, J. <title rend="quotes"
                        >The megalithic phenomenon in Southern Spain: Approaching the landscape
                        dimension</title>. <title rend="italic">Oxford Journal of
                        Archaeology</title>, 29 (4), (2010): 387–405.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wheatley and Gillings 2002" xml:id="wheatley2002">Wheatley, D. and
                    Gillings, M. <title rend="italic">Spatial technology and archaeology: the
                        archaeological applications of GIS</title>. New York: Taylor &amp; Francis
                    (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl label="William 1975" xml:id="williams1975">Williams, L.A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Road Transport in Cumbria in the Nineteenth Century</title>. London: George
                    Allen &amp; Unwin (1975)</bibl>
                <bibl label="Wood 1996" xml:id="wood1996">Wood, J. <title rend="italic">The
                        geomorphological characterisation of digital elevation models.</title> PhD
                    Thesis. University of Leicester, UK (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Young 1770" xml:id="young1770">Young, A. <title rend="italic">A six
                        months tour through the north of England</title>. London: Strahan
                    (1770).</bibl>
                <bibl label="Yu et al 2003" xml:id="yu2003">Lee amd Yu, C., Lee, J., and
                    Munro-Stasiuk, M.J. <title rend="quotes">Research Article: Extensions to
                        least-cost path algorithms for roadway planning</title>. <title
                        rend="italic">International Journal of Geographical Information
                        Science</title>, 17 (4), (2003): 361–376.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Yubero et al 2015" xml:id="yubero2015">Yubero-Gómez, M.,
                    Rubio-Campillo, X., López-Cachero, F.J., and Esteve-Gràcia, X. <title
                        rend="quotes">Mapping Changes in Late Prehistoric Landscapes: A Case Study
                        in the Northeastern Iberian Peninsula</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal
                        of Anthropological Archaeology</title> 40 (December), (2015): 123–34.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
