<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
  xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
  xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">

  <!-- BEGIN TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Book Review: Digital Sound Studies (2018) </title>
        <dhq:authorInfo>
          <dhq:author_name>Tracey <dhq:family>El Hajj</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
          <dhq:affiliation>University of Victoria</dhq:affiliation>
          <email>tmelhajj@uvic.ca</email>
          <dhq:bio>
            <p>Tracey El Hajj is a PhD candidate in the Department of English at the University of
              Victoria in the field of Science and Technology Studies. Her research focuses on the
                <soCalled>algorhythmics</soCalled> of networked communications. She was a 2019-20
              President’s Fellow in Research-Enriched Teaching at UVic, where she taught an advanced
              course on <title rend="quotes">Artificial Intelligence and Everyday Life.</title> She
              is also a programmer with the Map of Early Modern London and Linked Early Modern Drama
              Online as well as a research fellow in residence at the Praxis Studio for Comparative
              Media Studies, where she investigates the relationships between artificial
              intelligence, creativity, health, and justice.</p>
          </dhq:bio>
        </dhq:authorInfo>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
        <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
        <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000543</idno>
        <idno type="volume">015</idno>
        <idno type="issue">1</idno>
        <date when="2021-03-05">05 March 2021</date>
        <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
        <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
          <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This is the source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <classDecl>
        <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
          <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at<ref
              target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
              >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
        </taxonomy>
        <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
          <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
        </taxonomy>
      </classDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
      </langUsage>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
          <list type="simple">
            <item/>
          </list>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2020-09-18" who="Taylor Arnold">Created file</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <!-- END TEI HEADER ELEMENTS -->

  <!-- BEGIN TEXT -->
  <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
    <!-- FRONT TEXT -->
    <front>
      <dhq:abstract>
        <p> The edited volume <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> brings together
          various voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound, practically and
          theoretically <ptr target="#lingold2018"/>. Contributors explore methodologies, platforms,
          and initiatives that demonstrate interdisciplinary and inclusive work that centers sound
          and listening while demonstrating how such work can advance humanities scholarship. The
          contributions provide a balanced critique of DH as a norm and culture alongside detailing
          digital sound studies' contributions to DH, the humanities, and the public. The volume is
          an excellent resource for those interested in digital sound studies.</p>
      </dhq:abstract>
      <dhq:teaser>
        <p>A book review of the edited volume Digital Sound Studies.</p>
      </dhq:teaser>
    </front>

    <!-- BODY TEXT -->
    <body>
      <div>
        <head/>
        <p><title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>, edited by Mary Caton Lingold, Darren
          Mueller, and Whitney Trettien and published by Duke University Press (2018), brings
          together a variety of voices addressing the potential of digital approaches to sound,
          practically and theoretically. While most contributors acknowledge the field's novelty,
          they all agree on its timely interventions and the value of the interdisciplinary work
          this domain can provide. The field of digital sound studies not only investigates new
          methodologies but also contributes to — if not provokes — the field of digital humanities
          (DH). In their introduction, the editors note that "[w]hile digital media [...] create a
          space of possibility for the study of sound, critical, interpretive labor fulfills this
          potential, not the technology itself" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="3"/>. This early
          statement in the book echoes throughout the collection, particularly as authors discuss
          their processes in the making and success of a particular project or sonic investigation.
          The projects emphasize the labour that scholars invest and the initiative they take to
          advance sound studies and experiment with material, using a multitude of technologies that
          do not require advanced technical skills or expensive devices. In the afterward, Whitney
          Trettien asks Jonathan Sterne about "the primary engine of change in the academy" <ptr
            target="#lingold2018" loc="269"/>. It is not technology. Sterne argues that
          institutions, money, and academic fashion drive academic change, as is the case for DH. In
          this edited volume, scholars demonstrate how individual initiative and labour play a big
          part in pushing scholarship in innovative directions. Intellectual and experimental labour
          are predominant in the chapters as the authors question DH's bias for text, all the while
          exploring pedagogical methods and research techniques that invite scholars — as well as
          the broader public — to invest in sound and listening as cultural approaches to the
          humanities. <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> demonstrates how sound and
          listening can advance humanities scholarship, detailing pedagogical methodologies that are
          often critical of DH while addressing its gaps and proposing ways for sound studies and DH
          to be complementary.</p>
        <p>Contributors to <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> mostly come from an
          academic setting, and pedagogy emerges as a focus. Although not every chapter clearly
          defines a pedagogical intervention or approach, most do gesture at the importance of
          digital sound studies in humanities classrooms. The three chapters in "Theories and
          Genealogies" — by contributors Richard Cullen Rath, Myron M. Beasley, and Jonathan W.
          Stone — investigate sound and listening as performance, and highlight the importance of
          interdisciplinarity in their works. Richard Cullen Rath explores the importance of
          introducing computers with sound cards to classrooms, and emphasizes how it "mak[es] more
          accessible the experiences of people who are not well represented in traditional
          documentary sources" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="37"/>. In "The Pleasure (Is)
          Principle," Aaron Trammell, Jennifer Lynn Stoever, and Liana Silva share their experience
          as editors of the <title rend="italic">Sounding Out!</title> blog. Aside from their focus
          on the processes and maintenance that go into the site, the authors explain how <title
            rend="italic">Sounding Out!</title> aims beyond academia. The team's work toward the
          accessibility of sound studies is partly a pedagogical gesture. <title rend="italic"
            >Sounding Out!</title>'s interdisciplinary content and multimodal format allow its
          audience to access and hear multiple voices instead of a limited corpus of scholars whose
          work is already being broadly disseminated. Such an approach makes <title rend="italic"
            >Sounding Out!</title> a go-to platform for academics who share an investment in social
          justice and interdisciplinary conversations. Disseminating knowledge to the broader
          public, beyond institutional boundaries and inequities, is another timely issue that
            <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> addresses.</p>
        <p>W. F. Umi Hsu also focuses on pedagogy in "Reprogramming Sounds of Learning," where the
          readers journey with the author's students as they work on their projects. The author
          successfully "propose[s] a series of experimental approaches that attempt to reprogram
          sounds back into learning and teaching" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="131"/>. The
          chapter argues for the strong impact of sound on engaged learning, centralizing the
          learning experience on "the experience of sounding and listening" <ptr
            target="#lingold2018" loc="134"/>. In that respect, Hsu explores three principles:
          "remediation, reflexivity, and resonance" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="134"/>. These
          principles align well with media studies and bring forth key aspects of multimodality in
          pedagogy. Hsu further highlights the role of reflexivity in bringing pedagogy outside the
          classroom: "Deconstructing the recipe of how digital sound media are made via an act of
          remaking can afford students [...] to gain an access to personal and reflexive meanings of
          technology in their everyday lives" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="139"/>. Hsu's
          methodology entails having college students work with elementary school students to
          fulfill their project requirements. This approach bridges academic work and everyday life
          through sound and listening, and fosters sonic curiosity and appreciation among elementary
          students along with their college partners. As Michael J. Kramer argues, "[t]he digital
          'remediation' of the image [...] provides an opportunity to open ears as well as eyes more
          fully to the echoes of the past" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="180"/>. Bringing together
          the visual and sonic study of artifacts is another example of active sensorial encounters
          with the material, proving as an effective means to engage a broad audience with diverse
          interests.</p>
        <p>Beyond its contributions to pedagogy, <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>
          is an excellent resource for scholars looking to explore venues of accessible sound
          projects and the technological turn in the humanities. In "Rhetorical Folkness:
          Reanimating Walter J. Ong in the Pursuit of Digital Humanity," Jonathan W. Stone urges
          that "[a]s we look toward the future of digital sound studies, [...] frameworks, from
          secondary orality to digital humanity, usefully conceptualize the various ways
          contemporary vernacular culture is embedded within, performed through, and transformed by
          digital technology" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="76"/>. In that sense, technological
          accessibility promotes a broad reach for investigating humanities subjects through sound,
          beyond the limits of academic institutions. In "Becoming OutKasted," Bradley discusses her
          initiative "OutKasted Conversations," a webcast series published on YouTube. This series
          managed to "creat[e] a digital site for teasing out how hip-hop can serve as a catalyst of
          change in the post-civil rights American South" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="120"/>.
          The author highlights the work of the group, OutKast, as it addresses a variety of issues,
          "including race, gender, education, economics, spirituality vs. organized religion,
          sexuality, and identity" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="122"/>. The series consists of
          interviews that engage with the music in question, as it offers a critical framework to
          exploring issues — listed above — to "speak to a wider audience than exists inside the
          classroom or between the pages of an academic journal" <ptr target="#lingold2018"
            loc="127"/>. Similarly, the HiPSTAS institute is concerned with how new, accessible
          methods of sound studies and their infrastructure affect scholarship. The project's
          principal investigator, Tanya Clement, explores modes of tagging sound clips and the
          politics and histories that standard classifications entail, examining the TEI
          Transcription for Speech guidelines. Similarly, Joanna Swafford describes the process of
          creating <title rend="italic">Augmented Notes</title> and how the platform intends to
          "build greater support for MEI (Music Encoding Initiative)" because "this additional
          functionality would increase the tool's interoperability and usefulness" <ptr
            target="#lingold2018" loc="222"/>. The platforms and initiatives discussed in <title
            rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> aim to increase accessibility and provide
          more functionalities to sound studies scholars, all the while addressing the politics,
          histories, and cultures inherent to the field. In that sense, contributors raise important
          questions about DH in an attempt to provide ways for it and sound studies to work
          together, or at least in parallel.</p>
        <p>Another common theme throughout <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> is DH
          and how — or whether — it can encompass sound studies. The main premise for such an
          inclusion is the use of technology. While DH and digital sound studies involve the use of
          technology, platforms and initiatives in this book seem to be asking for inclusion and
          acknowledgment within DH. For instance, Trammell, Stoever, and Silva explain that
          "[b]ecause many bloggers like [them] use a digital platform created by someone else, the
          question of whether blogging really constitutes 'making' — a key but contested tenet of
          digital humanities — is a roiling debate. Of course, as this essay argues, [they]
          definitely think it does" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="84"/>. Although I agree that
          making in DH has been the subject of various debates, projects like <title rend="italic"
            >Sounding Out!</title> — which is well established in sound studies — do not need to be
          acclaimed as DH projects to be scholarly interventions. Nevertheless, in calling for
          acknowledgment by DH, contributors to <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>
          extend an invitation for DH to be more inclusive. For example, Steph Ceraso "proposes
          several 'sound practices' that are intended to help scholars account for full embodied
          kinds of sensory engagement; these practices amplify the ecological relationship between
          sound, bodies, and environments" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="251"/>. Such approaches
          promise a well-rounded undertaking of subject matter, beyond previously established
          intellectual biases. Further, in their introduction, Lingold, Mueller, and Trettien
          explain that scholars "worry that the [DH] field has a far too comfortable relationship
          with systems of power that cultural criticism has long sought to challenge," adding that
          "the text-centricity of the field [is] a bias that is baked into its institutional
          history" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="9"/>. As discussed in this review, contributors
          to the book communicate the efforts needed for sound and listening to be more appreciated
          as methodologies in the humanities. For instance, the platforms and initiatives described
          in the book place great weight on having sound clips be part of scholarship.</p>
        <p><title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title> invites conversation around sound
          studies and its relationships with neighboring fields, mostly DH. Contributors explore
          methodologies, platforms, and initiatives that demonstrate interdisciplinary and inclusive
          work that centers sound and listening. The chapters also provide examples of how sound
          scholarship can reach a wider public than is accessible through academic journals. Rebecca
          Dowd Geoffroy-Schwinden argues that "[a] turn to diverse media in the presentation of
          audible history will encourage a vital rethinking of the performance of archival research
          as well as scholarly production and reception" <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="232"/>.
          This statement is yet another invitation for scholars to invest in the affordances of
          sound as a methodology towards advanced understandings of the humanities. As Sterne
          asserts in his interview, "what we need are deep and multidimensional infrastructures"
            <ptr target="#lingold2018" loc="282"/>. <title rend="italic">Digital Sound
            Studies</title> provides models of how to create such infrastructures. While I believe
          that this collection places more emphasis on DH than is necessary, the contributions
          provide a balanced critique of DH as a norm and culture while detailing digital sound
          studies' contributions to the humanities and the public. This edited volume is an
          excellent resource for people interested in non-conventional experiences that defy
          standard and mainstream methods of learning and teaching within the humanities. It invites
          critical thought from cultural, social, and artistic frameworks, with a sustained and
          sustainable focus on the potential of sound and listening.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <!-- BACK TEXT -->
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl xml:id="lingold2018" label="Lingold et al. 2018">Lingold, Mary Caton, Darren Muller,
          and Whitney Trettien, eds. (2018). <title rend="italic">Digital Sound Studies</title>.
          London: Duke University Press.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
    </back>
  </text>
  <!-- END TEXT -->

</TEI>
