<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Reaping the Harvest: Descendant Archival Practice to
               Foster Sustainable Digital Archives for Rural Black Women</title>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Jazma <dhq:family>Sutton</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-4903-045X</idno>
            	<dhq:affiliation>Miami University, Ohio</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>Suttonj5@miamioh.edu </email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Jazma Sutton is a PhD candidate in the Department of History at Indiana
                     University Bloomington. Her research explores race, gender, migration, and the
                     transition from slavery to freedom in antebellum Indiana and Ohio. More
                     specifically, she is interested in nineteenth-century Black women’s pursuits of
                     freedom and citizenship in rural communities.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <dhq:author_name>Kalani <dhq:family>Craig</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <idno type="ORCID">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-8909-0369</idno>
               <dhq:affiliation>Indiana University Bloomington</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>craigkl@indiana.edu </email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p>Kalani Craig is Clinical Associate Professor of History, Co-Director of the
                     Institute for Digital Arts &amp; Humanities, and Associate Director of the
                     Medieval Studies Institute at Indiana University Bloomington. She is also the
                     PI on Net.Create, an NSF-funded (#1848655) network-analysis tool designed for
                     teams of digital-humanities practitioners.</p>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id"><!--including leading zeroes: e.g. 000110-->000640</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006-->016</idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2-->3</idno>
         	<date when="2022-07-22">22 July 2022</date>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability status="CC-BY-ND">
               <!--If using a different license from the default, choose one of the following:
                  CC-BY-ND (DHQ default):        
                  CC-BY:    
                  CC0:  -->
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
            <!--add <language> with appropriate @ident for any additional languages-->
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Black women</item>
                  <item>Black digital humanities</item>
                  <item>History harvest</item>
                  <item>Memory work</item>
                  <item>Digital community archive</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change who="BRG" when="2022-07-29">revised encoding to resolve encoding errors</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <p>Little is left of the built environment that marked the Greenville-Longtown Black
               Settlement, a once-thriving, free Black agricultural community on the border of
               Randolph County, Indiana, and Darke County, Ohio. The people of Greenville have not
               been forgotten, however, because of the memory-work undertaken by each generation of
               Black women whose power and agency connects their past with their future descendants.
               This article draws on “descendant archival practices” as a method to understand the
               importance of Greenville’s Black women in the preservation of rural Black community
               heritage and in the writing of Black women’s histories in the antebellum Midwest.
               Descendant archival practices connect Black digital humanities practices to the
               Longtown-Greenville descendant community's digitization of artifacts and oral
               histories and supports a community-owned version of their active Facebook group. The
               result, a History Harvest called <title rend="quotes"><ref
                     target="https://longtownhistory.github.io/">Remembering Freedom: Longtown and
                     Greenville History Harvest</ref></title>, will facilitate ongoing community
               participation and future history harvests for overlooked, forgotten, and
               long-silenced communities.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <p>In a world that has always conceived of Black women in opposition to others, but
               never on her own terms, <title rend="italic">Remembering Freedom History
                  Harvest</title> builds a local Indiana historiography that relies less on
               resistant readings of archives and more on the community archives and memory work
               that join together in <emph>descendant archival practice</emph> as a way to generate
               Black women’s histories.</p>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head/>
            <epigraph>
               <cit>
                  <quote rend="block">By memory, those fond associations and ties of love which
                     unite us together on earth, will be preserved in eternity...Memory should be
                     cultivated. Like all other faculties of the mind and body, its vigor and
                     activity depend on its exercise. The more the memory is exercised the stronger
                     it becomes.<lb/>
                  	<hi rend="italic">-J.B. Harrison, Greenville Settlement, 1864</hi>
                  </quote>
               </cit>
            </epigraph>
            <p>95-year-old Cleo Fay Goens Mason is determined to narrate her own story. In her
               words, <quote rend="inline">Everybody has their own idea of what’s important. And you
                  have to respect that</quote>
               <ptr target="#mason2019b"/>. Perhaps this was a lesson she learned from her mother,
               who kept the books at Bethel Wesleyan Church in the early 1900s and held on to many
               of the items that adorned her during her life. Mrs. Mason, like her mother, is a
               memory keeper and descendant of the historic Longtown community, formerly known as
               the Greenville Black Settlement and now visible as Longtown on a map of Ohio. Mrs.
               Mason’s participation in the September 29, 2019 history harvest at the annual
               homecoming of Longtown, and the deliberate ways in which she unveiled her family's
               heirlooms, suggests that her memory work is a practice cultivated across generations
               to bridge the gap of time and space between ancestor and descendant, between past and
               present, between the collections built by an individual and those housed in
               independent community archives <ptr target="#mason2019a"/><ptr target="#flinn2009"
                  loc="73"/>.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Mason’s contributions to <title rend="italic"><ref
                     target="https://longtownhistory.github.io">Remembering Freedom: Longtown and
                     Greenville History Harvest</ref></title>, henceforth <title rend="italic"
                  >Remembering Freedom History Harvest</title>, extend her own memory work into a
               collaborative space that includes both Longtown descendants and a group of
               researchers and volunteers from Indiana University–Bloomington <ptr
                  target="#powell2018"/>. Like other history harvests, this history harvest paired
               the ethical concerns of community archiving with university partners, including the
               Institute for Digital Arts &amp; Humanities and the Center for Research on Race and
               Ethnicity in Society, to digitize, preserve and showcase community historical
               artifacts in an open-source digital archive project <ptr
                  target="#universityofnebraska"/><ptr target="#rondo2017"/>. This shifts focus away
               from mainstream archives, the collections of predominantly white institutions that
               pose as inclusive and representative but fail to label Black people and their
               material as authoritative and constitutive. Women like Mrs. Mason and her female
               ancestors often show up in these institutional archives, both physical and digital,
               as nameless, faceless, victimized, objectified, or in the perspectives of others <ptr
                  target="#cifor2018"/><ptr target="#zavala2017"/><ptr target="#hartman2019"
                  loc="31"/>. Like the <title rend="italic"><ref
                     target="https://omeka.macalester.edu/rondo/">Remembering Rondo History
                     Harvest</ref></title>, <title rend="italic">Remembering Freedom</title> was
               created, and will be owned and sustained, by the individuals who have defined these
               descendant communities, foregrounding what rural Black women have been able to
               accomplish, across time and space, through an inherited practice of preservation
               work.</p>
            <p>Mrs. Mason’s own ancestors shaped and preserved the memories that she then preserved
               for her own granddaughters and contributed to the <title rend="italic">Remembering
                  Freedom</title> in a conversation between individual, ancestral line and
               contemporary community that we are calling <emph>descendant archival
               practices</emph>. This approach explores alternative conceptions of community
               archives and memory work to expand the definition of slavery’s archive specifically.
               From historical documents stored in manila folders and cardboard boxes to memories
               invoked at her own will or with her granddaughter’s persuasion, Mrs. Mason’s
               individual contributions to the Longtown history harvest reveal the strategies of
               memory keeping individual women contributed to the communal legacies of Longtown’s
               history, which have not been erased but were instead preserved in plain sight. They
               left marks on the land they bequeathed their descendants, at the schools and churches
               in which they labored, in the secret rooms fugitive women used as safe havens, in the
               photographs they commissioned to recast the image of Black womanhood, and in the
               documents they passed down to their children and grandchildren.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Jazma Sutton, Mrs. Mason, and others at Longtown History Harvest.</head>
               <figDesc> Jazma Sutton, Mrs. Mason, and others at Longtown History Harvest. They are
                  in a church and talking in a loose circle. </figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image1.png"/>
            </figure>

            <figure>
               <head>Jazma Sutton, Mrs. Mason, and others at Longtown History Harvest.</head>
               <figDesc> Jazma Sutton, Mrs. Mason, and others at Longtown History Harvest. Another
                  angle of figure 1. </figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image2.jpeg"/>
            </figure>

            <p>
               <emph>Descendant archival practices</emph> cites as experts the many generations of
               Black women elders whose memory work preserves their history, and it holds as
               custodians the present generations of Black women whose power and agency connects
               their memory-work inheritance with their future descendants. The <title rend="italic"
                  >Remembering Freedom History Harvest</title> builds on these intergenerational
               processes — which encompass on the collaborative aspects of community archiving, the
               individual actions of descendants who choose to keep their family’s histories, and
               the collection practices of history harvests — to examine free and fugitive Black
               women’s experiences of freedom in the rural Midwest who have been overlooked in
               accounts of slavery and freedom. Over the past five years Jazma Sutton has worked
               collaboratively with individual Longtown descendants to center the sources, archives,
               and narratives produced by nineteenth-century Black women and their descendants,
               illuminate the multiplicity of archives that descendants of free and enslaved people
               have managed to create and preserve despite the constraints of white colonial power
               and white supremacy. <emph>Descendant archival practice</emph> foregrounds the
               individual and communal archival power of Black women, past and present, to <quote
                  rend="inline">confront inequalities of power in the production of sources</quote>
               as we look toward a digital future <ptr target="#trouillot2015"/>. The project thus
               grapples with the methodological and ethical concerns situated between archival
               excess and absence across the digital and analog divide. In a world that has always
               conceived of Black women in opposition to others, but never on her own terms, <title
                  rend="italic">Remembering Freedom History Harvest</title> builds a local Indiana
               historiography that relies less on resistant readings of archives and more on the
               community archives and memory work that join together in <emph>descendant archival
                  practice</emph> as a way to generate Black women’s histories.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Sowing the Seeds</head>
            <p>The Greenville Settlement, which overlapped the borders of Indiana and Ohio, was one
               of the earliest and most prosperous Black communities in the region. The settlement
               was founded in 1818 in Darke County, Ohio, by James and Sophia Clemens. By 1822, it
               extended over the state-line into Randolph County, Indiana where Thornton Alexander
               purchased the first tract of Black-owned land in the county. At times, Indiana and
               Ohio both passed state laws that prohibited immigration into the state, denied access
               to public schools, promoted Black immigration to Africa, and stripped Black people of
               any rights and privileges in court. Despite this, by the mid nineteenth century the
               free and fugitive Black people of Greenville had collectively amassed the most
               Black-owned land of any county in Indiana. They had established Wesleyan and African
               Methodist Episcopal Churches, founded an integrated, co-educational school of manual
               labor known as the Union Literary Institute (ULI), and operated safehouses on the
               Underground Railroad. In these ways, Greenville pioneers forged a community that was
               conducive to rural life and anti-slavery activism.</p>
            <p>Today, the Clemens farmstead, a disintegrating ULI school building, and three
               cemeteries, one of which stands neglected in the middle of a white-owned farm, are
               all that remain of the settlement’s built-environment. The joint forces of racial
               violence, industrialization, agricultural innovation, and mass migration decreased
               the Black population of Longtown to 0.76%. Roane Smothers, a family historian,
               asserts <quote rend="inline">When this has happened at other African American
                  settlements, the buildings and cemeteries were demolished and the story about
                  these African American pioneers are forgotten and buried</quote>
               <ptr target="#staff2015"/>. Sustained resistance to archival and cultural erasure has
               allowed Longtown descendants to digitize hundreds of historical documents and
               artifacts, to obtain historical markers, and to restore old buildings and register
               them on the National Register of Historic Places and as Underground Railroad sites
               with the National Park Service. Despite what Greenville descendants have been able to
               achieve through grassroots preservation practices, we still know very little about
               the women who W.E.B. Du Bois noted, after visiting the settlement in 1909, <quote
                  rend="inline">took hold of the community</quote>
               <ptr target="#dubois1909"/>.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Map of Longtown, past and present</head>
               <figDesc> Map of Longtown, past and present. On the left side is a screenshot from
                  Google Maps while the right side includes a hand drawn map. </figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image3.png"/>
            </figure>

            <p>In this changing landscape of the Indiana-Ohio borderland, it was the women of
               Greenville and Longtown who carried its history into the present. Prior to the Civil
               War, Greenville women created spaces for themselves as free people, citizens, and
               women. Landownership and rural seclusion enabled Black women to raise families that
               could not be separated or destroyed, to educate their children, and to manage their
               own farms and homes. They labored as mothers, wives, caregivers, farm hands, and
               community leaders for the sake of community survival. The meager evidence that exists
               about Greenville women in male family members’ estate records, white men’s and
               women’s reminiscences of the Underground Railroad, and some oral histories suggest
               that they were savvy. They adjusted to, and spearheaded at times, the latest
               agricultural, technological, industrial, and political advancements in arguably one
               of the most anti-Black states in the Midwest at that time — Indiana.</p>
         </div>
         <div>

            <head>Nurturing the Archive</head>
            <p>The historical examination of slavery and freedom in the Northwest Territory
               (present-day Midwest) has been slow. A move towards engaging the lives of free,
               enslaved and fugitive Black women who lived in the territory’s hundreds of free Black
               communities has lagged even further behind. Scholars like Erica Armstrong Dunbar,
               Amrita Chakrabarti Myers and Jessica Millward focus on urban spaces, pushing us to
               consider enslaved and free Black women’s lived experiences of freedom, their
               definitions of freedom, and the varying degrees of freedom they occupied. To a
               certain extent, they each rely on traditional records such as court records, wills,
               church minutes, city directories, other official documents, and in rare cases like
                  <title rend="italic">A Fragile Freedom</title>, Black women’s friendship albums to
               partially piece together the lives of free Black women who often left little to no
               sources behind about their lives <ptr target="#dunbar2008"/>
               <ptr target="#dunbar2017"/>. In <title rend="italic">Forging Freedom</title>, some of
               these women were considered exceptional, having owned property and other enslaved
               people, yet they appear in the archive, not strictly in their own right, but mainly
               as a result of their legal negotiations or sexual relations with white men <ptr
                  target="#myers2011"/>. Millward, in <title rend="italic">Finding Charity’s
                  Folk</title> is fortunate to have one formerly enslaved woman’s manumission
               papers, will, and court case, but is also aware that these records alone can not
               reconstruct the multifacet lives of enslaved and free Black women. In search of
               Charity Folk whose <quote rend="inline">ghost refuses to be silent</quote>, Millward
               turns to memory, descendants of enslavers and enslaved people, historical buildings,
               and cemeteries to chronicle the life of a single woman <ptr target="#millward2015"/>.
               In <title rend="italic">All That She Carried: The Journey of Ashley’s Sack, a Black
                  Family Keepsake </title>, historian Tiya Miles uses a single artifact from Black
               women’s material culture — a sack filled with a tattered dress, three handfuls of
               pecans, and a braid of hair, which one enslaved woman bequeathed her daughter before
               being sold away — to trace the lives of a mother, daughter, and granddaughter trio
               during slavery and its immediate aftermath. Miles’ treatment is an innovative
               assessment of the inheritance practices Black women drew on to maintain family
               connections between generations when the forces of slavery severed those connections
               all too readily <ptr target="#miles2021"/>. Millward and Miles show us what is
               possible when historians of enslaved women step outside of the confines of the
               traditional archive and demonstrate the importance of naming <emph>descendant
                  archival practice</emph> to acknowledge the many contexts in which it appears in
               Black women’s history.</p>
            <p>Saidiya Hartman in <title rend="quotes">Venus in Two Acts</title> finds Black women
               in the <quote rend="inline">archives of slavery</quote> in similar deplorable
               conditions — <quote rend="inline">No one remembered her name or recorded the things
                  she said, or observed that she refused to say anything at all</quote>. To make
               meaning of this sort of archival encounter with <quote rend="inline">Black
                  Venus</quote>, for Hartman, is akin to entering a mortuary — it permits one final
               viewing and allows for a last glimpse of persons about to disappear into the slave
               hold <ptr target="#hartman2008"/><ptr target="#hartman2006"/>. Her account is as much
               an account of the violence of the archive as it is of enslaved women. Like Hartman,
               in <hi rend="italic">Dispossessed Lives,</hi> Marisa Fuentes, reckons with archival
               power, the violence of the archive, and the impossibilities of writing about Black
               women during slavery. While Hartman encourages historians to <quote rend="inline"
                  >respect the limits of what cannot be known</quote>, Marisa Fuentes suggests that
               we stretch these limits by <quote rend="inline">reading against the bias
                  grain</quote>
               <ptr target="#fuentes2016"/>. Instead of focusing solely on the lived experiences of
               enslaved women, she shifts her methods to examining the production of historical
               narratives that result from <quote rend="inline">archival fragments</quote>
               <ptr target="#fuentes2016"/>.</p>
            <p>Black digital humanists have engaged a number of insurgent archival practices that,
               like <emph>descendant archival practice</emph>, model best-practice collaboration
               with community partners and bring digital methods to bear in both the practical and
               ideological transformation of tools and organizations that <quote rend="inline"
                  >resist and counteract slavery’s dehumanizing impulses</quote> as Jessica Marie
               Johnson notes in <title rend="quotes">Markup Bodies: Black [Life] Studies and Slavery
                  [Death] Studies at the Digital Crossroads</title>. Johnson further defines Black
               digital practice as <quote rend="inline">the revelation that Black subjects have
                  themselves taken up science, data, and coding, in other words, have commodified
                  themselves and digitized and mediated their own Black freedom dreams in order to
                  hack their way into the system (modernity, science, the West), take root, and live
                  where they were “never meant to survive</quote>
               <ptr target="#johnson2018"/>. In that vein, <emph>descendant archival practice</emph>
               in <title rend="italic">Remembering Freedom</title> echoes the engaging
               public-facing, community-based digital research done at #DigBlk, the Center for Black
               Digital Research at Penn State University in its community involvement. It orients
               toward <q>information</q> with the intent of bringing technology into play as a
               platform for descendants to convene regular conversation, as do the spaces defined by
               eBlack Studies, Black social media, and conversations like those at the Afrofuturism
               listserv.</p>
            <p>Descendant archival practice builds on the concept of community archiving to
               understand Black women’s personalized family <q>collections</q> as sites of
               resistance, identity formation, and community empowerment <ptr target="#zavala2017"
               />. While institutional examples of post-custodial approaches like the University of
               Texas Libraries or the University of Nebraska’s history harvest offer community
               empowerment through the collection of community owned objects, descendant archival
               practice offers a community-owned model built on history harvests like <title
                  rend="italic">Remembering Rondo</title>, in which the community and the
               institutional partner hold joint ownership of the digital records themselves <ptr
                  target="#alpert2019" loc="4"/>. This community ownership makes explicit the give
               and take between individual family record-keeping done by descendants and the labor
               required to build digital community histories that will continue to bind those
               discrete families together into a whole in the future <ptr target="#alpert2019"
                  loc="73"/><ptr target="#cook1994" loc="301"/>.</p>
            <p>Like the <title rend="italic">South Asian American Digital Archive</title>, <title
                  rend="italic">Transgender Archive</title>, and <title rend="italic">Documenting
                  the Now</title>, the <title rend="italic">Remembering Freedom History
                  Harvest</title> acknowledges and respects the agency and values of rural Black
               communities, and emulates the participatory and activist approaches of exclusively
               digital post-custodial archives <ptr target="#cifor2018"/><ptr target="#jules2018"/>.
               However, instead of focusing on the documentation of current events or a contemporary
               activist focus, <title rend="italic">Remembering Freedom</title> is most interested
               in what the material culture of Black women can tell us about the intergenerational
               memory work of Black women descendants. In that way, descendant archival practice
               follows Black women archivists Chaitra Powell, Holly Smith, Shanee’ Murrain and Skyla
               Hearn, themselves connected to this culture of care and memory-keeping, in
               understanding how a culture of dissemblance and careful management of archival
               practices within a closed community keeps that community safe. As historian Vanessa
               Holden puts it <quote rend="inline">silence saves lives</quote>
               <ptr target="#holden2021a"/>.</p>
            <p>As these studies show, some of the most innovative methodologies for studying free,
               enslaved, and fugitive women have emerged from encounters with colonialism, silence,
               fragmentation, and violence in the archive. The <title rend="italic">Remembering
                  Freedom History Harvest</title> builds on these methods by examining free and
               fugitive Black women’s experiences of freedom in the rural Midwest who have been
               overlooked in accounts of slavery and freedom. As part of <emph>descendant archival
                  practice</emph>, we expand the definition of the archive of slavery to include
               living individuals who hold, in their ancestry, an inheritance that keys to what is
               unknown. The major ethical concern driving the <title rend="italic">Remembering
                  Freedom History Harvest</title> is the normalization of silence and violence in
               the narratives, archives, and methods we use to write about Black women during
               slavery. At the same time, <emph>descendant archival practice</emph> does not accept
               that enslaved women must always appear nameless, faceless, and forgotten in the
               archives of slavery. In fact, attention to the preservation practices of descendants
               and other Black digital humanists who are concerned with centering overlooked Black
               communities and issues of accessibility allow us to create intentional practices to
               ensure that this does not happen in the future.</p>
            <p>Because of its joint emphasis on openness and digital-community-engagement structure,
               the history harvest model offers a platform for enacting the elements of
                  <emph>descendent archival practice</emph> that hold space for the individual and
               communal voices of Black women in particular. A more adequate counter-history of
               slavery — a history of the past and present intertwined — privileges the overlooked
               communities of descendants, the archives they have produced, and the stories they
               have to tell. For the descendants of Greenville, women have taken up this call. One
               such archive is <ref
                  target="https://www.facebook.com/Remembering-Freedom-James-Clemens-and-the-Longtown-Settlement-170627093017850/"
                  >their Facebook page, <title rend="quotes">Remembering Freedom</title></ref>,
               which serves as a core inspiration for this history harvest. As a digital archive,
               and an easy-to-use platform for community empowerment, the <title rend="quotes"
                  >Remembering Freedom</title> Facebook page echoes the technical expertise that has
               always been necessary for Black people to flourish in rural communities. The ability
               to learn, adapt, and invent technologies was one of the hidden hallmarks of free
               Black rural communities, and Longtown's women descendants are carrying on that
               tradition in digital and analog spaces. Its near-ubiquity as a social media platform
               — Pew Research estimates 69% of adults had Facebook accounts in 2019, and 74% of
               those users visited the site daily <ptr target="#perrin2019"/> — and its ease of use
               offers equitable access to Longtown descendants, historians and other interested
               parties from across many demographic groups to collaboratively fill the silences in
               Longtown’s history. At the same time, Facebook’s proprietary approach to and control
               over its data means that, without consideration for backups or presentation
               elsewhere, any digitized archives on Facebook’s platform are prone to unexpected loss
               and erasure (though to be fair, this isn’t a concern limited to Facebook for
               born-digital archives). Its algorithmic presentation of a “feed” selected for each
               user also serves to make the silences and gaps in that feed invisible and unknowable
               to the average Facebook visitor.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Reaping the Harvest </head>
            <p>An emphasis on <emph>descendant archival practice </emph>helps surface the voices of
               enslaved, free, and fugitive Black communities in parallel with those of their
               individual descendants in the present. As we considered how to honor this parallel in
               both the in-person and digital components of the <title rend="italic">Remembering
                  Freedom History Harvest</title>, several projects informed our work. Some of these
               projects were good models for the technical and community-engagement portions of the
               history harvest; others provided grounded examples of our theoretical frameworks
               expressed in practice.</p>
            <p>Our first reference point was the project’s namesake, the <ref
                  target="https://historyharvest.unl.edu">first history harvests at Nebraska</ref>
               in 2013.<note> From the History Harvest site at historyharvest.unl.edu: <quote
                     rend="inline">The University of Nebraska-Lincoln Department of History partners
                     with institutions and individuals within highlighted communities to collect,
                     preserve, and share their rich histories. Advanced undergraduates lead the
                     History Harvest project and curate and digitize these artifacts and stories....
                     The History Harvest, then, is an invitation to local people to share their
                     historical artifacts, and their stories, for inclusion in a unique digital
                     archive of what we are calling the people’s history.</quote></note>
               <ptr target="#universityofnebraska"/>. The basic principle is built on community
               contribution of objects, with academic support in order to digitally preserve family
               heirlooms that might otherwise not be included in the historical record without
               removing them from the families whose history they tell. These history harvests
               provided a service-learning model that puts historians into dialogue with the
               public-history needs of local community members. Such digital-public-engagement
               projects foster collaboration between community members and the academy, a
               democratization of history that still maintains the academic-history connection
               between preservation and the analysis of change and continuity. While a later K-12
               model extends the history-harvest practices to <ref
                  target="https://www.ops.org/InvisibleHistory"><title rend="quotes">Invisible
                     Histories</title> in Omaha’s minoritized communities</ref>, the prominent
               early models presented in the <ref target="https://historyharvest.net/?page_id=152"
                     ><title rend="quotes">History Harvest Handbook</title></ref> are those in which
               undergraduates worked in classroom settings with largely white homesteader audiences
               in the communities surrounding Lincoln <ptr target="#friefeld2015"/>. While
               contributions solicited by undergraduates from these rural Russian and German
               immigrant communities lack some representation in the archives, the experiences of
               rural white communities in general are already well represented in academic
               history.</p>
            <p>To bridge that gap, we looked then to <title rend="italic">Remembering Rondo</title>
               History Harvests for a community engagement model that emphasized the efforts of
               Detroit’s largest red-lined Black community working to preserve the community’s
               memory of the community before and after it was forcibly divided in 1956 by the
               construction of the I-94 freeway <ptr target="#wingo2020"/>. These history harvests
               focused on the importance of community agency and operational oversight, a process
               driven by now-retirement-age community members. The community’s interest in these
               history harvests were meant not just to preserve Rondo’s memory of itself before the
               I-94’s construction. The history harvest team also served as one prong of many
               community efforts to highlight and publicize Rondo’s unity through its long physical
               divide, as Rondo’s residents sought to address the physical reuniting of Rondo
               through, among other efforts, construction of a land-bridge over the I-94. Rondo’s
               model of community custody with university-provided sustainability, compared to the
               post-custodial models in previous history harvests, was particularly instructive.</p>
            <p>Finally, we looked to the <ref
                  target="https://www.thetexasfreedomcoloniesproject.com">Texas Freedom Colonies
                  Project</ref>, which has elements of the community contributions that are central
               to history harvests but re-focuses the communal element of the history harvest on
               pre-existing Black community preservation practices that can be supported and
               extended through digital means <ptr target="#roberts2018"/>. This project is also
               driven by what founder Andrea Roberts, calls <quote rend="inline">critical sankofa
                  planning — a process of looking back, believing there’s wisdom there, and applying
                  that knowledge to current dilemmas</quote>. As she points out, the social justice
               aim embedded in critical sankofa planning is especially relevant to <quote
                  rend="inline">rural or unincorporated [black] spaces</quote> like Longtown,
               dealing with <quote rend="inline">gentrification and cultural erasure</quote> in the
               present.</p>
            <p>To continue redressing the absences and erasure in the archive, we focused on five
               features that reshaped some of the history harvest digital conventions in ways that
               center the existing community practices unique to Longtown descendants. Two of these
               shifts were part of the history-harvest day itself. First, we were invited to
               participate in an already scheduled community homecoming day. We also shifted away
               from archival-level capture practices that emphasize specific preservation quality
               (and therefore equipment) requirements. Instead, we focused on low-cost easy-to-use
               equipment that community members would be likely to have on hand already (cell
               phones, desk lamps) or could purchase for very low cost (e.g. homemade cardboard
               lightboxes or inexpensive pop-up lightboxes to improve photo quality<note>
                  <ref target="https://expertphotography.com/diy-light-box/">The pop-up
                     lightboxes.</ref></note>). Both of these considerations are directly connected
               to the idea of the archive as a nexus of community-academy partnership, rather than a
               site of academic praxis that seeks to meet purely academic standards.</p>
            <p>The other three technical shifts are situated in the digital context of the history
               harvest: a series of vocabulary changes to the history harvest site, a move to <ref
                  target="https://pages.github.com">Github Pages</ref>, and the interleaving of the
               community’s Facebook page with the history harvest page. Each of these technical
               considerations was driven by our digital-engagement theory. Compounded, all five draw
               on considerations of <quote rend="inline">racialized design</quote> — an intentional
               challenge to uninterrogated project management and design standards that perpetuate
               racism <ptr target="#mercer2019"/>. The choice of Github Pages in particular meant
               that we could effectively support community custody of the web site with a free,
               stable, sustainable hosting solution that emphasizes simple, static web pages. That
               in turn allowed us to draw on university-sponsored resources and workflows to
               facilitate regular <q>backups</q> of the <title rend="italic">Remembering Freedom
                  History Harvest</title> web site on the <ref
                  target="https://web.archive.org/web/2021*/https://longtownhistory.github.io"
                  >Internet Archive’s Wayback Machine</ref>, ensuring long-term public access to
               the site regardless of community hosting considerations. Together, these five changes
               radically transform the history harvest from a space that perpetuates <quote
                  rend="inline">white colonial power</quote> in present-day archives and narratives
               to one that truly promotes <quote rend="inline">innovative new authentic learning
                  initiatives</quote> for the future through the historical productions of
               overlooked people.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>In the Pews at Longtown</head>
            <p>First, we scheduled the event day around several pre-existing community traditions
               centered on gathering at the physical site of Longtown and Greenville itself.
               Descendant Brenda Jett was responsible for organizing the event at the local Bethel
               Wesleyan Church, and she functioned as the main contact between researcher and
               community. Homecoming events like the one at which the history harvest took place are
               evidence of how the community sees its past as a source of identity and a guide for
               future conduct. The invitation to participate in the history harvest portion of the
               homecoming event was explicitly focused on memory as an heirloom. By signaling that
               oral histories rooted in the built environment itself, in an ancestral home, were
               equally valid as contributions of digitized family heirlooms, we acknowledged the
               silences of free and enslaved voices in archives that are often dependent on physical
               objects and traditional historical texts to anchor a community’s history.</p>
            <p>Second, we centered the event on digitization tools that would minimize the amount of
               computing and technology necessary to generate a digital archive and situate that
               digitization effort in the community’s most familiar spaces <ptr target="#gil2016"/>.
               This minimal-computing approach, which we address more fully below, allowed us to be
               flexible and take community direction once we arrived at the homecoming, rather than
               requesting guaranteed access to WiFi or power outlets, which might redirect community
               focus to our needs rather than theirs.</p>
            <p>Upon arrival, we were invited to attend the community’s Homecoming church service.
               Our digitization efforts would be located at the church and began at the conclusion
               of the Homecoming ceremony. In a small room behind the sanctuary, where we were able
               to access a few power outlets, we set up a single, foldable light box, a scanner, and
               a sign-in table. Members crowded the space; some were holding a few folders, others
               carried boxes filled with decades-old materials. Still, others toted nothing but
               their personal stories and histories. We sent a few graduate and undergraduate
               students to the pews with handheld battery-powered audio recorders for interviews and
               began encouraging community members to fill out our paper forms.</p>
            <p>Standing together in the small room, we issued directions and were also directed. One
               descendant sought accommodations for Shari Petersime, a family historian who is
               visually impaired. Shari, still residing in the Longtown area, contributed a draft of
               the family history book she was writing titled, <title rend="quotes">Only God Can
                  Make a Tree: Tracing my Burden Family Roots</title>" <ptr target="#petersime2019"
               />. A couple of months after the history harvest, she contacted Sutton via phone and
               made arrangements to send her a copy of the final project. Sutton has since then
               cited the publication, which has a wealth of information on antebellum women from the
               settlement, in her dissertation and consulted Petersime’s expertise to weave together
               archival fragments. This is also when we first met Mrs. Mason, who offered the
               largest collection of documents and objects of any descendant. The particularity with
               which she handled her material or responded to our requests was evidence of the
               intentionality that generations of rural Black women have placed on how they wanted
               to be remembered. Mrs. Mason, highlights the ways in which rural Black women and
               their female descendants have subverted the fate of Black Venus. We could not ignore
               the care and concentration with which she chose the information she wanted to share
               from her personal archive.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>Shari Petersime’s Family History Book</head>
               <figDesc>Shari Petersime’s Family History Book. The image is the front cover of the
                  books which is spiral bound and white. </figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image4.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>As the example of Mrs. Mason makes clear, the amount of material to collect far
               exceeded the number of hands and time available to do the work of collecting. We
               worked with descendants to choose – or limit — what they wanted scanned,
               photographed, or recorded, but those choices were circumscribed by the sometimes-slow
               nature of high-quality digital capture. In some cases, we compromised the quality of
               the digitization process in order to acknowledge the importance of a memory or
               heirloom. In each of these cases, the question looming over our labor is one of
               theoretical, practical, and historical importance: Would those interested in seeing
               this archive, whether they be researchers, descendants of the public, <quote
                  rend="inline">emerge from the encounter [with the archive] with a sense of
                  incompleteness and with the recognition that some part of the self is missing as a
                  consequence of this engagement?</quote>
               <ptr target="#hartman2008"/>. We were compelled to contend with the possibility that,
               in our efforts to address the silences and violence of the archive, we had sustained
               them because of the twin limitations of time and technical ability.</p>
            <p>At the same time, we did not <quote rend="inline">stumble upon her in exorbitant
                  circumstances that yield no picture of everyday life, no pathway to her thoughts,
                  no glimpse of the vulnerability of her face or what looking at such a face might
                  demand</quote>
               <ptr target="#hartman2008"/>. In fact, we encountered her — Venus, rural free and
               fugitive Black women, Mrs. Mason — because she made the decision to show up. The sum
               of Mrs. Mason’s collections — birth, death and church records, marriage certificates,
               property deeds, poetry, sewing baskets, photographs, a kerosene light, photos of the
               1850 home built by the founder of the settlement in which she was born and raised —
               yield a picture of everyday life that no archive in the states of Indiana and Ohio,
               together, has been able to reveal <ptr target="#mason2019a"/><ptr
                  target="#mason2019b"/>. Looking at her face and witnessing the choices she made
               about the information she wanted to share, demanded that we see her as evidence of
               the past and allow her to narrate her own story.</p></div>
         <div>
            <head>Longtown Online</head>
            <p>This worry stayed with us after we returned home, and the remaining three of our five
               changes were driven by the ongoing realization that we would need to do more work to
               address the archive as a site of erasure. To that end, our third major change
               reoriented the web site around the idea of descendant voices, even down to the
               variable names. As we noted earlier, our pre-event Call for Contributions included a
               call to contribute voice in addition to object; on site, we stressed the importance
               of descendants’ preferences for digitizing the items that were significant to them —
               not to us or anyone else — as a way to emphasize the community’s archival power. To
               echo that emphasis, what would have been the <q>Collections</q> and <q>Items</q>
               portion of another history harvest site is now called <title rend="quotes">Descendant
                  History</title> In that section, we bring digitized objects together with
               descendant interviews and give both equal weight as part of the preservation efforts.
               We also addressed the divide between <q>contributor</q>, <q>creator</q>, and
                  <q>owner</q> in the language of the original history harvest metadata, a holdover
               that assumes creation, ownership, and contribution have a transactional nature. These
               divided roles are gone, replaced by <q>descendant</q> to acknowledge the inheritance
               that makes descendants like Mrs. Mason the guardians of their own history.</p>
            <p>Fourth, the <title rend="quotes">Remembering Freedom</title> Facebook page created by
               Lori Archey, which is descendant-driven and will see more regular updates than the
               history harvest page, is embedded front-and-center on the history-harvest home page
               and on the page that documents the 2019 homecoming event <ptr target="#archey2011"/>.
               Similarly, some of the photos that are part of the community’s own archive on
               Facebook are re-presented as part of the history harvest collection, clearly labeled
               and with additional links to the Facebook site and its preserved heirlooms. These
               embeddings and linkages highlight the active role Longtown and Greenville’s
               descendants have taken for years in their own ongoing preservation efforts. Just as
               Mrs. Goens’ particularity in person is matched digitally in how her history is told
               in the history harvest, the interweaving of Facebook and history harvest is a visible
               expression of the community’s own notions of preservation as a link between their
               past and their present.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>A Screenshot of the Remembering Freedom Facebook Page sharing the History
                  Harvest</head>
               <figDesc>A Screenshot of the Remembering Freedom Facebook Page sharing the History
                  Harvest. The screenshot is from a Facebook community post. </figDesc>
               <graphic url="resources/images/image5.png"/>
            </figure>
            <p>A fifth change required more substantive effort as we considered the entwined issue
               of sustainability, affordability, and access in archive building and digital
               preservation. The community’s Facebook preservation efforts are robust,
               well-organized and literally well-liked in Facebook terms. Community organizers,
               however, acknowledge that the platform is less well suited to long-term permanence.
               The need for stability, combined with a low-cost solution that encourages community
               ownership of the archive, led us to GitHub. Most history harvests are built on a
               custom Omeka installation, a boutique university-built content-management system with
               built-in metadata processing that makes duplication in a university-sponsored
               repository easy. It does so at the cost of ongoing access to paid hosting with more
               complex requirements that require academic intervention; these requirements also make
               it more likely that academic ownership of the site would become the default. We
               instead opted for a simple, static, text-only site hosted using <ref
                  target="https://jekyllrb.com">Jekyll</ref> in Github Pages, a free platform whose
               primary function is shared, collaborative technical practices. This hosting choice
               also better supported the necessary metadata vocabulary changes that acknowledge the
               need to move away from colonizing ideals of creation, contribution, and ownership.
               While we are committed to partnering for whatever technical needs the
               Longtown/Greenville community identifies in the future, this platform choice is part
               of an overall design shift that offers the community full stewardship of their own
               preservation practices, including more history harvests in the future, with minimal
               computing needs <ptr target="#gil2016"/>.</p>
            <p>In the near future, we intend to engage more fully with one necessary feature of
               digital projects generally, and history harvests in particular: documentation. This
               effort has begun, but our long-term documentation efforts will be designed to offer a
               sustainable method for Longtown and Greenville’s communities to incorporate the
               history-harvest option as one of their own preservation efforts. We chose a
               well-documented Jekyll theme <ref target="https://jekyllthemes.io/theme/mediumish"
                  >Medium-ish</ref> on which to build our template, which gives future
               history-harvest preservationists a community of practitioners that is much larger
               than the IUB history harvest team <ptr target="#sal2019"/>. Our own customization,
               including storage and naming convention for images and text, builds on the standards
               built into that existing structure, making it more likely that anyone with basic web
               skills can learn how to update and add to the site. Finally, we have begun the
               process of documenting our approach to customizing Medium-ish through a combination
               of in-person training, <ref target="https://longtownhistory.github.io/documentation/"
                  >video tutorials</ref>, and in-line commented code. In this way, too, we actively
               sought to subvert the supposed <quote rend="inline">clarity and simplicity</quote> of
               code that obscures and excludes non-white voices and use it intentionally to support
               Longtown’s descendants as they voice their own preservation <ptr
                  target="#mcpherson2012"/>.</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Let She Who Has Watered Be Watered</head>
            <p>As we look forward into the future of the <title rend="italic">Remembering
                  Freedom</title> History Harvest, our thoughts turn to an emphasis on what the
               descendant community will need to guide their preservation and outreach efforts
               moving forward. That will take on several dimensions. As academic collaborators, we
               need to address not just the transfer of the accounts and passwords that provide
               access to Github and the email addresses that are used for Github logins. We also
               need to center the community’s Facebook practices as we work together to grow the
               site; new additions to the Facebook page that encourage community cohesion can go
               hand in hand with the stability of Github preservation. These endeavors should also
               situate a more formal university partnership, which should address backups and
               long-term file migration support for permanent preservation. In all of these formal
               partnership efforts, we will work with the community to emphasize a similar centering
               of descendant community needs that brings Black voices back into archival spaces
               without reifying the archive as the only legitimate site of preservation. To make
               this history harvest the site of true change, however, we need to consider one final
               step: a clear provision of outreach, time, tutorials and resources so that other
               communities can draw on this site for their own preservation work in the absence of
               the extractive patterns that are the hallmark of <q>traditional</q> academic
               archives. Our hope is that this focus on community-based archival production and
               sustainability — using digital technologies and platforms that are easily adaptable
               for the creation of sustainable/equitable/democratized archives for the future — will
               continue to serve those whose lives and experiences have been left void by
               traditional archives.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alpert2019" label="Alpert-Abrams, Bliss, and Carbajal 2019">Alpert-Abrams,
               H., Bliss, D. A., &amp; Carbajal, I. (2019). <title rend="quotes">Post-Custodial
                  Archiving for the Collective Good: Examining Neoliberalism in US-Latin American
                  Archival Partnerships</title>. <title rend="italic">Journal of Critical Library
                  and Information Studies</title>. 2.1 <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v2i1.87"
                  >https://doi.org/10.24242/jclis.v2i1.87</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="archey2011" label="Archey 2011">Archey, L. (2011). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Remebering freedom: James Clemens and the Longtown Settlement [Online].</title>
               <ref target="https://www.facebook.com/Remembering-Freedom-James-Clemens-and-the-Longtown-Settlement-170627093017850/"
                  >https://www.facebook.com/Remembering-Freedom-James-Clemens-and-the-Longtown-Settlement-170627093017850/</ref>.
               Acccessed July 5, 2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="cifor2018" label="Cifor et al. 2018">Cifor, M., Caswell, M., Migoni, A.A.,
               &amp; Geraci, N. (2018). <title rend="quotes"><q>What We Do Crosses over to
                     Activism</q>: The Politics and Practice of Community Archives</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">The Public Historian</title>. 40.2: 69-95. <ref
                  target="https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/737515"
                  >https://www.muse.jhu.edu/article/737515</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="cook1994" label="Cook 1994">Cook, T. (1994). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Electronic records, paper minds: the revolution in information management and
                  archives in the post/custodial and post/modernist era</title>. [Based on a
               presentation delivered by the author during his November 1993 Australian tour.].
                  <title rend="italic">Archives and Manuscripts</title> 22.2: 300-328.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dubois1909" label="Du Bois 1909">Du Bois, W. E. B. (1909). <title
                  rend="quotes">Long in Darke</title>. <title rend="italic">Colored American
                  Magazine.</title>
            </bibl>



            <bibl xml:id="documenting" label="Documenting the Now">Documenting the Now. Available:
                  <ref target="https://www.docnow.io/">https://www.docnow.io/</ref>. Accessed August
               25, 2021.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dunbar2008" label="Dunbar 2008">Dunbar, E. A. (2008). <title
                  rend="italic">A fragile freedom: African American women and emancipation in the
                  antebellum city</title>. New Haven, CT: Yale University Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="dunbar2017" label="Dunbar 2017">Dunbar, E. A. (2017). <title rend="italic"
                  >Never caught: The Washingtons' relentless pursuit of their runaway slave, Ona
                  Judge</title>. New York, NY: Simon and Schuster (Aladdin).</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="flinn2009" label="Flinn, Steven, and Shepherd 2009">Flinn, A., Stevens, M.
               AND Shepherd, E. (2009). <title rend="quotes">Whose memories, whose archives?
                  Independent community archives, autonomy and the mainstream</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">Archival science</title>. 9.12: 71-86. <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-009-9105-2"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1007/s10502-009-9105-2</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="friefeld2015" label="Friefeld et al., 2015">Friefeld, J. K., Thomas III,
               W. G., Jones, P. &amp; Class, T. U. O. N.-L. H. H. (2015). <title rend="italic">The
                  history harvest handbook</title>. University of Nebraska — Lincoln. <ref
                  target="https://historyharvest.net/?page_id=152"
                  >https://historyharvest.net/?page_id=152</ref></bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="fuentes2016" label="Fuentes 2016">Fuentes, M. J. (2016). <title
                  rend="italic">Dispossessed lives: Enslaved women, violence, and the
                  archive</title>. Philadelphia, PA: University of Pennsylvania Press.</bibl>
         	<bibl xml:id="gallon2016" label="Gallon 2016"> Gallon, Kim. <title rend="quotes">Making a Case for the Black Digital Humanities.</title> <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital Humanities</title> (2016): 42-49.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="gil2016" label="Gil and Ortega 2016">Gil, A. &amp; Ortega, É. (2016).
                  <title rend="quotes">Global outlooks in digital humanities: Multilingual practices
                  and minimal computing</title>. In C. Crompton, R. J. Lane, &amp; R. Siemens
               (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Doing digital humanities: Practice, training,
                  research.</title> New York, NY: Routledge.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hartman2006" label="Hartman 2006">Hartman, S. (2006). <title rend="italic"
                  >Lose your mother: A journey along the Atlantic slave route</title>. New York, NY:
               Macmillan.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hartman2008" label="Hartman 2008">Hartman, S. (2008). <title rend="quotes"
                  >Venus in two acts</title>. <title rend="italic">Small Axe: A Caribbean Journal of
                  Criticism</title>. 12: 1-14.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="hartman2019" label="Hartman 2019">Hartman, S. (2019). <title
                  rend="italic">Wayward lives, beautiful experiments: Intimate histories of riotous
                  Black girls, troublesome women, and queer radicals</title>. New York, NY: WW
               Norton &amp; Company.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="holden2021a" label="Holden 2021">Holden, V.M. (2021). <title rend="italic"
                  >Surviving Southampton: African American women and resistance in Nat Turner's
                  community</title>. Champaign, IL: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="holden2021b" label="Holden and Dunbar 2021">Holden, V. M. &amp; Dunbar, E.
               A. (2021). <title rend="quotes">Surviving Southampton Virtual Event: Vanessa M.
                  Holden in conversation with Erica Armstrong Dunbar</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >YouTube video</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2phoHE2iVo"
                  >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=G2phoHE2iVo</ref>. Accessed July 30, 2021.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="johnson2018" label="Johnson 2018">Johnson, Jessica Marie. (2018). <title
                  rend="quotes">Markup bodies</title>. <title rend="italic">Social Text</title>.
               36.4: 57–79. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1215/01642472-7145658</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="jules2018" label="Jules, Summers, and Mitchell 2018">Jules, B., Summers,
               E., &amp; Mitchell, V. (2018). <title rend="quotes">Ethical considerations for
                  archiving social media content generated by contemporary social movements:
                  Challenges, opportunities, and recommendations</title>
               <title rend="italic">Documenting the Now Whitepaper</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf"
                  >https://www.docnow.io/docs/docnow-whitepaper-2018.pdf</ref>. Accessed Aug 25,
               2021.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="longtown2020" label="LongtownHistory@gmail.com 2020"
               >LongtownHistory@gmail.com (2020). <title rend="quotes">Welcome to history harvest
                  item editing</title>. <title rend="italic">YouTube</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://youtu.be/aqMoGK50vt0">https://youtu.be/aqMoGK50vt0</ref>. Accessed
               July 5, 2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mason2019a" label="Mason 2019a">Mason, C. F. G. (2019). <title
                  rend="quotes">Collection of Cleo Fay Goens Mason</title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Remembering Freedom: Longtown and Greenville History Harvest</title>. Available:
                  <ref target="https://longtownhistory.github.io/descendants/mason.html"
                  >https://longtownhistory.github.io/descendants/mason.html</ref>. Accessed July 5,
               2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mason2019b" label="Mason 2019b">Mason, C. F. G. (2019). <title
                  rend="quotes">Interview with Cleo Fay Goens Mason </title>. <title rend="italic"
                  >Remembering Freedom: Longtown and Greenville History Harvest</title>. Available:
                  <ref target="https://longtownhistory.github.io/oralhistories/mason.html"
                  >https://longtownhistory.github.io/oralhistories/mason.html</ref>. Accessed Aug
               31, 2021.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mcpherson2012" label="McPherson 2012">McPherson, T. (2012). <title
                  rend="quotes">Why are the digital humanities so white? Or thinking the histories
                  of race and computation</title>. In M. K. Gold (Ed.), <title rend="italic">Debates
                  in the digital humanities.</title> Minneapolis, MN: University of Minnesota
               Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="mercer2019" label="Mercer and Moses 2019">Mercer, L. E. &amp; Moses, T.
               (2019). <title rend="quotes">Identifying racialized design to cultivate a culture of
                  awareness in design</title>. <title rend="italic">The Design Journal</title>. 22:
               1399-1407.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="miles2021" label="Miles 2021">Miles, T. (2021). <title rend="italic">All
                  that she carried: The journey of Ashley's sack, a Black family keepsake</title>.
               New York, NY: Penguin Random House.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="millward2015" label="Millward 2015">Millward, J. (2015). <title
                  rend="italic">Finding charity’s folk: Enslaved and free Black women in
                  Maryland</title>. Athens, GA: University of Georgia Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="myers2011" label="Myers 2011">Myers, A. C. (2011). <title rend="italic"
                  >Forging freedom: Black women and the pursuit of liberty in Antebellum
                  Charleston</title>. Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="perrin2019" label="Perrin and Anderson 2019">Perrin, A. &amp; Anderson, M.
               (2019). <title rend="quotes">Share of U.S. adults using social media, including
                  Facebook, is mostly unchanged since 2018</title>. <title rend="italic"> Pew
                  Research</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/04/10/share-of-u-s-adults-using-social-media-including-facebook-is-mostly-unchanged-since-2018/"
                  >https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2019/04/10/share-of-u-s-adults-using-social-media-including-facebook-is-mostly-unchanged-since-2018/</ref>.
               Accessed November 5, 2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="petersime2019" label="Petersime 2019">Petersime, S. (2019). <title
                  rend="italic">Only God can make a tree: Tracing my burden family
               roots</title>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="powell2018" label="Powell et al. 2018">Powell, C., Smith, H., Murrian, S,
               &amp; Hearn, S. (2018). <title rend="quotes">This [Black] woman’s work: Exploring
                  archival projects that embrace the identity of the memory worker</title>. <title
                  rend="italic">KULA: Knowledge Creation, Dissemination, and Preservation
                  Studies</title> 2.1: 5. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5334/kula.25"
                  >https://doi.org/10.5334/kula.25</ref>.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="rondo2017" label="Rondo Ave, Inc. and Macalester College 2016 and 2017"
               >Rondo Avenue, Inc. &amp; Macalester College (2016 &amp; 2017). <title rend="italic"
                  >Remembering Rondo | A History Harvest</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://omeka.macalester.edu/rondo/"
                  >https://omeka.macalester.edu/rondo/</ref>. Accessed November 1, 2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="roberts" label="Roberts">Roberts, A. <title rend="italic">The Texas
                  Freedom Colonies Project Atlas &amp; Study: Mapping the Unmapped Black Settlements
                  of Texas </title>. Available: <ref
                  target="http://www.thetexasfreedomcoloniesproject.com"
                  >http://www.thetexasfreedomcoloniesproject.com</ref>. Accessed July 5,
               2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="roberts2018" label="Roberts 2018">Roberts, A. (2018). <title rend="quotes"
                  >The Texas Freedom Colonies Atlas (BETA) Guidebook: Mapping the Unmapped Black
                  Settlements of Texas</title>. <title rend="italic">Texas A&amp;M University
                  College of Architecture, Center of Digital Humanities Research</title>. <ref
                  target="https://oaktrust.library.tamu.edu/bitstream/handle/1969.1/168567/The%20Texas%20Freedom%20Colonies%20Atlas%20%28BETA%29%20Guidebook_DRAFT.pdf?sequence=2"
                  >https://oaktrust.library.tamu.edu/bitstream/handle/1969.1/168567/The%20Texas%20Freedom%20Colonies%20Atlas%20%28BETA%29%20Guidebook_DRAFT.pdf?sequence=2</ref>.
               Access April 7, 2022.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="sal2019" label="sal@wowthemesnet 2019">sal@wowthemesnet (2019). <title
                  rend="italic">Mediumish Jekyll Theme</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://github.com/wowthemesnet/mediumish-theme-jekyll"
                  >https://github.com/wowthemesnet/mediumish-theme-jekyll</ref>. Accessed July 5,
               2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="southasian" label="South Asian American Digital Archive"><title
                  rend="italic">South Asian American Digital Archive</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://www.saada.org/">https://www.saada.org/</ref> [Accessed August 25,
               2021].</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="staff2015" label="Staff of the Dailey Advocate 2015)">Staff of the Dailey
               Advocate (2015). <title rend="quotes">Wright State student Connor Keiser works to
                  preserve historical black settlement of Longtown</title>. <title rend="italic">The
                  Daily Advocate</title>. Available: <ref
                  target="https://www.dailyadvocate.com/news/education/7764/wright-state-student-connor-keiser-works-to-preserve-historic-black-settlement-of-longtown"
                  >https://www.dailyadvocate.com/news/education/7764/wright-state-student-connor-keiser-works-to-preserve-historic-black-settlement-of-longtown</ref>.
               Accessed July 5, 2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="transgender" label="Transgender Archive"><title rend="quotes">Transgender
                  Archive</title>. <title rend="italic">University of Victoria</title>. Available:
                  <ref target="https://www.uvic.ca/transgenderarchives/"
                  >https://www.uvic.ca/transgenderarchives/</ref>. Accessed August 25, 2021.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="trouillot2015" label="Trouillot 2015">Trouillot, M-R. (2015). <title
                  rend="italic">Silencing the past: Power and the production of history</title>.
               Champaign, IL: University of Illinois Press.</bibl>


            <bibl xml:id="universityofnebraska"
               label="University of Nebraska at Lincoln History Department 2014">University of
               Nebraska at Lincoln History Department (2014). <title rend="italic">History
                  Harvest</title>. Available: <ref target="http://historyharvest.net/"
                  >http://historyharvest.net/</ref>. Accessed July 5, 2020.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="wingo2020" label="Wingo and Anderson 2020">Wingo, R. S. &amp; Anderson, M.
               R. (2020). <title rend="quotes">Harvesting History</title>. In R. S. Wingo, J. A.
               Heppler, &amp; P. Schadewald (Eds.), <title rend="italic">Digital Community
                  Engagement: Partnering Communities with the Academy.</title> Cincinnati, OH:
               University of Cincinnati Press.</bibl>

            <bibl xml:id="zavala2017" label="Zavala et al. 2017">Zavala, J., Migoni, A.A., Caswell,
               M., Geraci, N. &amp; Cifor, M. (2017). <title rend="quotes"><q>A process where we’re
                     all at the table</q>: community archives challenging dominant modes of archival
                  practice</title>. <title rend="italic">Archives and Manuscripts</title>. 45.3:
               202-215. <ref target="https://doi.org/10.1080/01576895.2017.1377088"
                  >https://doi.org/10.1080/01576895.2017.1377088</ref></bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
