<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title>Reconstructing a website’s lost past Methodological issues concerning the
                    history of Unibo.it</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Federico <dhq:family>Nanni</dhq:family></dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Mannheim</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>federico@informatik.uni-mannheim.de</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Federico Nanni is a final year PhD Student in Digital Humanities at the
                            University of Bologna, under the supervision of Maurizio Matteuzzi and
                            Simone Paolo Ponzetto. Since May 2016, he is also a researcher at the
                            Data and Web Science Group of the University of Mannheim, working with
                            Laura Dietz and Nikolay Marinov. Historian by training, Federico is
                            exploring the intersections between digital humanities, internet studies
                            and natural language processing.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000292</idno>
                <idno type="volume">011</idno>
                <idno type="issue">2</idno>
                <date when="2017-05-22">22 May 2017</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref></bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change when="2017-02-27" who="JDF">Proofread file</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>This paper describes how to deal with the scarcity of born-digital primary
                    sources while retrieving materials on the recent past of an academic
                    institution. The case study is an analysis of the first 25 years online of the
                    University of Bologna. The focus of this work is primarily methodological:
                    several different issues are presented, starting with the fact that the
                    University of Bologna website has been excluded for thirteen years from the
                    Internet Archive's Wayback Machine, and possible solutions are proposed and
                    applied. Moreover, this study aims at highlighting how web materials could give
                    us new and distinct insights into the recent past of academic institutions,
                    thereby becoming the starting point for several new studies.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <!-- Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence -->
                <p>How born digital documents could offer new insights on the recent history of the
                    University of Bologna</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <!-- Use <div> only if there is more than one section -->
            <div>
                <head>Introduction</head>
                <p>The University of Bologna is considered to be the world’s oldest university in
                    terms of continuous operation. Its nine-hundred year old roots can be traced
                    back to the figure of the early recorded scholar, jurist and instructor Irnerius
                        <ptr target="#capitani1987"/><note>Consider also how the university presents
                        itself on its website:<ref
                            target="http://www.unibo.it/en/university/who-we-are/our-history/university-from-12th-to-20th-century"
                            >http://www.unibo.it/en/university/who-we-are/our-history/university-from-12th-to-20th-century</ref></note>.
                    The study of specific aspects of the past of this institution has already
                    offered researchers the unique possibility of digging deeper into the
                    relationship between the university, its large student community and the city of
                    Bologna itself <ptr target="#brizzi1991"/>; <ptr target="#barbagli2009"/>.
                    Additionally, this kind of research has also allowed a better understanding of
                    its key historical role in the Italian academic <quote rend="inline"
                        source="#brizzi2007">ecosystem</quote>
                    <ptr target="#brizzi2007"/>. Several sources have been used to trace its past,
                    starting from textual documents preserved in the university archive <ptr
                        target="#rea1996"/>; <ptr target="#romano2007"/> to its collection of over
                    six hundred portraits <ptr target="#gandolfi2011"/>.</p>

                <p>Since the introduction of the World Wide Web, a new and different kind of primary
                    source has been available for historical research on the recent past of this
                    academic institution: born digital documents, materials that exist only online
                    and the role of which will increasingly be recognized as complementary to
                    traditional-analogue and digitized sources <ptr target="#brügger2016"/>.
                    However, due to their digital nature, these new sources are already more
                    difficult to preserve, retrieve and analyze compared to traditional materials
                        <ptr target="#rosenzweig2003"/>;<ptr target="#brügger2009"/>;<ptr
                        target="#lafrance2015"/>. For this reason, during the last twenty years,
                    public and private web archive initiatives all around the world have been
                    preserving them for future studies.</p>
                <p>Materials from the Internet Archive, the most important and comprehensive web
                    archive <ptr target="#gomes2011"/>, have already shown their potential as new
                    primary sources in a few pioneering studies <ptr target="#bendavid2016"/>;<ptr
                        target="#milligan2017"/>. Specifically talking about these new documents,
                    Ian Milligan has recently raised a very provocative question: <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#milligan2017">Could one even study the 1990s and
                        beyond without web archives?</quote><note>Milligan raised the question
                        during his talks, both at the 2015 meeting of the International Internet
                        Preservation Consortium and at the 2016 meeting of the American Historical
                        Association.</note>. Milligan, with this question, re-evokes an old teaching
                    from Marc Bloch, namely the fact that <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#bloch1949">everything that man says or writes,
                            everything that he makes, everything he touches can or ought to teach us
                            about him</quote>
                        <ptr target="#bloch1949"/>
                    </cit><note>Translation from: Bloch, M. The Historians’ Craft, Manchester Univ.
                        Press (1992).</note>. However, at the same time, Milligan’s question
                    addresses another, more methodological, aspect. Could one study the past, and
                    more precisely our <emph>recent digital past</emph>, without web archives?</p>

                <p>This study, which focuses on the recent past of the University of Bologna through
                    its digital sources, explores both aspects of Milligan’s question. It starts by
                    considering the facts that (a) the University of Bologna’s main website
                    (hereafter <title rend="quotes">Unibo.it</title>)<note>All the URLs mentioned in
                        this research have been most recently checked on the 14th of October
                        2016.</note> was not accessible through the Internet Archive’s Wayback
                    Machine when this research was conducted (as described in <ptr
                        target="#nanni2015"/>) and (b) Italy is one of the few countries in Western
                    Europe that does not systematically preserve its National web sphere <ptr
                        target="#gomes2011"/><note>Gomes, Miranda and Costa have curated a Wikipedia
                        page precisely on the topic: <ref
                            target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Web_archiving_initiatives"
                            >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Web_archiving_initiatives</ref></note>.
                    By doing so, the goal of this paper is to address the following research
                    questions:</p>

                <list>

                    <item>Is it possible to reconstruct and study the past of a university website
                        (namely the changes in its layout, structure and content, but more
                        importantly the reasons that have caused them) without having at prompt
                        disposal a collection of web archive snapshots?</item>

                    <item>Could this study guide us to better understand the role the website has
                        played in the interactions between the academic institution and its large
                        and variegated community and, by that, could we obtain new insights in the
                        recent past of the institution in itself?</item>

                    <item>Will this research bring new materials <emph>to the surface</emph>, in
                        ways that are useful for the research communities that, so far, have focused
                        on the past and present of academic institutions?</item>

                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Specific contribution</head>
                <p>Before starting, it is important to note a few aspects of the paper presented
                    here. First of all, this research does not set out to be a comprehensive
                    overview on the methodological approaches used in the diachronic study of
                    websites. On the contrary, the goal of this paper is to present a first-hand
                    experience on the issues that emerge when employing born digital materials as
                    primary sources and when considering websites as <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#brügger2009">objects of study</quote>
                        <ptr target="#brügger2009"/>
                    </cit>. Presenting the problems encountered while retrieving born digital
                    documents and the solutions adopted could be useful to other scholars who, in
                    the near future, intend to use the same materials in their research.
                    Additionally, while the focus of our first research question is primarily
                    methodological (more explicitly: how a website’s lost past was reconstructed),
                    this study does not intend to be limited to what Blevins recently defined the <cit>
                        <quote rend="inline" source="#blevins2015">perpetual sunrise of
                            methodology</quote>
                        <ptr target="#blevins2015"/>
                    </cit>
                    <ptr target="#blevins2016"/>, which in his vision is the main characteristic of
                    current digital history. In fact, the other two research questions emphasize how
                    web materials could give us new and distinct insights into the recent past of
                    academic institutions, thereby becoming the starting point for several new
                    studies.</p>

                <p>This paper is organized in five parts. First, a series of works on web archives
                    and their use in humanities research, together with an overview on the research
                    fields that study the recent past of academic institutions, are presented. Next,
                    the types of sources employed in this work and their reliability are described
                    and discussed. The reconstruction of the web past of the University of Bologna
                    occupies the central part of the paper. Given the peculiarity of the exclusion
                    issue that happened in the case of Unibo.it, the work which was conducted
                    together with the Internet Archive to understand and solve the exclusion of
                    Unibo.it from the Wayback Machine is then described. Finally, a new type of
                    primary source that was collected during the research is presented, highlighting
                    its usefulness for the communities that study academic institutions.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Related Work</head>
                <p>The study presented in this paper places itself at the intersection of three
                    different research fields. First, it discusses the consequences of the ways we
                    preserve (or not preserve – as in the case of Italy) the web of the past.
                    Second, it considers how web archival materials could be adopted in historical
                    research. Finally, it highlights the impact that these sources will have on
                    different research areas that focus on examining the recent past of academic
                    institutions. In the next pages, a general overview of these research areas by
                    presenting a series of related works will be offered.</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Preserving the web of the past</head>
                    <p>In 1989 Tim Berners-Lee introduced his project at CERN, which later was
                        identified as the <title rend="quotes">World Wide Web</title>. In 1991 he
                        created the first website, <ref target="http://info.cern.ch/"
                            >http://info.cern.ch/</ref>, and in the same year he publicly announced
                        it in the Usenet newsgroup <title rend="quotes">alt.hypertext</title>. The
                        World Wide Web, after a slow start <ptr target="#frana2004"/>, rapidly
                        reached more than 16 million users<note><ref
                                target="http://www.internetworldstats.com/emarketing.htm"
                                >http://www.internetworldstats.com/emarketing.htm</ref></note>, who
                        were, already in 1995, the creators of a great amount of born digital
                        traces. However, the first project that focused on the preservation of this
                        new kind of information started only at the end of 1996 under the leadership
                        of Brewster Kahle. His utopian purpose was to archive the web in its
                        entirety <ptr target="#kahle1997"/>. The project he presented under the name
                        of <title rend="quotes">Internet Archive</title> has become, during the last
                        two decades, a fundamental archival resource for the preservation of our
                        digital past. Its crawlers started acquiring and preserving snapshots of web
                        pages in November 1996, performing an ever-increasing uphill climb with the
                        never-ending growth and continuous change of the web. In 2001, the Internet
                        Archive introduced the Wayback Machine, the platform that permits the
                        displaying and browsing (through a URL search tool) of the results of the
                        crawl.</p>

                    <p>During the last twenty years, several other platforms, often inspired by the
                        ideas behind the Internet Archive but with a more specific national focus,
                        have been developed, such as Pandora in Australia (1996), the UK Web Archive
                        (2004), Netarkivet in Denmark (2005) and the Portuguese Web Archive (2007).
                        Moreover, in 2003, the Internet International Preservation Consortium (IIPC)
                        was founded at the National Library of France<note><ref
                                target="http://netpreserve.org/about-us"
                                >http://netpreserve.org/about-us</ref></note> which, during the last
                        decade, has coordinated national and international efforts to preserve
                        Internet contents for the future. Today, with a General Assembly meeting
                        every year since 2011 and organizations joining from 25 different countries,
                        the IIPC has become the leading guide of these born-digital preservation
                        projects.</p>

                    <div>
                        <head>The past of the Italian web sphere</head>
                        <p>Currently the national libraries of Florence and Rome are not a part of
                            the IIPC and no project with the specific purpose of preserving the
                            Italian web-sphere exists. In 2006, thanks to the effort of the project
                                <title rend="quotes">Crawler</title>
                            <ptr target="#bergamin2006"/>;<ptr target="#tammaro2006"/>, which was
                            supported by the <title rend="quotes">Biblioteca Digitale
                                Italiana</title> (Italian Digital Library), Italy cooperated with
                            the European Archive Foundation (now called <title rend="quotes"
                                >Internet Memory Foundation</title>) and conducted its first
                            wide-spread crawling of the <q>.it</q> domain<note>This was conducted
                                between May and June 2006, the snapshots are available here: <ref
                                    target="http://collection.europarchive.org/bncf/"
                                    >http://collection.europarchive.org/bncf/</ref></note>. However,
                            no other project has been developed following this and the only part of
                            its national web-sphere which has been constantly crawled and preserved
                            are the PhD theses repositories of Italian universities, thanks to the
                            activities of the <title rend="quotes">Magazzini Digitali</title>
                                    project.<note><ref target="http://www.depositolegale.it/"
                                    >http://www.depositolegale.it/</ref></note></p>

                        <p>For these reasons, researchers interested in diachronically studying the
                            Italian web sphere can currently rely only on the snapshots of websites
                            preserved on the Internet Archive<note>Or, as it will be described
                                later, in some specific cases on snapshots archived in other
                                national web archives.</note>. However, as Unibo.it was excluded
                            from the Wayback Machine, this issue threatened to leave no trace of the
                            web past of this academic institution.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Studying the web of the past</head>
                    <p>There are two different ways of considering web archive materials as primary
                        sources in historical studies. The first, described for example by Brügger
                            <ptr target="#brügger2012a"/>, has its roots in the fields of media and
                        Internet studies and aims at examining the web of the past by
                        contextualizing and understanding changes in layout, structure, content and
                        use. In 2010, Brügger edited the first book on the topic, and the title of
                        the volume, <title rend="italic">Web History</title>, clearly highlighted
                        the research topic of the community <ptr target="#brügger2010"/>. A similar
                        focus emerges upon reading the objectives of a new journal titled <title
                            rend="italic">Internet Histories</title>, recently launched by Niels
                        Brügger and others.<note><ref target="http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/rint20"
                                >http://www.tandfonline.com/loi/rint20</ref></note></p>

                    <p>The second way of considering these materials as primary sources has,
                        instead, a wider spectrum of applications. As already remarked by Roy
                        Rosenzweig <ptr target="#rosenzweig2003"/>, born digital materials (with
                        their <emph>scarcity</emph> and <emph>abundance</emph>) will have an impact
                        on the entire historical profession; for this reason, web archive materials
                        could soon become new sources for political as well as social, cultural and
                        economic historians. Recent works, such as the studies conducted by Anat Ben
                        David <ptr target="#bendavid2016"/> and Sophie Gebeil <ptr
                            target="#gebeil2016"/> already show how topics such as the Yugoslav
                        conflict and North African immigration in France could be studied fruitfully
                        from a web archive perspective.</p>

                    <p>In both areas, researchers have explored the potential of computational
                        methods, such as text mining and network analyses, for extracting
                        information from large web archive collections. Examples are presented in
                        Milligan <ptr target="#milligan2012"/>, <ptr target="#milligan2017"/>, Hale
                        et al. <ptr target="#hale2014"/> and Holzmannet al. <ptr
                            target="#holzmann2016"/>.</p>

                    <div>
                        <head>Reliability of Web Archives and Sources</head>
                        <p>A substantial number of articles focused on the reliability of web
                            archives and web archival sources have been published in the last years.
                            Howell <ptr target="#howell2006"/> analyzed how to use the Internet
                            Archive in research and Murphy et al. <ptr target="#murphy2007"/>
                            established the Wayback Machine as a valid tool for identifying, among
                            other information, web page contents, <q>website age</q> and updates.
                            However, Brügger <ptr target="#brügger2008"/> highlighted a series of
                            problems in web preservation and underlined the need of what he called a
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#brügger2008">web-philology</quote>
                            to deal with the reconstruction of partially archived websites. More
                            recently he also defined the resources preserved in web archives as <cit>
                                <quote rend="inline" source="#brügger2012b">reborn digital
                                    materials</quote>
                                <ptr target="#brügger2012b"/>
                            </cit>, which must be considered as different objects compared to the
                            originals. Along the same lines, Dougherty et al. <ptr
                                target="#dougherty2010"/> summarized the state of the art of web
                            archiving in relation to researchers needs. Ankerson <ptr
                                target="#ankerson2012"/> remarked that web historians need to <quote
                                rend="inline" source="#ankerson2012">consider broadcast[ing]
                                historiography scholarship that grapples with questions of power,
                                preservation, and the unique challenges of ephemeral media</quote>.
                            Finally Huurdeman and Ben David <ptr target="#huurdeman2014a"/> explored
                            how to go beyond current limitations of search tools in web archives
                            and, with Kamps, Samar and de Vries <ptr target="#huurdeman2014b"/>,
                            employed a new approach to analyze hyperlinks in web archives in order
                            to deal with the reconstruction of the unarchived web.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <div>
                    <head>Past and Present of Academic Institutions</head>
                    <p>While higher education has been a fundamental component of every advanced
                        civilization, only in medieval Europe arose a new type of public institution
                        of learning, which is now defined as <q>university</q>
                        <ptr target="#perkin2007"/>. Considering this type of institution as a
                        political, economic and social actor initially has attracted the interest of
                        historians, who wanted to understand how its power, role and influence
                        changed over time, especially in relation to other actors, such as the city,
                        the church, the national government (e.g. <ptr target="#bowosky1973"/>;<ptr
                            target="#clark1976"/>). The massive four-volume book series <title
                            rend="italic">A History of the Universities in Europe</title>,
                        commissioned by the European University Association, edited by Hilde de
                        Ridder-Symoens and Walter Rüegg and published between 1992 and 2011, offers
                        an unprecedented comprehensive overview of how universities have changed
                        what they have taught and researched, how they have been institutionalized
                        and how they have interacted with the society. In these studies, researchers
                        adopt a large variety of primary and secondary sources, from
                        university-archived materials such as matriculation and graduation
                        statistics <ptr target="#brockliss1978"/>;<ptr target="#macleod1978"/> to
                        scientific publications <ptr target="#richardson1999"/>, from public reports
                            <ptr target="#dewied1991"/> to the results of large-scale statistical
                        analyses <ptr target="#finkenstaedt2011"/>. Based on these data, scholars
                        have described and drawn conclusions on the recent history of universities
                        on a large variety of topics, such as the way universities have managed
                        resources, the way the admission processes have changed before and after
                        1970, and how the major branches of knowledge have been taught and
                        studied.</p>

                    <p>While universities have been largely examined as institutions that change and
                        evolve in relation to each other and are conditioned by (while also
                        conditioning) political and economic powers, they are also the physical
                        place where scientists and humanities scholars conduct their work. For this
                        reason, academic institutions have also been examined by historians of
                        science and technology, interested in understanding how STEM (Science,
                        Technology, Engineering and Mathematics) have been taught and studied in
                        universities <ptr target="#fox1993"/>, how scientific knowledge has moved
                        back and forth between universities and the private sector <ptr
                            target="#mahoney1988"/>;<ptr target="#guagnini1988"/>, how political,
                        economic and social actors have influenced scientific research in academia
                            <ptr target="#pancaldi2006"/> and how scientists work in their
                        laboratories <ptr target="#worboys2011"/>.</p>

                    <p>Another perspective on universities and their recent past is offered through
                        the scientometrics discipline, whose goal is to measure and analyze the
                        impact of publications, journals and institutes, and to produce indicators
                        that would be adopted in policy and management contexts. The use of metrics
                        such as citation and co-citation measures <ptr target="#vanraan1997"/> has
                        attracted a lot of attention from university administrations, politicians,
                        sociologists and quantitative historians (for further discussion, see <ptr
                            target="#debellis2009"/>); additionally, the quantification of the
                        scientific output as a measure of evaluating and comparing academic
                        institutions has had a huge impact on their recent past, influencing hiring
                        strategies as well as the pursuit of certain research topics and practices.
                        In addition to bibliometric measures, more recently, a series of
                        publications has focused on the use of word-based and topic-based approaches
                        in order to conduct scientometrics studies (see <ptr target="#lu2012"/>).
                        These contributions have expanded the type of materials that could be
                        analyzed (e.g. not just research papers, but also the content of grant
                        proposal or awards as in <ptr target="#nichols2014"/>), the methods at
                        disposal of the research community and the points of view that can be
                        employed.</p>


                    <div>
                        <head>Studying the Past of the University of Bologna</head>
                        <p>The University of Bologna currently has two centers specifically
                            dedicated to the history of academic institutions, namely the <title
                                rend="quotes">Centre for the History of Universities and
                                Science</title> (CIS) and the <title rend="quotes">Interuniversity
                                Centre for the History of Italian Universities</title> (CISUI).
                            These research groups continue the tradition of the oldest center in
                            Italy for the history of universities, the <title rend="quotes">Centre
                                for the History of the University of Bologna</title>, founded in
                            1906.</p>

                        <p>CIS was initiated in 1991 at the Department of Philosophy, as a direct
                            consequence of the IX Century anniversary of the Alma Mater <ptr
                                target="#pancaldi1993"/>. Originally, CIS was a small research group
                            with a focus on the history of science and universities. The first
                            volume published, <title rend="italic">Universities and the Sciences:
                                Historical and Contemporary Perspectives</title> (Pancaldi,
                                <emph>ibidem</emph>), clearly highlights the goal of the group to
                            build a bridge between the history of universities and the history of
                            science. Among the board of directors was Gian Paolo Brizzi, a professor
                            of modern history with a strong research focus on the history of Italian
                            universities.</p>

                        <p>After a few years, Brizzi started a second research center completely
                            dedicated to the history of Italian universities, this time at the
                            Department of History and in collaboration with other institutions such
                            as the universities of Padova, Messina, Sassari and Torino <ptr
                                target="#pomante2010"/>. In the two following decades CISUI and CIS
                            differentiated their research topics, with the first becoming a
                            coordination structure in Italy for the study of Italian academic
                            institutions (see for example <ptr target="#negrini1998"/>;<ptr
                                target="#dröscher2002"/>) and the second moving increasingly towards
                            the history of science, technology and the STS. However, a few doctoral
                            students at CIS have continued to examine the recent history of
                            universities and their interactions with political, economic and social
                            actors (see for example <ptr target="#serafini2011"/>;<ptr
                                target="#parolini2013"/>;<ptr target="#piazza2013"/>.</p>

                        <p>This paper is also part of an ongoing PhD research project conducted at
                            CIS, with a focus on adopting born digital materials as primary sources
                            for studying the past of academic institutions. In particular, the
                            specific goal of this work is to highlight new challenges that born
                            digital sources present, to describe the way in which they have been
                            dealt with and emphasize how the retrieved materials could be useful to
                            the different communities that are studying the past and present of
                            academic institutions.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Setting up the research</head>
                <p>In this study, different types of primary sources have been adopted, offering an
                    overview of the role of the website for the university and its community. As a
                    first step, information related to the website was collected from the university
                    yearbooks and through the analysis of the university’s archived records. This
                    provided an initial understanding of the administrative role of the website
                    (through a top-down view) and indicated the people involved in its supervision.
                    As a second step, interviews were conducted with those who have been managing
                    Unibo.it during the last two decades. This helped, especially, in discovering
                    the motivations behind specific changes and to trace down who, in the early 90s,
                    created the website and for what reasons. The analysis was then consolidated by
                    employing information retrieved from local and national newspaper archives, such
                    as <title rend="italic">La Repubblica</title> and <title rend="italic">Il Resto
                        del Carlino</title>, student forums and Usenet discussion groups. These
                    materials facilitated a better understanding of the role that the website has
                    played over the years as a <q>bridge</q> between the institution and its
                    community.</p>

                <p>The last step of the study aimed at restoring access to the previous versions of
                    the website. In order to do so, information currently available on the live web
                    was collected and its availability in foreign web archives was explored. The
                    combination of these sources offers a comprehensive perspective on the changes
                    of the website and the political (e.g. school reforms) and educational reasons
                    behind specific choices and decisions.</p>


                <div>
                    <head>Critically Assessing Sources</head>
                    <div>
                        <head>Library and archive materials.</head>
                        <p>In this study different materials from the university library and
                            archives have been used as primary resources. One that has been very
                            useful in different steps of our work is the university yearbook. The
                            yearbook offers a general overview of the main activities of the
                            university during the year, highlighting its management and indicating
                            innovative decisions as well as presenting several statistics. Professor
                            Fausto Desalvo has been in charge of the publication of the yearbook
                            since the early 90s. The yearbooks are accessible online (first edition
                            available: 1994/95<note><ref target="http://www.unibo.it/annuari/"
                                    >http://www.unibo.it/annuari/</ref></note>) and at the library
                            of the Department of History.</p>

                        <p>Even if, especially during the 90s, only a few pieces of information
                            regarding the website would be mentioned in the yearbook, this source
                            has nevertheless been an essential starting point for obtaining a
                            diachronic overview of the official teams that were managing Unibo.it.
                            When the different teams were contacted, the goal was to conduct
                            interviews and to collect materials related to the website, such as
                            archived documents as well as backups.</p>

                        <p>The website has been managed by four different teams in the last twenty
                            years. However, especially during the 90s, large parts of the website
                            were directly modified by single departments and research groups. Very
                            little analogue archival information has been preserved by the teams and
                            researchers that have worked on the website and its sub-sections. Even
                            more importantly, not even a single backup of the old versions of the
                            website has been preserved. However, this initial research helped in
                            identifying the key people to interview.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Interviews.</head>
                        <p>Given the ephemerality of born digital materials and the general lack of
                            their preservation by the teams that worked on the website, oral
                            memories have played a key role in this research. These direct sources
                            have been helpful for capturing the rationale behind the changing
                            architecture of the website<note>At the 2015 International Internet
                                Preservation Consortium General Meeting (IIPC2015), the importance
                                of oral memories for web historical research has been emphasized
                                both by Ahmed AlSum and by the author of this paper in two
                                consequential presentations: <ref
                                    target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AHrxvRWf9OM"
                                    >https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AHrxvRWf9OM</ref>.</note>. For
                            this work, the different teams who managed the main website were
                            interviewed, together with technicians and researchers who worked on the
                            development of the pages of various departments in the past two
                            decades.</p>

                        <p>So much has been already written about the reliability and the criticism
                            of oral memories (see for example <ptr target="#hoffmann1994"/>). In
                            this research – especially given the fact that primary materials (e.g.
                            backups of the website) were not at our prompt disposal – assessing the
                            validity of the collected pieces of information has not always been an
                            easy task. Therefore I proceeded by comparing the outputs of different
                            interviews and, when possible, validated them by using other sources,
                            such as newspaper articles. It is important to remark here that public
                            and private backups of emails have often been used by the interviewees
                            in order to recollect memories of their experience in working on
                            Unibo.it and to confirm passages of the historical reconstruction. While
                            email backups are <quote rend="inline" source="#cohen2006">waiting
                                to become</quote> a new primary source for historians<note>Dan Cohen
                                    <ptr target="#cohen2006"/> discussed it when considering the
                                large abundance of sources that public administration will leave us
                                in the next decades.</note>, the social and ethical implications of
                            collecting, consulting and sharing their contents to sustain an argument
                            still must be fully discussed.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Newspapers and forums.</head>
                        <p>Another way of finding information related to previous versions of
                            Unibo.it and its role for the University of Bologna is to search
                            newspaper archives and retrieve articles that mention or describe it.
                            The practice of using printed media to retrieve information about the
                            web of the past has been already described, for instance in Brügger <ptr
                                target="#brügger2011"/>. In this research the digital archive of the
                            newspaper <title rend="quotes">La Stampa</title><note><ref
                                    target="http://www.archiviolastampa.it"
                                    >http://www.archiviolastampa.it/</ref></note> was used in order
                            to retrieve specific articles published between 1996 and 1999 that
                            described the general use of the web by Italian universities<note>E.g.
                                the article <title rend="quotes">Anche l'università via
                                    Internet</title>, written by Giovanna Favro and published the
                                14th of May 1998.</note>. A great role in this study has been played
                            by local and national newspapers (such as the digital archives of <title
                                rend="italic">La Repubblica</title> and <title rend="italic">Il
                                Resto del Carlino</title>), which especially during the 90s offered
                            an overview on the new functionalities on the website (e.g. free email
                            account for all students, online fee payments, etc.), together with
                            university digital magazines (<title rend="italic">Alma2000</title>,
                                <title rend="italic">AlmaNews</title>, <title rend="italic">Unibo
                                Magazine</title>). However, it is important to employ news articles
                            critically and always consider how and why a specific piece of
                            information regarding the website was selected and published in the
                            daily edition of a general newspaper<note>For example this short article
                                on the possibility of creating university email accounts in 2002:
                                    <ref
                                    target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2002/10/09/mail-gratuita-per-gli-studenti.html?ref=search"
                                    >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2002/10/09/mail-gratuita-per-gli-studenti.html?ref=search</ref></note>.</p>

                        <p>Other sources that have been employed in this study include student
                            forums (e.g. UniversiBo) and, to go further back in time, Usenet
                            discussions preserved by Google. While academic forums offer new
                            materials for historians of universities interested in better
                            understanding student life, they also present the perspective of a very
                            small and specific subset of the academic community. In particular, in
                            the early 90s,these online forums were mainly kept running by students
                            (together with researchers and professors) in STEM fields, whose
                            departments were often the first to offer access to the web.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Live web materials.</head>
                        <p>While the previous versions of Unibo.it were not available through the
                            Wayback Machine when this research was conducted, at the same time the
                            website has always been online, offering to the user a variety of
                            primary sources. Live web materials reveal the current role of website
                            in the university's organization and management (e.g. attracting
                            national and international students and researchers, promoting
                            collaborations with the private sector, etc). Additionally, by combining
                            documents from the website and from social media pages of the
                            institution (such as Facebook, Youtube and Twitter profiles), we can
                            make reasonable assumptions about the digital interactions with the
                            larger community. While materials from social networking websites will
                            play a fundamental role in better understanding the multidirectional
                            communication between academic institutions and their community, it is
                            important to remember that their suitability for historical analysis is
                            currently under scrutiny, as several issues have been raised <ptr
                                target="#webster2015"/>; <ptr target="#zimmer2015"/>.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <head>Web archive materials.</head>
                        <p>Even if the University of Bologna homepage and all its subsections were
                            not accessible through the Wayback Machine, its sub-domains were
                            available on the Internet Archive and have been constantly preserved in
                            the last twenty years (i.e. <title rend="italic">Unibo
                                    Magazine</title><note><ref
                                    target="https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://magazine.unibo.it"
                                    >https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://magazine.unibo.it</ref></note>)<note>The
                                reasons will be discussed in the final section of this
                            paper.</note>.In addition, sources pertaining to Unibo.it were retrieved
                            from other national web archives. The practice of retrieving primary
                            sources related to an Italian university website in foreign web archives
                            could sound strange as the goal of a national web archive is precisely
                            to preserve the web of its country. However, as this preservation
                            process is highly complex (as described by <ptr target="#brügger2009"
                            />), from time to time part of the non-national web will also end up
                            being unintentionally preserved. For example, to archive national web
                            spheres in an automatic way, archivists could set up crawlers with a
                            maximum number of hyperlinks they can follow, with a specific set of
                            starting points. A crawler which is set to go at most 10 links away from
                            one of these URLs could also end up crawling non-national content, as it
                            will systematically follow all the hyperlinks. For this reason, if the
                            University of Bologna were to organize a Summer School and the
                            University of Amsterdam had linked it from its website, the University
                            of Bologna website (or at least part of it) would be unintentionally
                            preserved in the Netherlands Web Archive.</p>

                        <p>The critical combination of the sources presented above provided the
                            possibility of reconstructing the changing in Unibo.it structure,
                            emphasizing the different roles that the institution assigned to its
                            website during the years and the way the student community interact with
                            the website so as to establish a dialogue with the university.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Unibo.it : 2015 – 2002, retracing steps</head>
                <p>The narrative below follows the path in rediscovering the past of the University
                    of Bologna website. This first part will take us back in time, starting from
                    what is available now on the live web to a significant change in the content and
                    structure of the website, which implied the removal of the majority of the
                    materials published online during the 90s.</p>

                <div>
                    <head>The website as it is structured today</head>
                    <p>The website of the University of Bologna is currently offered in two
                        different linguistic versions: an Italian (which is available at the URL:
                            <ref target="http://www.unibo.it/it">http://www.unibo.it/it</ref>), and
                        an English one. Moreover, as the university has five campuses, the website
                        is consequently divided into five subsections (for example, <ref
                            target="http://www.unibo.it/it/campus-forli"
                            >http://www.unibo.it/it/campus-forli</ref>). As the English version
                        offers the translation of only a part of the website, the focus of this
                        research will be mainly on the Italian version.</p>

                    <!--Figure 1. Unibo.it homepage in 2016.-->


                    <figure>
                        <head>Unibo.it homepage in 2016.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>This website (see Figure 1) is currently managed by two different offices:
                            <title rend="quotes">CeSIA - SettoreTecnologie web</title> that takes
                        care of the structure (called <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale di
                            Ateneo</title>), and <title rend="quotes">AAGG — UfficioPortale Internet
                            e Intranet di Ateneo</title><note><ref
                                target="http://www.unibo.it/it/ateneo/organizzazione/amministrazione-generale/81380/817/index.html"
                                >http://www.unibo.it/it/ateneo/organizzazione/amministrazione-generale/81380/817/index.html</ref></note>
                        that manages the content. If we consider its subsections, such as <title
                            rend="quotes">Didattica</title> (educational information) and <title
                            rend="quotes">Ricerca</title> (research), its sub-domains, such as the
                            <title rend="quotes">Unibo Magazine</title>, and retrieve current and
                        old abandoned department web pages<note><ref
                                target="http://www2.stat.unibo.it/"
                            >http://www2.stat.unibo.it/</ref>; <ref
                                target="http://www2.stat.unibo.it/"
                                >http://www2.classics.unibo.it/</ref></note>, we can obtain an
                        initial overview of the current status and structure of the website. This
                        allows us to notice that large pieces of information published online by the
                        university between the early 2000s and 2015 are still available online (for
                        example all the course programs, the descriptions of research projects and
                        the contracts and grants published by each School). However, in order to
                        retrieve them, a very basic <q>string-matching</q> search tool<note><ref
                                target="http://search.unibo.it/UniboWeb/UniboSearch/Default.aspx"
                                >http://search.unibo.it/UniboWeb/UniboSearch/Default.aspx</ref></note>
                        is the only tool promptly available.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The moment of transformation</head>
                    <p>To understand why most of the materials from the early 2000s is still
                        available online, while resources from the 90s seem way more difficult to
                        retrieve, I contacted the people who have been involved with the management
                        of the website during the last fifteen years.</p>

                    <p>Luca Garlaschelli was the Chief of the Information/Innovation Office (CIO) at
                        the University of Bologna between 2002 and 2012. Under his supervision the
                            <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale di Ateneo</title> was created. This
                        is a general interface to a hierarchical organization of all the digital
                        resources of the university that are available online, with a specific focus
                        on enhancing the accessibility of the information at disposal<note>As
                            underlined by Garlaschelli: <ref
                                target="http://www.osservatoriosullacomunicazione.com/mezzi/internet/prontoweb/interviste/garlaschelli.php"
                                >http://www.osservatoriosullacomunicazione.com/mezzi/internet/prontoweb/interviste/garlaschelli.php</ref>.
                            And also presented in the <title rend="quotes">Annuario degli anni
                                accademici 2003-2004 e 2004-2005</title>, pp. 777-780</note>. As it
                        will be presented in the next pages, this has led to a revolutionary
                        transformation of the digital presence of the institution, which made
                        Unibo.it a reference point for all other Italian university websites. As a
                        matter of fact, for three consecutive years Unibo.it received the <title
                            rend="quotes">Osc@r del web</title> prize as the best Italian public
                        administration website<note><ref
                                target="http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2007/oscar_del_2007"
                                >http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2007/oscar_del_2007</ref>. In
                            2007 Luigi Nicolais, the Italian Minister of Public Administration, was
                            also present to confer this honor.</note>.</p>

                    <p>Among several improvements of the website, this transformation required that
                        all departments and web pages which provided information on the various
                        degree programs change their structure and adopt a common layout and
                        organization of their content. As an example, the Department of Classic and
                        Medieval Philology and the Department of Computer Science had to change
                        their URL addresses to standardized ones (<q>abbreviation of the name of the
                            department</q> + <q>unibo.it</q>). Thus, the first one changed from:
                        http://www.classics.unibo.it/ to http://www.ficlit.unibo.it/ and the second
                        one from http://www.cs.unibo.it/ to http://www.informatica.unibo.it/. This
                        transition started in 2004 and often required the creation of completely new
                        department pages. A few departments decided to keep the older version of
                        their sub-domains online by adding a <q>2</q> after the <q>www</q><note>This
                            could be due to a personal choice of the person who was managing each
                            department page at that time and not to a decision of the CIO. On the
                            Department of Classic and Medieval Philology homepage it is explicitly
                            written that <quote rend="inline" source="#undocumented">the pages will continue to
                                be available, but will be no longer updated</quote>.</note> (as an
                        example, the previously mentioned <ref
                            target="http://www2.classics.unibo.it/"
                            >http://www2.classics.unibo.it/</ref>), while the majority simply
                        removed the old versions of their page from the live web, for example the
                        Department of History, whose URL was: http://www.dds.unibo.it/.</p>

                    <p>As previously described, it is still possible to retrieve a sub-domain of the
                        University of Bologna website (such as a department page) on the Internet
                        Archive, but only if the original URL is known, which is not a trivial issue
                        (as described in <ptr target="#nanni2015"/>;<ptr target="#bendavid2016"/>).
                        For example, the Department of Philosophy and Communication Studies were two
                        different departments until 2012 and the Department of Philosophy used
                        http://www.filosofia.unibo.it as a URL even before the transition to the
                            <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale d’Ateneo</title>. However, in the
                        90s, this department used another URL for a couple of years,
                        http://www.sofia.philo.unibo.it which, without the memories of the people
                        who managed the sub-section at that time, would have been be very difficult
                        to discover.</p>

                    <p>In summary, we can identify a specific turning point in the history of the
                        University of Bologna website. With the <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale
                            d’Ateneo</title> project and in particular with the standardization of
                        departments pages which started in 2004<note><ref
                                target="http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2004/dipartimenti"
                                >http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2004/dipartimenti</ref></note>,
                        the website has been completely re-organized and the majority of the
                        previous content on these pages has been deleted from the live web. However,
                        if they have maintained the same URL or if the previous URL is known<note>A
                            web page archived in 2002 could help us identify the URL of each
                            department in that year: <ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/20020224030346/http://alma2000.unibo.it/facolta/dipE.asp"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/20020224030346/http://alma2000.unibo.it/facolta/dipE.asp</ref></note>,
                        the subdomain materials and their structure can be retrieved from the
                        Internet Archive.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Exploring the <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale</title></head>
                    <p>Mauro Amico, head of the web-technologies department at CeSIA, offered a
                        collection of seven .png images (see Appendix) that capture the most
                        important instances in the evolution of the organization of the homepage
                        before the current layout (1996 – 2013)<note>They cover the periods:
                            01/1996-01/1998; 01/1998 – 09/1998; 09/1998-07/1999; 2002-2003;
                            2004-2206; 2006-2009; 2009-2013.</note>. This was important as a
                        starting point for understanding how the website structure and layout
                        changed during the years. Looking at the snapshots after 2002 we can observe
                        that, even if a few graphical adjustments were made (the Unibo-Magazine was
                        introduced on the left in 2004; the search tool was repositioned in the
                        center in 2006, etc.), the structure remained more or less the same until
                        the July 2013, when the current interface was presented. The present
                        organization of the <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale d’Ateneo</title> is
                        the first one to be completely created by CeSIA without the supervision of
                        Luca Garlaschelli and, along with a new graphic interface, its main
                        characteristic is the fact that it offers for the first time the possibility
                        of surfing the website as a specific user (a prospective student, a student,
                        a private company, etc.) and it proposes different contents accordingly,
                        thereby allowing better optimization and personalization of the website.</p>

                    <p>Even if these .png images give us a first idea of the different interfaces,
                        to be able to explore again the old versions of the website, other services
                        have to be employed. As a start, the Internet Memory Foundation offers the
                        results of the 2006 national <q>.it</q> crawl online, but only a single
                        snapshot of Unibo.it homepage is available (archived on the 8th of May
                                2006<note><ref
                                target="http://collection.europarchive.org/bncf/20060508021404/http://www.unibo.it/Portale/default.htm"
                                >http://collection.europarchive.org/bncf/20060508021404/http://www.unibo.it/Portale/default.htm</ref></note>)
                        and that is not even completely preserved. As previously noted, other
                        national web archives could have captured, from time to time, parts of the
                        Italian web sphere. Among them, it was discovered that both the Portuguese
                        (Arquivo) and Danish (Netarkivet) web archives have preserved parts of
                        Unibo.it several times from 2006. These snapshots (example in Figure 2)
                        permit us, for the first time, to explore and examine the differences in
                        structure and content of the previous versions of the <title rend="quotes"
                            >Sistema Portale</title>.</p>

                    <!--Figure 2. Unibo.it (2009) in a snapshot from Netarkivet.-->

                    <figure>
                        <head>Unibo.it (2009) in a snapshot from Netarkivet.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>
                    </figure>

                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>News from its recent past</head>
                    <p>The use of primary sources from the digital archive of the newspaper <title
                            rend="italic">La Repubblica</title> has been of significant help in this
                        study. As a matter of fact, these articles present an overview of the
                        interactions between the university and its community, as well as insights
                        on the key role of the website as an intermediary. It has been found, for
                        example, that in 2003 the university introduced, on its website, the digital
                        edition of the student-guide of the city of Bologna, as also described in a
                        news in the <title rend="italic">Unibo Magazine</title><note><ref
                                target="http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2003/09/22/guida-di-bologna"
                                >http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2003/09/22/guida-di-bologna</ref></note>.
                        The guide was written by Umberto Eco, Carlo Lucarelli and other renowned
                        professors and writers. This document provides a list of useful digital
                        resources for new students, i.e. the platform <title rend="quotes">Flash
                            Giovani</title>, created with the support of the municipality of Bologna
                        and focused on the cultural activities in the city and the website <title
                            rend="quotes">Studenti.it</title> which has, in the last fifteen years,
                        become one the most important Italian online communities for high school and
                        university students<note>Currently it is one of the 200 most visited
                            websites in Italy: <ref
                                target="http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/studenti.it#trafficstats"
                                >http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/studenti.it#trafficstats</ref></note>.</p>

                    <p>As described in the <title rend="italic">Unibo Magazine</title><note><ref
                                target="http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2004/pagina-personale-docente/"
                                >http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2004/pagina-personale-docente/</ref></note>,
                        since 2004 each professor has had a personal page, in which they publish
                        course programs (and all additional materials, such as slides), their
                        research interests and publications list<note>The main pages of professors
                            have been also excluded from the Wayback Machine; other national web
                            archives have preserved just a few of them.</note>. Digital sources
                        relating to the recent years of the university also allow us to discover how
                        in 2005 the future <title rend="quotes">Prorettore per la ricerca</title>
                        Dario Braga underlined the importance of starting to teach courses in
                        English (and also Chinese and Arabic) among his <quote rend="inline"
                            source="#undocumented">proposals for the future</quote><note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2005/04/13/proposte-per-ateneo-del-futuro.html?ref=search"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2005/04/13/proposte-per-ateneo-del-futuro.html?ref=search</ref></note>
                        or how five years later, during his administration, he actively
                                discussed<note><ref
                                target="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/docentipreoccupati/WqOJqQzkPmU"
                                >https://groups.google.com/forum/#!topic/docentipreoccupati/WqOJqQzkPmU</ref></note>
                        in a Google Group newsletter the impact of the <title rend="quotes"
                            >Gelmini</title> school reform with a group of professors who were
                        collectively termed as <title rend="quotes">Docenti preoccupati</title>
                        (“worried professors”)<note>Another interesting source to study the
                            experience of Dario Braga as Prorettore and its run for the future
                            Rettore of the university, will be his personal blog: <ref
                                target="http://www.dariobraga.com/blog"
                                >http://www.dariobraga.com/blog</ref></note>. Moreover, these
                        materials gave us insight into the activities of the <title rend="quotes"
                            >Centro Studi La Permanenza del Classico</title> whose director was the
                        former Rector, Ivano Dionigi<note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2006/10/25/umanisti-scienziati-insieme-alla-stessa-lezione.html?ref=search"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2006/10/25/umanisti-scienziati-insieme-alla-stessa-lezione.html?ref=search</ref></note>
                        and showed how the <title rend="italic">Unibo Magazine</title> presented
                        itself online in 2003 (with an interview<note><ref
                                target="http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2003/11/11/intervista-al-rettore"
                                >http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2003/11/11/intervista-al-rettore</ref></note>
                        of the then Rector, Pier Ugo Calzolari, who spoke the scarcity of funding
                        for higher education and research in Italy).</p>

                    <p>Among all these different resources, one source deserves special mention. In
                        May 2007, a group of activists decided to create a copy of the Unibo.it
                        interface. They were demonstrating against the European Credit Transfer and
                        Accumulation System (ECTS) for the evaluation of the number of hours of
                        study. They believed that the university website could be the perfect target
                        for their protest, in order to attract the attention of the institution. At
                        the URL <ref target="http://www.unibologna.eu/"
                            >http://www.unibologna.eu/</ref> an identical version of the homepage
                        was available, with the description of the reasons of the protest. In a
                        couple of weeks, the website attracted a high number of visitors and most of
                        all the attention of the university<note><ref
                                target="http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2007/attacco_al_portale"
                                >http://www.magazine.unibo.it/archivio/2007/attacco_al_portale</ref></note>,
                        which blocked the access to it from all its computers<note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2007/06/13/clonato-il-sito-dell-ateneo-per-protesta.html?ref=search"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2007/06/13/clonato-il-sito-dell-ateneo-per-protesta.html?ref=search</ref></note>.
                        This source is not only important in our study as it documents a different
                        and innovative way of conducting a protest against an academic
                            institution<note>To know more on cyber protests see Van Laer and Van
                            Aelst, 2009.</note>, but as the fake-website has been preserved by the
                        Internet Archive it also paradoxically offers a preserved version of
                        Unibo.it, so that we can browse and study (see Figure 3).</p>


                    <!--Figure 3. The cloned version of Unibo.it (2007).-->


                    <figure>
                        <head>The cloned version of Unibo.it (2007).</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure15.png"/>
                    </figure>

                </div>

            </div>

            <div>
                <head>The history of www.unibo.it: 2002- the early 90s</head>
                <p>Neither material on the live web nor documents in other national web archives are
                    available for the first ten years of history of this website. For this reason,
                    the second part of this study will mainly employ information from local and
                    national newspapers, which have often described new services offered by the
                    university to its community and will combine it with archive resources (in
                    particular from the university yearbooks). As before, a pivotal role in this
                    study has been played by the collection and critical selection of oral
                    memories.</p>


                <div>
                    <head>Different ways of going back in time</head>
                    <p>In order to study the structure of the website before the <title
                            rend="quotes">Sistema Portale d’Ateneo</title> several different sources
                        have been employed, which will in turn help us in understanding what the
                        website looked like, how it was used and how relevant it was in the academic
                        digital <q>ecosystem</q>.</p>

                    <p>In particular, as described earlier, the archive of the newspaper <title
                            rend="italic">La Repubblica</title> offers important information on how
                        the website changed during the 90s. For example, it was discovered that the
                        institution offered a free email account to all students from 2002<note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2002/10/09/mail-gratuita-per-gli-studenti.html?ref=search"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2002/10/09/mail-gratuita-per-gli-studenti.html?ref=search</ref></note>
                        and it was the first Italian university which gave the possibility of paying
                        fees online (2000)<note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2000/07/17/tasse-online-per-universita.html?ref=search"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/2000/07/17/tasse-online-per-universita.html?ref=search</ref></note>;
                        moreover since 1999 some departments also guaranteed the possibility of
                        enrolling for courses and exams online<note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/1999/09/13/finalmente-offerta-portata-di-mouse.html?ref=search"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/1999/09/13/finalmente-offerta-portata-di-mouse.html?ref=search</ref></note>.
                        Another interesting piece of news retrieved from the digital archive of
                            <title rend="italic">La Repubblica</title> is from October 2001, a few
                        months before the project <title rend="quotes">Portale d’Ateneo</title>
                        started. In those days, the University of Bologna website won the <q>WWW</q>
                        prize from the Italian economic newspaper <title rend="italic">Il Sole 24
                            Ore</title> for the best website in the category <title rend="quotes"
                            >School, university and research</title>. At the ceremony Salvatore
                        Mirabella, a technician who managed the website during the 90s, was also
                            present<note>He was the head of <title rend="quotes">Urp – Servizio
                                Web</title>, as described here: <ref
                                target="http://www2.unibo.it/Annuari/Annu9901/Indice/parte2/parte2sez1/parte2sez1.html"
                                >http://www2.unibo.it/Annuari/Annu9901/Indice/parte2/parte2sez1/parte2sez1.html</ref></note>.
                        However, as we can notice by looking at the images offered by CeSIA or by
                        analyzing a few examples that are still available on the live web (i.e. <ref
                            target="http://www2.unibo.it/annuari"
                            >http://www2.unibo.it/annuari</ref>)<note>It is important to note that
                            the page http://www2.unibo.it is not available on the live web anymore
                            and it was excluded from the Wayback Machine.</note>, before the <title
                            rend="quotes">Sistema Portale d’Ateneo</title> project the homepage of
                        Unibo.it was mainly an information page, presenting only a few links (see
                        Figure 4).</p>

                    <!--Figure 4. Unibo.it in 1999.-->

                    <figure>
                        <head>Unibo.it in 1999.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>At the same time, consulting <title rend="quotes">The list and map of the
                            Italian WWW servers</title><note>This is a useful starting point for
                            every researcher who is interested in the past of the Italian web
                            sphere.</note> created by Cilea and available from 1997 onwards on the
                        Internet Archive<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/19971025045601/http://www.cilea.it/WWW-map/"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/19971025045601/http://www.cilea.it/WWW-map/</ref></note>,
                        we can observe that several departments, faculties and research groups were
                        already online and, as opposed to the relatively passive homepage, very
                        active in the 90s. For example, we can retrieve all the information on
                        courses in history since 1998<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/19981206110539/http://www.dds.unibo.it/"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/19981206110539/http://www.dds.unibo.it/</ref></note>,
                        the organization of the university astronomical observatory<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/19970114105744/http://www.bo.astro.it/"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/19970114105744/http://www.bo.astro.it/</ref></note>
                        and of the Faculty of Engineering<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/19970422153341/http://www.ing.unibo.it/"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/19970422153341/http://www.ing.unibo.it/</ref></note>
                        since 1997, description on the inter-faculty library since October
                                1996<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/19961031164155/http://liber.cib.unibo.it/"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/19961031164155/http://liber.cib.unibo.it/</ref></note>
                        (the entire system was created in 1993<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/20010424195903/http://www.cilea.it/collabora/GARR-NIR/nir-it-2/atti/cib.html"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/20010424195903/http://www.cilea.it/collabora/GARR-NIR/nir-it-2/atti/cib.html</ref></note>),
                        the digitization of the students guide books carried out by the faculty of
                        economics in 1994<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/20010424195734/http://www.cilea.it/collabora/GARR-NIR/nir-it-2/atti/didbo.html"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/20010424195734/http://www.cilea.it/collabora/GARR-NIR/nir-it-2/atti/didbo.html</ref></note>.
                        The Internet Archive has also preserved Unibo.it’s old online magazine,
                            <title rend="italic">AlmaNews</title>, which offer several short videos
                        of important events, such as the ceremony<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/20050204125414/http://www.almanews.unibo.it/97_98/Html/Economia.htm"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/20050204125414/http://www.almanews.unibo.it/97_98/Html/Economia.htm</ref></note>
                        for the first degrees in Business Administration and Political Sciences in
                        1997. These different pages, extremely useful for prospective and enrolled
                                students<note><ref
                                target="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!search/%22esami%22$20%22unibo%22/it.reticiviche.bologna.universita/Ndj7QmZ2Iqc/1rTwBNK0gnMJ"
                                >https://groups.google.com/forum/#!search/%22esami%22$20%22unibo%22/it.reticiviche.bologna.universita/Ndj7QmZ2Iqc/1rTwBNK0gnMJ</ref></note>,
                        were continuously updated with new information by technicians, researchers,
                        professors and, from time to time, also with contributions of
                                students<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/19980117121355/http://caristudenti.cs.unibo.it/index.shtml"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/19980117121355/http://caristudenti.cs.unibo.it/index.shtml</ref></note>.
                        For these reasons, they all evolved differently during the 90s and they are
                        now interesting instances on how the departments of this university
                        approached the World Wide Web.</p>

                    <p>In addition to examining departmental pages, there are many other ways of
                        looking at the second half of the 90s’ history of Unibo.it. We could follow
                        the information related to AlmaNET, the university internal Internet
                        connection, which in 1988 was established to connect three departments and
                        was highly improved in 1996<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/19990503060118/http://naomi.bo.astro.it/~federico/almanet/smds/smdspage.html"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/19990503060118/http://naomi.bo.astro.it/~federico/almanet/smds/smdspage.html</ref></note>,
                        thanks to the collaboration of Telecom Italia and under the supervision of
                        CeSIA (which was created in 1994)<note>Additional materials on this topic
                            can be found in the bibliography dedicated to <q>Internet in Italy</q>
                            edited by Riccardo Ridi on his website : <ref
                                target="http://www.riccardoridi.it/esb/biblint/04.htm"
                                >http://www.riccardoridi.it/esb/biblint/04.htm</ref></note>. Another
                        perspective on the recent past of this institution could be developed by the
                        examination of the impact of the online service AlmaLaurea, presented in May
                                1998<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/20020225134330/http://www.almanews.unibo.it/Alma98.htm"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/20020225134330/http://www.almanews.unibo.it/Alma98.htm</ref></note>,
                        which aimed at improving the relationship between the institution, its
                        student community and the job-market. A third point of view might be focused
                        on the relation and mutual influence between the university and the
                        municipality, by considering the role played by the Internet. In fact, the
                        city of Bologna and its citizens have a strong bond with innovation in
                        computing technologies, with the municipality for instance having created
                        one of the first civic-networks in the world in 1995, giving to all citizens
                        free access to the Internet the very next year <ptr target="#chiara1998"/>.
                        The early importance of the web for Bologna citizens appeared also in a 1996
                        article retrieved from <title rend="italic">La Repubblica</title> digital
                        archive. As mentioned in the piece of news <ptr target="#venturi1996"/>, in
                        November of that year for the first time in Italy, a digital discussion was
                        censored and an entire mailing list named <title rend="quotes">Lisa</title>
                        was completely closed. This happened on the Unibo server<note><ref
                                target="http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/1996/11/24/troppe-parolacce-censurata-lisa.html?ref=searc"
                                >http://ricerca.repubblica.it/repubblica/archivio/repubblica/1996/11/24/troppe-parolacce-censurata-lisa.html?ref=search</ref></note>:
                        CeSIA informed the professor of computer science Dario Maio of the presence
                        of violent debates on the platform and the Department of Computer Science
                        decided to drastically intervene. As the article reported, these digital
                        conflicts were probably related to the internal discussion of an Italian
                        association named <title rend="quotes">La città invisibile</title><note><ref
                                target="http://www.citinv.it/intro.html"
                                >http://www.citinv.it/intro.html</ref></note> (<title rend="quotes"
                            >The invisible city</title>). This association, comprising early
                        Internet activists, was interested in sharing the importance of digital
                        cultures and rights. Among them there were also academics, for example Lucio
                        Picci (currently professor of Political Economy<note><ref
                                target="http://www2.dse.unibo.it/picci/"
                                >http://www2.dse.unibo.it/picci/</ref></note>), who was at that time
                        a young researcher at the University of Bologna<note><ref
                                target="http://www2.dse.unibo.it/picci/sfera/storia.html"
                                >http://www2.dse.unibo.it/picci/sfera/storia.html</ref></note>.</p>

                    <p>It is evident that diachronically examining the digital alter ego of the
                        institution and using these resources to extend our knowledge on its recent
                        past is a complex challenge, which relies on both an interdisciplinary set
                        of methodological approaches and specific research questions. The examples
                        presented above only highlight some specific perspectives on the topic,
                        which I have encountered while examining the collected sources. While each
                        one of the aspects previously presented would offer a different insight on
                        the early use of the web by the institution,the last part of this section
                        will focus on a different task: tracing the origin of the university
                        website. This will help us in understanding the process of creation of
                        Unibo.it: who was responsible for it, for what reasons was it created and in
                        which context. Old websites hold interesting stories on their origins, which
                        are often placed at the intersection of academic research, curiosity in
                        advanced digital technologies (together with aspiration of contributing to
                        them) and mutual human desire of communicating with others. Unibo.it is one
                        of them.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>At the beginning of the digital era</head>
                    <p>Tracing the first online presence of an entity such as the University of
                        Bologna has not been an easy task. In Italy a list of .it servers was
                        initially maintained by the research center CNUCE (Centro Nazionale
                        Universitario di Calcolo Elettronico) and is currently available on the
                        website Registro.it<note><ref target="http://www.nic.it/"
                                >http://www.nic.it/</ref></note>. However all early Italian websites
                        (created before 1996) have a common creation date: 29-01-1996 (Figure
                        5).</p>

                    <!--Figure 5. Unibo.it and Crs4.it (which is considered to be the first Italian website<note>The website of the “Centro di ricerca, sviluppo e studisuperiori in Sardegna” (CRS4 – www.crs4.it) was created between the second half of 1992 and November 1993. In different occasions the team behind it reported different dates, for example in Colletti, 2014; CRS4, 2015; Corrieredella sera, 2015.</note>) have the same starting date.-->


                    <figure>
                        <head>Unibo.it and Crs4.it (which is considered to be the first Italian
                                website<note>The website of the <title rend="quotes">Centro di
                                    ricerca, sviluppo e studisuperiori in Sardegna</title> (CRS4 –
                                www.crs4.it) was created between the second half of 1992 and
                                November 1993. In different occasions the team behind it reported
                                different dates, for example in <ptr target="#colletti2014"/>; <ptr
                                    target="#crs2015"/>; <ptr target="#corrieredellasera2015"
                                />.</note>) have the same starting date.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>
                    </figure>

                    <p>The research group <title rend="quotes">GARR-Network Information
                            Retrieval</title> organized a series of annual meetings in the early
                                90s<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/19971025045540/http://www.cilea.it/GARR-NIR/"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/19971025045540/http://www.cilea.it/GARR-NIR/</ref></note>,
                        dedicated to the spread of the World Wide Web in Italy at the university
                        level. Consulting the proceedings of 1994, I learned<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/20010424195903/http://www.cilea.it/collabora/GARR-NIR/nir-it-2/atti/cib.html"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/20010424195903/http://www.cilea.it/collabora/GARR-NIR/nir-it-2/atti/cib.html</ref></note>
                        that Unibo.it was already active at least in the August of the year before.
                        The fact that the university was fostering the use of the Internet and of
                        web materials could be also deduced by consulting the 1993/94 yearbooks,
                        where the importance of AlmaNet is mentioned, as well as the need of
                        adopting emails as a form of communication and online databases as new
                        resources.</p>

                    <p>During the first years of the World Wide Web Tim Berners-Lee curated a list
                        of web-servers on the CERN website; the last update available is from late
                                1992<note><ref
                                target="http://www.w3.org/History/19921103-hypertext/hypertext/DataSources/WWW/Servers.html"
                                >http://www.w3.org/History/19921103-hypertext/hypertext/DataSources/WWW/Servers.html</ref></note>.
                        Unibo.it is not mentioned in this list, but there is a link to another
                        Italian research institution, the Physics Institute in Trieste. Later, on
                        the NCSA website, a specific section called <title rend="quotes">What’s
                            New!</title> published a list of the new servers on the web each month
                        (from June 1993 to January 1996)<note><ref
                                target="http://web.archive.org/web/19961220071416/http://www.ncsa.uiuc.edu/SDG/Software/Mosaic/Docs/archive-whats-new.html"
                                >http://web.archive.org/web/19961220071416/http://www.ncsa.uiuc.edu/SDG/Software/Mosaic/Docs/archive-whats-new.html</ref></note>.
                        By consulting it, some interesting information about specific sub-sections
                        of Unibo.it was found: for example the <title rend="quotes">Bologna
                            Astrophysics Preprints</title> has offered online, since November 1994,
                        all the scientific publications of the Bologna Astronomical Observatory
                        (OAB), the Astronomy Department of Bologna University (DDA), the Radio
                        astronomy Institute of CNR (IRA) and the TESRE Institute of CNR (ITE).
                        However, for what concerns specifically the creation date of the website, in
                        December 1993 a link to a map of all Italian web-servers was published, but
                        this link is not available anymore (it redirects to the 1997 version of the
                        Cilea Map). Summarizing then, by consulting born digital materials as well
                        as traditional archival sources, we know that Unibo.it was already available
                        in the second half of 1993, and that the website was created after the end
                        of 1992, according to the CERN web-server list.</p>

                    <p>University websites have usually been created by researchers who were already
                        using the Internet in their work. For this reason, departments and research
                        centers in computer science<note><ref
                                target="https://web.archive.org/web/19970518021303/http://www.utexas.edu/teamweb/history/"
                                >https://web.archive.org/web/19970518021303/http://www.utexas.edu/teamweb/history/</ref></note>
                        and physics<note><ref
                                target="https://swap.stanford.edu/19911206000000/http://slacvm.slac.stanford.edu/FIND/default.html"
                                >https://swap.stanford.edu/19911206000000/http://slacvm.slac.stanford.edu/FIND/default.html</ref></note>
                        are generally good starting points for discovering who created the website
                        of a specific institution. However, in Bologna, the university website was
                        created in a different place, namely at the Department of Mathematics,
                        thanks to the collaboration between a Turkish professor who had at that time
                        arrived from the United States, and a young Italian researcher.</p>

                    <p>The story of the origins of Unibo.it emerged in an interview conducted with
                        Renzo Davoli. Davoli is currently professor of Computer Science at the
                        University of Bologna; in the early 90s he was working under the supervision
                        of Ozalp Babaoglu, who arrived in Bologna in 1988 from Cornell University
                        and wanted to use the Internet – among other things – to stay in touch with
                        his colleagues and friends from abroad. Given the fact that Bologna did not
                        have a Department of Computer Science at that time, Babaoglu and Davoli were
                        working at the Department of Mathematics. In 1988 the two of them
                        established the second Italian node to the Internet<note>The first node is
                            from the research institute CNUCE, in Pisa, as described here: <ref
                                target="http://www.30annidirete.it/"
                                >http://www.30annidirete.it/</ref>.</note>, from the Department of
                        Mathematics to CNUCE, in Pisa<note>This information is also offered by the
                            The Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) : <ref
                                target="https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1117#ref-AA62"
                                >https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc1117#ref-AA62</ref></note> and
                        Davoli became the person in charge of the University TCP/IP network. They
                        then became part of AlmaNet, the internal network initially established
                        between the Departments of Mathematics, Engineering and Physics. In the
                        following years, AlmaNet played an essential role in connecting university
                        departments, especially the ones located outside the city.</p>

                    <p>Interactions between the departments were again improved thanks to the advent
                        of the World Wide Web. Departments were the first to be online and, once
                        again, this was accomplished thanks to Babaouglu and Davoli. As a matter of
                        fact, in July 1993, the two researchers registered and created the web pages
                        of the domains <q>cs.unibo.it</q> (Computer Science) and <q>dm.unibo.it</q>
                        (Department of Mathematics). This helped colleagues in other departments
                        understand the huge potential of the web. Initially, Davoli and Babaoglu
                        managed the main website as well, which then passed under the supervision of
                        the Public Relation Office, and in particular of Salvatore
                                Mirabella<note><ref
                                target="http://www.unibo.it/annuari/Annu9597/final/c2/p1/sp1/index.html"
                                >http://www.unibo.it/annuari/Annu9597/final/c2/p1/sp1/index.html</ref></note>.</p>
                </div>


            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Working with the Internet Archive</head>
                <p>In the previous sections, it has been highlighted how the digital past of an
                    institution could be re-discovered without the prompt availability of Internet
                    Archive snapshots. The following paragraphs will describe the work I conducted,
                    for understanding why Unibo.it was excluded from the Wayback Machine.</p>

                <p>In order to understand the reasons of the removal of Unibo.it, the first step was
                    to find, in the exclusion-policy of the Internet Archive, information related to
                    the message <q>This URL has been excluded from the Wayback Machine</q>, which
                    appeared when <q>http://www.unibo.it</q> was searched. As described in the FAQ
                    section of the Internet Archive, the most common reason for this exclusion is
                    when a website explicitly requests to not be crawled by adding <q>User-agent:
                        ia_archiver Disallow: /</q> to its robots.txt file<note>The Internet Archive
                        follows the <q>robots.txt protocol</q>, which is a convention of advising
                        web crawlers and other web robots to access only parts of a website which is
                        otherwise publicly viewable.</note>. However, it is also explained that
                        <q>Sometimes a website owner will contact us
                        directly and ask us to stop crawling or archiving a site, and we endeavor to
                        comply with these requests. When you come across a <q>blocked site error</q>
                        message that means that a site owner has made such a request and it has been
                        honored. Currently there is no way to exclude only a portion of a site, or
                        to exclude archiving a site for a particular time period only. When a URL
                        has been excluded at direct owner request from being archived, that
                        exclusion is retroactive and permanent</q>.</p>

                <p>When a website has not been archived due to robots.txt limitations, a specific
                    message is displayed: <q>Page cannot be crawled or
                        displayed due to robots.txt</q>, which is different from the one that
                    appeared when searching the University of Bologna website (as shown in Figure
                    6). Therefore, the only possible conclusion is that someone had explicitly
                    requested to remove the University of Bologna website from the Archive.</p>

                <!--Figure 6. Two different exclusion messages (left University of Trento, right University of Bologna).-->

                <figure>
                    <head>Two different exclusion messages (left University of Trento, right
                        University of Bologna).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>
                </figure>

                <p>Before moving on, it is essential to mention that, when a website is excluded due
                    to robots.txt, its pages are not preserved by the Internet Archive. In the
                    second situation, as it will be presented in the next paragraphs, it was instead
                    discovered that the Internet Archive has continued to preserve the website
                    (despite what is described in the FAQ section), which was simply not available
                    for any kind of consultation through the Wayback Machine. Given the specificity
                    of the exclusion message, I decided to consult CeSIA, the team that has
                    supervised Unibo.it during the last decades, regarding this issue. However, they
                    did not submit any removal-request to the Internet Archive and they were not
                    aware nor had any trace in digital and archival documents of anyone submitting
                    it. To clarify this issue, the Internet Archive team was then contacted. Thanks
                    to the efforts of Mauro Amico (CeSIA), Raffaele Messuti (AlmaDL - Unibo),
                    Christopher Butler (Internet Archive) and Giovanni Damiola (Internet Archive), a
                    collaboration with the Internet Archive started at the end of March 2015. As we
                    contacted Butler, he told us that the Unibo.it case was similar to another one
                    that involved the New York government websites<note><ref
                            target="http://www.villagevoice.com/news/why-were-new-york-government-websites-hidden-from-an-internet-archive-for-13-years-6721316"
                            >http://www.villagevoice.com/news/why-were-new-york-government-websites-hidden-from-an-internet-archive-for-13-years-6721316</ref></note>.
                    With their help, I discovered that a removal request regarding the main website
                    and a list of specific subdomains had been submitted to the Internet Archive in
                    April 2002. Thanks to this collaboration, the university website became
                    available again on the Wayback Machine on the 13th of April 2015 (see Figure 7).
                    This also gives us the opportunity of attesting that the Internet Archive has
                    kept preserving Unibo.it in the last fifteen years; the website was simply not
                    available for any consultation. Additionally, having the website at our
                    disposal, once again, gave me the opportunity of re-evaluating the findings of
                    this study.</p>

                <!--Figure 7. Unibo.it is once again available on the Wayback Machine.-->


                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it is once again available on the Wayback Machine.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure16.png"/>
                </figure>


                <p>While the exclusion issue was solved, it was necessary to investigate its causes
                    further. As it has already been described, in 2002 the administration of
                    Unibo.it completely changed, during a general re-organization of the digital
                    presence of the university (the Portale d’Ateneo project). Therefore, while it
                    is evident that this request was made by someone who was in the position to ask
                    for the removal of the website<note>The Internet Archive says <q>the website
                            owner</q> and, even if they happened to be not absolutely rigid on this
                        point, it has to be someone at least involved in the management of the
                        website.</note> and who knew how the Internet Archive exclusion policy
                        works<note>As he/she explicitly declared a specific list of subdomains to
                        remove (as described above, the Internet Archive excludes urls and their
                        subsections – not subdomains).</note>, it still remains entirely unclear to
                    us who, in that very same month, could have been in the position to submit this
                    specific request, and the reasons behind it. Even though several years have
                    passed by, it was assumed that someone involved in the administration of the
                    website would have remembered (or had traces in a backup) this email exchange
                    with a team of digital archivists in San Francisco. Between April and June 2015
                    a last series of interviews was conducted with several people involved in the
                    Unibo.it website, pre- and post the 2002 reorganization. However, it was
                    impossible to retrieve any information on this issue.</p>

                <p>As the specificity of the request is the only hint that could help in identifying
                    its author, I decided to analyze the different urls in more detail. The majority
                    of them are server addresses (identified by <q>alma.unibo</q>), while the other
                    pages are subdomains of the main website, for example estero.unibo.it (probably
                    dedicated to international collaborations). A few questions therefore remain
                    unsolved: why would someone want to exclude exactly these pages and not all the
                    department pages, which were active online, at that time? Why exactly these four
                    subdomains were selected and not the digital magazine <title rend="italic"
                        >Alma2000</title> (<ref target="http://alma2000.unibo.it"
                        >alma2000.unibo.it</ref>) or the e-learning platform (<ref
                        target="http://www.elearning.unibo.it">www.elearning.unibo.it</ref>)?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>A new primary source</head>
                <p>In the previous sections, the paper has presented a) how the past of Unibo.it was
                    reconstructed without having snapshots from the Wayback Machine at prompt
                    disposal and b) how this process brought new light on the interaction between
                    the university and its community. This paper also stressed that different
                    research communities are currently studying the recent past of academic
                    institutions and that web materials could open for them new perspectives. For
                    this reason, in this final section I will highlight a specific type of primary
                    source that was collected during this study that could become useful for
                    obtaining new insights in these fields.</p>

                <div>
                    <head>Syllabi</head>
                    <p>The history of universities has traditionally focused on topics such as the
                        role of academic institutions in processes such as nation building as well
                        as on the influence of governments (through economic and political
                        decisions), on the experience and life of students as well as on the
                        relationship of institutions and professional realities. Another topic that
                        has attracted significant attention is the examination of universities as
                        institutions of higher education, where the manner in which topics are
                        taught and education is provided are also highly influenced by several
                        political, economic and social factors.</p>

                    <p>Examining what has been taught within a given timeframe at a specific
                        academic institution and understanding the global and local reasons that
                        influenced specific changes is a topic that has attracted the attention of
                        many historians of universities. For example, <ptr
                            target="#deridder-symoens1992-2011"/>, provides a complete overview of
                        the most recurrent teaching topics in European academic institutions and how
                        and why they have changed in the last centuries. Traditionally, historians
                        collect this information by examining different sources, such as student
                        transcript of lessons and professor’s notes<note>For example, a great
                            resource to know what Professor Pasquini taught about Dante at the
                            University of Bologna are the notes from its course from the academic
                            year 1992-93.</note> as well as university yearbooks and the reasons
                        behind widespread adoption of specific textbooks. In recent years, Dan Cohen
                            <ptr target="#cohen2006"/>; <ptr target="#cohen2011"/> has considered
                        the large and still unexplored potential that online syllabi could offer to
                        the study of academic teaching. The first digital-historical work on the
                        topic has been published in 2005 in the <title rend="italic">Journal of
                            American History</title>
                        <ptr target="#cohen2005"/>. The goal of the paper was to show how the
                        teaching of history in U.S. universities is still strongly based on
                        textbooks. These findings, which are directly in contrast to a round table
                        discussion published in the same journal four years prior <ptr
                            target="#kornblith2001"/>, were obtained thanks to a large study of
                        around 800 syllabi available on the web.</p>

                    <p>While Cohen’s work is a first step in this direction, the potential of online
                        syllabi goes beyond his study and could rapidly affect the practices, topics
                        and findings of historians of universities as well as the scientometrics
                        community. During the reconstruction of the past of Unibo.it, it was
                        possible to collect all syllabi published online by the institution, which
                        in the case of the University of Bologna are in the number of thousands for
                        each academic year<note>By analyzing the <title rend="quotes"
                                >Portale</title>, it is possible to collect all syllabi since the
                            academic year 2004-2005. Then, by using Internet Archive snapshots of
                            retrieved department’s pages, it is possible to identify all courses
                            programs for several departments, for example all syllabi of courses in
                            History since 1998-99.The dataset I collected is available at: <ref
                                target="https://federiconanni.com/syllabi-unibo/"
                                >https://federiconanni.com/syllabi-unibo/</ref></note>. This type of
                        documents will further allow to conduct large-scale analyses on what have
                        been, year after year, the topics that the University (and each single
                        school and department) decided to focus on in its educational programs.
                        Results of these studies will be useful for obtaining a wider perspective in
                        a scientometrics setting (by considering both the input and output of an
                        academic institution) and will also act as the starting point for addressing
                        questions regarding the underlying cultural, economic and political factors
                        that condition specific changes.</p>
                </div>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Conclusions</head>
                <p>The aim of this paper has been to highlight both the issues and the
                    potentialities of using born digital documents to study the recent past of the
                    University of Bologna. The main focus was to describe the methodological
                    approach employed in order to reconstruct its website (which has been excluded
                    for the last thirteen years from the Wayback Machine). In doing so, the paper
                    underlined how its history is divided into two parts (before and after the
                    setting up of the <title rend="quotes">Sistema Portale d’Ateneo</title>) and how
                    different sources (the yearbooks, materials from foreign web archives, document
                    preserved by CeSIA, articles on local, national and digital newspaper) have been
                    useful to improve our knowledge on the metamorphosis of this website
                    (specifically, on the role of department pages). This work also examined how
                    born-digital sources can offer new insights on common research topics related to
                    the history of this university and its relation with the students’ community and
                    the city itself.</p>

                <p>The different issues presented in this paper highlight the need of an even more
                    interdisciplinary approach for future historians. In the field of Internet
                    studies and digital archiving, researchers are already discussing the importance
                    of new ways of conceiving the retrieval, analysis, criticism and employment of
                    born digital primary sources. As historians, we should openly join this
                    discussion with both theoretical contributions as well as concrete examples. As
                    a matter of fact, these materials will sustain traditional historical research
                    questions and will lead to an infinite number of new ones.</p>
            </div>

            <div>
                <head>Appendix</head>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 01/1996 and 01/1998.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 01/1998 and 09/1998.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 09/1998 and 07/1999.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 2002 and 2003.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 2004 and 2006.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure07.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 2006 and 2009.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 2009 and 07/2013.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>
                </figure>

                <figure>
                    <head>Unibo.it between 07/2013 and 03/2015 (Snapshot taken on the 17th of March
                        2015).</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>
                </figure>

            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl xml:id="ankerson2012" label="Ankerson 2012">Ankerson, M. S. <title
                        rend="italic">Writing Web Histories with an Eye on the Analog Past</title>.
                    New Media and Society (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="barbagli2009" label="Barbagli 2009">Barbagli, M., Colombo, A., Orzi,
                    R. <title rend="italic">Gli studenti e la città: primo rapportosuglistudenti
                        dell'Università di Bologna</title>. Bologna University Press (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bendavid2016" label="Ben-David 2016">Ben-David, A. <title
                        rend="italic">What does the Web remember of its deleted past? An archival
                        reconstruction of the former Yugoslav top-level domain</title>. New Media
                    and Society (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bergamin2006" label="Bergamin 2006">Bergamin, G. <title rend="italic"
                        >La raccolta dei siti web: un test per ildominio “punto it”</title>.
                    DigItalia (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blevins2015" label="Blevins 2015">The Perpetual Sunrise of
                    <!--author missing--> Methodology (2015).
                    http://www.cameronblevins.org/posts/perpetual-sunrise-methodology/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="blevins2016" label="Blevins 2016">Blevins, C. "Digital History’s
                    Perpetual Future Tense", <title rend="italic">Debates in the Digital
                        Humanities</title> (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bloch1949" label="Bloch 1949">Bloch, M. <title rend="italic">Apologie
                        Pour l'Histoireou Métier d'Historien</title> (1949).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="bowosky1973" label="Bowosky 1973">Bowsky, W. M., Baldwin, J. W.,
                    Goldthwaite, R. A. <title rend="italic">Universities in Politics: Case studies
                        from the Late Middle Ages and Early Modern Period</title> (1973).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brizzi1991" label="Brizzi 1991">Brizzi, G P. "La presenza studentesca
                    nelle università italiane nella prima età moderna. Analisi delle fonti e
                    problemi di metodo", In Brizzi and Varni Angelo (eds.), <title rend="italic"
                        >L’università in Italia fra età moderna e contemporanea</title>. Aspetti e
                    momenti, Clueb (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brizzi2007" label="Brizzi 2007">Brizzi, G. P., Del Negro, P., Romano,
                    A. <title rend="italic">Storia delle Università in Italia, I-III</title>.
                    Sicania by Gem (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brockliss1978" label="Brockliss  1978">Brockliss, L. 'Patterns of
                    Attendance at the University of Paris, 1400–1800", <title rend="italic">The
                        Historical Journal</title> (1978).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2008" label="Brügger 2008">Brügger, N. "The Archived Website
                    and Website Philology: A new type of Historical Document?", <title rend="italic"
                        >Nordicom Review</title> (2008).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2009" label="Brügger 2009">Brügger, Niels. <title rend="italic"
                        >Website History and the Website as an Object of Study</title>. New Media
                    and Society (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2010" label="Brügger 2010"> Brügger, Niels (eds). <title
                        rend="italic">Web history</title>. Peter Lang (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2011" label="Brügger 2011">Brügger, Niels. "Web
                    Archiving-Between Past, Present, and Future", In M. Consalvo and C. Ess (eds)
                        <title rend="italic"> The Handbook of Internet Studies</title>.
                    Wiley-Blackwell (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2012a" label="Brügger 2012a">Brügger, N. <title rend="italic"
                        >When the Present Web is Later the Past: Web Historiography, Digital
                        History, and Internet Studies</title>. Historical Social
                    Research/HistorischeSozialforschung (2012a).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2012b" label="Brügger 2012b">Brügger, N. <title rend="italic"
                        >Web Historiography and Internet Studies: Challenges and
                        Perspectives</title>. New Media and Society (2012b).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2014" label="Brügger 2014">Brügger N. <title rend="italic"
                        >Probing a Nation’s Web Sphere: A New Approach to Web History and a New Kind
                        of Historical Source</title>. WebSci (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="brügger2016" label="Brügger 2016">Brügger, N. "Digital Humanities in
                    the 21st Century: Digital Material as a Driving Force", <title rend="italic"
                        >Digital Humanities Quarterly</title> (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="capitani1987" label="Capitani 1987">Capitani, O. (eds). <title
                        rend="italic">L'Università a Bologna: Personaggi, Momenti e Luoghi dalle
                        Origini al XVI Secolo</title>. Cassa di Risparmio (1987).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="chiara1998" label="Chiara 1998">Chiara, Stefano. <title rend="italic"
                        >La Telematica e la Città.</title> Il Progetto Iperbole a Bologna, MA Thesis
                    in “Comunicazioni di massa”, University of Bologna, A.A. 1997-98, (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="clark1976" label="Clark 1976"> Clark, B. R. and Youn, T. I. <title
                        rend="italic">Academic Power in the United States: Comparative Historic and
                        Structural Perspectives</title>, Research Report no. 3 (1976).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="colletti2014" label="Colletti 2014">Colletti G. <title rend="italic"
                        >Sardegna Apripista Di Internet. Pietro Zanarini, Pioniere Della Rete: "Il
                        Web Italiano Nacque Qui"</title>, La Repubblica, 6/07/2014.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen2005" label="Cohen 2005">Cohen, D. "By the Book: Assessing the
                    Place of Textbooks in Us Survey Courses", <title rend="italic">The Journal of
                        American History</title>, 91(4), (2005).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen2006" label="Cohen 2006">Cohen, D. "When Machines Are the
                    Audience", <title rend="italic">Personal blog</title> (2006).
                    http://www.dancohen.org/2006/03/02/when-machines-are-the-audience/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="cohen2011" label="Cohen 2011">Cohen, D. "A Million Syllabi", <title
                        rend="italic">Personal blog</title> (2011)
                    http://www.dancohen.org/2011/03/30/a-million-syllabi/.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="corrieredellasera2015" label="Corriere della Sera 2015">Corriere della
                    Sera, Internet e Ricerca: I 25 Anni del Crs4, Centro d’Eccellenza in Sardegna,
                    23/12/2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="crs2015" label="CRS 2015">CRS4. <title rend="italic">CRS4, Il Centro
                        Di Ricerca Sardo Compie 25 Anni</title> – Comunicato Stampa,
                    30/11/2015.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="debellis2009" label="De Bellis 2009">De Bellis, N. <title
                        rend="italic">Bibliometrics and Citation Analysis: From the Science Citation
                        Index to Cybermetrics</title>. Scarecrow Press (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="deridder-symoens1992-2011" label="de Ridder-Symoens 1992-2011">de
                    Ridder-Symoens, H., Rüegg, W. (eds). <title rend="italic">A History of the
                        Universities in Europe</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge
                    (1992-2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dewied1991" label="de Wied  1991">de Wied, D. <title rend="italic"
                        >Postgraduate Research Training Today: Emerging Structures for a Changing
                        Europe. Netherlands Ministry of Education and Science</title>. The Hague
                    (1991).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dröscher2002" label="Dröscher 2002"> Dröscher, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Le Facoltà Medico-Chirurgiche Italiane: 1860-1915: Repertorio Delle
                        Cattedre E Degli Stabilimenti Annessi, Dei Docenti, Dei Liberi Docenti E Del
                        Personale Scientifico.</title> Clueb (2002).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="dougherty2010" label="Dougherty 2010">Dougherty, M., Meyer, E. T.,
                    Madsen, C. M., Van den Heuvel, C., Thomas, A., Wyatt, S. <title rend="italic"
                        >Researcher Engagement with Web Archives: State of the Art</title>. Final
                    Report for the JISC-funded project “Researcher Engagement with Web Archives”
                    (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="finkenstaedt2011" label="Finkenstaedt  2011">Finkenstaedt, T.
                    "Teachers", In Walter Rüegg (eds) <title rend="italic">A History of the
                        University in Europe, Vol. IV: Universities since 1945</title>. Cambridge
                    University Press, Cambridge (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="fox1993" label="Fox 1993">Fox, R. and Guagnini, A. (eds) <title
                        rend="italic">Education, Technology and Industrial Performance in Europe,
                        1850-1939</title>. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="frana2004" label="Frana 2004">Frana, P. L. "Before the Web There Was
                    Gopher", <title rend="italic">IEEE Annals of the History of Computing</title>,
                    26(1) (2004).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gandolfi2011" label="Gandolfi 2011">Gandolfi, G. <title rend="italic"
                        >Imagines Illustrium Virorum: La Collezione Dei Ritratti Dell'Università E
                        Della Biblioteca Universitaria Di Bologna</title>. Clueb (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gebeil2016" label="Gebeil 2016">Gebeil, Sophie. Les MéMoires De La
                    Marche Pour L'éGalitéEtContre Le Racisme. Dans Les Archives Du Web. HommesEt
                    Migrations. Revue FrançAise De RéFéRence Sur Les
                    DynamiquesMigratoires(2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="gomes2011" label="Gomes 2011">Gomes, D., Miranda, J., Costa, M. A
                        <title rend="italic">Survey on Web Archiving Initiatives</title>,
                    International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries. Springer
                    (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="guagnini1988" label="Guagnini 1988">Guagnini, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Higher Education and the Engineering Profession in Italy: The Scuole of
                        Milan and Turin, 1859–1914</title>. Minerva (1988).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hale2014" label="Hale 2014">Hale, S. A., Yasseri, T., Cowls, J.,
                    Meyer, E. T., Schroeder, R., Margetts, H. <title rend="italic">Mapping the UK
                        Webspace: Fifteen Years of British Universities on the Web</title>. WebSci
                    (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="hoffmann1994" label="Hoffmann 1994">Hoffman, A. M., Hoffman, H. S.
                        <title rend="italic">Reliability and Validity in Oral History: The Case for
                        Memory</title>. Memory and History: Essays on Recalling and Interpreting
                    Experience (1994).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="holzmann2016" label="Holzmann 2016">Holzmann, H., Nejdl W., Anand, A.
                    "The Dawn of Today's Popular Domains: A Study of the Archived German Web over 18
                    Years", <title rend="italic">JCDL</title> (2016).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="howell2006" label="Howell 2006">Howell, B. A. "Proving web history:
                    How to use the Internet Archive", <title rend="italic">Journal of Internet
                        Law</title> (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huurdeman2014a" label="Huurdeman 2014a">Huurdeman, H. C., Ben-David,
                    A. <title rend="italic">Web Archive Search as Research: Methodological and
                        Theoretical Implications</title>. Alexandria (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="huurdeman2014b" label="Huurdeman 2014b">Huurdeman, H. C., Ben-David,
                    A., Kamps, J., Samar, T., de Vries, A. P. "Finding Pages on the Unarchived Web",
                        <title rend="italic">JCDL</title> (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kahle1997" label="Kahle 1997">Kahle, B. "Preserving the Internet",
                        <title rend="italic">Scientific American</title> (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="kornblith2001" label="Kornblith 2001">Kornblith, G. and Lasser, C.
                    "Teaching the American History Survey at the Opening of the Twenty-First
                    Century: A Round Table Discussion", <title rend="italic">The Journal of American
                        History</title>, 87(4) (2001).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lafrance2015" label="LaFrance 2015"> LaFrance, A. <title rend="italic"
                        >Raiders of the Lost Web</title>. The Atlantic (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="lu2012" label="Lu 2012"> Lu, K. and Wolfram, D. "Measuring Author
                    Research Relatedness: A Comparison of Word-Based, Topic-Based, and Author
                    Cocitation Approaches", <title rend="italic">Journal of the American Society for
                        Information Science and Technology</title>, (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="macleod1978" label="Macleod 1978">Macleod, R. and Moseley, R. <title
                        rend="italic">Breadth, Depth and Excellence: Sources and Problems in the
                        History of University Science Education in England, 1850-1914</title>
                    (1978).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="mahoney1988" label="Mahoney 1988">Mahoney, M. S. "The History of
                    Computing in the History of Technology", <title rend="italic">Annals of the
                        History of Computing</title> (1988).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="milligan2012" label="Milligan 2012">Milligan, I. "Mining the ‘Internet
                    Graveyard’: Rethinking the Historians' Toolkit", <title rend="italic">Journal of
                        the Canadian Historical Association/Revue De La Société Historique Du
                        Canada</title> (2012).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="milligan2017" label="Milligan 2017">Milligan, I. "Welcome to the Web:
                    The Online Community of GeoCities and the Early Years of the World Wide Web", In
                        <title rend="italic">The Web as History</title>, London: UCL Press
                    (2017).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="murphy2007" label="Murphy 2007">Murphy, J., Hashim, N. H., O’Connor,
                    P. "Take Me Back: Validating the Wayback Machine", <title rend="italic">Journal
                        of Computer‐Mediated Communication</title> (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nanni2015" label="Nanni 2015">Nanni, F. "Historical Method and
                    Born-Digital Primary Sources: A Case Study of Italian University Websites", In:
                        <title rend="italic">Officina Della Storia – Special Issue "From the History
                        of the Media to the Media as Sources of History"</title> (2015).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="negrini1998" label="Negrini 1998">Negrini, D. <title rend="italic"
                        >Repertorio Nazionale Degli Storici Dell'Università: 1993- 1997</title>.
                    Clueb (1998).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="nichols2014" label="Nichols 2014">Nichols, L. G. "A Topic Model
                    Approach to Measuring Interdisciplinarity at the National Science Foundation",
                        <title rend="italic">Scientometrics</title> (2014).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pancaldi1993" label="Pancaldi 1993">Pancaldi, G. (eds) <title
                        rend="italic">Universities and the Sciences: Historical and Contemporary
                        Perspectives</title>. CIS (1993).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pancaldi2006" label="Pancaldi 2006">Pancaldi, G. "Wartime Chemistry in
                    Italy: Industry, the Military, and the Professors", In <title rend="italic"
                        >Frontline and Factory: Comparative Perspectives on the Chemical Industry at
                        War, 1914–1924</title>. Springer (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="parolini2013" label="Parolini 2013">Parolini, G. <title rend="italic"
                        >"Making Sense of Figures": Statistics, Computing and Information
                        Technologies in Agriculture and Biology in Britain, 1920s-1960s</title>.
                    Doctoral Dissertation. University of Bologna (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="perkin2007" label="Perkin 2007">Perkin, H. "History of Universities",
                    In <title rend="italic">International Handbook of Higher Education</title>.
                    Springer (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="piazza2013" label="Piazza 2013">Piazza, S. <title rend="italic">La
                        Valutazione Della Ricerca Scientifica: Uno Studio Empirico Nelle Scienze
                        Umane</title>. Doctoral Dissertation. University of Bologna (2013).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="pomante2010" label="Pomante 2010">Pomante, L. <title rend="italic">The
                        Researches on the History of University and Higher Education in Italy. A
                        Critical Appraisal of the Last Twenty Years</title>. History of Education
                    and Children's Literature (2010).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rea1996" label="Rea 1996">Rea, L. S. (eds) <title rend="italic">La
                        Storia Delle Università Italiane: Archivi, Fonti, Indirizzi Di
                        Ricerca</title>. Atti Del Convegno: Padova, 27-29 ottobre 1994, 30. Lint
                    (1996).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="richardson1999" label="Richardson 1999">Richardson, W. <title
                        rend="italic">Historians and Educationists: The History of Education as a
                        Field of Study in Post-War England Part II: 1972–96</title>. History of
                    Education (1999).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="romano2007" label="Romano 2007">Romano, A. (eds) <title rend="italic"
                        >Gli Statuti Universitari: Tradizione Dei Testi E Valenze Politiche</title>,
                    Atti Del Convegno Internazionale Di Studi Messina-Milazzo (2007).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="rosenzweig2003" label="Rosenzweig 2003">Rosenzweig, R. "Scarcity or
                    Abundance? Preserving the Past in a Digital Era", <title rend="italic">The
                        American Historical Review</title> (2003).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="serafini2011" label="Serafini 2011">Serafini, M. <title rend="italic"
                        >Technological Innovation in Emilia-Romagna: Knowledge, Practice,
                        Strategies</title>. Doctoral Dissertation, University of Bologna
                    (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="tammaro2006" label="Tammaro 2006">Tammaro, A. M. (eds) <title
                        rend="italic">Biblioteche Digitali in Italia: Scenari, Utenti, Staff E
                        Sistemi Informativi</title>. Rapporto Di Sintesi Del Progetto Digital
                    Libraries Applications, Fondazione Rinascimento Digitale (2006).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanlaer2009" label="Van Laer 2009">Van Laer J, Van Aelst P.
                    "Cyber-Protest and Civil Society: The Internet and Action Repertoires in Social
                    Movements", In <title rend="italic">Handbook on Internet Crime</title>
                    (2009).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="vanraan1997" label="Van Raan 1997">Van Raan, A. "Scientometrics:
                    State-of-the-Art", <title rend="italic">Scientometrics</title> (1997).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="venturi1996" label="Venturi 1996">Venturi, Ilaria. “Troppe parolacce,
                    censurata ‘Lisa’”, <title rend="italic">La Repubblica</title>,
                    24/11/1996.</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="webster2015" label="Webster 2015">Webster, Peter. "Will Historians of
                    the Future Be Able to Study Twitter?", <title rend="italic">Personal
                        website</title> (2015).
                    http://peterwebster.me/2015/03/06/future-historians-and-twitter/</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="worboys2011" label="Worboys 2011">Worboys, M. "Practice and the
                    Science of Medicine in the Nineteenth Century", <title rend="italic"
                        >Isis</title> (2011).</bibl>
                <bibl xml:id="zimmer2015" label="Zimmer 2015">Zimmer, M. "The Twitter Archive at the
                    Library of Congress: Challenges for Information Practice and Information
                    Policy", <title rend="italic">First Monday</title>, 20(7) (2015).</bibl>
            </listBibl>


        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
