<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?><?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
    xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
    xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <!-- Author should supply the title and personal information-->
                <title type="article">Visualizing Theatrical Text: From Watching the Script to the
                    Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET)</title>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <!-- Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author -->
                    <dhq:author_name>Jennifer <dhq:family>Roberts-Smith</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Waterloo</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>j33rober@uwaterloo.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Jennifer Roberts-Smith is Assistant Professor and Associate Chair,
                            Undergraduate Drama in the Department of Drama and Speech Communication
                            at the University of Waterloo, and Principal Investigator of the
                            Simulated Environment for Theatre project. She serves as Associate
                            Co-Editor, Performance for Queen’s Men Editions and is a member of the
                            boards of directors of Digital Renaissance Editions and the University
                            of Toronto’s Centre for Performance Studies in Early Theatre. She has
                            published articles on early English theatre history, theatre pedagogy,
                            and Elizabethan metrics. Her current research interests include
                            applications of game design to theatre pedagogy and digital approaches
                            to historicizing Shakespeare’s language.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Shawn <dhq:family>DeSouza-Coelho</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Waterloo</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>shawnathanddc@hotmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Shawn DeSouza-Coelho is a Master's student in the Experimental Digital
                            Media program at the University of Waterloo, as well as an associate
                            researcher with the Simulated Environment for Theatre project, and
                            member of the research team for Gamifying Shakespeare: Theorizing and
                            Designing Game-Based Digital Media for Stratford Festival Audience
                            Engagement. He is a lead author of the SET project's paper, "Control
                            Freaks: An Iterative Story of Designing a Scholarly Environment in 3D",
                            which was presented at the 2012 meeting of the Canadian Society for
                            Digital Humanities/Société Canadienne des Humanités Numériques.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>


                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Teresa M. <dhq:family>Dobson</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of British Columbia</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>teresa.dobson@ubc.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Teresa M. Dobson is Associate Professor and Director of the Digital
                            Literacy Centre housed in the Department of Language and Literacy
                            Education at the University of British Columbia. She holds an
                            interdisciplinary PhD in English literature and secondary education. Her
                            primary areas of expertise are digital literacy, media culture, user
                            experience within digital knowledge environments, and digital
                            applications for literary education. She works with a number of digital
                            humanities teams in Canada on the design and use of digital tools for
                            humanities research and teaching.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Sandra <dhq:family>Gabriele</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sandrag@yorku.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Sandra Gabriele has been practicing and teaching design for over
                            twenty-five years. She is a graduate of the Ontario College of Art and
                            Design, Toronto, the School of Design, Basel and holds a MDes in Visual
                            Communication Design from the University of Alberta. In professional
                            practice, she has designed communications materials for a variety of
                            clients: government organizations, corporations, small businesses and
                            non-profit organizations, in both print and digital media. Her research
                            interests are in the area of typography (legibility and the digital
                            representation of large text collections) and information design
                            (specifically, patient safety initiatives involving graphic design).
                        </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Omar <dhq:family>Rodriguez-Arenas</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Alberta</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>orodrigu@ualberta.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Omar Rodriguez-Arenas is systems analyst at the University of Alberta's
                            Arts Resource Centre and a freelance software developer for
                            visualization projects. He holds an M.Sc. in Computing Science
                            (University of Alberta 2010) and a B.Sc. degree in Computing Science
                            (University of Sonora 2004). As part of his research at the University
                            of Alberta's Graphics Lab, Omar worked on simulations of Non-Newtonian
                            fluids. His current research interests include real-time 3D graphics,
                            physically-based animation, and humanities visualization. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Stan <dhq:family>Ruecker</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Illinois Institute of Technology</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sruecker@id.iit.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Stan Ruecker is Associate Professor of Design at the Institute of Design
                            in the Illinois Institute of Technology in Chicago. He holds advanced
                            degrees in English, Humanities Computing, and Design, and has expertise
                            in the design of experimental interfaces to support online browsing
                            tasks. His current research interests are in the areas of computer-human
                            interfaces, humanities visualization, and information design. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Stéfan <dhq:family>Sinclair</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>McGill University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>stefan.sinclair@mcgill.ca</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Stéfan Sinclair is an Associate Professor in Digital Humanities at McGill
                            University. His research focuses primarily on the design, development
                            and theorization of tools for the digital humanities, especially for
                            text analysis and visualization. He has led or contributed significantly
                            to projects such as Voyeur Tools, Simulated Environment for Theatre, and
                            BonPatron. Other professional activities include serving as associate
                            editor for Literary and Linguistic Computing and Digital Humanities
                            Quarterly, as well as serving on the executive boards of SDH/SEMI, ACH,
                            ADHO, and centerNET. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>
                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Annmarie <dhq:family>Akong</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>akongdesign@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Annmarie Akong is a graduate of the York Sheridan Bachelor of Design
                            program (2009). She is practicing interactive and user-centric design at
                            digital agencies in Toronto and has worked for clients such as Citibank,
                            Glad, and Panasonic.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Matt <dhq:family>Bouchard</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Alberta</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>matt.bouchard@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Matt Bouchard is a recent graduate of the University of Alberta (MA
                            Humanities Computing, 2010) where he also completed a combined BSc in
                            Computing Science and Creative Writing. Professionally, Matt is an
                            implementation and technology consultant for research groups,
                            businesses, and even a few government departments. Academically, Matt is
                            looking forward to starting a PhD in sports simulation interface design
                            as a continuation of his interests in video game design, information
                            design, visualization, and implementation advocacy.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Marcelo <dhq:family>Hong</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>marcelo.hong@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Marcelo Hong is a recent graduate of the York/Sheridan Joint Program in
                            Design. As a young professional, the majority of his work has been
                            focused on exploring the city as creative space and developing books and
                            magazines for cultural institutions.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>


                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Diane <dhq:family>Jakacki</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>Bucknell University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>dkj004@bucknell.edu</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Diane Jakacki is the Digital Scholarship Coordinator at Bucknell
                            University. Prior to joining Bucknell, Diane was a Marion L. Brittain
                            Postdoctoral Fellow at the Georgia Institute of Technology. She is an
                            assistant director of the Digital Humanities Summer Institute, and a
                            member of the digital advisory committees for the Records of Early
                            English Drama, the Map of Early Modern London project and Iter Gateway
                            to the Middle Ages &amp; Renaissance. Diane received her BA in English
                            and History from Lafayette College, an MA in English from the University
                            of Toronto, and a Ph.D. in English from the University of Waterloo,
                            specializing in Early Modern Theatre and Multimedia Theory and Design.
                        </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>David <dhq:family>Lam</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Waterloo</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>david.the.monkey@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>David Lam is a graduate of New York University's Tisch School of the Arts
                            Graduate Acting program. He studied mathematics and drama as an
                            undergraduate at the University of Waterloo.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Alexandra <dhq:family>Kovacs</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Toronto</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>sashakovacs@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Alexandra (Sasha) Kovacs is a Ph.D. candidate at the University of
                            Toronto’s Centre for Drama, Theatre, and Performance Studies. Her
                            doctoral research focuses on the performances of E. Pauline Johnson
                            (Tekahionwake). She has published in Canadian Theatre Review (CTR) and
                            is the recipient of the Social Sciences and Humanities Joseph Armand
                            Bombardier Canadian Graduate Scholarship (CGS).  </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Lesley <dhq:family>Northam</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>University of Waterloo</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>lesleynortham@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Lesley Northam is Lesley Northam is a PhD student in the Computer
                            Graphics Lab at the University of Waterloo. Through collaboration with
                            the Adobe Advanced Technology Lab (ATL), Side Effects Software and the
                            Screen Industries Research and Training Centre (SIRT), she has nurtured
                            research interests in previsualization, virtual production, film
                            language, stereoscopic 3D rendering and non-photorealistic computer
                            graphics. </p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>

                <dhq:authorInfo>
                    <dhq:author_name>Daniel <dhq:family>So</dhq:family>
                    </dhq:author_name>
                    <dhq:affiliation>York University</dhq:affiliation>
                    <email>dan.j.so@gmail.com</email>
                    <dhq:bio>
                        <p>Daniel So graduated from York University with a Bachelor of Design Degree
                            (YSDN Program in Design) in 2012. In professional practice, he focuses
                            on the design of motion graphics and has a special interest in
                            storytelling with time-based media.</p>
                    </dhq:bio>
                </dhq:authorInfo>



            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
                <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
                <!-- This information will be completed at publication -->
                <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000166</idno>
                <idno type="volume">007</idno>
                <idno type="issue">3</idno>
                <date when="2013-12-19">19 December 2013</date>
                <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
                <availability>
                    <cc:License rdf:about="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <p>This is the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
                    <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                            target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                            >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </taxonomy>
                <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
                    <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en"/>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
                    <!-- Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice -->
                    <list type="simple">
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!-- Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done. -->
            <change who="DD" when="2018-07-30">@source checking</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="en">
        <front>
            <dhq:abstract>
                <!-- Include a brief abstract of the article -->
                <p>The Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET) offers an alternative to static,
                    two-dimensional visualizations of theatrical text by modeling the process of
                    moving from text to performance in the Western, text-based tradition of live
                    theatre production. Its interface links a three-dimensional ‘Stage View’
                    populated by character avatars to a ‘Text View’ enhanced with text visualization
                    tools by means of a central ‘Line of Action’ analogous to a timeline. All three
                    parts of the interface can be edited; edits in any individual section appear in
                    the others; and all three can be played back simultaneously. While emphasizing
                    that the traditional medium of theatrical performance is the actor’s body moving
                    in time and space, and providing a digital analogue for that medium, the system
                    also frees users from the limitations of the single, time-bound spectator’s
                    perspective. Potential applications include theatre analysis, theatre pedagogy,
                    and preparation for theatrical production.</p>
            </dhq:abstract>
            <dhq:teaser>
                <p>Beyond the script: how can digital media enable uniquely theatrical uses of
                    theatrical text?</p>
            </dhq:teaser>
        </front>
        <body>
            <head>Visualizing Theatrical Text: From Watching the Script to the Simulated Environment
                for Theatre (SET)</head>
            <div>
                <head>Introduction: Visualizing Theatrical Text</head>
                <p>This paper describes the design evolution of our Simulated Environment for
                    Theatre (SET), a visualization system that conceives of theatrical text as a
                    flexible process or technology <ptr target="#worthen2010"/> occupying time and
                    three-dimensional space, rather than a fixed entity that can be captured in
                    two-dimensional media. The impetus for the project was our curiosity about how
                    digital media might enable uniquely theatrical uses of theatrical text; that is:
                    we began with the question, <q>what do scholars and artists do with scripts, and
                        can any of these things be done better in digital media than they can be
                        done in print or manuscript</q>? We are less interested in solving a problem
                    with existing uses of text than we are in extending the affordance of digital
                    media. As Brett D. Hirsch <ptr target="#hirsch2011"/> has recently pointed out,
                    digital editions of theatrical text ought to be able to do things that print
                    editions cannot do; yet to date, most digital editions of plays (largely as a
                    result of anxiety about their scholarly reception) adapt print conventions only
                    very conservatively. To describe this trend in functional terms, existing
                    digital editions of theatrical texts help readers to conduct textual
                    scholarship: to understand, analyze, interpret, and trace the bibliographic and
                    interpretive histories of printed texts; but we wondered, by contrast, how we
                    might help users conduct theatrical creation and scholarship: to analyze a text
                    for theatrical action; to conceptualize a production of a text; and to visualize
                    the relationships between text and other spatial and temporal elements that
                    function semiotically in theatrical performance. </p>
                <p>It will be obvious that our understanding of <q>theatre</q> has been grounded
                    throughout this project in the live, Western <q>dramatic</q> tradition, because
                    the role of text in that tradition is so central. Reaching all the way back to
                    Aristotle as our earliest point of reference, we think of this kind of
                    theatrical text as a means of recording a central theatrical action, a major
                    change in the world of a play, which is in process throughout a performance.
                    This action begins at a play’s beginning and ends at its end; in performance, it
                    is intelligible in the play’s plot, which is in turn expressed through the
                    arrangement of material elements of production (bodies, objects, sound, light)
                    in time and space. Aristotle’s tragedy – in performance – is hence a <quote
                        rend="inline" source="#aristotle1997">
                        <title rend="italic">mimesis</title> of an action</quote>
                    <ptr target="#aristotle1997" loc="67"/>. We have found Canadian theatre director
                    Richard Rose’s explicit application of Aristotelian analysis in production
                    particularly helpful in elucidating the role of theatrical action in a theatre
                    creation process <ptr target="#rose2009"/>. Rose describes a play’s <q>line of
                        action</q> as its organizing principle, on the basis of which all the
                    material manifestations of the performed work can be selected and deployed. He
                    encourages his directing students to define a line of action in terms of a
                    single verb that describes as precisely as possible the change in the play world
                    effected by the action between its beginning and its end. On the basis of that
                    concrete description of an overall change, directors can develop design and
                    choreographic metaphors to materialize it, and can guide actors to choices that
                    further its incremental progress from moment to moment in a production. Rose’s
                    methodology has been especially useful in illustrating for us how the Western
                        <q>dramatic</q> theatre both privileges text as a primary means of access to
                    the organizing principle of a stable work of art and also positions it in
                    performance as only one among a range of adaptable and manipulable semiotic
                    elements of production. Among contemporary theorists of theatrical text and
                    performance, Rose’s approach aligns most closely with that of William Worthen
                        <ptr target="#worthen2010"/>, who argues that this tension in the nature of
                    a theatrical text is a consequence of its simultaneous identity both as tool for
                    communicating a work of theatre and as a technology for creating it: <quote
                        rend="block" source="#worthen2010">Tools always have an immediate purpose,
                        are used to accomplish a specific task. Like tools, texts can be made to
                        function in socially accredited ways, in illicit ways, and in ways that
                        require a new technological adaptation, require us to rethink the technology
                        and the work it accomplishes. You can use a screwdriver to drive a screw, or
                        to open a paint can... Driving a screw, opening a paint can, ballasting a
                        sculpture, stealing a car, killing someone: each use of the tool engages a
                        different sociability, a different conduct of technology….the utility of
                        dramatic writing lies in the perception of what kinds of activity,
                        performance, doing something, those properties might afford in the social
                        technology of the theatre. <ptr target="#worthen2010" loc="21–22"/>
                    </quote>
                </p>
                <p>Our aim, then, in designing the SET system, has been to enable the analysis and
                    application of the technological function of theatrical text in the social
                    context of the theatre, rather than to represent any individual theatrical text,
                    material witness to it, interpretation of it, or historical perspective on it. </p>
                <p>The approach we have taken to designing SET differs considerably from our first
                    approach to theatrical text visualization, a prototype system called Watching
                    the Script, which was designed primarily as a reading tool to enhance students’
                    understanding of play-texts. In what follows here, we explain the ways in which
                    Watching the Script, despite its use of moving <q>character</q> dots on a
                        <q>stage</q> seen in ground plan, nonetheless parallels four major
                    print-based trends we have encountered in digital text visualization (we
                    categorize these as print analogy, analytic visualization, literal illustration,
                    and production illustration). Our departures from these trends in the new design
                    for SET include the system’s navigable three-dimensional Stage View, which
                    accommodates a variety of production elements linked directly to the central
                    organizing principle of a Line of Action, visualized as a kind of time line.
                    Text, which is linked to the Stage View through the Line of Action, is as
                    flexible and penetrable as any other performance phenomenon in the Stage View.
                    The interface also incorporates a set of specific sets and stages, consisting of
                    three-dimensional models of real spaces created to scale, so that the adoption
                    of the SET tool involves an awareness of an actual performance environment
                    rather than a single stylized space. Users can move avatars around in the Stage
                    View’s three-dimensional spaces and play text and action back in real time.
                    While the new design has the potential to be useful to three constituencies of
                    users – theatre researchers, theatre students, and theatre creators – our pilot
                    user study has indicated that a more intuitive interface and a broader range of
                    performance-related functions would enhance the system. In future development,
                    we are particularly interested in exploring the system’s capacity to represent
                    non-textual records of theatrical production, as well as less traditional
                    theatrical works, including works that emphasize non-textual elements of
                    performance, mediated performances, and other works that might be described as
                        <q>post-dramatic</q> theatre <ptr target="#lehmann2006"/>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Watching the Script (WTS): a two-dimensional visualization</head>
                <p>Our first prototype, Watching the Script, was conceived primarily as a reading
                    tool. Its interface visualizes theatrical text in the three Views illustrated in
                    Figure 1.</p>
                <figure>
                    <head>Our original text-centric design for Watching the Script showing a
                        visualization of Shakespeare's <title rend="italic">Romeo and
                        Juliet</title>.</head>
                    <graphic url="resources/images/figure01.png"/>

                </figure>

                <p>The <q>Overview</q> panel on the left side of the screen represents an entire
                    theatrical text in a single microtext column <ptr target="#ruecker2005"/>. The
                    Overview can be used to illustrate important structural patterns at a glance.
                    For example, each character’s lines can be rendered in a different colour to
                    illustrate the relative importance of characters in terms of line-count,
                    frequency of appearance, or presence in different parts of a play, or to reveal
                    patterns in the co-occurrence of characters that might suggest the development
                    of relationships over the play as a whole. Other tools permit users to select
                    and view patterns in scene locations and act and scene breaks.</p>
                <p>The <q>Reading View</q> panel, second to left, shows portions of the text at a
                    scale appropriate for reading; the context includes the moment currently visible
                    on the primary <q>Stage View</q> on the right. The same visualization tools
                    available in the Overview can also be applied to the Reading View, so that, for
                    example, speech headings for a character's lines are rendered in the same colour
                    used to represent that character in the Overview. Users are thereby offered
                    visual cues to help situate the textual details of a particular passage in the
                    context of the larger patterns of the play as a whole.</p>
                <p>The <q>Stage View</q> separates the text into speeches and associates them with
                    coloured dots representing the characters that deliver them. On a separate
                    interface, users can define a movement for each character-dot around a stylized
                    stage seen in ground-plan, as the text of that character's speeches scrolls; one
                    movement is possible for each speech. By liberating speeches from their
                    typographical sequence and associating them instead with mobile character dots,
                    the Stage View focuses attention on even smaller units of text and emphasizes
                    the relationship between text and speaker. Non-speaking characters remain on
                    stage, but are grayed out in order to retain focus on the current speaker. In
                    combination, the features of the Stage View create a visual argument <ptr
                        target="#galey2009"/> that the speech – the coherent, discrete utterance of
                    a single character, regardless of length – is the basic unit of a theatrical
                    text. The Stage View provides a visual metaphor for the act of speaking in
                    turns. </p>
                <p>The premise that one discrete, continuous utterance of a single character
                    (regardless of its length) is the basic unit of a theatrical work is
                    fundamentally typographical in nature. It extrapolates the aesthetic structure
                    of a theatrical text from its representation in print and manuscript
                    reproductions: because the words on a page are separated by character names, the
                    smallest unit of visual space is a complete utterance; because speeches are
                    delineated by changes in names, speeches are ontologically defined by character;
                    hence character utterances are the basic unit of a theatrical text. This
                    two-dimensional approach to visualizing theatrical text as <q>the act of
                        speaking in turns</q> is limited in obvious ways: even on its own terms, it
                    cannot represent more complex verbal interactions between characters, such as
                    overlapping dialogue or eavesdropping; but more importantly, it is not flexible
                    or sensitive enough to performance conditions to engage the technological nature
                    of theatrical text. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Watching the Script and traditional approaches to visualizing text</head>
                <p>Most digital visualizations of text – theatrical and non-theatrical – are
                    similarly concerned with the arrangement of information in configurations
                    analogous to those found in familiar material media. We have encountered four
                    major strategies or streams of approach.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Digital analogues for print editions</head>
                    <p>First, and most common, is the ubiquitous digital analogy for print or
                        manuscript most obviously represented by documents prepared using word
                        processing software. This approach imitates the visual appearance of print
                        or manuscript: the default setting of a word-processor's window in the
                        English-speaking world, for example, yields a two-dimensional image of black
                        letters arranged sequentially in lines from left to right and top to bottom
                        on a white rectangle; the relationship between words and background can be
                        set to represent the relative proportions of various fonts and margins on
                        various sizes of paper. Often the digital analogy for paper is enhanced with
                        navigational tools (such as hyperlinks, search functions, and zoom
                        features), and sometimes non-print media are embedded into paper-analogue
                        frames. YouTube is an obvious example, in which windows containing
                        time-based media appear in a two-dimensional, static white background
                        populated with black text; Sophie, a software system for creating,
                            <q>reading</q>, and annotating multimedia digital <q>books</q>
                        demonstrates a more sophisticated version of the same principle (it
                        similarly uses a static, two dimensional background with designated areas
                        for other kinds of media, including hyperlinking and collaborative authoring
                        tools); Wysiwyg Web Builder provides a 'what-you-see-is-what-you-get' system
                        for creating web pages that can also accommodate forms, PayPal, and RSS
                        functions. But these features are enhancements to print format rather than
                        violations of it, operating like traditional tables of contents, indexes,
                        annotations, or figures. Digital editions of theatrical works such as the
                        Internet Shakespeare Editions' annotated <title rend="italic">As You Like
                            It</title>
                        <ptr target="#bevington2007"/> and the Canadian Adaptations of Shakespeare
                        Project's multi-media Interactive Folio edition of <title rend="italic"
                            >Romeo and Juliet</title>
                        <ptr target="#fischlin2007"/> take advantage of opportunities like these to
                        illustrate textual variants, provide historical context, or even present
                        performance records from a range of productions. The Reading View of
                        Watching the Script also operates in this way. It divides a text into
                        passages of manageable length on a readable scale, minimally interfering
                        with the integrity of the text as a whole in order to make it more
                        accessible to readers, and in doing so maintains print's typographical
                        visualization of characters speaking in turns. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Analytic visualization </head>
                    <p>A second approach to digital text visualization deconstructs and re-assembles
                        texts to reveal patterns not visible within the confines of a single page or
                        window and then communicates the emergent patterns metaphorically in the
                        form of graphs, images, or concordances. This is essentially an analytic
                        approach to text visualization, described by Brent Nelson <ptr
                            target="#nelson2008"/> as the digital evolution of the disassembly and
                        reassembly of material artifacts that has been historically typical of
                        humanities research. An example from a theatre-related discipline is
                        ScriptGeist, a film pre-production software system that extracts mentions of
                        props, costumes, locations, and other material and logistical details from
                        scripts and re-assembles them into lists for distribution to various
                        production departments <ptr target="#mckie2007"/>. More innovative digital
                        visualizations communicate textual patterns in intuitive, challenging, and
                        aesthetically pleasing ways. Mandala, for example, a rich prospect
                            browser<note>Stan Ruecker <ptr target="#ruecker2006a"/> defines
                            rich-prospect browsing interfaces as <quote rend="inline"
                                source="#ruecker2006a">those in which some meaningful
                                representation of every item in a collection is combined with tools
                                for manipulating the display.</quote>
                        </note> for exploring text collections more intuitively than traditional
                        interfaces can, allows users to upload texts (including theatrical texts),
                        weight criteria for word-searches, and view results in circular patterns
                            <ptr target="#sinclair2009"/>. But the analytic approach nonetheless
                        maintains the analogy to print and manuscript formats. Like those formats,
                        its essential paradigm is the arrangement of information in two dimensional
                        space. It deconstructs the arrangement of words on a two dimensional page
                        and re-arranges the same words into new patterns in similar two-dimensional
                        spaces, patterns familiar from print and manuscript such as tables, figures,
                        graphs, two-dimensional images, and so on. Although the goal of re-arranging
                        the original text is to offer an alternative representation of the same
                        content, emphasizing patterns not readily discernible but nonetheless
                        present in the original text, the result of the process is an entirely new
                        text, often non-narrative or even non-syntactical in nature. </p>
                    <p>Watching the Script takes an analytic approach to visualization in its
                        Overview panel, its features for associating character and colour, and its
                        features for highlighting or excerpting certain kinds of text such as all
                        text belonging to one character. While there are clear benefits to this
                        approach, the casualties to the intended technological function of a
                        theatrical text are especially apparent in this last case: if the actor
                        playing Romeo has only his own lines for the Capulet ball scene to study, he
                        doesn’t know, for example, that he and the actor playing Juliet are together
                        speaking a sonnet, an elevated poetic form which signals that this new
                        romantic connection extends beyond the whimsical romantic intrigues of
                        Romeo’s past (1.4.206-223). Analytic visualization reduces rather than
                        enhances the intended functionality of a theatrical text as a theatre
                        technology. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Literal illustration</head>
                    <p>A third common approach to digital visualization of both theatrical and
                        non-theatrical texts participates in the long tradition of literalizing
                        images described in or suggested by a text. Sometimes the elements
                        illustrated are individual characters, objects, or events, as in Michael
                        Lahanas' interpretive drawing of the shield of Achilles posted with a
                        translation of Homer’s description of it from book 18 of the Iliad <ptr
                            target="#lahanas2006"/>. Sometimes literal illustrations are symbolic or
                        emblematic schemas synthesizing a variety of moments or ideas in a single
                        two-dimensional frame, visual <q>confections</q>, to use Edward Tufte’s term
                            <ptr target="#tufte1998"/>, such as the promotional posters for Baz
                        Luhrmann's Romeo + Juliet <ptr target="#bazmark1996"/>. A third strategy
                        selects and extracts a sequence of events or movements of characters or
                        objects as described or implied by a text, and plots them through
                        two-dimensional space over time, providing a kind of kinetic summary of a
                        textual work. Homer’s Trojan Theatre, for example, allows users to watch
                        icons representing ships and armies move through the of battles of the
                        Trojan war on a simplified map almost in ground-plan <ptr target="#clay2007"
                        />. Since they re-organize their originals, we might even think of these
                        latter two forms of literal illustration as literal, illustrative analytics.
                        Multi-media illustrations -- movie trailers, for example -- often combine
                        literal illustrative techniques to create analytic, kinetic confections.
                        Most software designed to assist in motion picture pre-visualization or
                        storyboarding operates as illustration: images representing shooting
                        locations defined in the equivalent of stage directions, and sometimes also
                        the arrangement of characters against these backgrounds, are organized in
                        visual sequences analogous to the traditional storyboards used to plan the
                        visual progression of a film. One example of such software is Celtx <ptr
                            target="#celtx2010"/>; FrameForge Previz Studio <ptr
                            target="#schafer2010"/> is a more sophisticated version, incorporating
                        3-D images embedded in two-dimensional frames; and the movie-making
                        simulation game <title rend="italic">Moviestorm</title>
                        <ptr target="#moviestorm2012"/> operates on similar principles. </p>
                    <p>The Stage View in Watching the Script attempts a limited stylized
                        literalization of textual images in its association of character dots with
                        characters’ speeches. In supplanting the typographical arrangement of the
                        text it represents, it, like other literal visualizations, distorts its
                        source text at the same time as enriching and augmenting it. Magnificent
                        though a drawing of Achilles' shield can be, it cannot capture the lines and
                        letters that indicate the rhythms and other sound-patterns of Homer's verse
                        and through them the connotative visceral and intellectual meanings
                        essential to the work as a whole. Nor, taken out of context, can a drawing
                        of the shield effect the sudden shift in a reader's imaginative experience
                        from syntagmatic progress through the epic to paradigmatic expansion of the
                        lyric moment in which the symbolic object is encountered. On the other hand,
                        the visualization adds specificity and detail not necessarily included in
                        the original, and helps a novice reader understand the detail that is
                        included in it. Similarly, animated maps and movie trailers do not
                        necessarily aim to create rich epic or theatrical experiences of the
                        inexorable accumulation of horrors – visitations from gods, violations of
                        the bodies of heroes, illicit sexual encounters, murders of cousins,
                        concealment in tombs, resurrections from the dead; instead, their concerns
                        are traffic patterns and release dates. </p>
                    <p>Any literal, illustrative approach to text visualization can represent a part
                        or an analysis or an interpretation of a printed textual work, demonstrably
                        faithful to something in the original work, whether that be its material
                        appearance (type, page, layout) or its contents (word, commentary, image,
                        event, pattern), or both. No method of literal illustration of a theatrical
                        text can faithfully represent a work of theatre, however, neither its
                        material appearance nor its contents. Theatrical text is clearly intended to
                        lead to a visualization of some kind, a material manifestation of something
                        suggested by the text, but not to a literal visualization of the world of
                        the play. Rather, a theatrical text is intended to lead to another material
                        manifestation of the work, a theatrical production in which characters
                        embodied by living actors move around on a three-dimensional stage in real
                        time and space before an audience. That visualization is in turn intended to
                        suggest the world and action of the play, making the work of theatre
                        imaginatively present in the minds of an audience. Since theatrical texts
                        rarely literally describe stages, but instead describe the fictions that
                        staging is in turn intended to describe, a literal illustration of a
                        theatrical texts skips over its performativity altogether; it treats text
                        not as a performance technology, but as another, non-technological form of
                            literature.<note> There are exceptions, of course. 'Closet dramas', for
                            example, are not intended for performance. Some theatrical texts are
                            choreographic rather than verbal: Samuel Beckett's Act without words
                                <ptr target="#beckett1958"/> is a canonical example by a playwright
                            deeply engaged in language. George Bernard Shaw's stage directions
                            notoriously define the appearance of his characters in terms unlikely to
                            be reproducible except in the physiognomy of actors; see Man and
                            Superman <ptr target="#shaw2000"/>, for example. </note> To the extent
                        that theatrical texts are intended for performance, they, unlike other kinds
                        of texts, require the addition of representational elements other than those
                        that can be supplied imaginatively by readers. Even a theatrical work whose
                        primary mode of expression is verbal must necessarily incorporate elements
                        other than text. Literal illustration alters theatrical text at the
                        ontological level. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Production illustration</head>
                    <p>In response to this challenge, modern print and digital editions take a
                        fourth approach to visualizing theatrical text, incorporating images of
                        theatrical production rather than literal illustrations of the text. Jill L.
                        Levenson's introduction to the recent Oxford edition of <title rend="italic"
                            >Romeo and Juliet</title>
                        <ptr target="#shakespeare2000"/>, for example, includes eight illustrations
                        of stage productions and two of films <ptr target="#zeffirelli1968"/>, <ptr
                            target="#lurhmann1996"/>. Other print series such as Cambridge's
                        Shakespeare in Production interpolate notes on and images of stage
                        production into the text itself (see <ptr target="#shakespeare2002"/>). The
                        online Internet Shakespeare Editions provides a broader collection of
                        records in a searchable database embedded in a separate section of the site;
                        it functions somewhat like an appendix to the text <ptr
                            target="#prescott2009"/>. A number of Peter S. Donaldson's projects,
                        including the <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Electronic Archive</title>,
                            <title rend="italic">Shakespeare in Asia</title>, <title rend="italic"
                            >Hamlet on the Ramparts</title>, and his Cross-Media Annotation System
                        (XMAS) explore new ways of linking and integrating performance records and
                        texts <ptr target="#donaldson2011a"/>, <ptr target="#donaldson2011b"/>, <ptr
                            target="#mit"/>. By representing a variety of productions in relation to
                        an individual text, these approaches to visualization implicitly acknowledge
                        that no individual illustration of an individual production should be
                        privileged. Accepting the premise that different productions of <title
                            rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title> can represent the same work, they
                        provide a variety of alternative visualizations for comparison.</p>
                    <p>Nonetheless, no group of contrasting production records can be said to
                        visualize the work any more than any individual production record does.
                        Production records participate in the same conventions as other material
                        media, and perhaps more importantly, by providing a set of alternative
                        illustrations for the same single text, groups of contrasting production
                        records privilege the printed text as the locus of the work. Even editions
                        that include extended representations of alternate texts (see Levenson's
                        inclusion of the entire first Quarto of <title rend="italic">Romeo and
                            Juliet</title>
                        <ptr target="#shakespeare2000"/>, for example, or the Internet Shakespeare
                        Editions' inclusion of early variants of the plays <ptr target="#best2005"
                        />) treat texts as coherent entities derived from print sources. Production
                        records, on the other hand, are fragmented excerpts, arguing that coherence
                        lies outside or between those records rather than in any individual
                        production that may be represented by one or another of them. Visualized in
                        this way, the theatrical work is still, ultimately, conceived as a complete
                        and stable textual entity. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Re-visualizing theatrical text</head>
                <p>Watching the Script, our initial prototype for visualizing theatrical text,
                    employs methods of visualization analogous to those used in familiar material
                    media in its Stage View; consequently, it cannot visualize the technological
                    nature of theatrical text. To create a digital visualization of theatrical text
                    without misrepresenting its defining characteristic, we have attempted instead
                    to visualize the process of moving from text to performance. </p>
                <div>
                    <head>Precedents</head>
                    <p>There are some precedents for a technological approach to visualizing
                        theatrical text in digital media. Michael Best, Stewart Arneil, and Martin
                        Holmes' Scenario <ptr target="#best2002"/> enables students to create
                        blocking tableaux of scenes from Shakespeare's plays by placing characters
                        in fixed positions on a two-dimensional perspective-drawing of a stage
                        similar to the Globe theatre. Each frame can be annotated with explanatory
                        notes. Larry Friedlander's TheatreGame <ptr target="#friedlander1991"/>
                        allows students to make audio recordings of scenes, program synchronized
                        stage action in a 2.5D graphical interface (a pseudo 3D or ¾ perspective
                        such as that used commonly in first-person shooter computer games), and play
                        back the virtual 'scene' created. Both systems acknowledge the spatial
                        medium of theatrical performance by offering a visual analogue for
                        three-dimensional space; Scenario invests more fully in the specificity of
                        the performance space, whereas TheatreGame acknowledges time as a
                        performance medium. Both also engage users in activities that imitate a
                        theatre artist's evolving use of theatrical space through a rehearsal
                        process, Scenario emphasizing the analytical and interpretive activities of
                        a director in its annotation function, and TheatreGame emphasizing the
                        actor's work by having students record audio performances of scenes. Credo
                        Interactive's DanceForms system for choreographing dance implies a
                        relationship between tools and technologies of performance by presenting a
                        view of a choreographic record in the same interface as a view of avatars
                        executing the choreography <ptr target="#credo2009"/>. However, none of
                        these systems makes an explicit visual argument about the nature of the
                        relationship between theatrical text and performance in its interface
                        design. </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>The Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET)</head>
                    <p>Our new prototype adopts some of the same principles as these systems, but
                        offers a different range of functions in response to our thinking about the
                        nature of theatrical text. The Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET) is
                        shown in Figure 2. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>Our re-visualized three-dimensional Simulated Environment for Theatre
                            (SET) emphasizes the line of action rather than the text, and situates
                            the characters on scale models of actual venues and sets. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure02.png"/>

                    </figure>



                    <p>SET offers a centrally-placed visualization of a line of action in the form
                        of a horizontal image analogous to a timeline. The Line of Action links a
                        Reading View in the lower half of the screen to a Stage View consisting of a
                        three-dimensional scale model of an actual venue and set populated by
                        abstracted character avatars in the upper half of the screen. The user’s
                        agency is emphasized in that users can upload, edit, and annotate all
                        aspects of the Stage View, Line of Action, and Reading View, including the
                        texts and stage and set models used, and the movements of
                            <soCalled>characters</soCalled> on the stage. The Line of Action can be
                        broken down by users into smaller units of action, ranging in size from acts
                        to scenes to French scenes (delineated by the entrance or exit of a
                        character) to speeches to individual <q>beats</q> of dramatic action. Users
                        define divisions between units of action by associating them with words,
                        stage directions, or intervals between words and stage directions in the
                        Reading View, or with character movements in the Stage View. All three views
                        can be edited in the main interface; edits made in one view affect the
                        others; and all three views scroll simultaneously during playback. In other
                        words, the system treats units of action, rather than individual characters'
                        speeches, as the basic units of the works visualized. </p>
                    <p>In each individual view, additional features serve the new paradigm. The
                        Reading View shifts primary ontological integrity to the line of action
                        rather than the text. The text in the Reading View can be cut, augmented
                        with stage business, expanded with textual additions, and annotated; but any
                        and all of these alterations are linked to (and hence metaphorically
                        justified by) actions in the continuous Line of Action. The Reading View
                        also emphasizes the embodied nature of text by placing it next to a
                        Character Panel, which visualizes the presence or absence of characters
                        during the passage shown in the Text Panel, whether they are speaking or
                        silent. Our revised Stage View attempts to visualize the materialization of
                        a theatrical text in fuller and more concrete terms than our first model
                        did. Instead of offering a map-like aerial view of hypothetical
                        traffic-patterns, our new Stage View uses three-dimensional models of actual
                        theatre spaces.<note>Some forms of non-traditional theatre are produced in
                            vertical audience-performer orientations: in the Argentinian dance
                            theatre company De La Guarda's 2010 touring show, for example, the
                            audience stands in the centre of a large room while performers travel up
                            the walls and across the ceiling; and some of Australian-based
                            performance artist STELARC's early work involved hanging his own body
                            from meat-hooks suspended from a ceiling or outdoor structure, with
                            audience looking up from below (photographs are available on both
                            artists' web sites) <ptr target="#stelarc1994"/>. But these were
                            nonetheless both embodied performances presented in relationship to
                            architectural spaces of some kind.</note> Models are populated by
                        abstract, three-dimensional avatars representing five classes of beings:
                        adults, children, babies, large animals, and small animals, as shown in
                        Figure 3. Each has a <q>nose</q> to indicate the direction in which it is
                        facing. The avatars are distinguished from one another by colours keyed to
                        names in the Character Panel, and their user-defined movements are
                        optionally visualized in colour-coded <q>paths</q> showing each character's
                        progress and stopping-points <ptr target="#ruecker2013"/>. Speeches also
                        appear in the Stage View, in colour-coded bubbles, visually associating
                        characters' bodies and voices. Alterations to the Stage View are, like
                        alterations to the Reading View, linked to the Line of Action.</p>

                    <figure>
                        <head>SET provides five classes of avatars with noses: adults, children,
                            babies, large animals, and small animals.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure03.png"/>

                    </figure>
                    <p>An additional advantage of the new model is that it permits users to move
                        through three-dimensional space to view the stage or the audience from a
                        variety of perspectives, including actors' perspectives, as demonstrated in
                        Figures 4, 5 and 6. So the system can represent the multiple perspectives of
                        audience members in different parts of the theatre, a phenomenon that must
                        be accounted for both in planning and in analyzing theatrical production.
                        The Stage Map in the upper right corner can be used to define predetermined
                        viewpoints, for ease of navigation. </p>

                    <figure>
                        <head>SET permits users to view theatre spaces from any point in the
                            audience. This is a view from house left. The viewing position is
                            highlighted in yellow and red on the Stage Map at upper right.
                            Alternative viewing positions are visible on the Stage Map in
                            grey.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure04.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <figure>
                        <head>This is a view from house right. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure05.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <figure>
                        <head>SET permits users to adopt the perspectives of performers. Here, we
                            see through the eyes of the actor playing Juliet.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure06.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <p>Finally, the visual emphasis on any individual element of the interface is
                        determined by the user, by adjusting the sizes and positions of panes, as
                        shown in Figure 7. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>With the Character Panel and Stage View minimized, and the tear-away
                            option for text panels utilized, this user-defined configuration of the
                            SET interface emphasizes text.</head>
                        <graphic url="./resources/images/figure07.png"/>

                    </figure>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Next steps: usage cases, usability, and multiple modalities</head>
                <p>During the first stage of development of the SET system, we conducted a pilot
                    usability study with scholars as participants <ptr target="#roberts-smith2010"/>
                    and consulted informally with theatre creators about the system’s potential
                    applications. In our next phase of development, we are exploring potential
                    differences in the needs of the three constituencies of users we envision for
                    the SET system – theatre researchers, theatre students, and theatre creators —
                    and experimenting with new functions tailored to each group's needs. We are
                    assessing new functions and design ideas in a full-scale user study with twenty
                    participants who have advanced expertise in one or more of our three target
                    fields. Our methodology combines recording participants’ interactions with the
                    SET interface <ptr target="#nielsen2000"/> and conducting semi-structured
                    interviews <ptr target="#guha2005"/> that include questions about the potential
                    for the tool to be an important resource for participants in future <ptr
                        target="#ruecker2006b"/>. The findings of our study will be integrated with
                    our ongoing participatory design process, which includes interactions between
                    designers, programmers and domain experts who are themselves potential end users
                    of the system <ptr target="#gabriele2010"/>.</p>
                <div>
                    <head>Usage cases and usability</head>
                    <p>There are four main areas of focus to this new phase of development. For
                        theatre researchers, we have added an annotation function that permits users
                        to transparently acknowledge and document their research sources, as
                        illustrated in Figure 8. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>A visualization of the University of Waterloo Drama program’s 2008
                            production of Shakespeare’s <title rend="italic">Julius Caesar</title>,
                            directed by Jennifer Roberts-Smith, annotated with technical drawings of
                            the university’s Theatre of the Arts and an image of the maquette of
                            William Chesney’s design for the production’s set. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure08.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <p>Because our research-oriented usage case makes non-textual performance
                        records explicit, we have come to think of it as a historiographical
                        iteration of SET <ptr target="#roberts-smith2013a"/>. For students of
                        theatre, by contrast, we are conscious of the need to embed pedagogical
                        guidance into the design of the system, so that students’ experience as
                        users is a learning activity in itself. In our first tentative exploration
                        of a pedagogical iteration of SET, we have analyzed the ways in which our
                        current design implicitly guides users through the process of answering a
                        theatre-historical research question <ptr target="#roberts-smith2013b"/>, by
                        first presenting users with an empty environment to which theatre-historical
                        records must be added before the records can be interpreted in a
                        visualization like the one shown in Figure 8 above. This step-by-step
                        process is illustrated in Figures 9, 10, and 11. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>The empty SET. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure09.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <figure>
                        <head>Empty SET and source: the technical drawings for the Theatre of the
                            Arts. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure10.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <figure>
                        <head>SET, source, and visual interpretation of the source: our model of the
                            Theatre of the Arts. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure11.png"/>

                    </figure>
                    <p>We hope to develop our pedagogical usage case into an iteration that can
                        guide students through a process of theatrical text and performance
                        analysis, as well as theatre-historical research. We are beginning to
                        develop our third, creation-oriented usage case by re-imagining our avatars
                        as sketching tools for theatre directors to use in preparation for
                        rehearsal. This process is taking the form of an open-ended, iterative
                        movement back and forth between an analysis of preparatory sketches in
                        Richard Rose’s rehearsal scripts <ptr target="#rose2011"/> and the SET
                        team’s collaborative generation and review of a range of potential
                        approaches to visualizing the creative functions of Rose’s sketches. We have
                        come to think of this design methodology as a <cit><quote rend="inline"
                            source="#gabriele2013">research discourse of alterity</quote>
                        <ptr target="#gabriele2013"/></cit>; it is typical of our development process to
                        date. Lastly, the fourth strand of our current exploration of use cases and
                        usability addresses the more intuitive interface that was indicated as a
                        priority by participants in our pilot user study. To that end, we have begun
                        to explore the potential applications of game interface design to our system
                            <ptr target="#roberts-smith2012"/>, and we are seeking responses to our
                        initial re-conceptions of the interface, along with our approaches to
                        research annotation, pedagogical organization, and creation-oriented avatar
                        design, in our user study.</p>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <head>Multiple modalities and digital performance editions </head>
                    <p>In addition to these four main areas of focus, however, we are also exploring
                        an interesting theoretical question that arose during the first stage of SET
                        development, namely: can non-textual records of production be visualized as
                        elements of a technological process, like theatrical texts, or are their
                        modalities different enough to warrant a different approach to
                        visualization? It is obvious, for example, that some records – such as a set
                        design like William Chesney’s in Figure 8 — are intended to directly to lead
                        to material manifestations that we might think of as literal illustrations
                        of their contents. Since they are not necessarily used literally, however
                        (for example, the set actually built for the University of Waterloo
                        production of <title rend="italic">Julius Caesar</title> made a significant
                        change to the horizon line indicated in the set model), they may arguably
                        become technological in the process of their application. Other production
                        records – such as Richard Rose’s pre-rehearsal sketches – are designed to be
                        technological, since they record the deployment of material production
                        elements whose spatial and temporal semiotics can be analyzed for theatrical
                        action <ptr target="#rose2011"/>. Still other records operate primarily as
                        production illustrations, as do production photographs that record moments
                        in a live performance event (though these need to be carefully distinguished
                        from publicity photographs, which are often artificially set up during
                        dedicated photo shoots). Lastly, a final category of production records seem
                        to intend a hybrid of literal, technological, and illustrative/documentary
                        functions. Our curiosity about this final category of record has led to some
                        tentative experimentation inside the SET system with the well-known map
                        appended to the only surviving manuscript copy of the medieval morality
                        play, <title rend="italic">The Castle of Perseverance</title>
                        <ptr target="#castle"/>, shown in Figure 12. It records a set design, which
                        apparently is not only intended for future literal materialization, but also
                        describes possible alternative future materializations, as well as seeming
                        to record how the set was built in a particular past performance. The map’s
                        stage directions seem similarly intended for future technological
                        application while simultaneously recording how the play has already been
                        staged. </p>

                    <figure>
                        <head>The Castle of Perseverance Map.</head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure12.png"/>

                    </figure>


                    <p>Figures 13 and 14 show our early experiments in visualizing the multiple
                        modalities of this text in the SET system. </p>
                    <figure>
                        <head>A visualization distinguishing between some of the Castle of
                            Perseverance Map’s technological and literal functions while maintaining
                            its integrity as a single research source in SET’s Stage View (2D for
                            technological function; 3D for literal illustration). </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure13.png"/>

                    </figure>

                    <figure>
                        <head>A visualization distributing some of the different functional
                            modalities of the Castle of Perseverance Map into different areas of the
                            SET interface. </head>
                        <graphic url="resources/images/figure14.png"/>

                    </figure>



                    <p>These initial, incomplete experiments have opened a new avenue of inquiry for
                        us, namely: might it be possible to conceive of an entirely new approach to
                        editing plays as digital performance editions? By performance
                            <emph>edition</emph>, we mean a visualization that takes on the
                        traditional responsibilities of communicating the transmission and
                        interpretive histories of a text, as well as acknowledging its extant
                        material witnesses, without sacrificing access to its technological
                        functions. How might we acknowledge the multiple modalities of our research
                        sources, their historical development, and their continuing present
                        technological instability, all in the same virtual space?</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Conclusion: scope and ambition</head>
                <p>SET's new approach to visualizing theatre allows users to engage with the process
                    of analyzing a theatrical text for action and materializing action through
                    embodied movement in time and space. Each tool (text, space, character, and so
                    on) is concrete and specific, but is also treated as a participant in the
                    technology of the theatre through its relationships both to other tools and to
                    the organizing principle governing the deployment of them in an individual work
                    of theatre. That technology is further represented as active and processual,
                    generated at all levels by the user through his or her selection and deployment
                    of the tools of production. Design challenges now centre on integrating the
                    theoretical premises and visual arguments made by the system with the needs and
                    interests of users in three primary user-groups — theatre scholars, students,
                    and creators — working in the live, Western, text-based tradition. </p>
                <p>The current version of SET has some flexibility for representing works that fall
                    outside this tradition. An Aristotelian understanding of theatre as dramatic
                    action need not be limited to works whose <q>emphatic production element</q> —
                    the element that bears proportionally the highest level of responsibility for
                    generating theatrical action <ptr target="#rose2009"/> — is words. We might as
                    easily have a prop-based tradition or a sound-based tradition as a text-based
                    tradition of theatre, as long as these elements of production generate embodied
                    action in space over time. (Samuel Beckett's <title rend="italic">Breath</title>
                    <ptr target="#beckett1974"/>, which has no actors at all, is an example of a
                    form such a prop- and sound-based tradition might take.) The verbal text in
                    SET’s Reading View could hypothetically be replaced by a musical score or a
                    choreographic record or a storyboard. Similarly, users could begin by moving
                    visualizations of characters around in the Stage View and define a line of
                    action based on these visual patterns. Since the system will accept any
                    consistent three-dimensional model of a stage space and/or set, any individual
                    line of action might also be viewed against two or more venues; any venue or set
                    model might be viewed against a number of different texts. This flexibility
                    offers the opportunity to analyze the impact of changes in the deployment of
                    individual production elements upon our perception of a particular line of
                    action, the impact of a change in technological application, in Worthen's terms,
                    of textual and non-textual theatrical elements. SET also offers some freedoms
                    from the hermetic linearity of Aristotelian theatre. Although its timeline
                    provides a linear perspective, users can also move forwards and backwards in
                    time, focus on individual moments or individual characters, visualize
                    choreographic traffic-patterns over time, and access multiple audience and
                    performer viewpoints, rather than being limited to the single, time-bound
                    viewpoint of the live spectator.</p>
                <p>Among the limitations we acknowledge in the current design of the system, is the
                    fact that it does not represent works of theatre that take non-Aristotelian
                    forms. Our singular Line of Action, for example, may not be adequate to
                    represent the multiple, simultaneous actions in a medieval mystery cycle, or the
                    cyclical action in a work like Beckett’s Play <ptr target="#beckett1970"/>.
                    Additionally, since the system takes virtual, three-dimensional space as an
                    analogy for material space, it cannot account for performances that originate in
                    virtual environments, nor can it accommodate multi-media performance elements
                    such as video projections in its virtual sets. Furthermore, since those sets are
                    treated as hermetic fictional worlds, the system is only relevant to works that
                    do not participate in the <q>post-dramatic</q>
                    <ptr target="#lehmann2006"/> interest in interactive performance environments,
                    whether live, as in the work of such such artists as <title rend="italic">Improv
                        Everywhere</title>
                    <ptr target="#improv"/>; mediated, as in Stern and Mateas’ <q>one-act
                        interactive drama</q>, <title rend="italic">Façade</title>
                    <ptr target="#stern2005"/>; or in the hybrid forms of such theatrical marketing
                    games as 42 Entertainment’s <title rend="italic">I Love Bees</title>
                    <ptr target="#entertainment2004"/> or <title rend="italic">Year Zero</title>
                    <ptr target="#entertainment2007"/>. Consequently, in addition to our short-term
                    interests in developing usage cases, enhancing the system’s usability, and
                    exploring the possibility of a digital performance edition, a longer-term
                    ambition of the SET research team is to consider how – or even whether –
                    constructions of theatricality in non-Aristotelian forms might be visualized in
                    digital media.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Acknowledgments</head>
                <p>We gratefully acknowledge the support of the Social Sciences and Humanities
                    Research Council of Canada. Thanks also to our anonymous reviewers for their
                    extremely helpful suggestions; to Peter S. Donaldson for directing our attention
                    to some other digital systems for visualizing theatre; to Cassandra Silver for
                    introducing us to 42 Entertainment; and to participants in the Implementing New
                    Knowledge Environments 2009 Birds of a Feather Conference for their comments on
                    an earlier draft of this paper. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <listBibl>
                <bibl label="42 Entertainment 2004" xml:id="entertainment2004"
                    key="entertainment2004">42 Entertainment (2004). <title rend="italic">I Love
                        Bees</title> [online]. Microsoft Corporation, Aug. 2004. Available from:
                        <ref target="http://ilovebees.com">http://ilovebees.com</ref> [Accessed 22
                    Feb. 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="42 Entertainment 2007" xml:id="entertainment2007"
                    key="entertainment2007">42 Entertainment (2007). <title rend="italic">Year
                        Zero</title> [online]. Nine Inch Nails, 12 Feb. 2007. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.42entertainment.com/">www.42entertainment.com</ref>
                    [Accessed 22 Feb. 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Aristotle 1997" xml:id="aristotle1997" key="aristotle1997">Aristotle,
                    1997. <title rend="italic">Aristotle’s Poetics</title>. George Whalley, trans.
                    John Baxter, ed. Montreal: McGill-Queen’s University Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bazmark Films 1996" xml:id="bazmark1996" key="bazmark1996">Bazmark
                    Films and Twentieth Century Fox Film Corporation, 1996. Posters for Romeo +
                    Juliet. In: <title rend="italic">Romeo + Juliet</title>. Internet Movie Database
                    [online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0117509/posters"
                        >http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0117509/posters</ref> [Accessed 11 January
                    2011].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Beckett 1958" xml:id="beckett1958" key="beckett1958">Beckett, S., 1958.
                        <title rend="italic">Act without words: a mime for one player. Endgame, a
                        play.</title> New York: Grove Press. 85-91. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Beckett 1970" xml:id="beckett1970" key="beckett1970a">Beckett, S.,
                    1970. <title rend="quotes">Play.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Cascando and other short dramatic pieces.</title> New York:
                    Grove Press. 43-63.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Beckett 1974" xml:id="beckett1974" key="beckett1974">Beckett, 1974.
                    Breath. <title rend="italic">First Love and Other Shorts.</title> New York:
                    Grove Press. 89.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Best 2005" xml:id="best2005" key="best2005">Best, M., 2005. <title
                        rend="quotes">About the Internet Shakespeare Editions.</title> Internet
                    Shakespeare Editions [online]. University of Victoria. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/"
                        >http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca</ref> [Accessed 13 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Best, Arneil and Holmes 2002" xml:id="best2002" key="best2002">Best,
                    M., Arneil, S., and Holmes, M., 2002. Scenario. <title rend="italic">Half-Baked
                        Software.</title> University of Victoria Computer-Aided Language Learning
                    Laboratory.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Bevington, ed. 2007" xml:id="bevington2007" key="bevington2007"
                    >Bevington, D., ed., 2007. William Shakespeare. <title rend="italic">As You Like
                        It</title> (Modern). In: Michael Best, gen. ed. 2009. Internet Shakespeare
                    Editions [online]. University of Victoria. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/"
                        >http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca</ref> [Accessed 13 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Castle of Perseverance" xml:id="castle" key="castle">[The <title
                        rend="italic">Castle of Perseverance</title> Map.] <title rend="italic">The
                        Castle of Perseverance</title>. Ca. 1440. MS. Folger Shakespeare Library,
                    Washington. Shelfmark V.a.354. 191v. Image ID 120742. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Celtx 2010" xml:id="celtx2010" key="celtx2010">Celtx [online], 2010.
                    Available from: <ref target="http://celtx.com/">http://celtx.com</ref> [Accessed
                    13 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Clay and Kenan 2007" xml:id="clay2007" key="clay2007">Clay, J. S. and
                    Kenan, W. R., 2007. <title rend="italic">Homer's Trojan Theatre</title>
                    [online]. Institute for Advanced Technology in the Humanities, University of
                    Virginia. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.homerstrojantheater.org/index.html"
                        >http://www.homerstrojantheater.org/index.html</ref> [Accessed 13 July
                    2010]. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Credo Interactive 2009" xml:id="credo2009" key="credo2009">Credo
                    Interactive, 2009. DanceForms. Credo Interactive [online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://charactermotion.com/index.html"
                        >http://charactermotion.com/index.html</ref> [Accessed 23 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Credo Interactive" xml:id="credo" key="credo">Credo Interactive, n.d.
                    LifeForms. Credo Interactive [online]. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://charactermotion.com/index.html"
                        >http://charactermotion.com/index.html</ref> [Accessed 23 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="DeSouza-Coehlo and Roberts-Smith 2012" xml:id="roberts-smith2012"
                    key="roberts-smith2012">DeSouza-Coelho, S., Roberts-Smith, J. et al. <title
                        rend="quotes">Control Freaks: An Iterative Story of Designing a Scholarly
                        Environment in 3D.</title> Society for Digital Humanities/Société pur
                    l'étude des médias interactifs, Congress, May 26-28, 2012.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Donaldson 2011a" xml:id="donaldson2011a" key="donaldson2011a"
                    >Donaldson, P. S., <title rend="italic">Shakespeare Performance in Asia</title>
                    [online]. Available from: [Accessed 11 January 2011].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Donaldson 2011b" xml:id="donaldson2011b" key="donaldson2011b"
                    >Donaldson. <title rend="italic">Cross-Media Annotation System</title> [online].
                    Available from: [Accessed 11 January 2011].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Fischlin 2007" xml:id="fischlin2007" key="fischlin2007">Fischlin, D.,
                    2007. <title rend="italic">Interactive Folio. Canadian Adaptations of
                        Shakespeare Project</title> [online]. University of Guelph. Available from:
                        <ref target="http://www.canadianshakespeares.ca/folio/folio.html"
                        >http://www.canadianshakespeares.ca/folio/folio.html</ref> [Accessed 13 July
                    2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Friedlander 1991" xml:id="friedlander1991" key="friedlander1991"
                    >Friedlander, L., 1991. <title rend="quotes">The Shakespeare Project:
                        Experiments in Multimedia.</title> In: George Landow and Paul Delany, eds.
                        <title rend="italic">Hypermedia and Literary Studies</title>. Cambridge: MIT
                    Press. 257-71.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gabriele 2010" xml:id="gabriele2010" key="gabriele2010">Gabriele, S.,
                    et al. 2010. <title rend="quotes">From Surface to Space: Adding a Dimension to a
                        Theatrical Visualization Interface.</title> Society for Digital
                    Humanities/Congress of the Humanities and Social Sciences. Montreal, May
                    2010.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Gabriele and Ruecker 2013" xml:id="gabriele2013" key="gabriele2013"
                    >Gabriele, S. and Ruecker, S., forthcoming 2013. <title rend="quotes">The
                        Emergent Discourse of Alterity in the Extended Collaborative Making of the
                        Simulated Environment for Theatre.</title> Designa 2013 International
                    Conference on Design Research, Universidade da Beira Interior, Portugal, 21-22
                    November 2013.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Galey and Ruecker 2009" xml:id="galey2009" key="galey2009">Galey, A.
                    and Ruecker, S., 2009. <title rend="quotes">Design as a Hermeneutic Process:
                        Thinking Through Making from Book History to Critical Design.</title>
                    Digital Humanities 2009 Conference, University of Maryland, June 22-25,
                    2009.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Guha and Saraf 2005" xml:id="guha2005" key="guha2005">Guha, T. K. and
                    Saraf, V., <title rend="quotes">OPAC usability: Assessment through verbal
                        protocol.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Electronic Library. </title>23.4 (2005): 463–473.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Hirsch 2011" xml:id="hirsch2011" key="hirsch2011">Hirsch, Brett D.,
                    2011. <title rend="quotes">The Kingdom Has Been Digitized: Electronic Editions
                        of Renaissance Drama and the Long Shadows of Shakespeare and Print</title>.
                        <title rend="italic">Literature Compass</title> [online] 8 (9): 568-591.
                    Available from: <ref
                        target="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/lico.2011.8.issue-9/issuetoc"
                        >http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/lico.2011.8.issue-9/issuetoc</ref>
                    [Accessed 27 September 2012].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Improv Everywhere" xml:id="improv" key="improv">
                    <title rend="italic">Improv Everywhere | We Cause Scenes</title> [online].
                    Everywhere Productions, Inc., 5 Feb. 2013. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://improveverywhere.com">http://improveverywhere.com</ref>
                    [Accessed 22 Feb. 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Lahanas 2006" xml:id="lahanas2006" key="lahanas2006">Lahanas, M., 2006.
                        <title rend="italic">The Shield of Achilles.</title> Hellenica [online].
                    Available from: <ptr
                        target="http://www.mlahanas.de/Greeks/Mythology/AchillesShield.html"/>
                    [Accessed 13 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Lehmann 2006" xml:id="lehmann2006" key="lehmann2006">Lehmann, H.-T.,
                    2006. <title rend="italic">Postdramatic Theatre.</title> Trans. Karen
                    Jürs-Munby. London: Routledge.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Lurhmann 1996" xml:id="lurhmann1996" key="lurhmann1996">Lurhmann, Baz.
                        <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>. Starring: Kate Winslet,
                    Leonardo DiCaprio. Twentieth Century Fox. Film. 1996.</bibl>

                <bibl label="McKie 2007" xml:id="mckie2007" key="mckie2007">McKie, S., 2007.
                    ScriptGeist [online]. Available from: <ref target="http://www.scriptgeist.com/"
                        >http://www.scriptgeist.com</ref> [Accessed 13 July 2010]. </bibl>
                <bibl label="MIT Shakespeare Project" xml:id="mit" key="mit">MIT Shakespeare Project
                    [online]. Massachusetts Institute for Technology. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://web.mit.edu/shakspere/index.html"
                        >http://web.mit.edu/shakspere/index.html</ref> [Accessed 23 July 2010]. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Moviestorm Ltd. 2012" xml:id="moviestorm2012" key="moviestorm2012"
                    >Moviestorm Ltd., 2012. <title rend="quotes">The Virtual Movie Studio.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Moviestorm </title>[online]. Moviestorm Ltd., 2012.
                    Available from: <ref target="http://www.moviestorm.co.uk/hub/home"
                        >http://www.moviestorm.co.uk/hub/home</ref> [Accessed 13 April 2012]. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Nelson 2008" xml:id="nelson2008" key="nelson2008">Nelson, B., 2008.
                        <title rend="quotes">Introduction: Reassembling the Disassembled
                        Book.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">CHWP</title> (2008), rptd. <title rend="italic">Digital
                        Studies/Le champ numérique</title> 0.12 (2008) [online], 1. Available from:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/issue/view/12"
                        >http://www.digitalstudies.org/ojs/index.php/digital_studies/issue/view/12</ref>
                    [accessed 25 February 2013].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Nielsen 2000" xml:id="nielsen2000" key="nielsen2000">Nielsen, Jakob.
                    2000. <title rend="italic">Designing Web Usability: the practice of
                        simplicity</title>. Indianapolis, IN: New Riders. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Prescott 2009" xml:id="prescott2009" key="prescott2009">Prescott, P.,
                    2009. <title rend="quotes">Shakespeare in Performance.</title> In: Michael Best,
                    gen. ed. 2009. <title rend="italic">Internet Shakespeare Editions</title>
                    [online]. University of Victoria. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca/"
                        >http://internetshakespeare.uvic.ca</ref> [Accessed 21 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rose 2009" xml:id="rose2009" key="rose2009">Rose, R., 2009. <title
                        rend="italic">Directing Intensive</title> [DVD]. Tarragon Theatre, Toronto,
                    Canada, February-March 2009. Unpublished. Used with permission.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Rose 2011" xml:id="rose2011" key="rose2011">Rose, R., dir., 2011.
                    Director’s script with sketches for <title rend="italic">Forests.</title> By
                    Wajdi Mouawad. Tarragon Theatre, Toronto, 2011. Private collection of the
                    artist. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Roberts-Smith 2010" xml:id="roberts-smith2010" key="roberts-smith2010"
                    >Roberts-Smith, J., et al., 2010. <title rend="quotes">Literary Theory and
                        Theatre Practice: Watching the Script and the Simulated Environment for
                        Theatre</title> [poster]. Digital Humanities Conference 2010. King's College
                    London, UK, 7-11 July.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Roberts-Smith 2013" xml:id="roberts-smith2013a"
                    key="roberts-smith2013a">Roberts-Smith, J., et al., forthcoming 2013. <title
                        rend="quotes">Visualizing Performance History: Two Productions of Judith
                        Thompson’s <title rend="italic">White Biting Dog</title> in the <title
                            rend="italic">Simulated Environment for Theatre</title>
                    </title> (SET). <title rend="italic">Special Issue: Digital Inquiry Into Textual
                        Relations: Research and Teaching with Online Tools</title>. Ed. S. Brown and
                    S. Ruecker. <title rend="italic">Digital Studies/Le champ numérique.</title>
                </bibl>
                <bibl label="Roberts-Smith and Harvey 2013" xml:id="roberts-smith2013b"
                    key="roberts-smith2013b">Roberts-Smith, J., Harvey, K. et al., forthcoming 2013.
                        <title rend="quotes">Is There an Archivist in the Sim? Teaching Literacy
                        Through Experience in a Post-Positivist, Mixed-Media Virtual Theatre
                        Archive.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Canadian Theatre Review</title> 156.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ruecker, Homich and Sinclair 2005" xml:id="ruecker2005"
                    key="ruecker2005">Ruecker, S., Homich, E., and Sinclair, S., 2005. <title
                        rend="quotes">Multi-level Document Visualization.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Visible Language,</title> 39 (1). 33-41. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Ruecker 2006a" xml:id="ruecker2006a" key="ruecker2006a">Ruecker, S.,
                    2006a. <title rend="quotes">Experimental Interfaces Involving Visual Grouping
                        During Browsing.</title>
                    <title rend="italic">Partnership: the Canadian Journal of Library and
                        Information Practice and Research</title> [online], 1 (1). Available from:
                        <ref
                        target="http://www.criticalimprov.com/index.php/perj/article/view/142/177"
                        >http://www.criticalimprov.com/index.php/perj/article/view/142/177</ref>
                    [Accessed 11 January 2011]. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Ruecker 2006b" xml:id="ruecker2006b" key="ruecker2006b">Ruecker, S.,
                    2006b. <title rend="quotes">Proposing an Affordance Strength Model to Study New
                        Interface Tools.</title> Paper presented at the Digital Humanities 2006
                    conference, at the Sorbonne, Paris, France. July 5-9, 2006.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Ruecker, Grotkowski, et al. 2013" xml:id="ruecker2013"
                    key="ruecker2013">Ruecker, S., Grotkowski, A. et al., forthcoming 2013. <title
                        rend="quotes">Abstraction and Realism in the Design of Avatars for the
                        Simulated Environment for Theatre (SET)</title>. <title rend="italic">Visual
                        Communication</title> 12.4 (November). </bibl>
                <bibl label="Schafer 2010" xml:id="schafer2010" key="schafer2010">Schafer, K., 2010.
                    FrameForge Previz Studio [online]. Innoventive Software. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.frameforge3d.com/">http://www.frameforge3d.com</ref>
                    [Accessed 13 July 2010]. </bibl>

                <bibl label="Shakespeare 2000" xml:id="shakespeare2000" key="shakespeare2000"
                    >Shakespeare, W., 2000. <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>. J. L.
                    Levenson, ed. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Shakespeare 2002" xml:id="shakespeare2002" key="shakespeare2002"
                    >Shakespeare, W. 2002. <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>. James N.
                    Loehlin, ed. <title rend="italic">Shakespeare in Production</title>. Cambridge:
                    Cambridge University Press. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Shaw 2000" xml:id="shaw2000" key="shaw2000">Shaw, B., 2000. <title
                        rend="italic">Man and Superman.</title> London: Penguin Books.</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sinclair, et al. 2009" xml:id="sinclair2009" key="sinclair2009"
                    >Sinclair, S., et al., 2009. Mandala [online]. Humanities Visualization Project.
                    Available from: <ref target="http://www.mandala.humviz.org/"
                        >http://www.mandala.humviz.org</ref> [Accessed 13 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Sophie 2010" xml:id="sophie2010" key="sophie2010">Sophie [online],
                    2010. Astea Solutions AD. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.sophiproject.org/">http://www.sophiproject.org</ref>
                    [Accessed 12 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Stern and Mateas 2005" xml:id="stern2005" key="stern2005">Stern, A.,
                    and Mateas, M., 2005. <title rend="italic">Façade</title> [online]. Available
                    from: <ref target="http://www.interactivestory.net/"
                        >http://www.interactivestory.net</ref>/ [Accessed 11 January 2011].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Tufte 1998" xml:id="tufte1998" key="tufte1998">Tufte, E. R., 1998.
                        <title rend="italic">Visual Explanations: Images and Quantities, Evidence
                        and Narrative.</title> Cheshire, CT: Graphics Press.</bibl>
                <bibl label="STELARC 1994" xml:id="stelarc1994" key="stelarc1994">STELARC [online],
                    1994. Available from: <ptr target="http://www.stelarc.va.com.au/images.html"/>
                    [Accessed 13 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Worthen 2010" xml:id="worthen2010" key="worthen2010">Worthen, W., 2010.
                        <title rend="italic">Drama: Between Poetry and Performance.</title> Malden,
                    MA: Wiley-Blackwell. </bibl>
                <bibl label="Wysiwyg Web Builder" xml:id="wysiwyg" key="wysiwyg">Wysiwyg Web Builder
                    7 [online], 2010. Available from: <ref
                        target="http://www.wysiwygwebbuilder.com/"
                        >http://www.wysiwygwebbuilder.com</ref> [Accessed 12 July 2010].</bibl>
                <bibl label="Zeffirelli 1968" xml:id="zeffirelli1968" key="zeffirelli1968"
                    >Zeffirelli, F., director. <title rend="italic">Romeo and Juliet</title>. Film.
                    1968.</bibl>
            </listBibl>

        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
