<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../common/schema/DHQauthor-TEI.rng" type="xml"?>
<?oxygen SCHSchema="../../common/schema/dhqTEI-ready.sch"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:cc="http://web.resource.org/cc/"
   xmlns:rdf="http://www.w3.org/1999/02/22-rdf-syntax-ns#"
   xmlns:dhq="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/ns/dhq"
   xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <!--Author should supply the title and personal information-->
            <title type="article" xml:lang="en">Developing Geographically Oriented NLP Approaches to
               Sixteenth–Century Historical Documents: Digging into Early Colonial Mexico</title>
            <!--Add a <title> with appropriate @xml:lang for articles in languages other than English-->
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <!--The value of xml:id should be first_last without diacritics, all lower case.-->
               <dhq:author_name>Diego <dhq:family>Jiménez–Badillo</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Museo del Templo Mayor, Instituto Nacional de Antropología e
                  Historia</dhq:affiliation>
               <email>diego_jimenez@inah.gob.mx</email>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <!--The value of xml:id should be first_last without diacritics, all lower case.-->
               <dhq:author_name>Patricia <dhq:family>Murrieta–Flores</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Digital Humanities Hub–History Department, Lancaster
                  University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <!--The value of xml:id should be first_last without diacritics, all lower case.-->
               <dhq:author_name>Bruno <dhq:family>Martins</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>The Instituto de Engenharia de Sistemas e Computadores, Investigação
                  e Desenvolvimento em Lisboa, INESC–ID, University of Lisbon</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <!--The value of xml:id should be first_last without diacritics, all lower case.-->
               <dhq:author_name>Ian <dhq:family>Gregory</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Digital Humanities Hub–History Department, Lancaster
                  University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <!--The value of xml:id should be first_last without diacritics, all lower case.-->
               <dhq:author_name>Mariana <dhq:family>Favila-Vázquez</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Museo del Templo Mayor, Instituto Nacional de Antropología e
                  Historia</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
            <dhq:authorInfo>
               <!--Include a separate <dhq:authorInfo> element for each author-->
               <!--The value of xml:id should be first_last without diacritics, all lower case.-->
               <dhq:author_name>Raquel o<dhq:family>Liceras-Garrid</dhq:family>
               </dhq:author_name>
               <dhq:affiliation>Digital Humanities Hub–History Department, Lancaster
                  University</dhq:affiliation>
               <email/>
               <dhq:bio>
                  <p/>
               </dhq:bio>
            </dhq:authorInfo>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Alliance of Digital Humanities Organizations</publisher>
            <publisher>Association of Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <publisher>Association for Computers and the Humanities</publisher>
            <!--This information will be completed at publication-->
            <idno type="DHQarticle-id">000490</idno>
            <idno type="volume"
               ><!--volume number, with leading zeroes as needed to make 3 digits: e.g. 006--></idno>
            <idno type="issue"><!--issue number, without leading zeroes: e.g. 2--></idno>
            <date/>
            <dhq:articleType>article</dhq:articleType>
            <availability>
               <cc:License rdf:about="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nd/2.5/"/>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>This is the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="dhq_keywords">
               <bibl>DHQ classification scheme; full list available at <ref
                     target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml"
                     >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="authorial_keywords">
               <bibl>Keywords supplied by author; no controlled vocabulary</bibl>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en" extent="original"/>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#dhq_keywords">
               <!--Authors may suggest one or more keywords from the DHQ keyword list, visible at http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/taxonomy.xml; these may be supplemented or modified by DHQ editors-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item/>
               </list>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#authorial_keywords">
               <!--Authors may include one or more keywords of their choice-->
               <list type="simple">
                  <item>Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España</item>
                  <item>early colonial history</item>
                  <item>Mexico</item>
                  <item>geographical text analysis</item>
                  <item>named entity recognition</item>
                  <item>name entity disambiguation</item>
                  <item>named entity classification</item>
                  <item>geographic collocation</item>
                  <item>natural language processing</item>
                  <item>machine learning</item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <!--Each change should include @who and @when as well as a brief note on what was done.-->
         <change when="2020-08-14" who="jmurel">Created file</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>

   <text xml:lang="en" type="original">
      <front>
         <dhq:abstract>
            <!--Include a brief abstract of the article-->
            <p>This article introduces an ongoing Digital Humanities project aimed at leveraging the
               benefits of Natural Language Processing, Corpus Linguistics, Machine Learning, and
               Spatial Analysis for advancing the computational analysis of vast historical corpora.
               As a case study, the project concentrates on the <title rend="italic">Relaciones
                  Geográficas de la Nueva España</title> (1577–1585), one of the key corpora for
               understanding the early colonial period of Mexico.</p>
            <p>Using a computer–assisted methodology called Geographical Text Analysis (GTA), the
               project offers automatic means for parsing historical texts and the markup of words
               referring both to place names (toponyms) and analytical concepts that are then linked
               to their geographic locations. Adding geospatial intelligence to the parsing of texts
               allows exploring hidden geographies and narratives in the historic corpus. The
               article provides a general overview of the corpus, describes the GTA methodology step
               by step, and reports on the progress achieved so far.</p>
         </dhq:abstract>
         <dhq:teaser>
            <!--Include a brief teaser, no more than a phrase or a single sentence-->
            <p/>
         </dhq:teaser>
      </front>
      <body>

         <p>1. Introduction</p>
         <p>DELETE THIS LATER
            This article introduces the project <title rend="italic">Digging into Early Colonial
               Mexico: A Large–Scale Computational Analysis of Sixteenth–Century Historical
               Sources</title>, and describes the progress achieved so far.<note> This project
               operates thanks to a grant received from the 2017 “Digging into Data” initiative of
               the Trans–Atlantic Platform for Social Sciences and Humanities Research (T-AP). T-AP
               is a consortium supported by research institutions in 16 countries, among them the
               Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC, UK), the Foundation for Science and
               Technology (FCT, Portugal), and the National Council of Science and Technology
               (CONACyT, México). This project is conducted by three teams of historians,
               archaeologists, geographers, linguists and computer scientists from the following
               institutions: The Digital Humanities Hub and the History Department of Lancaster
               University, UK; The Instituto de Engenharia de Sistemas e Computadores, Investigação
               e Desenvolvimento em Lisboa, INESC–ID, University of Lisbon, Portugal; and the
               Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia in México. The website of the project
               can be accessed at: <ref target="http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/digging-ecm"
                  >http://www.lancaster.ac.uk/digging-ecm</ref>
            </note> The project focuses on developing novel methods and tools for mining new
            knowledge from textual and pictorial historical records to facilitate the study of early
            Latin American history. It concentrates on one of the most important corpora related to
            the geography, culture, religion, economy, and history of native and Spanish peoples in
            Mexico and Guatemala, namely the <title rend="italic">Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva
               España</title> (Geographic Reports from New Spain), and specifically those compiled
            between 1577 and 1585, hereafter referred to as RGs.</p>
         <p>The proposed methodology — called Geographical Text Analysis (GTA) — enables the
            automatic markup of words referring both to place names (toponyms) and analytical
            concepts relevant to historical research, and adds geospatial intelligence to the
            parsing of texts. This process is useful not only to find the most salient terms in
            textual corpora or to identify and disambiguate personal and geographical names, but
            also to facilitate the discovery of unsuspected data patterns and relationships, such as
            spatial correlation of events, interaction of people, links of persons and themes to
            places, and many others.</p>
         <p>One of the main contributions of this project has been the development of an analytical
            model based on deep-learning and adapted to the specific challenges found in texts like
            the RGs. In order to achieve named entity recognition, disambiguation and
            classification, GTA employs methodologies from the fields of Natural Language Processing
            (NLP), Corpus Linguistics (CL) and Machine Learning (ML). Although NLP, CL and ML
            techniques are used frequently in textual analysis today, they are most commonly applied
            to contemporary texts composed in English. Little work has been done to adapt their use
            to historical corpora written in old language forms like the sixteenth–century
               Spanish.<note> NLP techniques have often been applied to annotated texts written in
               modern English, and a few have been tried with historical documents composed in
               earlier forms of speech in several languages (Borin et al. 2007; Brooke et al. 2015;
               Byrne 2007; Crane and Jones 2006; Ehrmann et al. 2016; Grover et al. 2008; Sprugnoli
               et al. 2017; Van Hooland et al. 2015; Won et al. 2018). </note> The RG corpus
            additionally contains other features that complicate the use of such tools, which makes
            very difficult the automatic “reading” of the documents. These include the presence of
            multi-lingual expressions in Nahuatl, Zapotec, Otomi, and many other indigenous
            languages (Harvey, 1972), as well vocabulary only used in certain regions at the time. </p>
         <p>A second contribution of our project has been to facilitate, using Geographical
            Information Systems (GIS), the automatic linking of the results of these processes of
            textual analysis with locational data. This combination of NLP, CL and ML techniques
            with spatial analysis methods creates powerful resources to discover unsuspected
            geographies in the textual reports. Our model will allow scholars of colonial Latin
            America to learn new information, extract it, cross–link it to other document resources,
            and, most importantly, study significant historical topics, such as those we discuss in
            section 3.5 below. </p>
         <p>Apart from the GTA model itself, we foresee several other products of this project. The
            first is a digital version of the RGs corpus, annotated in accordance with analytical
            categories that can be applied to other corpora through an interoperable ontology. The
            second is a digital gazetteer containing geographic coordinates as well as political,
            cultural, administrative and physical data, not only of the sixteenth-century sites
            mentioned in the RGs, but from other relevant sources and historical periods. The third
            is a set of software tools that link the spatial information contained in the gazetteer
            with the textual and pictorial contents of the RGs in order to facilitate the discovery
            and analysis of geographies not immediately apprehended with normal reading. </p>
         <p>In writing this paper, our goal is to raise awareness about the possibilities of
            applying computer-assisted methods to the analysis of historical texts. Thus, we
            describe every step of GTA in the context of our specific study case, hoping that this
            will encourage more Humanities researchers to adopt this kind of approach.</p>
         <p>The rest of the article is organized as follows: Section 2 provides an overview of the
               <hi rend="italic">Relaciones Geográficas</hi> corpus; Section 3 describes our
            analytic methodology and reports on our progress; Section 4 describes future
            applications to the study of history; and the final section offers a general
            conclusion.</p>
         <p>2. The Sixteenth Century Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España</p>
         <p>The compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Relaciones Geográficas de la Nueva España</hi>
            was part of a large, long–standing project, sponsored first by Emperor Charles V and
            then by King Philip II, who sought to collect geographic, economic, historic and
            cultural information from all the kingdoms and territories under their rule. The
            initiative emerged not only from the need to control the exploitation of resources and
            resolve important issues such as land possession, management of labor and the transfer
            of privileges to colonists, but also to compile scientific knowledge and fulfill
            intellectual curiosity (Delgado López 2010; De la Garza 1983). This involved both
            collecting descriptions and making maps (Mundy 1996: 1–27). The whole project included
            Castile, Aragon, Italy, the Netherlands, Portugal (since its annexation in 1581), and
            the viceroyalties of Peru and New Spain.</p>
         <p>For the New World enterprise, the Spanish king, through the Council of Indies,
            commissioned his leading cosmographers to gather information by means of questionnaires.
            These were conceived by Juan de Ovando and sent to the Indies in 1569 (37 questions),
            1570 (200 questions) and 1573 (135 questions). The responses that came back to Madrid,
            however, were scarce, probably because the burden of collecting data was put on
            high-level ecclesiastical and government officials who lacked the necessary knowledge or
            were not willing to answer so many questions. </p>
         <p>The project was revived by Juan López de Velasco, cosmographer–chronicler of Philip II,
            who in 1577 devised more feasible enquiries. The first one attempted to gather
            observations about moon eclipses from various parts of the Indies (Cline 1964). This
            would allow solving the elusive problem of determining longitude coordinates for the
            American territories, which in turn would make it possible to establish correctly the
            position of the Indies with respect to Europe in a universal map (Edwards 1969; Mundy
            1996: 17–19). A second independent enquiry sought to complete the scarce descriptions
            received in the previous years, sending only fifty carefully formulated questions to be
            answered not by high-level authorities, as in previous attempts, but by <hi
               rend="italic">corregidores </hi>and <hi rend="italic">alcaldes mayores, </hi>the
            local administrative officials with direct knowledge of the situation in towns, villages
            and hamlets, who also received printed instructions on how to answer the survey. Figure
            1 shows the first page (out of three) of the printed<hi rend="italic"> Instrucción y
               Memoria</hi> sent as a guide to the respondents.</p>
         <p>The questionnaire included very detailed information about the life in New Spain. One
            single query might cover topics such as demography, type of settlements, intercultural
            opinions, and ethnolinguistics.<note> To give a complete picture of the enquiry, we
               reproduce the questions list in Appendix 1. The questionnaire in Spanish can also be
               found in De la Garza (1983: 7-12) and Acuña (1982-1988, vol. 1: 73-78), as well as in
               English publications by Nutall (1926), Cline (1964, 1972c: 234-237), Mundy (1996:
               227–230), and Bravo-García (2018: 417-422).</note> There are also questions about
            local history, including the names and settlement of towns, and about agricultural and
            mineral resources. See Appendix 1 for a complete translation of the questionnaire. </p>
         <p>Responses to the questionnaire were produced between 1579 and 1585 and are now held in
            Spain, Scotland, and the United States. In total there are 168 written reports
            corresponding to an equal number of main <hi rend="italic">cabeceras </hi>(“head-towns”
            or main districts). These also contain descriptions of 248 subordinate jurisdictions,
            414 towns and many smaller villages and hamlets (Cline 1964). Together they cover more
            than half the political subdivisions existing in New Spain circa 1580 (Cline,
               1972c).<note> The census of these RGs published by Cline (1964, 1972d) and updated by
               Acuña (1982–1988) enumerates 34 RGs from Antequera; 17 from Michoacán; 15 from
               Tlaxcala; 54 from Yucatán; 2 from Guatemala; 34 from Mexico and 12 from Nueva Galicia
               (i.e. Guadalajara), though Cline (1972d) counts only 33 from Mexico. The collection
               is spread across four repositories: 80 documents are in the Archivo General de Indias
               in Seville; 46 in the Real Academia de la Historia in Madrid; 41 in the Latin
               American Collection of the Benson Library, University of Texas; and one in the
               Glasgow University Library. Two handmade transcriptions of the RGs, made by Joaquín
               García Icazbalceta, are now in the National Library of Mexico City (Cline, 1964: 359;
               (Acuña, 1982-1988, vol. 1: 9).</note> Figure 2 reproduces one of the manuscript pages
            of the Relación de Atlatlauhca (present–day Atlatlauhcán, Morelos).</p>
         <p>Alongside the texts, the corpus contains 78 maps. Some were painted by indigenous
            artists following native representations of places and landscape (Figure 3 and Figure
            4), while others were clearly drawn by creoles or peninsular Spaniards (Figure 5). In
            the words of Robertson (1972: 243), they represent “…the largest single group of
            interrelated early colonial pictorial manuscripts which has come down to us.”<note> The
               latest comprehensive analysis of these maps is by Mundy (1996).</note> Of these maps,
            23 came from Mexico; 3 from Michoacán; 1 from Nueva Galicia; 21 from Oaxaca; 18 from
            Tlaxcala; 3 from Yucatán and 2 from Guatemala. There are also accounts of 26 manuscripts
            and 16 maps lost centuries ago (Cline 1972c: tables 6 and 10; Robertson 1972), as well
            as an additional map that disappeared more recently (Mundy 1996: 226). </p>
         <p>Despite the fact that some authors failed to answer several questions, both the texts
            and the maps offer favorable conditions to test new approaches for the analysis of large
            historical corpora. The corpus of RGs offers highly structured information — due to the
            standardized questionnaire — which gives the reports a degree of homogeneity rarely seen
            in other sixteenth–century collections. The geographic descriptions also cover more than
            half the territory of New Spain and the level of detail is remarkable not only in terms
            of orography, landscape, and natural resources, but also the way of life of native
            peoples and colonists, as well as the interactions between different social groups. Such
            richness, consistency, and span facilitate comparative research across small, medium,
            and large areas on topics of social, historical, ethnographic, linguistic, economic, and
            political interest.</p>
         <p>A further reason for selecting the RGs is a desire to improve the accessibility and
            valorization of the corpus as a main source for historical enquiry. Seminal research has
            been conducted by Cline (1972), Bravo-García (2018), Gerhard (1972), Gruzinski (1991),
            Moreno Toscano (1968), Mundy (1996) and a few other scholars (Cáceres Lorenzo, 2013;
            Delgado López, 2010). The publications by Cline (1972) and Gerhard (1972), for example,
            were ground-breaking works of Mexican historical geography. Moreno Toscano (1968), on
            the other hand, used the complete textual information of the RGs to perform a matrix
            analysis oriented to reconstruct the economic geography of New Spain, whilst Mundy
            (1996) analyzed all the surviving maps to identify continuities and changes in the
            indigenous cartographic tradition during the colonial period. For his part, Gruzinski
            (1991: 77-103) has approached the corpus by studying how the contrasting — sometimes
            conflicting — worldview of conquistadors and native peoples shaped the responses to the
            questionnaire, pointing out interesting details about the colonization of the
            imaginary.</p>
         <p>Single documents of the <hi rend="italic">Relaciones</hi> have also been the focus of
            historical research (Afanador-Pujol, 2015; Ballesteros 2005; Barlow, 1949; Fernández
            Christlieb and Garza Merodio, 2006; Morato-Moreno, 2017; Mundy, 2013; Nutall 1926, among
            others), but in general the textual and cartographic documents have served as ancillary
            sources in regional studies, rather than as a principal mine of data (Dahlgren, 1954;
            Brand, 1960; Gibson, 1967). This is due perhaps to the difficulty of cross–linking
            information among the many documents or to a lack of tools for uncovering non–explicit
            knowledge hidden in the subtext of the answers to the questionnaire.</p>
         <p>3. Methodology and current progress </p>
         <p>As discussed in the introduction, we are developing advanced tools for unveiling new
            information from the RGs corpus by applying a methodology known as Geographical Text
            Analysis (GTA). The resulting digital resources and software tools will be released at
            the end of the project under an open-access license. The methodology was originally
            produced by some members of this project to reveal new, unsuspected patterns of
            information by focusing on the geographic components of the historical narrative (Cooper
            and Gregory 2011; Murrieta et al. 2015; Donaldson et al. 2015; Gregory et al. 2015;
            Porter et al. 2015; Martins and Murrieta–Flores 2017; Murrieta–Flores and Gregory 2017;
            Gregory et al. 2018). </p>
         <p>We are now in the process of refining and extending this methodology with contributions
            from all members of this project and from researchers engaged in parallel initiatives
            (e.g., Santos et al. 2017; Santos et al. 2018; Won et al., 2018). In this particular
            project we followed four phases: obtaining a computer-readable corpus, the creation of a
            gazetteer, the semantic annotation and geoparsing of the corpus, and data mining and
            historical analysis. In the following sections, we discuss each stage in detail.</p>
         <p>3.1 First phase: Obtaining a computer-readable corpus</p>
         <p>The first phase of the methodology is obtaining computer–readable files from the more
            comprehensive editions of the RGs. We began with Francisco del Paso y Troncoso’s <hi
               rend="italic">Papeles de Nueva España</hi>, which contains a significant portion of
            the corpus. Transcriptions from the original manuscripts were already available in
            electronic format, but it was necessary to identify and correct significant errors
            caused by the Optical Character Recognition (OCR) software. This is a common problem
            with old documents, to which Alpert–Abrams offers an approach in her 2016 article on the
            corpus known as <hi rend="italic">Primeros Libros</hi>.</p>
         <p>After completing six volumes of <hi rend="italic">Papeles de Nueva España</hi> (Del Paso
            y Troncoso 1905), the work continued with the RGs from Yucatán, published in volume 11
            of <hi rend="italic">Colección de documentos inéditos de las posesiones de España en
               ultramar</hi> (1898). Additionally, thanks to a generous permission from the National
            Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM), we were also able to digitize a more recent
            version of the 54 RGs from Yucatán transcribed and edited by De la Garza (1983) and to
            acquire in a digital format 114 RGs published in ten volumes by Acuña (1982–1988). In
            the end, we obtained two versions of the whole corpus in machine–readable format: the
            first one includes the notes, references and commentary from the scholars who
            transcribed and studied the documents, while the second contains only the transcription
            of the original RGs texts. A third version that includes all the NLP annotations was
            produced during the third phase of the project.</p>
         <p>3.2 Second phase: Creation of a gazetteer</p>
         <p>The second phase starts with a compilation of all the place names that exist in the
            corpus as well as many others from relevant sources, and then solving any linguistic and
            locational uncertainties that prevent their unequivocal identification.</p>
         <p>3.2.1 Compilation of place names<hi rend="italic">. </hi>This is done by extracting
            toponym indices from published editions of the RGs, as well as from comprehensive
            studies on the historic geography of New Spain (Gerhard 1972a, 1972b, 1991; Cline 1972a,
            1972b, 1972c; Moreno Toscano, 1968; Tanck de Estrada et al., 2005). Through this
            procedure, the UK and Mexican teams were able to compile a list of 14,654 place names
            (Liceras-Garrido et al. 2019).</p>
         <p>3.2.2 Linguistic disambiguation<hi rend="italic">.</hi> The resulting list was then
            subjected to a linguistic disambiguation process, during which the most difficult
            challenges were dealing with place names found in different native languages, as well as
            resolving name variations and spelling inconsistencies. Important names of cities, like
            Tlaxcala, have remained in original form since the sixteenth century, but many others
            have changed significantly over time for a variety of reasons, including: historic
               causes;<note> For instance, Antequera is now Oaxaca.</note> renaming due to changes
            in the boundaries of original settlements;<note> In one example, sixteenth–century
               Cempoala (Hidalgo) moved from a hill to a valley to guarantee access to water, which
               caused severe alterations on its limits.</note> and addition of words such as the
            name of a patron saint to an indigenous toponym.<note> Tetlapayac, for instance, is the
               modern Santiago Teltlapayac.</note> Another problem relates to spelling variations of
            the same toponym,<note> Quauhyocan is also written as Quacyocan, for example.</note> the
            application of Castilian transliterations to the names of ancient settlements,<note> For
               example, ancient Quahnahuac is modern Cuernavaca.</note> or dealing with
               homonymies.<note> Tetela, for instance, refers both to a town in modern Morelos and
               to a settlement in Puebla, and towns called Atlatlauhca can be found both in Morelos
               — origin of an RG — and Oaxaca.</note>
         </p>
         <p>State–of–the–art methods to tackle these challenges are discussed in Nick and Tent
            (2017) and Santos et al. (2015, 2017, 2018). Additionally, there is a valuable body of
            research on the subject of Mexican toponomy, so we have benefited from publications by
            Anaya Monroy (1960), Guzmán Betancourt (1987, 1989, 1998), Lefevre and Paredes Martínez
            (2017), León Portilla (2002), Márquez and Ramos Navarro Wold (1998), Mundy (2014),
            Muntzel and Villegas Molina (2010), etc. This adds to the exhaustive research done by
            the editors of the RGs, especially Acuña (1982–1988), De la Garza (1983) and Del Paso y
            Troncoso (1905). </p>
         <p>3.3.3. Geographic disambiguation. Another challenge at this stage is finding latitude
            and longitude coordinates of towns and villages. The solution involves, first, detecting
            and merging duplicate entries by comparing the place name list with records found in
            online geographical databases, such as the catalogue of indigenous localities, produced
            by Instituto Nacional de Estadística Geografía a Informática (INEGI) and Comisión
            Nacional para el Conocimiento y Uso de la Biodiversidad (CONABIO);<note>
               <ref target="http://www.cdi.gob.mx/localidades2010-gobmx/"
                  >http://www.cdi.gob.mx/localidades2010-gobmx/</ref>
            </note> the geographic dataset created for the cartography of Mexico by INEGI; the
            general registrar of archaeological sites compiled by Instituto Nacional de Antropología
            e Historia (INAH);<note>
               <ref target="http://registropublico.inah.gob.mx/index.php"
                  >http://registropublico.inah.gob.mx/index.php</ref>
            </note> the GeoNames geographical database;<note>
               <ref target="http://www.geonames.org/">http://www.geonames.org/</ref>
            </note> and the Getty Thesaurus of Geographical Names.<note>
               <ref target="http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/index.html"
                  >http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/index.html</ref>
            </note> Through both linguistic and locational disambiguation, we were able to obtain
            12,748 correct names. Of these, we have so far been able to pin-point 3919 physical
            locations (Figure 6), which are the entries used for the gazetteer.</p>
         <p>The structure of the gazetteer complies with Linked Open Data standards to guarantee its
            interoperability between different systems and repositories and facilitate its
            application into other projects. We have relied on the experience of massive reference
            resources like the Getty Thesaurus of Geographical Names<note>
               http://www.getty.edu/research/tools/vocabularies/tgn/</note> and especially the
            Alexandria Digital Library Gazetteer (ADL), from which we adopted the relational
            database schema (Hill, 2000; Hill et al., 1999). For importing and exporting data, we
            adopted the file format JSON, created by the World Historical Gazetteer<note>
               http://whgazetteer.org</note>, which is now an accepted standard in many textual
            annotation and analysis platforms, such as Recogito. The database of our gazetteer will
            be made available through the World Historical Gazetteer, the Pelagios Network, and
            through Recogito. In addition, the gazetteer will be also available in a standalone
            downloadable GIS format from the project’s website and repositories.</p>
         <p>3.4 Third phase: Semantic annotation of the corpus</p>
         <p>The third stage comprises four tasks: defining an annotation schema by selecting the
            most relevant analytic categories for the intended historical analysis; annotating
            manually, and in accordance with the previously defined annotation schema, two different
            samples of documents: one for training the NLP deep-learning model and another one to
            validate it; tuning the deep-learning model to automatically perform name entity
            recognition, disambiguation and classification, in order to obtain a fully annotated
            corpus; and assessing the performance of the model in accordance with the gold-standard
            validated by experts. </p>
         <p>3.4.1 Defining the annotation schema (ontology). The selection of the ontology
            categories can be done by consensus among expert linguists and historians, or with the
            help of automatic computer methods that extract a “seed ontology” directly from the
            corpus (Eynard et al., 2012). The first method is more time-consuming, but it is simpler
            and on many occasions yields better results, so this was the approach we followed.</p>
         <p>The RGs ontology contains 21 entity classes and many more sub-categories relevant to
            social, political, territorial and economic terms appearing recurrently through the RGs
            (Table 2). For example, the general entity class “architecture” includes sub-categories
            such as “domestic” and religious”, which offers the possibility to distinguish between
            house and convent buildings described in texts. Another class “cosmogony” includes
            sub-categories such as “ritual”, “festivity”, “deity”, etc. Each entity type follows the
            definitions and linked-data standards of DBpedia to ensure the interoperability of our
            dataset.</p>
         <p>3.4.2 Manual annotation of text samples for training the NLP model. Using such entity
            classes we carried out a manual annotation of two samples of 18 out of 168 documents
            (10% of the corpus) from the RGs using the online tagging tools developed by Tagtog, a
            commercial company that generously provided a free license to our project.<note>
               www.tagtog.net</note> In order to ensure the quality of the annotated samples, five
            experts tagged the same documents independently. We then obtain statistics on the level
            of consensus among the experts by using the inter-annotator agreement tool from Tagtog.
            Figure 7 illustrates an annotated document.</p>
         <p>3.4.3 Development of the NLP deep-learning model. Once the training and gold-standard
            sample data are available, the actual development of the NLP model can begin. Our team
            in Portugal, led by Bruno Martins, combined two state-of-the-art approaches of
            deep-learning: neural networks and word embedding.</p>
         <p>3.4.3.1 Neural networks. A neural network is a computational model, loosely inspired on
            the neural structure of the brain, that is able to "learn by example" how to perform
            repetitive complex tasks. In the NLP and CL fields, it is applied, among other things,
            to perform word classification, or the assigning of a label to each word in an input
            text, indicating whether it belongs to a certain semantic category (e.g. toponym,
            person, animal, plant, institution, cultural concept), or to a “part-of-speech”
            syntactic category (i.e. noun, pronoun, adjective, determiner, verb, adverb,
            preposition, conjunction, and interjection).</p>
         <p>Modern NLP software libraries leverage such statistical models (Goldberg, 2017), making
            probabilistic decisions on the best annotations for previously unseen texts. One of the
            best is SpaCy. To run a deep-learning model in SpaCy we need to conduct a training phase
            during which the software is fed with the training data sample (in our case 10% of the
            corpus). This annotated training sample contains many known examples of the kind of
            words expected in the unannotated text (the remaining 90% of the corpus). </p>
         <p>Because we know the correct answers — thanks to the gold-standard data sample — , we can
            give the model feedback on its predictions in the form of an error gradient or the loss
            function that calculates the difference between the training example and the expected
            output. If the accuracy of the annotations is not sufficient, then an iterative refining
            process can be carried out until accomplishing satisfactory results.</p>
         <p>Then, to link the gazetteer with the corpus texts, it is necessary to assign correct
            longitude and latitude coordinates to each toponym recognized by the neural network. The
            Mordecai geoparsing library (Halterman, 2017) is a good tool for that job. It takes as
            input the place names recognized by SpaCy, and uses an index over the contents of the
            gazetteer to find the potential coordinates of extracted place names. In other words,
            the names recognized in the text are matched against similar names in the gazetteer.
            Through this process the gazetteer and the corpus are finally linked and ready for the
            implementation of query tools.</p>
         <p>3.4.3.2 Word-embedding. Complementing the above procedures, the word–embedding algorithm
            makes it easier for the neural network to distinguish all of the different semantic
            contexts in which a word might be used. This process follows the idea that "a word is
            characterized by the company it keeps" (Firth, 1957). For example, in the phrase “[t]he
            order of San Francisco was established in these lands in 1524”, the term <hi
               rend="italic">San Francisco</hi> refers to an institution, but in “[t]he mendicant
            friars helped the poor following the teachings of San Francisco”, the same term refers
            to a person. In another context, it could mean a geographic location, as for instance in
            the sentence “San Francisco Tlalcilalcalpan is inhabited at the present by 18,721
            people.”</p>
         <p>We specifically pre-trained a word–embedding algorithm in an unsupervised way to
            statistically predict the meaning of words in the context of real natural language
            utterances. Thus, we needed training data sufficiently big and varied to tackle the
            specific challenges of the RGs. One is that the spelling in the corpus varies
            considerably among the many authors. This is sometimes, in part, because words are
            spelled in accordance with their Latin origin, rather than their actual pronunciation.
            Another is that the corpus borrows heavily on vocabulary from indigenous languages,
            especially place names, and terms to identify flora, fauna, cultural concepts, etc.</p>
         <p>Given the fact that the structure of modern Spanish still resembles to a high degree the
            language recorded in the RGs, we decided to combine modern and historical data sources
            to train our model. Contemporary data came from several Spanish corpora such as ANCora
            (Taulé et al., 2008), IMPACT-es (Sánchez-Martínez et al., 2013), or the <hi
               rend="italic">Corpus del Español,</hi>
            <note>
               <ref target="https://www.corpusdelespanol.org">https://www.corpusdelespanol.org</ref>
            </note> while numerous examples of sixteenth–century Spanish texts from different
            archives and ten dictionaries of indigenous languages (García Cubas, 1888-1991;
            Peñafiel, 1897; Robelo, 1897, 1900, 1902, 1902b; 1904; 1905; Starr, 1920) provided
            resources to deal with the language complexities particular to New Spain.</p>
         <p>By thus leveraging modern and historical data in a combined training dataset, we can
            simultaneously benefit from having large amounts of contextual information from which
            the model can learn more easily, together with some data representing the specificities
            of historical Spanish. Furthermore, to avoid problems with out-of-vocabulary words, such
            as those brought forward by the inconsistent spelling or cultural expressions, we used a
            word–embedding method that also creates representations for sub-words, and which is able
            to reconstruct entire word representations from such sub-words (Bojanowski et al.,
            2017).</p>
         <p>4. Future Work: Data mining and historical analysis</p>
         <p>At this stage, several data mining and analysis procedures can be carried out. The first
            is an adaptation of collocation analysis — a technique from Corpus Linguistics (CL) —
            which allows for extracting the most statistically significant phrases that are found
            next to a term or keyword of interest (the “collocates,” in CL jargon). Our variant of
            the technique is <hi rend="italic">geographic collocation analysis</hi>, originally
            developed by the research group at Lancaster (Gregory et al., 2015, Murrieta-Flores et
            al., 2015, 2017a, 2017b). This facilitates the recognition and retrieval, across the
            corpus, of all place names that collocate or are close to a keyword of interest
            according to a predefined proximity threshold, usually defined in terms of the maximum
            number of words between the search–term and the collocate. In this manner, if a
            researcher is interested in investigating economic aspects related to agriculture, they
            could retrieve, for instance, all phrases in the context of words like <hi rend="italic"
               >maíz</hi>, <hi rend="italic">siembra</hi>, <hi rend="italic">subsistencia</hi>, <hi
               rend="italic">mantenimientos, comida</hi> (i.e. maize, sowing, subsistence,
            sustenance, food), which would appear linked to a map showing the geographic locations
            where such terms appear. </p>
         <p>Furthermore, by putting words in context through collocation, a historian could extract
            in a few seconds — as opposed to the weeks that it would take to access the information
            without GTA tools — interesting details about the first colonists in New Spain. Such a
            query, for instance, might involve running a collocate search of the word “conquistador”
            (Figure 8). Another type of search can be conducted using general categories, such as
            employing the term <hi rend="italic">food</hi> to retrieve words like <hi rend="italic"
               >beans, fish, </hi>or <hi rend="italic">bread</hi> (Figure 9).</p>
         <p>In the following subsections, we highlight several topics of historic analysis that we
            plan to examine through this research.</p>
         <p>4.1 Historical phenomena changing the face of New Spain at the end of the sixteenth
            century</p>
         <p>One area of application for the techniques detailed in this study is understanding the
            coexistence of competing systems of land ownership and labor in New Spain during the
            colonial period. In New Spain during the short time of compilation of the RGs, there was
            a strong debate about the system of <hi rend="italic">encomiendas </hi>and the desire to
            replace it with the so-called <hi rend="italic">repartimientos</hi>. The <hi
               rend="italic">encomienda</hi> was the right to exploit the labor of indigenous
            populations, granted by the Spanish Crown to conquistadors, who at the beginning of the
            colonization held this privilege in perpetuity and could, therefore, pass it to their
            descendants with little intervention from the royal government in Madrid. In contrast,
            the <hi rend="italic">repartimiento</hi> only allocated the labor force of native
            workers for a fixed period of time in exchange for a meager remuneration. The latter
            gave the royal government more control over its subjects and resources. Neither the
            holders of <hi rend="italic">encomiendas </hi>nor <hi rend="italic">repartimientos</hi>
            were allowed to appropriate lands, as private property was reserved for <hi
               rend="italic">haciendas</hi>. These three systems coexisted in the 1570s despite the
            enactment of the so-called New Laws in 1542, which attempted to protect the rights of
            the indigenous populations and prevent the dispossession of their lands by abolishing
            the <hi rend="italic">encomiendas</hi>. Throughout the texts of the RGs, therefore, it
            is common to find claims by conquistadors’ descendants of their <hi rend="italic"
               >encomienda</hi> rights, and others defending the benefits of <hi rend="italic"
               >repartimientos</hi>. A comprehensive study of the claims and contentions found in
            the RG corpus would improve our understanding of the period.</p>
         <p>4.2 The local government organization of New Spain toward the third quarter of the
            sixteenth century</p>
         <p>A second application of these methodologies has to do with disambiguating local
            structures of governance in New Spain. The early colonial period was a time when the
            functions and spheres of influence of the four branches of colonial government were not
            well defined, and consequently the spatial boundaries of the judicial, administrative,
            military and ecclesiastical jurisdictions overlapped (Figure 10). This was especially
            true at the municipal level. Consequently, the corpus contains terms associated with
            several kinds of jurisdictions whose meanings were not consistent throughout the vast
            territory of New Spain (e.g. <hi rend="italic">partidos de clérigos</hi>, <hi
               rend="italic">distrito de mision</hi>, <hi rend="italic">custodia</hi>, <hi
               rend="italic">guardianía</hi>, <hi rend="italic">vicaría, presidencia, </hi>etc.).
            The subject has been a matter of ongoing debate among historians (Gerhard, 1972b: 66),
            but we believe that applying collocation analysis for extracting the contextual use of
            such words would shed light on how those institutions functioned in parallel to <hi
               rend="italic">alcaldías mayores</hi> and <hi rend="italic">corregimientos</hi> and
            this would be an important contribution to the knowledge of this period.</p>
         <p>4.3 Settlement pattern analysis to elucidate the territorial organization of New Spain </p>
         <p>A third area for future study has to do with demarcating the boundaries of territories
            in New Spain. By reading the RGs, we could attempt to identify the names and boundaries
               (<hi rend="italic">linderos</hi>) of towns belonging to <hi rend="italic"
               >corregimientos</hi> (territorial demarcations for administrative and judicial
            purposes) mentioned in the corpus. Circa 1570, there were 200 of such units whose
            frontiers have been outlined by Gerhard (1972a). However, the smaller demarcations
            (towns, villages) suffered adjustments in boundaries and jurisdictions. As Gerhard
            points out, at the time of the RGs, “[e]arly civil and ecclesiastical divisions lost
            importance and were eliminated; others came into being as a result of conquest,
            proselytization, mining activity, and other causes” (Gerhard, 1972b: 66-69). The
            application of a mathematical model that analyzes the maximum available territory around
            each settlement within a region, like the one proposed by Ducke and Kroefges (2008),
            could provide preliminary hypotheses on such demarcations. These would then be tested
            against the actual historical information extracted from the corpus through geographic
            collocation analysis. One of the many ways that such a study could begin is by
            extracting references on the routes that local administrators take for their visits to
            towns within their jurisdiction, the distances they traversed, the geographic features
            and topography of the landscape, etc. (Figure 10) This, and much other information, is
            available throughout the corpus, but more specifically in the answers to questions 7, 8,
            11, and 12 (see Appendix 1).</p>
         <p>4.4 Analysis of historical diseases</p>
         <p>A fourth research question has to do with our understanding of the outbreak of disease
            (1576-1581) that took the lives of half the population of New Spain during the early
            colonial period (Acuña-Soto et al., 2004). This was the second time that <hi
               rend="italic">cocoliztli</hi> (as the epidemic was called) had decimated the native
            population, causing the disappearance of whole communities, shortages in labor-force for
            the <hi rend="italic">encomiendas</hi> and <hi rend="italic">repartimientos</hi>, the
            displacement of people over different regions, or, on the contrary, the congregation of
            survivors (sometimes of different ethnic communities) in new Indian towns, all of which
            altered dramatically the traditional settlement pattern (Gerhard, 1972a: 24). How did
            this phenomenon vary over different regions? How many people died in each locality? How
            did this epidemic compare with others in the past? How did the new settlement change in
            comparison with Prehispanic times? These are all questions that GTA could help to answer
            by collocating words and phrases related to health (such as diseases, symptoms, and
            remedies) and analyzing them with spatial mathematical models of disease contagion. </p>
         <p>4.5 The spatial distribution of natural resources (flora, fauna, minerals, etc.) and
            exploitation practices at the time of the RGs</p>
         <p>A fifth application of our methodology has to do with the study of natural resources.
            GTA will allow the extraction and analysis of regional historical information on natural
            resources such as plants. There are already interesting archaeological, historical and
            ethnographic research related to plants and their use in Mesoamerica, medicinal and
            otherwise (Álbores Zárate, 2015; Chávez Mejía, 2020; Hersch, 1999). Some further
            research has been also dedicated to assessing the importance of the trees and edible
            plants introduced by Europeans. With the annotation of the RGs in this project and the
            development of GTA, it is now possible not only to extract information regarding native
            and European plants introduced in the different regions of New Spain, but also to
            contribute to further debates. It is known, for instance, that Mesoamerican cultures had
            an extended knowledge of plants for medicinal use and most of the research about this
            has been carried out using colonial primary sources. We could now create a map of all
            the plants mentioned in the RGs and compare this dataset with archaeological data and
            other primary sources that were dedicated to the recording of medicinal plants, such as
            the Códice Badiano or the Historia Natural de Nueva España. This would allow
            researchers, for instance, to assess the continuation in the use of specific plants for
            remedies and consumption in specific regions of New Spain. Other interesting avenues of
            possible research with GTA analysis are the availability of food and animals both native
            and introduced, the use of natural resources, the existence of cultural artefacts, the
            presence of priests and religious orders in particular regions, as well as types of
            architecture.</p>
         <p>4.6 Exchange networks, trading practices and communication routes</p>
         <p>An additional topic is the study of exchange networks and trading practices, as well as
            communication routes, both terrestrial and aquatic, among the populations described in
            the RGs. One such study has already been conducted by Favila-Vázquez (2019), who
            successfully reconstructed aquatic communication networks in the Rio Balsas region by
            extracting information from the responses available to queries 38 to 47 of the RGs
            (Figure 11). These contain crucial data regarding navigation by sea, including location
            of ports and coastal landscape. Together with data from question 19 (focused on fluvial
            networks), the extraction of data from the RGs corpus allowed Favila-Vázquez to
            reconstruct a riverine and coastal system of communication that explains the spatial
            connectivity of the Valley of Mexico to the Pacific coast.  </p>
         <p>5. Conclusion</p>
         <p>Geographical Text Analysis can make an important contribution to the study of massive
            corpora, like the RGs<hi rend="italic">,</hi> by expediting the extraction and analysis
            of specific information that would be too slow or cumbersome to find in big datasets
            through traditional reading methods. It also can provide tools to uncover patterns
            behind the narrative of historical sources and link them to their geographic locations.
            Thus, GTA creates a way for historians to apply what in computational literary studies
            is called “distant reading.”<note> The premise of distance reading is that there are
               simply too many documents for anyone to read and study simultaneously and within the
               limits of the human brain and under the time imposed by contemporary academic
               schedules.</note>
         </p>
         <p>At the same time, the use of geographic collocations and the concept of “keywords in
            context” permit a more detailed, granular comprehension of the corpus by identifying
            those parts that deserve a “close reading.” This flexibility has been demonstrated in
            previous research projects employing GTA (Donaldson et al., 2017; Murrieta–Flores et
            al., 2017; Taylor et al., 2017). Having a multiplicity of “place names in context”
            associated with keywords of interest opens an unprecedented range of possibilities in
            terms of identifying information patterns and hypothesis–testing across large corpora,
            which in turn allows answering historical questions in a way that would be impossible
            otherwise. </p>
         <p>In such a context, the proposal of GTA must not be seen as an attempt to replace the
            careful micro study of historical sources practiced by modern historians. More exactly,
            GTA is a methodology for parsing and crosslinking information at a macro scale
            throughout a whole corpus in a relatively short period of time, so historians can use
            their efforts and time more efficiently to focus on the more important documents or
            fragments of texts.</p>
         <p>One of the main contributions of our project specifically has been adapting named entity
            recognition, disambiguation, and classification techniques to text collections that
            either belong to specific historical periods or might pose a further challenge due to
            their multi–language nature. We have succeeded in developing a new deep-learning model
            to process the language of the RGs despite the orthographic variance across the corpus
            and the high frequency of indigenous vocabulary. Nevertheless, there is still much work
            to be done, especially for the indigenous languages of the Americas (Mager et al. 2018). </p>
         <p>Finally, we have already produced a significant number of digital datasets of value,
            such as the gazetteer, which includes not only sixteenth–century localities but place
            names from other Mexican historic periods. Hopefully, these will prove valuable
            resources for humanists engaged in studying the Latin American historical and
            archaeological past. The methods and tools being developed by the project have the
            advantage of being generic, and therefore, applicable to other corpora. </p>
         <p>We are committed to releasing the digital products and software tools through several
            repositories, including GitHub and our own online platform. Our hope is that scholars
            from diverse fields will be able to identify the desired information, extract it,
            cross–link it to other document resources, and most importantly, answer significant
            research questions: Where do certain phenomena happen more often? Who was responsible
            for certain events? What was happening in specific places at certain times? Such kind of
            enquiry will take historical analysis a step further, contributing significantly to
            advancing research on the colonial period in Latin America, and humanities research more
            generally. </p>
         <p>Appendix 1. The Questionnaire of the Relaciones Geográficas<note> Reproduced from Mundy,
               Barbara. 1996. The mapping of New Spain. Indigenous cartography and the maps of the
               Relaciones Geográficas, Appendix B, pp. 227-230. Chicago: The University of Chicago
               Press.</note>
         </p>
         <p>MEMORANDUM OF THE THINGS THAT ARE TO BE ANSWERED, AND OF THAT WHICH SHALL BE TAKEN INTO
            ACCOUNT.</p>
         <p>l. Firstly: For towns of Spaniards, state the name of the district or province in which
            it lies. What does this name mean in the native language, and why is it so called?</p>
         <p>2. Who was the discoverer and conqueror of this province? By whose order was it
            discovered? In what year was it discovered and conquered, as far as is readily
            known?</p>
         <p>3. What is the general climate and character of the province or district? Is it very
            cold or hot, humid or dry? Does it have much or little rain, and when, approximately,
            does it fall? How violently and from where does the wind blow, and at what times of the
            year?</p>
         <p>4. Is the terrain flat or rugged, clear or wooded, with many or few rivers or springs,
            abundant in or lacking water? Is it fertile or without pasture, abundant or lacking in
            fruits and sustenance?</p>
         <p>5. Are there many or few Indians? Were there more or fewer at other times, and what are
            the known causes of this? Are they presently settled in planned and permanent towns?
            Describe the degree and quality of their intelligence, inclinations, and way of life.
            Are there different languages in the province or a general language that all speak? </p>
         <p>6. What is the latitude, or the altitude of the Pole Star, at each Spanish town, if it
            has been taken and is known, or if anyone knows how to observe it? Or on which days of
            the year does the sun not cast a shadow at midday?</p>
         <p>7. What are the league distances and the direction of each Spanish city or town in the
            district to the city of its <hi rend="italic">Audiencia, </hi>or to the town where the
            governor to whom it is subject</p>
         <p>resides? </p>
         <p>8. Likewise, what are the league distances and the direction of each Spanish city or
            town to adjacent ones? Are these leagues long or short, through flat or hilly land, over
            straight or winding roads, easy or difficult to travel? </p>
         <p>9. What are the present and former names and surnames of each city or town? Why are they
            so called, if known? Who gave each its name, who was its founder, by whose order was it
            settled? What year was it founded? How many residents did the settlement first have, and
            how many does it have now? 10. Describe the sites upon which each town is established.
            Is each upon a height, or low-lying, or on a plain? Make a map of the layout of the
            town, its streets, plazas and other features, noting the monasteries, as well as can be
            sketched easily on paper. On it show which part of the town faces south or north.</p>
         <p>11. For native towns, state only how far they are from the town in whose corregimiento
            or jurisdiction they are, and how far they lie from their cabecera de doctrina. </p>
         <p>12. In addition, state how far the native towns lie from surrounding native or Spanish
            towns. Declare for all their direction from these other towns. Are the leagues long or
            short, the roads through level or hilly land, straight or winding?</p>
         <p>13. What does the name of this [native] town mean in the indigenous language? Why is it
            called this, if known? What is the name of the language spoken by the natives of this
            town?</p>
         <p>14. Who were their rulers in heathen times? What rights did their former lords have over
            them? What did they pay in tribute? What forms of worship, rites, and good or evil
            customs did they practice? </p>
         <p>15. How were they governed? With whom did they wage war? How did they battle? What was
            their battle dress and clothing like, both formerly and now? What was their former and
            is their present means of subsistence? Were they more or less healthy than now and what
            are reasons for this that you may know?</p>
         <p>16. For all towns, both Spanish and native, describe the sites where they are
            established. Are they in the mountains, in valleys, or on open flat land? Give the names
            of the mountains, valleys, and districts, and for each, tell what the name means in the
            indigenous language. </p>
         <p>17. Is the land or site healthy or unhealthy? If unhealthy, why (if it is known)? What
            illnesses commonly occur, and what cures are commonly used for them? </p>
         <p>18. How far or near, and in what direction does each town lie from a nearby prominent
            mountain or range? Supply its name.</p>
         <p>19. What major river or rivers flow nearby? How distant and in what direction do they
            lie? How great is their flow? Is there anything notable known about their sources,
            water, orchards and other growth along their banks? Are there or could there be
            irrigated lands of value?</p>
         <p>20. What are the significant lakes, lagoons, or springs within the town boundaries? Note
            anything remarkable about them.</p>
         <p>21. What are the volcanoes, caves, and all other notable and remarkable aspects of
            nature in the district worthy of being known?</p>
         <p>22. Which wild trees and their fruits are commonly found in the district? What are the
            uses of them and their woods, and to what good are they or could they be put?</p>
         <p>23. Which cultivated trees and fruit orchards are in the region? Which were brought from
            Spain and elsewhere? Do these grow well?</p>
         <p>24. What are the grains and seed plants, and other garden plants and vegetables that are
            or have been used as sustenance for the natives?</p>
         <p>25. Which were brought from Spain? Does the land yield wheat, barley, wine, or olive
            oil, and in what quantities? Is there silk or cochineal in the region, and in what
            quantities?</p>
         <p>26. What are the herbs or aromatic plants that the natives use for healing? What are
            their medicinal or poisonous properties? </p>
         <p>27. What animals and birds, both wild and domestic, are in the region? Which ones were
            brought from Spain, and how well have they bred and multiplied?</p>
         <p>28. In the region or within the town lands, are there any gold or silver mines or
            sources of other metals, or black or colored pigments? </p>
         <p>29. Are there any quarries of precious stone, jasper, marble, or other notable ones?
            What value might they have?</p>
         <p>30. Are there sources of salt in the town or nearby? If [residents] lack salt and other
            items necessary for their sustenance or clothing, where do they procure all these
            things? </p>
         <p>31. How are the houses built and what is their form? What building materials are found
            in the town, or brought from elsewhere?</p>
         <p>32. What are the towns' fortifications? Are there barracks, or any fortified or
            impregnable places within the boundaries of the district?</p>
         <p>33. Through what dealings, trade, and profits do both Spaniards and Indians live and
            sustain themselves? What are the items involved and with what do they pay their tribute? </p>
         <p>34. In which diocese of the archbishopric, bishopric, or abbey does each town lie? In
            which district does each lie? How many leagues and in which direction does each town lie
            from the town of the cathedral and the cabecera of the district? Are the leagues long or
            short, along straight or winding roads, and through flat or hilly land?</p>
         <p>35. In each town, what are the cathedral and parish church or churches? What is the
            number of endowed church offices and allotments for clergymen's salaries in each? Do any
            have a chapel or significant endowment, and, if so, whose it is and who established
            it?</p>
         <p>36. What are the monasteries or convents of each Order? By whom and when were they
            founded? How many notable things do they contain? And what is the number of
            religious?</p>
         <p>37. What are the hospitals, schools, and charitable institutions in the towns? By whom
            and when were they founded?</p>
         <p>38. If the towns are on the seacoast, in addition to the above, report in your account
            the nature of the sea in the vicinity, whether it is calm or stormy, the nature of the
            storms and other dangers. What times, approximately, are they frequent?</p>
         <p>39. Is there beach or cliffs along the coast? What are the prominent reefs and other
            dangers to navigation along it?</p>
         <p>40. How great are the tides and tidal ranges? On which days and at which hours do they
            occur? In which season are they greater or lesser?</p>
         <p>41. What are the notable capes, points, bights, and bays in the district? Note their
            names and sizes, as well as can be determined.</p>
         <p>42. What are the ports and landings along the coast? Make a map showing their shape and
            layout as can be drawn on a sheet of paper, in which form and proportion can be
            seen.</p>
         <p>43. What is their size and capacity? Note their approximate width and length in leagues
            and paces, as well as can be determined. Also note how may ships they will
            accommodate.</p>
         <p>44. What is the depth in fathoms of each? Is the bottom clear? Are there any shallows
            and shoals? Indicate their locations, and whether the port is free of shipworm and other
            impediments.</p>
         <p>45. What directions do their entrances and exits face? With which winds must one enter
            and depart?</p>
         <p>46. What are their advantages or lack of them in the way of firewood, water, and
            provisions? What are the favorable or unfavorable considerations for entering and
            remaining?</p>
         <p>47. What are the names of the islands along the coast? Why are they so named? Make a
            map, if possible, of their form and shape, showing their length, width, and lay of the
            land. Note the soil, pastures, trees, and resources they may have, their birds and
            animals, and the notable rivers and springs.</p>
         <p>48. Where are the abandoned Spanish towns located in the region? When were they settled
            and abandoned? What is known about the reasons for abandonment?</p>
         <p>49. Describe any other of the notable aspects of nature, and any notable qualities of
            the soil, air, and sky in any part of the region.</p>
         <p>50. Having completed the account, the persons who have collaborated on it will sign it.
            It must be returned without delay, along with these directions, to the person from whom
            it was received.</p>
         <p>Acknowledgements</p>
         <p>We would like to thank the generous grant awarded by the 2017 T–AP initiative of the
            Trans–Atlantic Platform in Social Sciences and Humanities Research, as well as the
            support received in each country by the Economic and Social Research Council (ESRC, UK)
            (ES/R003890/1), the Foundation for Science and Technology (FCT, Portugal), and the
            Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tecnología (project 275015). Likewise, we would like to
            thank the Red Conacyt de Tecnologías Digitales para la Difusión del Patrimonio Cultural
            (project 294971), also supported by Conacyt.</p>

         <p>Figure captions</p>
         <p>Figure 1. First page of the printed <hi rend="italic">Instrucción y Memoria</hi> sent by
            the Council of Indies to guide the compilation of the <hi rend="italic">Relaciones
               Geográficas</hi>. Photograph courtesy of the Benson Latin American Collection. The
            General Libraries, The University of Texas at Austin (JGI xxiii-13).</p>
         <p>Figure 2. Manuscript from the <hi rend="italic">Relación of Atlatlauhca</hi> (Morelos)
            containing responses to the first two questions of the enquiry.</p>
         <p>Figure 3. Map of Ixtapalapa (Ciudad de Mexico) included in the <hi rend="italic"
               >Relación Geográfica de Ixtapalapa (1580), belonging to the corregimiento</hi> of
            Mexicaltzingo. Size of the original: 43 x 31 cm. The author is Martin Cano, a native
            local artist, who, as Mundy (1996: 63) points out, is one of the uses pictographs to
            represent the town´s name, which in Nahuatl means “water near the flagstones”: “Below
            the church, a hexagonal flagstone is surrounded by a blue ribbon of water. Ixtapalapa´s
            church dominates one axis of the composition, while its twin community buildings, at
            left, dominate the other”. Photograph courtesy of the Benson Latin American Collection.
            The General Libraries, The University of Texas at Austin (JGI xxiv-8).</p>
         <p>Figure 4. Map of the <hi rend="italic">Relación de Amoltepec</hi>. This is another
            example of the indigenous tradition to represent a geographic region. The place names of
            neighbor and subject towns are drawn with logographs organized in a semi-circle,
            surrounding the church and the ruler´s palace (Mundy, 1996: 113). Photograph courtesy of
            the Benson Latin American Collection. The General Libraries, The University of Texas at
            Austin (JGI xxiv-5).</p>
         <p>Figure 5. Map of the <hi rend="italic">Relación de Tlacotalpa</hi>. One of the best
            examples of charts in the European tradition that can be found in the RGs corpus. This
            was produced by Francisco Stroza Gali, a professional mariner in 1580 (Mundy, 1996: 51).
            A detailed study of the document reveals the extraordinary precision of the geographic
            measurements achieved by Gali (Morato-Moreno, 2017). </p>
         <p>Figure 6. Location of the 3919 sites georeferenced so far (April 2020) through
            linguistic and locational disambiguation, which are added to the project´s
            gazetteer.</p>
         <p>Figure 7. Annotation of the <hi rend="italic">Relación de Merida</hi> with the Tagtog
            software tool. Notice the color code to distinguish different annotation categories: red
            is used for words referring to persons, either by name, profession or roles; green to
            locations (either toponyms or geographic features); light blue to dates, and so on.</p>
         <p>Figure 8. Extracting information with GTA tools (which are still a work in progress). In
            this example, the keyword “conquistador” is used to recover data from the colonists
            mentioned in the <hi rend="italic">Relación de Tekal</hi>. The map shows the location of
            this town in Yucatán. Queries like this can be apply to a single document or to the
            complete corpus.</p>
         <p>Figure 9. Another type of query that retrieves works in context belonging to the food
            category. In this example, the threshold for the collocation has been set 10 words
            before and after the key category.</p>
         <p>Figure 10. Map illustrating the overlapping of three types of colonial jurisdictions:
            political (<hi rend="italic">gobiernos</hi>), ecclesiastic (dioceses), and
            administrative (<hi rend="italic">provincias</hi>).</p>
         <p>Figure 11. Map showing the location of towns that were part of the indigenous network of
            navigation through the Pacific coast and the Balsas river towards the third quarter of
            the 16th century. Photograph courtesy of Favila-Vázquez (2019).</p>
      </body>
      <back>
         <listBibl>
            <bibl xml:id="acuna1982" label="Acuña 1982-8">Acuña, René. 1982–1988. <title
                  rend="italic">Relaciones Geográficas del siglo XVI</title>, 10 vols. México:
               Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México. Instituto de Investigaciones Antropológicas.
                  <ref
                  target="https://books.google.com/books/about/Relaciones_Geogr%C3%A1ficas_Del_Siglo_XVI.html?id=XuQ0834CgVAC"
                  >https://books.google.com/books/about/Relaciones_Geogr%C3%A1ficas_Del_Siglo_XVI.html?id=XuQ0834CgVAC</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="acuna-soto2004" label="Acuña–Soto et al. 2004">Acuña–Soto, Rodolfo, David
               W. Stahle, Matthew D. Therrell, Richard D. Griffin, and Malcolm K. Cleaveland. 2004.
                  <title rend="quotes">When half of the population died: The epidemic of hemorrhagic
                  fevers of 1576 in Mexico</title>. <title rend="italic">FEMS Microbiology
                  Letters</title> 240(1): 1–5. doi:<ref target="10.1016/j.femsle.2004.09.011"
                  >10.1016/j.femsle.2004.09.011</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alboreszarate2015" label="Albores Zarate 2015">Albores Zarate, B. (Ed.).
               2015. <title rend="italic">Flor-flora: Su uso ritual en Mesoamérica</title>. Toluca
               de Lerdo, Estado de México : Fondo Editorial Estado de México; El Colegio
               Mexiquense.</bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="alpert-abrams2016" label="Alpert-Abrams 2016">Alpert–Abrams, Hannah. 2016.
                  <title rend="quotes">Machine reading the <title rend="italic">Primeros
                     Libros</title></title>, <hi rend="italic">DHQ: Digital Humanities Quaterly</hi>
               10(4). <ref target="http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000268/000268.html"
                  >http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/10/4/000268/000268.html</ref></bibl>
            <bibl xml:id="anayamonroy1960" label="Anaya Monroy1960">Anaya Monroy, Fernando. 1960.
                  <title rend="quotes">Presencia espiritual de la cultura náhuatl en la
                  toponimia</title>. <hi rend="italic">Estudios de Cultura Náhuatl</hi> 2:
               9–25.</bibl>
            <bibl>Ballesteros García, Víctor Manuel. 2005.<hi rend="italic"> La Pintura de la
                  Relación de Zempoala de 1580</hi>. México: Universidad Autónoma del Estado de
               Hidalgo.</bibl>
            <bibl>Barlow, Robert H. 1949. Relación de Zempoala y su partido, 1580. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Tlalocan. Revista de Fuentes para el Conocimiento de las Culturas Indígenas de
                  México</hi> 3(1): 29-41.</bibl>
            <bibl>Borin, Lars, Dimitrios Kokkinakis, and Leif–Jöran Olsson. 2007. Naming the past:
               Named entity and animacy recognition in 19th century Swedish literature. In <hi
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the Workshop on Language Technology for Cultural
                  Heritage Data (LaTeCH 2007), </hi>pp. 1–8. Prague, Czech Republic: Association for
               Computational Linguistics. http://www.aclweb.org/anthology/W/W07/W07–0901.pdf</bibl>
            <bibl>Bravo-García, Eva. 2019. <hi rend="italic">Las voces del contacto. Edición y
                  estudio de Las Relaciones Geográficas de México (Siglo XVI)</hi>. Warsaw:
               University of Warsaw. </bibl>
            <bibl>Brand, Donald. 1960. <hi rend="italic">Coalcoman and Motines del Oro, an
                  ex-Distrito of Michoacan, México</hi>. Austin: University of Texas, Institute of
               Latin American Studies.</bibl>
            <bibl>Brooke, Julian, Adam Hammond, and Graeme Hirst. 2015. GutenTag: An NLP–driven tool
               for digital humanities research in the project Gutenberg Corpus. In <hi rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the North American Association for Computational Linguistics</hi>,
               pp. 1–6. Denver, Colorado.
               http://www.cs.toronto.edu/pub/gh/Brooke–etal–2015–CLfL.pdf</bibl>
            <bibl>Byrne, Kate. 2007. Nested named entity recognition in historical archive text. In
                  <hi rend="italic">International Conference on Semantic Computing (ICSC 2007)</hi>.
               Irvine, CA, USA: IEEE. Doi:10.1109/ICSC.2007.107.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cáceres Lorenzo, María Teresa. 2013. Tipos de Relaciones Geográficas en el siglo
               XVI. <hi rend="italic">Crítica Hispánica</hi> 35(1): 45-66.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cáceres Lorenzo, María Teresa. 2016. Heteregeneidad léxica en las Relaciones
               Geográficas de Yucatán, <hi rend="italic">Alpha. Revista de Artes, Letras y
                  Filosofía, 42 (online).
               </hi>http://dx.doi.org/10.4067/S0718-22012016000100007 </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <ref
                  target="https://scielo.conicyt.cl/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0718-22012016000100007"
                  >https://scielo.conicyt.cl/scielo.php?script=sci_arttext&amp;pid=S0718-22012016000100007</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>Chávez Mejía, M.C., L. White Olascoaga, S. Moctezuma Pérez, F. Herrera Tapia.
               2020. Practicas curativas y plantas medicinales: Un acercamiento a la etnomedicina de
               San Nicolás, México. <hi rend="italic">Cuadernos Geográficos, </hi>56(2): 26. <ref
                  target="http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=edb&amp;AN=124569245&amp;lang=es&amp;site=eds-live"
                  >http://search.ebscohost.com/login.aspx?direct=true&amp;db=edb&amp;AN=124569245&amp;lang=es&amp;site=eds-live</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>Cline, Howard F. 1964. The <hi rend="italic">Relaciones Geográficas</hi> of the
               Spanish Indies, 1577–1586. <hi rend="italic">The Hispanic American Historical
                  Review</hi> 44(3): 341–374. doi:10.2307/2511856.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cline, Howard F. 1972a. Introductory notes on territorial divisions of Middle
               America. In <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Middle American Indians, Volume 12: Guide
                  to Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>, edited by Howard F. Cline, pp. 17–62.
               Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cline, Howard F. 1972b. Ethnohistorical regions of Middle America. In <hi
                  rend="italic">Handbook of Middle American Indians, Volume 12: Guide to
                  Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>, edited by Howard F. Cline, pp. 166–182.
               Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cline, Howard F. 1972c. The Relaciones Geográficas of the Spanish Indies,
               1577–1648. In <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Middle American Indians, Volume 12: Guide
                  to Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>, edited by Howard F. Cline, pp. 183–242.
               Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cline, Howard F. 1972d. A census of the <hi rend="italic">Relaciones
                  Geográficas</hi> of New Spain, 1579–1612. In <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Middle
                  American Indians, Volume 12: Guide to Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>,
               edited by Howard F. Cline, pp. 364–369. Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Cooper, David, and Ian N Gregory. 2011. Mapping the English Lake District: A
               literary GIS. <hi rend="italic">Transactions of the Institute of British
                  Geographers</hi> 36(1): 89–108. doi:10.1111/j.1475–5661.2010.00405.x.</bibl>
            <bibl>Crane, Gregory, and Alison Jones. 2006. The challenge of Virginia Banks: An
               evaluation of named entity analysis in a 19th–century newspaper collection. In <hi
                  rend="italic">Proceedings of the 6th ACM/IEEE–CS Joint Conference on Digital
                  Libraries (JCDL ‘06)</hi>, Chapel Hill, NC, USA: ACM Press.
               doi:10.1145/1141753.1141759.</bibl>
            <bibl>Dahlgren de Jordan, Barbro. 1954. <hi rend="italic">La Mixteca: su cultura e
                  historia prehispánicas</hi>. México: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México. </bibl>
            <bibl>De la Garza, Mercedes (Ed.). 1983. <hi rend="italic">Relaciones
                  histórico–geográficas de la gobernación de Yucatán: (Mérida, Valladolid y
                  Tabasco).</hi> First edition, 2 vols. México: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de
               México.</bibl>
            <bibl>Del Paso y Troncoso, Francisco (Ed.). 1905. <hi rend="italic">Papeles de Nueva
                  España</hi>. Segunda Serie: Geografía y Estadística, vols. 1, 3–7. Madrid:
               Sucesores de Rivadeneyra.</bibl>
            <bibl>Delgado López, Enrique. 2010. Las Relaciones Geográficas como proyecto científico
               en los albores de la modernidad. <hi rend="italic">Estudios Mesoamericanos</hi> 2(9):
               97–106.</bibl>
            <bibl>Donaldson, Christopher, Ian N. Gregory, and Patricia Murrieta–Flores. 2015.
               Mapping ‘Wordsworthshire’: A GIS study of literary tourism in Victorian Lakeland. <hi
                  rend="italic">Journal of Victorian Culture</hi> 20(3): 287–307.
               doi:10.1080/13555502.2015.1058089.</bibl>
            <bibl>Donaldson, Christopher, Ian N. Gregory, and Joanna E. Taylor. 2017. Locating the
               beautiful, picturesque, sublime and majestic: Spatially analysing the application of
               aesthetic terminology in descriptions of the English Lake District. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Journal of Historical Geography</hi> 56 (April): 43–60.
               doi:10.1016/j.jhg.2017.01.006.</bibl>
            <bibl>Ducke, Benjamin and Peter C. Kroefges. 2008. Layers of Perception. Proceedings of
               the 35th International Conference on Computer Applications and Quantitative Methods
               in Archaeology (CAA2007), Berlin, Germany, April 2–6, <hi rend="italic">edited by </hi>
               <hi rend="italic">Axel </hi>Posluschny, Karsten Lambers, and Irmela Herzog, <hi
                  rend="italic">pp. 246-251.</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">(Kolloquien zur Vor- und Frühgeschichte, Vol. 10). Bonn: Dr. Rudolf
                  Habelt GmbH.</hi>
               <ref target="https://proceedings.caaconference.org/paper/78_ducke_kroefges_caa2007/"
                  >https://proceedings.caaconference.org/paper/78_ducke_kroefges_caa2007/</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>Edwards, Clinton R. 1969. Mapping by questionnaire: An early Spanish attempt to
               determine New World geographic positions. <hi rend="italic">Imago Mundi</hi> 23:
               17–28.</bibl>
            <bibl>Ehrmann, Maud, Giovanni Colavizza, Yannick Rochat, and Frédéric Kaplan. 2016.
               Diachronic evaluation of NER systems on old newspapers. In <hi rend="italic"
                  >Proceedings of the 13th Conference on Natural Language Processing (KONVENS
                  2016))</hi>, edited by Stephanie Dipper, Friedrich Neubarth, and Heike
               Zinsmeister, pp. 97–107. Bochum, Germany: Bochumer Linguistische Arbeitsberichte.
                  <ref target="http://infoscience.epfl.ch/record/221391"
                  >http://infoscience.epfl.ch/record/221391</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Eynard, Davide, Matteo Matteucci, and Fabio Marfia. 2012. A modular framework to
               learn seed ontologies from text. In Semi-automatic ontology development processes and
               resources, edited by Maria Teresa Pazienza and Armando Stellato, pp. 22-47. Hershey,
               PA: IGI Publishing.</bibl>
            <bibl>Favila Vázquez, Mariana. 2019. La navegación prehispánica: Un sistema de
               conectividad del paisaje mesoamericano. Modelo de interacción entre la costa del
               Pacífico y el Altiplano Central (Postclásico Tardío-Siglo XVI). PhD Thesis, México:
               Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México. Facultada de Filosofía y Letras, Instituto
               de Investigaciones Filológicas. Programa de Maestría y Doctorado en Estudios
               Mesoamericanos.</bibl>
            <bibl>Fernández Christlieb, Federico and Gustavo Garza Merodio. 2006. La pintura de la
               Relación Geográfica de Metztitlán, 1579. <hi rend="italic">Secuencia. Revista de
                  historia y ciencias sociales</hi> 66: 160-186.</bibl>
            <bibl>García Cubas, Antonio. 1888-1891. <hi rend="italic">Diccionario geográfico,
                  histórico y biográfico de los Estados Unidos Mexicanos</hi>. 2 vols. México:
               Antigua Impr. de Murguía. <ref
                  target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/010416157"
                  >https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/010416157</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gerhard, Peter. 1972a. <hi rend="italic">A Guide to the historical geography of
                  New Spain</hi>. first edition. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gerhard, Peter. 1972b. Colonial New Spain, 1519–1786: Historical notes on the
               evolution of minor political jurisdictions. In <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Middle
                  American Indians, Volume 12: Guide to Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>,
               edited by Howard F. Cline, pp. 63–137. Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gerhard, Peter. 1991. <hi rend="italic">La frontera sureste de la Nueva
                  España</hi>. México: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de México.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gibson, Charles. 1967. <hi rend="italic">Tlaxcala in the sixteenth century</hi>.
               California: Stanford University Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Goldberg, Yoav. 2017. Neural network methods for natural language processing. <hi
                  rend="italic">Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies</hi> 10(1): 1-309.
               doi:10.2200/S00762ED1V01Y201703HLT037.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gómez, Raúl. 2004. <hi rend="italic">Los Virreinatos americanos</hi>. Madrid:
               Dastin Export.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gregory, Ian, Christopher E. Donaldson, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, and Paul E.
               Rayson. 2015. Geoparsing, GIS, and textual analysis: Current developments in spatial
               humanities research. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and Arts
                  Computing</hi> 9(1): 1–14. doi:10.3366/ijhac.2015.0135.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gregory, Ian Norman, Christopher E. Donaldson, Andrew Hardie, and Paul E. Rayson.
               2018. Modelling Space in Historical Texts. In <hi rend="italic">The shape of data in
                  Digital Humanities: Modeling texts and text–based resources</hi>, edited by Julia
               Flanders and Fotis Jannidis. London: Routledge.
               http://eprints.lancs.ac.uk/81427/.</bibl>
            <bibl>Grover, C., S. Givon, R. Tobin, and J. Ball. 2008. Named entity recognition for
               digitised historical texts. In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the Sixth
                  International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’08)</hi>.
               Paris: ELRA.</bibl>
            <bibl>Gruzinski, Serge. 1991. <hi rend="italic">La colonización de lo imaginario.
                  Sociedades indígenas y occidentalización en el México español. Siglos XVI-XVIII.
               </hi>México: Fondo de Cultura Económica (original in French, <hi rend="italic">La
                  colonization de l´imaginaire, Sociètés indigènes et occidentalisation dans le
                  Mexique espagnol XVI</hi>e<hi rend="italic">-XVIII</hi>e<hi rend="italic">
                  siècle</hi>. Paris: Editions Gallimard, 1988).</bibl>
            <bibl>Guzmán Betancourt, Ignacio (Ed.). 1987. <hi rend="italic">De toponimia y
                  topónimos. Contribuciones al estudio de los nombres de lugar provenientes de
                  lenguas indígenas de México</hi>. México: Instituto Nacional de Antropología e
               Historia.</bibl>
            <bibl>Guzmán Betancourt, Ignacio. 1989. <hi rend="italic">Toponimia mexicana.
                  Bibliografía general</hi>. México: Instituto Nacional de Antropología e
               Historia.</bibl>
            <bibl>Guzmán Betancourt, Ignacio, ed. 1998. <hi rend="italic">Los nombres de
                  México.</hi> México: Secretaría de Relaciones Exteriores.</bibl>
            <bibl>Halterman, Andrew. 2017. Mordecai: Full text geoparsing and event geocoding. <hi
                  rend="italic">The Journal of Open Source Software,</hi> 2 (January): 91.
               doi:10.21105/joss.00091.</bibl>
            <bibl>Harvey, H. R. 1972. The Relaciones Geográficas, 1579-1586: Native Languages. . In
                  <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Middle American Indians, Volume 12: Guide to
                  Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>, edited by Howard F. Cline, pp. 279–323.
               Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hersch, Martinez, P. (1999). De hierbas y herbolarios en el Mexico actual. <hi
                  rend="italic">Arqueología Mexicana</hi>, 39:60-65.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hill, Linda L. 2000. Core elements of digital gazetteers: Placenames, categories,
               and footprints. In <hi rend="italic">Research and advanced technology for digital
                  libraries</hi>, pp. 280–290. Lecture Notes in Computer Science 1923. Berlin:
               Springer. doi:10.1007/3–540–45268–0_26.</bibl>
            <bibl>Hill, Linda, James Frew, and Qi Zheng. 1999. Geographic names: The implementation
               of a gazetteer in a georeferenced digital library. <hi rend="italic">D–Lib
                  Magazine</hi> 5(1). doi:10.1045/january99–hill.</bibl>
            <bibl>Lefebvre, Karin and Carlos Paredes Martínez, eds. 2017. <hi rend="italic">La
                  memoria de los nombres: la toponimia en la conformación histórica del territorio.
                  De Mesoamérica a México</hi>. Morelia, Michoacán: Universidad Nacional Autónoma de
               México, Centro de Investigaciones en Geografía Ambiental. <ref
                  target="http://www.h–mexico.unam.mx/node/19835"
                  >http://www.h–mexico.unam.mx/node/19835</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Liceras-Garrido, Raquel, Mariana Favila-Vázquez, Katherine Bellamy, Patricia
               Murrieta-Flores, Diego Jiménez-Badillo, et al. 2019. Digital Approaches to Historical
               Archaeology: Exploring the Geographies of 16th Century New Spain. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Open Access J</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">ournal</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">of </hi>
               <hi rend="italic">Arch</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">aeology</hi>
               <hi rend="italic"> &amp; Anthropol</hi>
               <hi rend="italic">ogy </hi>2(1). OAJAA.MS.ID.000526. DOI:
               10.33552/OAJAA.2019.02.000526.</bibl>
            <bibl>León Portilla, Miguel. 2002. El destino de las lenguas indígenas de México. In <hi
                  rend="italic">El despertar de nuestras lenguas (Queman tlachixque
                  totlahtolhuan)</hi>, edited by Natalio Hernández. México: Editorial Diana, Fondo
               Editorial de las Culturas Indígenas.</bibl>
            <bibl>López de Velasco, Juan. 1894. <hi rend="italic">Geografía y descripción universal
                  de las Indias</hi>. Madrid: D. Justo Zaragoza: Establecimiento tipográfico de
               Fortanet.
               http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/obra–visor/geografa–y–descripcin–universal–de–las–indias–recopilada–por–el–cosmgrafocronista–juan–lpez–de–velasco–desde–el–ao–de–1571–al–de–1574–publicada–por–d–justo–zaragoza–0/html/.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mager, Manuel, Ximena Gutierrez–Vasques, Gerardo Sierra, and Ivan Meza. 2018.
               Challenges of language technologies for the indigenous languages of the Americas. In
                  <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on
                  Computational Linguistics (COLING 2018).</hi>
               https://arxiv.org/abs/1806.04291.</bibl>
            <bibl>Márquez, Ofelia, and Lilian Ramos Navarro Wold. 1998. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Compilation of colonial Spanish terms and document related phrases</hi>. Midway
               City, CA: SHAR Press (Society of Historical and Ancestral Research).
               http://www.somosprimos.com/spanishterms/spanishterms.htm.</bibl>
            <bibl>Martins, Bruno, and Patricia Murrieta–Flores. 2017. GeoHumanities 2017 workshop
               report. In <hi rend="italic">Proceedings of the 1st ACM SIGSPATIAL Workshop on
                  Geospatial Humanities, </hi>Redondo Beach, California, USA.</bibl>
            <bibl>Morato-Moreno, Manuel. 2017. The Map of Tlacotalpa by Francisco Gali, 1580: An
               early example of a local coastal chart in Spanish America. <hi rend="italic">The
                  Cartographic Journal</hi> 55(1): 3-15. </bibl>
            <bibl>Moreno Toscano, Alejandra. 1968. <hi rend="italic">Geografía económica de México
                  (siglo XVI)</hi>. México: El Colegio de México.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mundy, Barbara. 1996. <hi rend="italic">The mapping of New Spain: Indigenous
                  cartography and the maps of the Relaciones Geograficas</hi>. Chicago: University
               of Chicago Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Mundy, Barbara E. 2013. Mapping Babel: A 16th Century Indigenous Map from Mexico.
                  <hi rend="italic">The Appendix: A New Journal of Narrative &amp; Experimental
                  History</hi>. Online publication available at: <ref
                  target="http://theappendix.net/issues/2013/10/mapping-babel-a-sixteenth-century-indigenous-map-from-mexico"
                  >http://theappendix.net/issues/2013/10/mapping-babel-a-sixteenth-century-indigenous-map-from-mexico</ref>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>Mundy, Barbara E. 2014. Place–names in Mexico–Tenochtitlan. <hi rend="italic"
                  >Ethnohistory</hi> 61 (2): 329–355. doi:10.1215/00141801–2414190.</bibl>
            <bibl>Muntzel, Martha C., and María Elena Villegas Molina, (Eds.). 2010. <hi
                  rend="italic">Itinerario toponímico de México: Ignacio Guzmán Betancourt</hi>.
               México: Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia.</bibl>
            <bibl>Murrieta–Flores, Patricia, Alistair Baron, Ian Gregory, Andrew Hardie, and Paul
               Rayson. 2015. Automatically analyzing large texts in a GIS environment: The Registrar
               General’s Reports and cholera in the 19th century. <hi rend="italic">Transactions in
                  GIS</hi> 19(2): 296–320. doi:10.1111/tgis.12106.</bibl>
            <bibl>Murrieta–Flores, Patricia, Christopher Donaldson, and Ian N Gregory. 2017. GIS and
               literary history: Advancing digital humanities research through the spatial analysis
               of eighteenth–century travel writing. <hi rend="italic">Digital Humanities
                  Quarterly</hi> 11(1).
               http://www.digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/11/1/000283/000283.html.</bibl>
            <bibl>Murrieta–Flores, Patricia, and Ian N. Gregory. 2017. Cruzando Fronteras en
               humanidades digitales: Análisis geográfico de textos de interés histórico y
               arqueológico con sistemas de información geográfica. In <hi rend="italic">Arqueología
                  computacional. Nuevos enfoques para la documentación, análisis y difusión del
                  patrimonio cultural</hi>, edited by Diego Jiménez–Badillo, pp. 199–212. México:
               Instituto Nacional de Antropología e Historia.</bibl>
            <bibl>Nick, I. M., and Jan Tent. 2017. Guest editorial on indigenous names and toponyms.
                  <hi rend="italic">Names, A Journal of Onomastics</hi> 65(4): 190–193.</bibl>
            <bibl>Nuttall, Zellia, (Ed.). 1926. Official reports on the towns of Tequizistlan,
               Tepechpan, Acolman, and San Juan Teotihuacan, sent by Francisco de Castañeda to His
               Majesty, Philip II, and the Council of the Indies, in 1580. <hi rend="italic">Papers
                  of the Peabody Museum of Archaeology and Ethnology</hi>, 11(2): 45–84. Cambridge,
               Massachusetts: Harvard University.</bibl>
            <bibl>Pedrote Romero, Antonio and Eva Bravo-García. 2019. La autoría de las Relaciones
               Geográficas mexicanas: Las voces náhuatl a través de los redactores. <hi
                  rend="italic">Anuario de Estudios Americanos, 76(1): 123-153.</hi> Doi: <ref
                  target="https://doi.org/10.3989/aeamer.2019.1.06"
               >10.3989/aeamer.2019.1.06</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Peñafiel, Antonio. 1897. <hi rend="italic">Nomenclatura geográfica de México,
                  etimologías de los nombres de lugar correspondientes a los principales idiomas que
                  se hablan en la República</hi>. 3 vols. México: Oficina tipográfica de la
               Secretaria de Fomento. <ref target="http://archive.org/details/nomenclaturageog00pe"
                  >http://archive.org/details/nomenclaturageog00pe</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Porter, Catherine, Paul Atkinson, and Ian Gregory. 2015. Geographical Text
               Analysis: A new approach to understanding nineteenth–century mortality. <hi
                  rend="italic">Health &amp; Place,</hi> 36 (November): 25–34.
               doi:10.1016/j.healthplace.2015.08.010.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robelo, Cecilio Agustín. 1897. <hi rend="italic">Nombres geográficos indígenas del
                  estado de Morelos. Estudio crítico de varias obras de Toponomatología nahoa</hi>.
               Cuernavaca: Luis G. Miranda, impresor. <ref
                  target="http://archive.org/details/nombresgeogrfi00robeuoft"
                  >http://archive.org/details/nombresgeogrfi00robeuoft</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robelo, Cecilio Agustín. 1900. <hi rend="italic">Nombres Geográficos Indígenas Del
                  Estado de México: Estudio Crítico Etimológico</hi>. Cuernavaca: Luis G. Miranda
               impresor. <ref target="http://cd.dgb.uanl.mx/handle/201504211/14251"
                  >http://cd.dgb.uanl.mx//handle/201504211/14251</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robelo, Cecilio Agustín. 1902a. <hi rend="italic">Nombres geográficos mexicanos
                  del estado de Veracruz: Estudio critico etimológico</hi>. Cuernavaca: Luis G.
               Miranda impresor.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robelo, Cecilio Agustín. 1902b. <hi rend="italic">Toponimia
                  tarasco-hispano-nahoa</hi>. Cuernavaca: Impr. de J. D. Rojas. <ref
                  target="http://archive.org/details/toponimiatarasc00robegoog"
                  >http://archive.org/details/toponimiatarasc00robegoog</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robelo, Cecilio Agustín. 1904. <hi rend="italic">Diccionario de aztequismos, ó
                  sea, catalogo de las palabras del idioma nahuatl, azteca ó mexicano, introducidas
                  al idioma castellano bajo diversas formas.</hi> Cuernavaca: Printed by the author.
                  <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/009024985"
                  >https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/009024985</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robelo, Cecilio Agustín. 1905. <hi rend="italic">Diccionario de mitología
                  náhuatl</hi>. México: Ediciones Fuente Cultural; Librería Navarro. <ref
                  target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001940449"
                  >https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001940449</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Robertson, Donald. 1972. The pinturas (maps) of the <hi rend="italic">Relaciones
                  Geográficas</hi> with a catalog. In <hi rend="italic">Handbook of Middle American
                  Indians, Volume 12: Guide to Ethnohistorical Sources, Part One</hi>, edited by
               Howard F. Cline, pp. 243–278. Austin: University of Texas Press.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sánchez–Martínez, Felipe, Isabel Martínez–Sempere, Xavier Ivars–Ribes, and Rafael
               C. Carrasco. 2013. An Open diachronic corpus of historical Spanish: Annotation
               criteria and automatic modernisation of spelling. <hi rend="italic">arXiv:1306.3692
                  [cs]</hi>, June. http://arxiv.org/abs/1306.3692.</bibl>
            <bibl>Santos, João, Ivo Anastácio, and Bruno Martins. 2015. Using machine learning
               methods for disambiguating place references in textual documents. <hi rend="italic"
                  >GeoJournal</hi> 80(3): 375–392. doi:10.1007/s10708–014–9553–y.</bibl>
            <bibl>Santos, Rui, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, and Bruno Martins. 2017. Learning to
               combine multiple string similarity metrics for effective toponym matching. <hi
                  rend="italic">International Journal of Digital Earth</hi>.
               doi:10.1080/17538947.2017.1371253.</bibl>
            <bibl>Santos, Rui, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, Pável Calado, and Bruno Martins. 2018.
               Toponym matching through deep neural networks. <hi rend="italic">International
                  Journal of Geographical Information Science</hi> 32(2): 324–348.
               doi:10.1080/13658816.2017.1390119.</bibl>
            <bibl>Sprugnoli, Rachele, Giovanni Moretti, Bruno Kessler, Sara Tonelli, and Stefano
               Menini. 2017. Fifty years of European history through the lens of Computational
               Linguistics: The De Gasperi Project. <hi rend="italic">Italian Journal of
                  Computational Linguistics</hi> 2(2): 89–100.</bibl>
            <bibl>Starr, Frederick. 1920. <hi rend="italic">Aztec place-names, their meaning and
                  mode of composition, selected from the Spanish of Agustin de la Rosa, Antonio
                  Peñafiel and Cecilio A. Robelo</hi>. Chicago: Privately printed by the author.
                  <ref target="https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001360976"
                  >https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/001360976</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Tanck de Estrada, Dorothy. 2005. <hi rend="italic">Atlas ilustrado de los pueblos
                  de indios</hi>. México: El Colegio de México, El Colegio Mexiquense, Comisión
               Nacional para el Desarrollo de los Pueblos Indígenas, and Fomento Cultural
               Banamex.</bibl>
            <bibl>Taulé, Mariona, M. Antònia Martí, and Marta Recasens. 2008. AnCora: Multilevel
               annotated corpora for Catalan and Spanish. <hi rend="italic">LREC 2008</hi>.
               https://aclanthology.info/papers/L08–1222/l08–1222.</bibl>
            <bibl>Taylor, Joanna E., Ian N. Gregory, and Christopher E. Donaldson. 2017. Combining
               close and distant reading: A multiscalar analysis of the English Lake District’s
               historical soundscape. <hi rend="italic">International Journal of Humanities and Arts
                  Computing</hi>, 12(2): 163-182. <ref target="http://eprints.lancs.ac.uk/89167/"
                  >http://eprints.lancs.ac.uk/89167/</ref>.</bibl>
            <bibl>Van Hooland, S., M. de Wilde, R. Verborgh, T. Steiner, and R. Van de Walle. 2015.
               Exploring entity recognition and disambiguation for cultural heritage collections.
                  <hi rend="italic">Digital Scholarship in the Humanities</hi> 30(2): 262–279.
               doi:10.1093/llc/fqt067.</bibl>
            <bibl>Won, Miguel, Patricia Murrieta–Flores, and Bruno Martins. 2018. Ensemble named
               entity recognition (NER): Evaluating NER Tools in the identification of place names
               in historical corpora. <hi rend="italic">Frontiers in Digital Humanities</hi> 5.
               doi:10.3389/fdigh.2018.00002.</bibl>
         </listBibl>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
